<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<p>
			1.
			<lb />
			The parties entered into an agreement on 30.12.1996 under
			<lb />
			which the petitioner was to provide services for obtaining statutory
			<lb />
			clearances from various authorities for setting up a Central India Refinery
			<lb />
			Project by the respondent. The parties agreed to refer the dispute therein
			<lb />
			to arbitration. The petitioner made 12 separate claims. The learned
			<lb />
			Arbitrator has rejected each one of the claims under the impugned award
			<lb />
			dated 5 th March, 2010 which has been challenged in this petition under
			<lb />
			Section 34 of the Arbitration and Conciliation Act, 1996 (the Act)
			<lb />
			essentially as being vitiated by bias and upon the Arbitrator not having
			<lb />
			considered the evidence led before him and it being against the terms of
			<lb />
			the contract and various specified laws. It would be appropriate to deal
			<lb />
			initially with each of the claims separately and then with the general
			<lb />
			aspects of law vitiating awards.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<head>
			CLAIMS
			<lb />
			Claim No.1 : Interest on Security Deposit
			<lb />
		</head>
		<p>
			2.
			<lb />
			This is for the payment of interest on the delayed refund of the
			<lb />
			security deposit to the petitioner by the respondent. The security deposit
			<lb />
			was to be of 10% of the value of the tender and payable at specified times
			<lb />
			under Clause 3 of Section 3A and Clause 4 of Section 3B of the Special
			<lb />
			Conditions of Contract which run thus:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			3.0 SECURITY DEPOSIT:
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			3.1 A sum of 10% of the accepted value of the tender shall be
			<lb />
			deposited by the contractor as security deposit with the Owner. For
			<lb />
			details refer Item 14 of Conditions of Contract attached.
			<lb />
			Security Deposit will be released after successful completion of
			<lb />
			defects liability period of one year after completion of works.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			4.0 SECURITY DEPOSIT:
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			4.1 A sum of 10% of the accepted value of the tender shall be
			<lb />
			deposited by the person/persons (hereafter called the Contractor) as
			<lb />
			security deposit with the Owner. For details refer Item 14 of
			<lb />
			Conditions of Contract attached.
			<lb />
			Security Deposit will be released soon after completion of work in all
			<lb />
			respects as per scope of work and terms and conditions and after
			<lb />
			payment/passing of final bill by BORL.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			3.
			<lb />
			There is a dichotomy when the security deposit is repayable.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			Under Clause 3.1 the security deposit had to be released after the
			<lb />
			successful completion of the defects liability period of one year after the
			<lb />
			completion of work. The work was completed on 11.08.1999. The
			<lb />
			petitioner would contend that the security deposit became refundable on
			<lb />
			10.08.2000. It was refunded on 10.10.2001. The petitioner claims interest
			<lb />
			on the wrongful withholding of the security deposit from 11.08.2000 to
			<lb />
			10.10.2001, a period of 14 months.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			Under Clause 4.1 the security deposit had to be released
			<lb />
			immediately after the completion of work and after the payment of the
			<lb />
			final bill. It is argued on behalf of the petitioner that the security deposit
			<lb />
			is, therefore, not payable after the defects liability period is over but
			<lb />
			immediately after the contract is completed. This contention is not wholly
			<lb />
			correct. Clause 4.1 requires release of security deposit not only upon
			<lb />
			completion of the work but upon passing of the final bill. The security
			<lb />
			deposit is released by the respondent along with the payment of the final
			<lb />
			bill on 10.10.2001.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			4.
			<lb />
			Besides the petitioner had not completed the work entirely.
			<lb />
			The contract was terminated.
			<lb />
			The respondent contended that the
			<lb />
			petitioner offered to do certain jobs being the work left undone which fell
			<lb />
			within the scope of its work in the defect liability period. The respondent
			<lb />
			would claim that this aspect would show that the petitioner had sought
			<lb />
			more time to complete the job.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			5.
			<lb />
			Item No.14 of the Conditions of Contract consisted of 2
			<lb />
			components being 7.5% to be recovered in installments through deduction
			<lb />
			@ 10% on each running bill of the petitioner and 2.5% which was given as
			<lb />
			bank guarantee under Clause 14.1 relating to security deposit in the
			<lb />
			agreement between the parties.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			6.
			<lb />
			Under Clause 14.4 no interest was to be payable under
			<lb />
			security deposit.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			7.
			<lb />
			The respondent would contend that Clause 14.4 implied that
			<lb />
			there would be no payment of interest on the security deposit at any time.
			<lb />
			The petitioner would contend that non payment of interest was to be for
			<lb />
			the period of deposit and if that period was exceeded by the deposit not
			<lb />
			being refunded as per the terms of the contract at the end of the contract,
			<lb />
			interest would be chargeable upon the amount of security deposit withheld
			<lb />
			by the respondent under the general law. If that is so, on which date the
			<lb />
			security deposit became payable and was not paid so that the deposit
			<lb />
			would start earning interest which was not, until then, payable would have
			<lb />
			to be shown by the petitioner and interest thereafter would have to be
			<lb />
			demanded by the petitioner.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			8.
			<lb />
			It is argued on behalf of the petitioner that the petitioner was
			<lb />
			deprived of the use of its own money from 10.08.2000 till 10.10.2001 and
			<lb />
			was entitled to be compensated for the deprivation under the general law.
			<lb />
			The petitioner has relied upon the judgment in the case of Secretary,
			<lb />
			Irrigation Department, Government of Orissa &amp; Ors. Vs. G. C. Roy AIR
			<lb />
			1992 SC 732 in para 43 of which the claim for granting interest pendente
			<lb />
			lite is considered. The petitioner&apos;s claim is not for interest pendente lite or
			<lb />
			under Section 34 of the CPC. However the judgment considered the case
			<lb />
			where an agreement does not proceed for the grant of interest and also
			<lb />
			does not prohibit the grant. It has been held that in such cases when a
			<lb />
			person is deprived of the use of money to which he is legitimately entitled,
			<lb />
			he has the right of interest, compensation or damages. In this case the fact
			<lb />
			that no interest was otherwise payable is set out in Clause 14.4 of the
			<lb />
			Contract.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			9.
			<lb />
			There has been no provision for payment of interest for
			<lb />
			withholding the security amount. After the completion or termination of
			<lb />
			the contract the petitioner has claimed interest in the form of damages for
			<lb />
			wrongful withholding of a security deposit, albeit in the form of bank
			<lb />
			guarantee.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			10.
			<lb />
			Mr. Sancheti relied upon the judgment in the case of Union of
			<lb />
			India Vs. Krafters Engineering and Leasing Pvt. Ltd., (2011) 7 Supreme
			<lb />
			Court Cases 279. It relates to a bar under the contract against payment
			<lb />
			for interest upon the earnest money or security deposit.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			11.
			<lb />
			It would have to be seen whether the interest can be granted
			<lb />
			under the Interest Act for the security deposit wrongfully withheld for a
			<lb />
			period of time. That would be under the Interest Act, 1978. No demand
			<lb />
			for any specific rate of interest from a specific date is made. The
			<lb />
			petitioner&apos;s case would not fall under that legislation.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			12.
			<lb />
			The petitioner has relied upon Section 31(7)(a) of the
			<lb />
			Arbitration and Conciliation Act, 1996 (the Act) which runs thus:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			31. Form and contents of arbitral award. (1)....
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(2) …........
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(3) …........
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(4) …........
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(5) …........
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(6) …........
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(7)(a) Unless otherwise agreed by the parties, where and insofar as
			<lb />
			an arbitral award is for the payment of money, the arbitral tribunal
			<lb />
			may include in the sum for which the award is made interest, at
			<lb />
			such rate as it deems reasonable, on the whole or any part of the
			<lb />
			money, for the whole or any part of the period between the date on
			<lb />
			which the cause of action arose and the date on which the award is
			<lb />
			made.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(b) A sum directed to be paid by an arbitral award shall, unless the
			<lb />
			award otherwise directs, carry interest at the rate of eighteen per
			<lb />
			centum per annum from the date of the award to the date of
			<lb />
			payment.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			Under the aforesaid provision when a money award is passed, award
			<lb />
			of interest at a reasonable rate until then may be made.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			13.
			<lb />
			The section relates to a money award being passed upon any
			<lb />
			claim. Upon such money award reasonable interest has to be granted. In
			<lb />
			this case the security deposit has been refunded, though belatedly. The
			<lb />
			award is, therefore, not for the refund of security deposit of any amount.
			<lb />
			Interest which chargeable is, therefore, not upon an award for payment of
			<lb />
			money which is contemplated under the aforesaid subsection. Interest
			<lb />
			which is claimed for the period during which the security deposit though
			<lb />
			having become refundable was not refunded cannot be claimed under
			<lb />
			Section 31(7)(a).
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			14.
			<lb />
			The learned Arbitrator has rejected the claim of interest on the
			<lb />
			security deposit on the ground that there is no provision in the contract for
			<lb />
			payment of interest nor any notice was received in respect of the same.
			<lb />
			This notice is the one contemplated under Section 3(1)(b) of the Interest
			<lb />
			Act, 1978 in respect of the date of refund of security deposit. The learned
			<lb />
			Arbitrator has also considered that the security deposit was refunded
			<lb />
			before the last bank guarantee extended by the petitioner expired on
			<lb />
			31.12.2001. As to the claim on the facts of the case between the parties for
			<lb />
			the security deposit, the learned Arbitrator has considered that the
			<lb />
			petitioner itself sought time to rectify/complete the job as shown in the
			<lb />
			aforesaid letter. The learned Arbitrator concluded that consequently the
			<lb />
			due date of the refund of the security deposit amount would automatically
			<lb />
			get extended. It is argued on behalf of the petitioner that this finding has
			<lb />
			been made without considering the material on record because the
			<lb />
			petitioner never sought time to rectify defects in the job of the petitioner
			<lb />
			alleged by the respondent; the petitioner only sought time for the work it
			<lb />
			was enjoined to do under the contract during the defect liability period.
			<lb />
			Counsel on behalf of the petitioner would have the Court go through
			<lb />
			various correspondence on what was the extra work which the petitioner
			<lb />
			was called upon to do outside the terms of the contract and in the defect
			<lb />
			liability period which would not extend the time for refund of security
			<lb />
			deposit whether those new jobs were done or not done by the petitioner.
			<lb />
			This cannot be gone into by this Court in a petition under Section 34 of the
			<lb />
			Act when the petitioner admittedly sought time to do same work which
			<lb />
			evidence has been considered.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			15.
			<lb />
			The learned Arbitrator has considered the law relating to the
			<lb />
			claim, the extent of the bank guarantee given for the security deposit and
			<lb />
			the terms of the contract. Hence the petitioner has not shown a legitimate
			<lb />
			legal right to claim interest on the security deposit and the rejection of its
			<lb />
			claim by the Arbitrator cannot be interfered with.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<head>
			Claim No.2 : Payment for ROU and ROW
			<lb />
		</head>

		<p>
			16.
			<lb />
			The petitioner has submitted 18 running bills, the 18 th bill
			<lb />
			dated 09.09.1999 being the final bill after the termination of the contract
			<lb />
			by the respondent on 11.08.1999 for Rs.15.98 Cr. against which a payment
			<lb />
			of Rs.8.39 Cr. has been made leaving a balance of Rs.7.58 Cr. outstanding.
			<lb />
			The claim relates to the Right of Use (ROU) and the Right of Way (ROW)
			<lb />
			in private and public lands respectively through which the cross country
			<lb />
			crude pipeline for the Central India Refineries Project of the respondent
			<lb />
			runs. The petitioner was to obtain statutory clearances for the laying of the
			<lb />
			pipeline through private and public land. The petitioner was required to
			<lb />
			make various applications to various authorities as required at different
			<lb />
			places throughout the length of the pipeline.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			17.
			<lb />
			Item No.2.0 in Section 3A of the Special Conditions of
			<lb />
			Contract lays down the mode of the payment of ROU acquisition. This was
			<lb />
			to be as per Section VI of the General Conditions of Contract. This is
			<lb />
			specified in Annexure1 to the Contract being the Schedule of Rates for the
			<lb />
			ROU acquisition. The ROU was to be upto 30 meters wide strip of land for
			<lb />
			103000 meters of land. The unit of payment was to be per running meter
			<lb />
			@ Rs.250/ per unit. Hence the total payment payable under the Contract
			<lb />
			agreed upon by the parties as specified in the Contract was Rs.7.52 Cr. for
			<lb />
			the ROU. The quantity specified in the annexure was 301000 which is
			<lb />
			accepted to be running meters. There is no dispute with regard to the
			<lb />
			payment for ROU under Claim No.2.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			18.
			<lb />
			Annexure1 also provide the Schedule of Rates for the
			<lb />
			statutory approvals. This was in respect of ROW which was claimed
			<lb />
			through various government lands.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			Item No.1 of the Schedule of Rates requires approvals in respect of
			<lb />
			various crossings. The approvals would be required from whichever
			<lb />
			ministry that was relevant. The schedule specified that each crossing may
			<lb />
			involve obtaining approvals of a number of authorities. The crossings
			<lb />
			contemplated in the schedule showing the description of the work were of
			<lb />
			10 types A to J being Railway Crossings, National Highways, State
			<lb />
			Highways, District/Village Roads, River Crossings, Canals/sub canals,
			<lb />
			Creeks/Nallas, Protected/Reserved and other Forests, Social Forestry and
			<lb />
			other miscellaneous crossings. The estimated quantity of the crossings are
			<lb />
			shown against each of the aforesaid specified crossings. The rate of
			<lb />
			payment was to be Rs.50,000/ or Rs.30,000/ per crossing. Consequently
			<lb />
			the amount (which is quantity multiplied by rate) is also specified in the
			<lb />
			annexures to the Schedule of Rates.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			19.
			<lb />
			This schedule would show that there were several estimated
			<lb />
			crossings of specified types for which approvals from all the relevant
			<lb />
			authorities was to be obtained. For each of the crossings the amount is
			<lb />
			specified. Hence the amount is dependent upon the crossings quantified in
			<lb />
			the Schedule of Rates. It would not matter how many approvals were to be
			<lb />
			obtained from various authorities per crossing. The amount payable to the
			<lb />
			petitioner was per crossing and not per approval. This is amplified in the
			<lb />
			description of Item No.1 of the Schedule of Rates relating to crossings by
			<lb />
			the term &quot;...... preliminary NOC and statutory approvals/clearance etc.
			<lb />
			from the respective authorities&quot;. It has been explained to the Court and it
			<lb />
			may be clarified that in the case of a single crossing more than one
			<lb />
			approval may be required. However the schedule would show that the
			<lb />
			petitioner would be entitled to be paid for the specified numbers of
			<lb />
			crossings. For example a nalla may run through a Railway Crossing as also
			<lb />
			a Forest. The permission of the relevant Railway Authority as also the
			<lb />
			Forest Conservator would have to be obtained for that one crossing
			<lb />
			requiring two approvals. The petitioner would be paid Rs.50,000/ or
			<lb />
			Rs.30,000/ as specified in the rates as shown in the rate column in the
			<lb />
			Schedule of Rates upon obtaining both approvals.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			20.
			<lb />
			Mr. Sancheti on behalf of the respondent has drawn the Court&apos;s
			<lb />
			attention to Clause 2.2 of the Contract setting out the authorities who
			<lb />
			would grant approvals for several of the approvals to be obtained. He has
			<lb />
			shown that for road crossings the relevant authority is a Public Works
			<lb />
			Department and hence all the approvals of the Collector showing the road
			<lb />
			(Rasta) would relate not to Item No.1 D and is not payable thereunder but
			<lb />
			approval obtained from only one authority under Item No.2.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			21.
			<lb />
			Similarly Mr. Sancheti has shown that the Municipal
			<lb />
			Corporation is the concerned authority for the crossing of roads, drainage
			<lb />
			etc. within the municipal boundary limit. Those special permissions would
			<lb />
			be under Item No.1 alone.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			22.
			<lb />
			Item No.2 of the Schedule of Rates relating to the ROW was
			<lb />
			for approvals of various authorities other than for the crossings specified in
			<lb />
			Item No.1. The petitioner was to be paid &quot;per approval, per district, per
			<lb />
			authority&quot;. The authorities from whom the approvals were required were
			<lb />
			also specified in the description to Item No.2 in the Schedule of Rates. The
			<lb />
			estimated quantity of approvals required from all or some of such
			<lb />
			authorities was specified to be 475. The rate at which the petitioner was to
			<lb />
			be paid was Rs.50,000/ per approval per district, per authority. The
			<lb />
			amount payable was specified to be Rs.2.37 Cr.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			23.
			<lb />
			Item No.1, therefore, dealt with the approvals required for the
			<lb />
			various crossings. Item No.2 dealt with the approvals required for other
			<lb />
			than the crossings. Both the approvals were payable at the rate of
			<lb />
			Rs.50,000/ per crossing and some at the rate of Rs.30,000/ per crossing
			<lb />
			and per approval, per authority, per district. It appears that the pipeline
			<lb />
			ran through 9 districts. The respondent would contend and the learned
			<lb />
			Arbitrator has held that the petitioner would be paid Rs.50,000/ per
			<lb />
			district. For 9 districts the petitioner has been awarded Rs.4.5 lacs instead
			<lb />
			of Rs.2.37 Cr. specified in the Item No.2 of the Schedule of Rates for 475
			<lb />
			approvals estimated or contemplated by the parties and forming a part of
			<lb />
			the money contract. The nallas shown in the various approvals of the
			<lb />
			Collector are the nallas en route the pipeline which would fall under Item
			<lb />
			No.2 and being the various approvals obtained from but one authority
			<lb />
			being the Collector, the petitioner would be entitled to one such payment
			<lb />
			per district.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			24.
			<lb />
			It may be mentioned that this is the most substantial part of
			<lb />
			the claim of the petitioner. The main contract was for making applications
			<lb />
			for various approvals. Mr. Andhyarujina contended that the payment
			<lb />
			depended upon the number of approvals obtained.
			<lb />
			The emphasis about the requirement of a number of approvals, albeit
			<lb />
			of one authority in each district in Item No.2 is shown from the Clause 5.0
			<lb />
			of Section 3B of the Special Conditions of Contract which runs thus:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			5.0 Number of approvals indicated in Scope of Work are
			<lb />
			approximate and contractor shall be paid according to the actual
			<lb />
			approvals obtained as certified by engineer-in-charge.
		</item>
		<lb />
		<p>
			This clause is the provision for ROW which is essentially based on
			<lb />
			government approvals.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			Mr. Andhyarujina contended that if the petitioner was to be paid
			<lb />
			Rs.4.5 lacs for all the approvals of various authorities to be obtained in a
			<lb />
			given district, the contract would not have specified 475 as the quantity
			<lb />
			and Rs.2.37 Cr. as the amount in the Schedule of Rates. Mr. Sancheti
			<lb />
			argued that there are various authorities shown in Item No.2 of the
			<lb />
			Schedule of Rates. If the petitioner obtained approvals of many authorities
			<lb />
			in a single district, he would be paid for the number of approvals of each
			<lb />
			authority obtained in a single district. If the petitioner obtained various
			<lb />
			approvals, but of only one authority, in each district (as it has), the
			<lb />
			petitioner would be entitled to only one payment for such authority (in this
			<lb />
			case the Collector) of each district. That having been done, the petitioner
			<lb />
			has been granted one payment for each of the 9 districts as per the contract
			<lb />
			rate of Rs.50,000/ per approval, per authority per district X 9 and paid
			<lb />
			Rs.4.50 lacs.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			25.
			<lb />
			The meaning and interpretation of the expression &quot;per
			<lb />
			authority, per approval, per district&quot; has to be understood from the contract
			<lb />
			itself. Each of these 3 terms must be given effect. Hence payment has to
			<lb />
			be made for each approval of each authority in each district. Of course,
			<lb />
			these must be the approvals which are actually necessitated and cannot be
			<lb />
			mischievously broken up to create more than one approval for a single unit
			<lb />
			of land in a given district considering that it would be en route the
			<lb />
			pipeline.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			26.
			<lb />
			We are required to consider the case of many approvals but of
			<lb />
			a single authority in each district. If the argument of Mr. Sancheti was to
			<lb />
			be accepted, the emphasis upon the words &quot;per approval&quot; would be
			<lb />
			diluted. If that one authority has given or could have given but one
			<lb />
			approval for the length of the pipeline in that district, one approval would
			<lb />
			suffice. If that could not be so, various approvals would have to be
			<lb />
			obtained. This would merit separate payments per approval (for each
			<lb />
			approval) because obtaining various approvals as necessitated would
			<lb />
			require work to that extent to be expended. It is, therefore, that the parties
			<lb />
			set out the approximate number of approvals required in Item No.2 of the
			<lb />
			Schedule of Rates. Hence various approvals obtained as required in each
			<lb />
			and every district (without exception) through which the pipeline ran
			<lb />
			would have to be paid. If the various approvals are of various authorities,
			<lb />
			for each of the approvals of each of the authorities in each of the districts
			<lb />
			the payment would have to be made. This would be the only meaningful
			<lb />
			interpretation of the expression &quot;per district&quot; without ignoring &quot;per
			<lb />
			approval&quot;.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			27.
			<lb />
			The petitioner was not to be paid only when the final approval
			<lb />
			was in fact obtained. The petitioner was entitled to be paid installments as
			<lb />
			set out in Clause 3.1 of the Contract. The petitioner was to charge the
			<lb />
			rates under Clause 3.1 of Section 3B which runs thus:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			3.1 Statutory Clearances
			<lb />
			20% of total quoted fee is payable on completion of collection
			<lb />
			of data and submission of application to all concerned
			<lb />
			authorities.
			<lb />
			60% of fee is payable against receipt of approval/permission
			<lb />
			from concerned authorities for each item.
			<lb />
			10% is payable on completion all activities and issue of
			<lb />
			certificates from contractor that all clearances required for
			<lb />
			Cross Country Crude Pipeline have been obtained.
			<lb />
			The remaining 10% is payable after completion of 1 year
			<lb />
			defect liability period.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			This clause would show the amount claimable by the petitioner from
			<lb />
			time to time. It would claim the first 20% of the amount so soon as the
			<lb />
			petitioner collected the data and submitted the applications to the
			<lb />
			respective concerned authorities. If the petitioner was to be paid for one
			<lb />
			approval in one district, it could not be paid for many applications. The
			<lb />
			petitioner has made a number of applications for Item Nos.1 &amp; 2 of the
			<lb />
			Schedule of Rates and the respondent has signed a number of applications.
			<lb />
			The petitioner would, therefore, be entitled to Rs.10,000/ per such
			<lb />
			application made. If the petitioner was entitled to be paid the 1 st
			<lb />
			installment of Rs.10,000/ for each of the applications made, how could it
			<lb />
			not be paid for each of the corresponding approvals obtained upon these
			<lb />
			applications?
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			It is argued on behalf of the respondent that the bill of the petitioner
			<lb />
			has itself shown several applications not signed by the respondent and
			<lb />
			several applications cancelled. The petitioner would not be entitled to any
			<lb />
			amount on such applications which are disputed by the respondent. The
			<lb />
			computation would have been required to be done in arbitration. It has
			<lb />
			been the case of the respondent that the petitioner has claimed not as per
			<lb />
			the approvals and the district but upon the number of applications. The
			<lb />
			petitioner would, of course, not be entitled to be paid on such basis. If the
			<lb />
			number of applications made are more than the approvals required in each
			<lb />
			district, the applications would not matter.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			28.
			<lb />
			The petitioner would be entitled to further 60% of the total
			<lb />
			amount of Rs.50,000/ upon obtaining approval/permission from the
			<lb />
			authorities for each item being item Nos.1 &amp; 2 of ROW. Hence in the later
			<lb />
			bills for each approval obtained, the petitioner would claim Rs.30,000/. It
			<lb />
			would be anomalous to contend that the petitioner would be entitled to be
			<lb />
			paid for a number of applications made but for just one approval in each
			<lb />
			district unless, of course, one application and one approval for the length
			<lb />
			of the pipeline in each district would suffice.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			29.
			<lb />
			It would, therefore, have to be seen how the petitioner has
			<lb />
			submitted its final bill which remained partly unpaid upon the disputes of
			<lb />
			the respondent. The bill shows the description of the item for ROW as
			<lb />
			stated in the Schedule of Rates. It further shows the tender quantity also
			<lb />
			precisely as per the quantity mentioned in the Schedule of Rates. This
			<lb />
			would be the approximate quantity as specified in the Schedule. The
			<lb />
			quantity shown in the bill shows the quantity upto previous bill, the
			<lb />
			quantity since previous bill and the total upto date. It is argued on behalf
			<lb />
			of the petitioner that the quantity upto previous bill shows the quantity
			<lb />
			that was sanctioned in the previous bill. It is argued on behalf of the
			<lb />
			respondent that this column shows the quantity charged by the petitioner
			<lb />
			upto the previous bill. Mr. Sancheti would argue that the petitioner has
			<lb />
			grossly exaggerated the quantity since the previous bill in the final bill. Mr.
			<lb />
			Andhyarujina argued that the column of quantity of the previous bill shows
			<lb />
			a low amount because the higher amounts per approvals obtained were
			<lb />
			rejected though demanded in the previous bill and only the quantities
			<lb />
			accepted and paid are shown as quantities &quot;paid&quot; upto previous bill as the
			<lb />
			bills were running bills and the petitioner would claim all the unpaid
			<lb />
			amounts in the final bill.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			30.
			<lb />
			The petitioner has charged 20% of the amount chargeable
			<lb />
			which forms the first part of the payment for statutory clearance under
			<lb />
			Clause 3.1 of Section 3B cited above showing the charge until completion
			<lb />
			of data and submission of applications to all the concerned authorities.
			<lb />
			This is followed by 60% charged for the approvals obtained and further
			<lb />
			10% and 10% for completion of activities (which would be upto
			<lb />
			11.08.1999) and after 1 year defect liability period (though the period
			<lb />
			would expire one year after 11.08.1999).
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			31.
			<lb />
			Under Item No.2 of the bill which relates to the approvals to
			<lb />
			be obtained for other than the crossings, the petitioner has similarly sought
			<lb />
			amounts for the approvals upto previous bill, since the previous bills and
			<lb />
			the total number of approvals. The petitioner would be entitled to be
			<lb />
			charged for the precise number of approvals obtained from each authority
			<lb />
			in each district where the pipeline ran and the ROW was claimed. Of
			<lb />
			course, the petitioner would have to show why only one approval of the
			<lb />
			Collector would not suffice for the entire length of the pipeline running
			<lb />
			through one district.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			32.
			<lb />
			The Arbitrator alone would have to decide the actual
			<lb />
			computation of the amount claimed under the 18 th final bill of the
			<lb />
			petitioner. It would be for the petitioner to show the precise number of
			<lb />
			approvals obtained from the various authorities for other than the
			<lb />
			crossings. That arithmetical calculation cannot be done by the Court.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			33.
			<lb />
			The claim under Item No.2 was made by the petitioner upon
			<lb />
			the applications made by it in that behalf. The petitioner has produced the
			<lb />
			list showing the approvals granted in respect of various survey numbers
			<lb />
			upon the applications made. These show 269 approvals granted for one or
			<lb />
			more survey numbers. The petitioner&apos;s claim is based upon one or more
			<lb />
			survey numbers totalling 778 survey numbers. The petitioner claims sum
			<lb />
			of Rs.50,000/ for 778 such survey numbers. The petitioner has shown a
			<lb />
			list of other approvals for government lands showing inter alia the villages
			<lb />
			as also the districts and the survey numbers for the ROW claimed under
			<lb />
			each file bearing a separate number. It would be for the petitioner to show
			<lb />
			in arbitration the precise number of approvals stated to have been obtained
			<lb />
			in various villages and tehasils of each district. The total number of
			<lb />
			approvals obtained are shown to be 778. The petitioner would have had to
			<lb />
			actually show 778 approvals of the authorities and, of course, the fact that
			<lb />
			all of those were necessitated. The listing of the petitioner only shows the
			<lb />
			number of survey numbers involved totalling to 778. The petitioner cannot
			<lb />
			be paid on the basis of survey numbers because that is not the part of the
			<lb />
			contract. The petitioner would not be entitled to claim for more than one
			<lb />
			survey number merely because the pipe ran through more than one survey
			<lb />
			number since the contract between the parties is based upon the number of
			<lb />
			crossings and the number of approvals and not survey numbers.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			34.
			<lb />
			However if the petitioner has had to obtain separate approvals
			<lb />
			for each survey number from the same authority or from separate
			<lb />
			authorities, the petitioner would have to be paid for such approvals as per
			<lb />
			the rates mentioned in the Schedule of Rates.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			35.
			<lb />
			Under the contract between the parties the petitioner can
			<lb />
			claim for Item No.1 which are specific approvals for each crossing (per
			<lb />
			crossing) and not for applications made or the survey numbers of the land
			<lb />
			in respect of which the application is made. The petitioner can claim for
			<lb />
			Item No.2 which are general approvals in each district (per approval, per
			<lb />
			authority, per district). These are items other than crossings. The
			<lb />
			petitioner must, therefore, show which approval would fall under which
			<lb />
			item in respect of its claim.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			36.
			<lb />
			The petitioner never produced any approvals (except two by
			<lb />
			way of illustration) before the learned Arbitrator. The petitioner was
			<lb />
			required to obtain approvals for each crossing under Item No.1. The
			<lb />
			petitioner has produced a few approvals for the perusal of the Court
			<lb />
			showing that the petitioner&apos;s claim would fall under Item Nos.1 D &amp; G as
			<lb />
			they relate to village roads and nallas. The contract shows the estimated
			<lb />
			quantity of those crossings to be 237 and 541 for which the petitioner was
			<lb />
			to be paid Rs.71 lacs and Rs.1.62 Cr. respectively as the estimated amount
			<lb />
			upon the rate of Rs.30,000/ per crossing for the village roads and nallas.
			<lb />
			If the village roads and nallas are not crossings but approvals are required
			<lb />
			to be obtained in respect of those village roads and nallas (which are other
			<lb />
			than crossings in Item No.1), the petitioner would require to obtain the
			<lb />
			approvals of one or more of the authorities in the district through which
			<lb />
			the pipeline was to run under Item No.2. This would be the general
			<lb />
			approval upon application made in that behalf and required to be paid by
			<lb />
			installments as set out in Clause 3.1 of the Contract. Since the petitioner
			<lb />
			has not produced 269 approvals stated to have been obtained by the
			<lb />
			petitioner, the learned Arbitrator could not have considered them.
			<lb />
			Consequently the entire claim of the petitioner that there were 269
			<lb />
			approvals cannot be seen. This Court cannot go into the evidence not
			<lb />
			produced before the Arbitrator. It was for the petitioner to show that the
			<lb />
			approvals for the roads and nallas (Rasta and Nalla) are with regard to the
			<lb />
			crossings and not the approval for the various survey numbers en route the
			<lb />
			pipeline.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			37.
			<lb />
			The petitioner has obtained all the approvals only from the
			<lb />
			Collector of the respective districts. The pipeline runs through 9 districts.
			<lb />
			9 Collectors have, therefore, given their approvals in respect of various
			<lb />
			matters including village roads and nallas which are not crossings. Hence
			<lb />
			the petitioner claims to be paid in its final 18 th RA bill for as many
			<lb />
			approvals obtained by it as shown in the list showing applications made for
			<lb />
			Item No.2 shown as other &quot;authorities; government land&quot;.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			38.
			<lb />
			It would, therefore, have to be seen what the parties
			<lb />
			contemplated by the number 475 as the quantity to entitle the petitioner to
			<lb />
			Rs.2.37 Cr @ Rs.50,000/ per approval per authority in a given district en
			<lb />
			route of the pipeline for other than the crossings in Item No.1 given that a
			<lb />
			number of applications are made by the petitioner and signed also by the
			<lb />
			respondent.
			<lb />
			This exercise is not seen to have been undertaken.
			<lb />
			Approximately 475 contemplated applications seem to have been wholly
			<lb />
			ignored.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			39.
			<lb />
			The petitioner has also claimed the last stage payment for ROU
			<lb />
			&amp; ROW.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			Clause 6.0 in the contract shows the mode of payment about ROU
			<lb />
			acquisition. Under that clause the last 5% is payable on completion of all
			<lb />
			activities and issue of certificate by the ROU acquisition contractor that all
			<lb />
			jobs have been completed for ROU acquisition for the pipeline. The
			<lb />
			petitioner is the ROU acquisition contractor. Hence when all the activities
			<lb />
			of the petitioner are concluded, the petitioner would issue the certificate.
			<lb />
			Such certificate is issued. The petitioner claims to be entitled to the last
			<lb />
			payment of 5% of the amount which came to be retained in respect of the
			<lb />
			ROU. The respondent claims that this amount would be released if no
			<lb />
			claims certificate is given by the petitioner as demanded by the respondent
			<lb />
			in its letter dated 17.06.2000. That however is not in terms of Clause 6.0
			<lb />
			of the Contract. The petitioner would not be held not entitled to claim the
			<lb />
			last of the payments of the ROU only because he has made other claims.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			40.
			<lb />
			The claim for the last stage payment under Item Nos.1 &amp; 2 for
			<lb />
			the ROW is governed under Clause 3.1. The last payment of 10% is
			<lb />
			payable after completion of one year defect liability period. That period
			<lb />
			has long since expired. The payment is not made as per the statement
			<lb />
			supplied in the letter dated 17.06.2000.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			41.
			<lb />
			The learned Arbitrator has rejected the entire claim of the
			<lb />
			petitioner on the ground that it is an afterthought and made subsequent to
			<lb />
			termination of the contract by the respondent. This is in view of the
			<lb />
			quantity upto previous bill having been shown to be 9 (for 9 districts) since
			<lb />
			the 4 th RA bill dated 04.10.1996. The petitioner, of course, would be
			<lb />
			entitled to claim for as much of the work done upto the date of termination
			<lb />
			of the contract even if the claim was made subsequent to termination.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			42.
			<lb />
			The learned Arbitrator has considered the claim for the ROW
			<lb />
			under the aforestated Clauses 1 &amp; 2 of the Contract under Claim No.2 in
			<lb />
			the award. He has considered the separate items for which the claims are
			<lb />
			payable under both the items for crossings as also for government land. He
			<lb />
			has observed that the claim is raised by the petitioner not on the basis of
			<lb />
			approvals but on the basis of number of applications which are actually for
			<lb />
			separate survey numbers. He has considered the denial of the respondent
			<lb />
			for all the claims under various bills of the petitioner. He has concluded
			<lb />
			that the contract relates to approvals and not the number of applications.
			<lb />
			This would show the mind of the learned Arbitrator considering the
			<lb />
			importance of approvals as against applications. He has even seen the
			<lb />
			difference between 269 approvals and the claim for 778 approvals based
			<lb />
			upon separate survey numbers. The petitioner is seen to have bifurcated
			<lb />
			its claim in a number of parts dependent upon the survey numbers when
			<lb />
			the unit of payment is per approval, per district, per authority and not per
			<lb />
			application or per survey number. This argument has been correctly
			<lb />
			considered by the learned Arbitrator. The learned Arbitrator has concluded
			<lb />
			in that indeed the petitioner has not established that the approvals which
			<lb />
			are obtained by the petitioner are for the nallas which can be termed as
			<lb />
			crossings and which would fall under Item No.1. Indeed since the
			<lb />
			petitioner has admittedly not produced the approvals at all, it would not be
			<lb />
			able to establish the approval claimed to have been obtained and it is
			<lb />
			correctly observed not to have established that those approvals are for
			<lb />
			nallas contemplated in Item No.1. The learned Arbitrator has further
			<lb />
			observed that the claim was made also for applications which are cancelled
			<lb />
			and the applications which were not signed by the respondent on which
			<lb />
			also he cannot be faulted.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			43.
			<lb />
			Consequently the learned Arbitrator has otherwise acted
			<lb />
			within his jurisdiction upon the material on record having considered the
			<lb />
			contentions of the petitioner as also the respondent.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			44.
			<lb />
			It would also have to be seen whether the learned Arbitrator
			<lb />
			acted as per the terms of the contract. Indeed only the quantity numbers
			<lb />
			mentioned in Item No.2 of the Schedule of Rates is not accounted for in the
			<lb />
			award. The petitioner&apos;s applications signed by the respondent, which were
			<lb />
			in hundreds, would itself show that what was contemplated in quantity
			<lb />
			were for many applications and various authorities for obtaining various
			<lb />
			approvals in a given district. To that extent the Award of rejection falls
			<lb />
			foul. The approximate estimated quantity in a contract cannot be ignored.
			<lb />
			The difference between the estimated quantity of approvals for payment to
			<lb />
			be considered per approval, per authority, per district and the approvals
			<lb />
			allowed is too large to be bypassed. The respondent would require to
			<lb />
			explain the estimated quantity. The petitioner would require to show the
			<lb />
			actual number of approvals legitimately required and obtained for nallas &amp;
			<lb />
			rasta which are crossings under Item No.1 and for land en route the
			<lb />
			pipeline under Item No.2. The Award has not considered whether the last
			<lb />
			stage payment for ROU and ROW claimed by the petitioner is acceptable or
			<lb />
			why it is rejected. This would fall under Claim No.2. Hence the rejection
			<lb />
			of Claim No.2 in its entirety without considering these 2 aspects would
			<lb />
			have to be and is set aside.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<head>Claim No.3 : Compensation for delay/liquidated damages</head>
		<lb />

		<p>
			45.
			<lb />
			This claim is made under Clause 18 of the Contract which
			<lb />
			runs thus:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			18. COMPENSATION FOR DELAY/LIQUIDATED DAMAGES:
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			The time allowed for carrying out the work as entered in the
			<lb />
			Contract, shall be strictly observed by the Contractor. The work
			<lb />
			shall through out the stipulated period of the contract be proceeded
			<lb />
			with due diligence (time being essence of the Contract) and the
			<lb />
			contractor shall pay to the Owner as compensation an amount
			<lb />
			equal to 1% or such an amount as the EngineerinCharge (whose
			<lb />
			decision in writing shall be final), may decide on the amount of the
			<lb />
			contract value for every week that the work may remain incomplete
			<lb />
			as per the time schedule subject to a maximum compensation of
			<lb />
			10% of the contract value after which period action will be taken by
			<lb />
			the EngineerinCharge under the provisions of the Contract.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			Time is the essence of the contract. The petitioner shall have to pay
			<lb />
			the compensation at the rate agreed in the clause for the delay in
			<lb />
			completion of the work. The compensation of 1% was to be paid for every
			<lb />
			week of delay when the work remained incomplete subject to the
			<lb />
			maximum compensation of 10%. 10% would, therefore, be charged for 10
			<lb />
			weeks of delay. If the delay still further continued the engineerincharge
			<lb />
			may take action.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			46.
			<lb />
			It is contended by the respondent that the work was delayed
			<lb />
			for more than 10 weeks. The respondent has capped the payment to 10%.
			<lb />
			That amount has been withheld from the payment made to the petitioner.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			47.
			<lb />
			The petitioner contends that there was no engineerincharge.
			<lb />
			The respondent contends that the contract would never proceed without an
			<lb />
			engineerincharge at the site. For every aspect of the work the engineer
			<lb />
			incharge would have to be consulted and would be the first adjudicating
			<lb />
			authority. However, the presence of the engineerincharge would be
			<lb />
			necessitated if action was to be taken against the petitioner. No action has
			<lb />
			been taken. Much after the period of the contract expired, the contract has
			<lb />
			been terminated. The termination is not challenged; in fact it is accepted
			<lb />
			and the petitioner has contended that the contract period was completed
			<lb />
			on the date of the termination as shall be seen presently.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			48.
			<lb />
			The petitioner&apos;s claim of exception to the liquidated damages
			<lb />
			of Rs.1.26 Cr deducted and appropriated by the respondent from the
			<lb />
			amount payable under its final RA bill dated 09.09.1999. This has been
			<lb />
			considered in Clause 3 of the Award. The petitioner claims that time was
			<lb />
			not made the essence of the contract. The petitioner also contended that
			<lb />
			the action for liquidated damages should have been initiated by the
			<lb />
			engineerincharge. It stated that the delay was attributable not to the
			<lb />
			petitioner, but to facts beyond the control of the petitioner and which were
			<lb />
			attributable to the respondent and the petitioner also carried out activities
			<lb />
			beyond the scope of the contract.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			49.
			<lb />
			The petitioner further contended that the respondent never
			<lb />
			made loss despite the delay as the pipeline was not laid until the date of
			<lb />
			the arbitration and hence it could not deduct liquidated damages and the
			<lb />
			percentage could be only determined by the engineerincharge.
			<lb />
			Consequently the amount was illegally withheld and had to be given to the
			<lb />
			petitioner.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			50.
			<lb />
			The respondent contended that the date of commencement of
			<lb />
			work was 10.10.1996. It was to be completed on 09.10.1997. It remained
			<lb />
			incomplete through 1999 and even 2000. The petitioner did not deny but
			<lb />
			justified the delay on various grounds. The respondent contended that the
			<lb />
			delay was 670 days. The petitioner&apos;s letter seeking extension of time as
			<lb />
			also request for waiver were refused. The delay was not due to force
			<lb />
			majeure. Hence under the terms of the contract the respondent could
			<lb />
			charge upto to 10% of the contract price. It is only if the delay exceeded
			<lb />
			10 weeks, action against the petitioner for causing the delay could be taken
			<lb />
			by the engineerincharge. The respondent claimed that the petitioner
			<lb />
			failed and neglected to complete the job. Yet the petitioner was paid the
			<lb />
			amount for whatever work was completed job (though in part) at a later
			<lb />
			date.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			51.
			<lb />
			There is nothing in the contract to show that the engineerin
			<lb />
			charge must apply for or determine the loss due to the delay. The term
			<lb />
			liquidated damages itself implied that the extent of damages is fixed and
			<lb />
			liquidated by the parties in the written contract.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			52.
			<lb />
			The learned Arbitrator has considered the respective
			<lb />
			submissions of the parties. He has observed that there is delay of more
			<lb />
			than 10 weeks. He has observed that out of 670 days over 70 days or 10
			<lb />
			weeks are clearly on account of the petitioner itself. Hence liquidated
			<lb />
			damages could be charged. The learned Arbitrator has further considered
			<lb />
			that the engineerincharge is indispensable to such contract and that all
			<lb />
			verification would be upon the recommendations of the &quot;site incharge&quot;. It
			<lb />
			would imply that the person incharge of the site would be the concerned
			<lb />
			engineer. The petitioner would take exception to the expression &quot;site in
			<lb />
			charge&quot;. It would make no difference. The rule of interpretation of the
			<lb />
			contract would allow the respondent itself to deduct the specified
			<lb />
			percentage of the liquidated damages. Hence the reasoning of the learned
			<lb />
			Arbitrator upon the contention taken by the petitioner requires no
			<lb />
			interference.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			53.
			<lb />
			The petitioner claims that the delay in the work was caused
			<lb />
			because of extraneous factors. It claims to have proved that the delay is
			<lb />
			not caused by it upon the letters dated 5 th July, 1997, 27 th September, 1997,
			<lb />
			28 th September, 1997 etc. The petitioner has mentioned various reasons or
			<lb />
			justifications for the admitted delay in the execution of work of obtaining
			<lb />
			the approvals of various government authorities. The petitioner has
			<lb />
			applied for extension of the time limit on the ground that the delay has
			<lb />
			been caused of specified periods specially the gross delay which is
			<lb />
			demonstrated in the letter dated 28 th September, 1997.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			54.
			<lb />
			The respondent by its letter dated 10.10.1997 accepted the
			<lb />
			petitioner&apos;s application for extension only on account of the Patwari strike.
			<lb />
			The respondent claimed that the other reasons stated by the petitioner are
			<lb />
			not admissible. In the 18 th final bill dated 09.09.1999 the petitioner
			<lb />
			annexed the time limit extension proposal &quot;as annexure A&quot;. It set out 15
			<lb />
			major reasons for seeking extension of time. It further annexed a columnar
			<lb />
			statement showing the period of days of delay on account of various
			<lb />
			reasons totalling to 285 days.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			55.
			<lb />
			Mr. Andhyarujina relied upon the judgment in the case of Oil
			<lb />
			&amp; Natural Gas Corporation Ltd. Vs. Saw Pipes Ltd. (2003) 5 SCC 705
			<lb />
			which has been considered by the learned Arbitrator also. The judgment
			<lb />
			specifically deals with the liquidated damages contemplated and agreed by
			<lb />
			parties and specified in written contracts which are payable upon breach by
			<lb />
			delay in completion of contract essentially under Section 74 of the Indian
			<lb />
			Contract Act, 1872 which runs thus:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			74. Compensation for breach of contract where
			<lb />
			penalty stipulated for. When a contract has been broken, if a sum
			<lb />
			is named in the contract as the amount to be paid in case of such
			<lb />
			breach, or if the contract contains any other stipulation by way of
			<lb />
			penalty, the party complaining of the breach is entitled, whether or
			<lb />
			not actual damage or loss is proved to have been caused thereby, to
			<lb />
			receive from the party who has broken the contract reasonable
			<lb />
			compensation not exceeding the amount so named or, as the case
			<lb />
			may be, the penalty stipulated for.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			This section came to be considered. It may at once be mentioned
			<lb />
			that the section itself specifies the entitlement of the party complaining of
			<lb />
			the breach whether or not actual damages or loss was proved. Loss or
			<lb />
			damage would have to be proved by the party claiming damages under
			<lb />
			Section 73 of the Indian Contract Act which runs thus:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<head>
			CHAPTER VI
			<lb />
			OF THE CONSEQUENCES OF BREACH OF CONTRACT
			<lb />
		</head>

		<item>
			73. Compensation for loss or damage caused by breach
			<lb />
			of contract. When a contract has been broken, the party who
			<lb />
			suffers by such breach is entitled to receive, from the party who has
			<lb />
			broken the contract, compensation for any loss or damage caused to
			<lb />
			him thereby, which naturally arose in the usual course of things
			<lb />
			from such breach, or which the parties knew, when they made the
			<lb />
			contract, to be likely to result from the breach of it.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			The distinction between Sections 73 &amp; 74 is that in the latter case
			<lb />
			the parties themselves quantified the damages. Consequently in such cases
			<lb />
			the actual losses or damages had not to be proved upon the breach or delay
			<lb />
			being proved; the quantified damages would be payable.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			56.
			<lb />
			This is what has been held in para 46 of the judgment:
			<lb />
			The party suffering breach is entitled to receive compensation for the
			<lb />
			loss that arises from the breach. When the parties know that a particular
			<lb />
			loss is likely to result, they can agree for payment of such compensation.
			<lb />
			Hence they need not lead evidence to prove the damages. If this agreed
			<lb />
			damages is by way of penalty, the Court would grant any reasonable
			<lb />
			compensation but on a proof of damages. Hence if the amount stipulated
			<lb />
			is unreasonable, the party claiming the specified amount must prove the
			<lb />
			loss or damage.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			The Court further observed in para 64 of the judgment that if the
			<lb />
			compensation named in the contract was a penalty, reasonable
			<lb />
			compensation for the loss suffered would be granted but if the
			<lb />
			compensation named in the contract is the genuine preestimate of the loss
			<lb />
			that the parties knew they would make upon a breach of the contract, there
			<lb />
			was no question of proving such loss. The party claiming damages is not
			<lb />
			required to prove the actual loss but the other is then required to lead
			<lb />
			evidence for proving that no loss has occurred.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			57.
			<lb />
			The ratio as laid down by the Supreme Court is, therefore, is
			<lb />
			thus:
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			Damage or loss has to be proved. The liquidated damage or loss
			<lb />
			agreed by the parties has not to be proved unless it is in the nature of the
			<lb />
			penalty. Liquidated damages would have to be granted without proof if the
			<lb />
			condition for which it is agreed to be granted is satisfied. That would be a
			<lb />
			particular breach -in this case it is the delay in carrying out the work
			<lb />
			under the contract, time being of the essence, as specified in Clause 18 of
			<lb />
			the Contract between the parties.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			58.
			<lb />
			The aforesaid correspondence of the petitioner itself makes it
			<lb />
			clear that there was delay of far more than 10 weeks. The learned
			<lb />
			Arbitrator was, therefore, fully justified in concluding that at least 10
			<lb />
			weeks delay is not only shown but accepted by the petitioner. Hence he
			<lb />
			allowed 10% of the contract value deducted by the respondent.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			59.
			<lb />
			The judgment in the case of Saw Pipes (supra) has been
			<lb />
			followed in the case of Bharat Sanchar Nigam Ltd. &amp; Anr. Vs. Motorola
			<lb />
			India Pvt. Ltd. 2008(3) Arb. LR 531 (SC). In that case the contract
			<lb />
			provided in Clause 15.2 that delay by the supplier in performance of the
			<lb />
			delivery obligation would render it liable to sanction, forfeiture liquidated
			<lb />
			damages and/or termination of the contract. In Clause 16.2 it provided
			<lb />
			that if the supplier failed to deliver the goods and services, the purchaser
			<lb />
			would be entitled to recover 0.5% of the value of the delayed quantity of
			<lb />
			goods and services for each week of delay upto 10 weeks and thereafter at
			<lb />
			a higher rate etc.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			These clauses came up for consideration under Section 74 of the
			<lb />
			Indian Contract Act. In para 10 of the judgment the Supreme Court held
			<lb />
			that quantification of the liquidated damages under Clause 16.2 was
			<lb />
			material. It held that:
		</p>
		<lb />
		<item>
			It is necessary as a condition precedent to find that there has been a
			<lb />
			delay on the part of the supplier in discharging his obligation for
			<lb />
			delivery under the agreement.
		</item>
		<lb />
		<p>
			The Supreme Court observed that under Clause 15.2 the supplier
			<lb />
			was liable for payment of liquidated damages. Under Clause 16.2 whether
			<lb />
			the supplier caused any delay in delivery would be seen. Reading Clauses
			<lb />
			15 &amp; 16 together, it held that Clause 16.2 will come into operation only
			<lb />
			after a finding is entered that the supplier caused delay in delivery. Clause
			<lb />
			16.2 is, therefore, attracted only after the supplier&apos;s liability is fixed for
			<lb />
			delay in Clause 15.2. Consequently the liability of the supplier is different
			<lb />
			from the quantification of the amount to be paid upon such liability. It
			<lb />
			observed thus:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			Fixing of liability is primary, while the quantification, which is
			<lb />
			provided for under Clause 16.2, is secondary to it.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			I do not see how this judgment would show that liquidated damages
			<lb />
			are not payable. Once it is seen that there has been a delay in the
			<lb />
			performance of the contract which tantamounts to a breach, the damages
			<lb />
			specified and liquidated by the parties under their own agreement would
			<lb />
			be payable without any proof of loss.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			60.
			<lb />
			Both the aforesaid judgments are followed in the case of M/s.
			<lb />
			J. G. Engineers Pvt. Ltd. Vs. Union of India &amp; Anr. 2011(3) R.A.J. 528
			<lb />
			(SC). The Court had to consider the question of breach and the
			<lb />
			consequent liability upon quantification of damages. Setting out the
			<lb />
			aforesaid observations in para 10 of the judgment in the case of Bharat
			<lb />
			Sanchar Nigam Ltd. &amp; Anr. Vs. Motorola India Pvt. Ltd. 2008(3) Arb.
			<lb />
			LR 531 (SC) the Court held that quantification of liquidated damages
			<lb />
			would follow the delay; &quot;there has to be delay in the first place&quot;.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			61.
			<lb />
			Mr. Andhyarujina relied upon the judgment of this Court in the
			<lb />
			case of Oil and Natural Gas Corporation Ltd. Vs. Rais Coastal Survey &amp;
			<lb />
			Consultancy Services Pvt. Ltd. 2005 Law Suit (Bom) 311 to show that
			<lb />
			the Court interpreted the judgment in the case of Saw Pipes (supra) to
			<lb />
			hold that if the Court came to conclusion that no loss is likely to occur
			<lb />
			because of the breach, the Court would disallow compensation and hence
			<lb />
			in every case where damages are claimed for breach of contract, proof of
			<lb />
			loss is a condition precedent. This would be the loss under Section 73 of
			<lb />
			the Indian Contract Act which is distinct from Section 74, both of which
			<lb />
			came to be considered in the case of Saw Pipes (supra).
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			62.
			<lb />
			The case of Saw Pipes (supra) as also the earlier cases of
			<lb />
			Fateh Chand Vs. Balkishan Dass, 1963 DGLS (soft) 2 : AIR 1963 SC
			<lb />
			1405, Maula Bux Vs. Union of India, 1969 DGLS (soft) 286 : AIR 1970
			<lb />
			SC 1955 and Union of India Vs. Raman Iron Foundry, 1974 DGLS (soft)
			<lb />
			95 : AIR 1974 SC 1265 have been considered by the learned Single Judge
			<lb />
			of this Court in the case of Oil &amp; Natural Gas Corporation Ltd. Vs. Oil
			<lb />
			Country Tubular Ltd. 2011(5) Bom.C.R. 198. He concluded that when
			<lb />
			the contract provided for the payment of liquidated damages upon a
			<lb />
			breach, the aggrieved party could recover only the actual damages suffered
			<lb />
			by it and hence would have to prove the actual damages suffered by it and
			<lb />
			cannot rely merely on the provision for liquidated damages in the contract.
			<lb />
			The learned Judge has set out para 46 of the judgment in the case of
			<lb />
			Saw Pipes (supra) which lays down 2 contingencies:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			(i)
			<lb />
			When the party suffers by the breach of contract in which case he
			<lb />
			would be entitled to the loss which arises from the breach, and
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			(ii) When the parties know that the particular loss would result from a
			<lb />
			breach, they can agree for payment of specific compensation, in such a case
			<lb />
			there is no need to lead evidence for proving damages arising from the
			<lb />
			breach.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			It may be mentioned that the first part would be covered by Section
			<lb />
			73 of the Indian Contract Act which deals with compensation for loss or
			<lb />
			damage caused by the breach of contract. The second contingency would
			<lb />
			arise under Section 74 of the Indian Contract Act when the parties know of
			<lb />
			the amount of loss which would be the result of the breach and agree for
			<lb />
			payment of such loss. When the payment of a specific loss occurred is
			<lb />
			agreed upon, there is naturally no requirement to prove the loss which is
			<lb />
			already agreed upon. In such a case the party who suffered the damage
			<lb />
			must only prove the breach.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			63.
			<lb />
			Therefore, it has been held in Saw Pipes (supra) that when
			<lb />
			there is no loss which arises from a breach, the specified compensation is
			<lb />
			not payable. Therefore it is held in Saw Pipes (supra) that the party who
			<lb />
			alleges that no loss has been caused by the breach of the contract must
			<lb />
			prove that fact.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			The learned Single Judge of this Court however has held that the
			<lb />
			burden is always on the parties who claimed compensation to prove actual
			<lb />
			loss even for reasonable compensation. This is much like the judgment in
			<lb />
			the case Rais Coastal (supra) in which even after considering the
			<lb />
			judgment in the case of Saw Pipes (supra) the learned Single Judge held
			<lb />
			that in every case where damages are claimed for breach of contract, proof
			<lb />
			of loss is a condition precedent. This goes directly contrary to the
			<lb />
			judgment in the case of Saw Pipes (supra).
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			64.
			<lb />
			It may be mentioned that the claim for damages upon the
			<lb />
			breach of contract and the claim for compensation where the penalty is
			<lb />
			stipulated is covered in Chapter VI of the Indian Contract Act, 1872 which
			<lb />
			deals with the consequences of breach of contract. Section 73 arises
			<lb />
			whenever a contract is breached, it is availed of by the party who suffers
			<lb />
			the breach. It grants compensation for the loss caused by the breach. The
			<lb />
			compensation is given to the party who suffers it and has to be paid by the
			<lb />
			party who has breached the contract. The party who suffers, therefore, has
			<lb />
			to prove that the contract was breached and what damage is suffered by
			<lb />
			him/her/it. He would be entitled to such damage as would naturally arise
			<lb />
			in the usual course of things from such breach. It would be what the
			<lb />
			parties knew to be the result of the breach. Such a party would, therefore,
			<lb />
			essentially have to prove the extent of loss that was caused by the breach.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			65.
			<lb />
			Hence when damages are not specified in a contract, the
			<lb />
			damages proved can be claimed under Section 73 of the ICA. Section 74 is
			<lb />
			in the nature of exception to Section 73. It applies only when the parties
			<lb />
			specify the amount that would be paid if the contract is breached. If an
			<lb />
			amount is specified there would be no need to prove that amount; it is
			<lb />
			known to the parties and it is specified by the parties. Hence when such a
			<lb />
			contract is breached only the breach has to be shown. The expression
			<lb />
			&quot;whether or not actual damage or loss is proved&quot; in Section 74 would show
			<lb />
			that there would be some contingencies in which actual damage or loss
			<lb />
			may not be proved. That would be only if a sum is specified in the contract
			<lb />
			as the damage that would be caused. That would be the liquidated
			<lb />
			damage or the specified damage. Such damage may be in absolute term or
			<lb />
			may be by way of percentage; in this case as also in the case of Saw Pipes
			<lb />
			(supra) it was by way of percentage. It was a liquidated damage. It was
			<lb />
			stipulated under Section 74 of the Indian Contract Act. The actual damage
			<lb />
			would not have to be proved because whatever be the actual damage, only
			<lb />
			the stipulated compensation can be granted. If it is in a range such as in
			<lb />
			this contract from 1% to 10% of the contract price, it must be granted only
			<lb />
			within that range. The maximum extent may not be granted. That would
			<lb />
			be in the discretion of the adjudicating authority. That would be granted
			<lb />
			without proof of actual damage.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			66.
			<lb />
			It is argued by Mr. Andhyarujina that even if the actual
			<lb />
			damage is not to be proved, some damage has to be proved. There is no
			<lb />
			such requirement in the statute. That cannot be added by the Court. If so
			<lb />
			done it would tantamount to legislation. Mr. Andhyarujina drew the
			<lb />
			attention of the Court to the judgment of the learned Single Judge in the
			<lb />
			case of Rais Coastal (supra) to show that the proof of loss has to be made.
			<lb />
			Hence even if the actual damage is not shown, some loss has to be shown
			<lb />
			in every case. The expression &quot;in every case&quot; directly militates against the
			<lb />
			2 contingencies specified in Sections 73 and 74 of the Indian Contract Act.
			<lb />
			The requirement of proof of some loss out of the entire actual damage or
			<lb />
			loss is outside the bounds of the legislation and would not carry the case of
			<lb />
			the parties seeking damages much further. By proving some part of the
			<lb />
			loss the party cannot claim liquidated damages which it would claim only if
			<lb />
			loss has to be proved. If loss has to be proved, it has to be to the extent of
			<lb />
			the loss suffered. If the party would prove the loss upon the breach of the
			<lb />
			contract, it would prove it under Section 73 itself. The very purpose of
			<lb />
			enacting Section 74 would be lost. Section 74 itself would be rendered
			<lb />
			otiose. It would mean that whether or not any amount or compensation is
			<lb />
			stipulated in the contract, the party must prove some loss. The reasoning
			<lb />
			seems contrary to the statute.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			Similarly the expression &quot;the burden is always on the parties who
			<lb />
			claim compensation to prove actual loss&quot; in the case of Oil Country
			<lb />
			(supra) which goes even further than the case of Rais Coastal (supra)
			<lb />
			would be against the specific provision of Section 74 which exempts the
			<lb />
			requirement of proof in view of the compensation already specified.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			67.
			<lb />
			This Court, therefore, would, as it should, go by the specific
			<lb />
			ruling in the case of Saw Pipes (supra). The learned Arbitrator has also
			<lb />
			considered appropriately the said ruling basing his reliance upon Section
			<lb />
			74 of the Indian Contract Act whilst considering claim No.3.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			68.
			<lb />
			The position in law as laid down in para 65 in the case of Saw
			<lb />
			Pipes (supra) would run thus:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			…. if the compensation named in the contract for such breach is
			<lb />
			genuine preestimate of loss which the parties knew when they made
			<lb />
			the contract to be likely to result from the breach of it, there is no
			<lb />
			question of proving such loss or such party is not required to lead
			<lb />
			evidence to prove actual loss suffered by him. Burden is on the
			<lb />
			other party to lead evidence for proving that no loss is likely to
			<lb />
			occur by such breach.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			69.
			<lb />
			This Court is bound by the ultimate ruling of the Supreme
			<lb />
			Court in the case of Saw Pipes (supra). The parties&apos; case is covered by that
			<lb />
			ruling. This is notwithstanding the aforesaid two judgments of the two
			<lb />
			learned Single Judges of this Court.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			70.
			<lb />
			Mr. Andhyarujina would, therefore, argue that even if it is
			<lb />
			accepted that the petitioner would have to prove that no loss occurred by
			<lb />
			the breach committed by the petitioner, the petitioner has proved the same.
			<lb />
			Mr. Andhyarujina relied upon claim No.3 on account of liquidated
			<lb />
			damages. The claim in that behalf runs thus:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			…. as on today, the pipeline has not been laid, and therefore, no
			<lb />
			any loss in any manner whatsoever caused to the respondent, and
			<lb />
			when no loss is caused to the respondent, then in that
			<lb />
			circumstances, the respondent had no any legal right to deduct any
			<lb />
			amount towards liquidated damages....
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			Mr. Andhyarujina would claim that this position has remained
			<lb />
			untraversed and is accordingly proved. No oral evidence is, therefore,
			<lb />
			required to be led. The respondent has denied and disputed the claim of
			<lb />
			liquidated damages made by the petitioner as alleged in Claim No.3A in
			<lb />
			para 13.8.3 of its written statement. The respondent has not specifically
			<lb />
			denied that no loss was suffered by it because the pipeline was not laid
			<lb />
			even when the arbitration was in progress which was several years after
			<lb />
			the termination of the contract in 1999.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			71.
			<lb />
			Whereas Mr. Andhyarujina would argue that a general denial
			<lb />
			of this nature would not constitute denial of the fact of the respondent not
			<lb />
			having laid the pipeline and also of the fact of respondent not having
			<lb />
			incurred any loss thereby, Mr. Sancheti would argue that the general denial
			<lb />
			would encompass these facts and also that the fact that there is no traverse
			<lb />
			has neither been pleaded before the Arbitrator nor has been considered by
			<lb />
			the learned Arbitrator and nor is it pleaded in the petition as one of the
			<lb />
			grounds.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			72.
			<lb />
			The award would show the various claims of the petitioner
			<lb />
			under Claim Nos.3A &amp; 3B as cited above in Clause 3.1 of the award. It
			<lb />
			also shows the respondent&apos;s reply in Clause 3.2 thereof. This is considered
			<lb />
			in Clause 3.3 of the award by the learned Arbitrator. The learned
			<lb />
			Arbitrator has inter alia observed that the petitioner has simply made a
			<lb />
			statement that the respondent did not suffer any loss and has not led any
			<lb />
			evidence thereon. Though it is argued on behalf of the petitioner that no
			<lb />
			further oral evidence was required, it having not been specifically
			<lb />
			traversed, it is not shown to have been argued as such in the arbitration.
			<lb />
			petition relating to the claim made by the petitioner in respect of liquidated
			<lb />
			damages deducted by the respondent. The petitioner has indeed stated in
			<lb />
			the petition that no loss was caused to the respondent. The petitioner has
			<lb />
			relied upon Section 74 of the Indian Contract Act and claimed that in view
			<lb />
			of no loss no amount can be claimed under Section 74 of the Indian
			<lb />
			Contract Act. Mr. Andhyarujina claimed that this ground is a compendious
			<lb />
			way of showing the petitioner&apos;s objection. The specific submission that this
			<lb />
			case has not been traversed or has been left untraversed is not in so many
			<lb />
			words made in the petition. Mr. Sancheti relied upon the judgment in the
			<lb />
			case of Shipping Corporation of India Vs. Nissar Export Corporation,
			<lb />
			AIR 1981 Supreme Court 1212. In that case the plaintiff had not
			<lb />
			contended in the trial court that his allegations not having been traversed
			<lb />
			by the defendant should be deemed to have been admitted. The Supreme
			<lb />
			Court did not permit the plaintiff to raise that contention for the first time
			<lb />
			in appeal. Indeed even in this petition though the petitioner has claimed no
			<lb />
			loss was caused to the respondent, the fact that that aspect has not been
			<lb />
			traversed as neither been agitated by the petitioner in the claim nor in this
			<lb />
			petition challenging the award. The petitioner has only contended that he
			<lb />
			did not require to prove the loss suffered by the respondent upon his
			<lb />
			statement in the claim. In fact, the petitioner has submitted that the
			<lb />
			learned Arbitrator ought to have ascertained the veracity of the petitioner&apos;s
			<lb />
			statement from the respondent. This is indeed a tall claim. It is for the
			<lb />
			parties to prove their respective claims. It is not for the Arbitrator to verify
			<lb />
			and test the claims. If the claim is proved, it could be granted. A claim
			<lb />
			could be proved if it is admitted or not denied. A claim would have to be
			<lb />
			proved by oral or documentary evidence if it is denied. If the petitioner
			<lb />
			would contend that the denial of the respondent is only general and not
			<lb />
			specific, the petitioner would require to take up such a contention in the
			<lb />
			arbitration as also in the petition challenging the award. Had that
			<lb />
			contention been taken the respondent may have amended the written
			<lb />
			statement to show the specific denial of no loss. If then the petitioner had
			<lb />
			sought to prove that there could have been no loss because the pipeline
			<lb />
			was not laid until then, the respondent could have shown the expenses and
			<lb />
			cost incurred in obtaining further approvals not obtained by the petitioner
			<lb />
			to show the loss. For want of such contentions the aspect has remained at
			<lb />
			that and the petitioner is seen not to have proved no loss caused to the
			<lb />
			respondent by its delay.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			74.
			<lb />
			The claim of specific denial is as specified in Order 8 Rule 3 of
			<lb />
			the CPC. The recourse to CPC is not mandatory arbitration. Indeed in this
			<lb />
			case the parties merely relied upon documentary evidence contained
			<lb />
			essentially in the contract and the correspondence.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			75.
			<lb />
			The mere statement of the petitioner that there was no loss
			<lb />
			proves nothing. The denial of the respondent of that claim would require
			<lb />
			the petitioner to prove that no loss was occasioned to the respondent
			<lb />
			despite the petitioner&apos;s gross delay by concrete evidence; the mere fact that
			<lb />
			the pipeline was not laid is no evidence of no loss. The fact that the
			<lb />
			pipeline was later put shows that despite the non performance of the entire
			<lb />
			contract within time and thereafter the respondent caused the pipeline to
			<lb />
			be laid for which it could have incurred further costs.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			76.
			<lb />
			Mr. Andhyarujina would argue that since the time was not of
			<lb />
			the essence, by virtue of the contract having been extended by both the
			<lb />
			parties, by the petitioner obtaining approvals and the respondent accepting
			<lb />
			the approvals obtained by the petitioner, the liquidated damages to the
			<lb />
			extent of the amount specified in Clause 18 cannot be claimed by the
			<lb />
			respondent.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			77.
			<lb />
			The petitioner relies upon section 55 of the Indian Contract
			<lb />
			Act relating to time being of the essence or not of the essence of the
			<lb />
			contract. Section 55 runs thus :
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			55. Effect of failure to perform at fixed time, in contract in
			<lb />
			which time is essential.
		</item>
		<lb />
		<item>
			When a party to a contract promises to do a certain thing at or
			<lb />
			before a specified time, or certain things at or before specified times,
			<lb />
			and fails to do any such thing at or before the specified time, the
			<lb />
			contract, or so much of it as has not been performed, becomes
			<lb />
			voidable at the option of the promisee, if the intention of the parties
			<lb />
			was that time should be of the essence of the contract.
		</item>
		<lb />
		<item>
			Effect of such failure when time is not essential. -
		</item>
		<lb />
		<item>
			If it was not the intention of the parties that time should be of the
			<lb />
			essence of the contract, the contract does not become voidable by
			<lb />
			the failure to do such thing at or before the specified time ; but the
			<lb />
			promisee is entitled to compensation from the promisor for any loss
			<lb />
			occasioned to him by such failure.
		</item>
		<lb />
		<item>
			Effect of acceptance of performance at time other than that
			<lb />
			agreed upon.-
		</item>
		<lb />
		<item>
			If, in case of a contract voidable on account of the promisor&apos;s failure
			<lb />
			to perform his promise at the time agreed, the promisee accepts
			<lb />
			performance of such promise at any time other than that agreed, the
			<lb />
			promisee cannot claim compensation for any loss occasioned by the
			<lb />
			nonperformance of the promise at the time agreed, unless, at the
			<lb />
			time of such acceptance he gives notice to the promisor of his
			<lb />
			intention to do so.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			This section must be first analyzed to see its applicability to the
			<lb />
			parties in this lis. The section speaks of promisor or promisee. The person
			<lb />
			who promises to do a thing (make a proposal) is the promisor under
			<lb />
			Section 2(c) of the ICA. The person accepting the proposal is the promisee.
			<lb />
			In this case the respondent made an invitation to offer by inviting the bid.
			<lb />
			The petitioner offered to obtain the approvals (made a proposal/promise).
			<lb />
			The respondent accepted the proposal/promise. The petitioner is the
			<lb />
			promisor and the respondent is the promisee.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			Section 55 speaks of the promises in a contract and the rights and
			<lb />
			entitlements of the promisor and promisee (the petitioner and the
			<lb />
			respondent respectively in this case). Section 55 would have to be read
			<lb />
			accordingly.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			78.
			<lb />
			The petitioner promised to obtain the approvals. What would
			<lb />
			have to be seen is whether that was within a specified time or not within a
			<lb />
			specified time. Of course, Clause 18 of the contract for compensation for
			<lb />
			delay or liquidated damages specifies that time was the essence of this
			<lb />
			contract. Accordingly under Section 55 as the petitioner promised to
			<lb />
			obtain the approvals at or before the specified time being one year from
			<lb />
			the date of the contract (from 11 th October, 1996 to 10 th October, 1997),
			<lb />
			the contract would fall within the 1 st part of Section 55. Hence the
			<lb />
			contract as it stood would, upon failure of the petitioner to obtain the
			<lb />
			approvals within one year become voidable at the option of the respondent
			<lb />
			and the respondent would be entitled to avoid the contract by giving notice
			<lb />
			in that behalf.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			79.
			<lb />
			The respondent thus claimed that time was of the essence.
			<lb />
			The contract was to be performed within 12 months. The petitioner failed
			<lb />
			to obtain of the required approvals within the specified time. The part of
			<lb />
			the contract which was not performed by the approvals which were not
			<lb />
			obtained could be avoided by the respondent.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			This was sought to be done by the notice of termination of the
			<lb />
			contract. The notice of termination is dated 6 th August, 1999 it calls upon
			<lb />
			the petitioner to obtain the approvals by 11 th August, 1999 and it seeks to
			<lb />
			avoid the remainder of the contract which was not performed by the
			<lb />
			petitioner. The respondent has, of course, paid the petitioner for the work
			<lb />
			already done upto 11 th August, 1999. The petitioner has accepted the
			<lb />
			termination (though calling it unlawful) and contended that he completed
			<lb />
			the contract by 11 th August, 1999. The petitioner has not sought to state
			<lb />
			that he would be entitled to obtain further approvals on any ground. The
			<lb />
			petitioner has instead submitted his final 18 th RA bill on 9 th September,
			<lb />
			1999 and made the various claims for which the parties referred the
			<lb />
			dispute to the arbitration.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			80.
			<lb />
			It is contended on behalf of the petitioner that time was not of
			<lb />
			the essence of the contract though this aspect was mentioned in the
			<lb />
			contract. That was because the petitioner was allowed to carry out the
			<lb />
			promise made by him in the contract for a period of 22 months after the 12
			<lb />
			month period of the contract until it was finally terminated. Thus, it is
			<lb />
			contended, this act has shown the intention of the parties that the time was
			<lb />
			not of the essence. Consequently the respondent as the promisee would
			<lb />
			not be entitled to avoid the contract by the failure of the petitioner to
			<lb />
			perform its promise before the specified time. However, under the 2 nd part
			<lb />
			of Section 55 the respondent as the promisee would be entitled to
			<lb />
			compensation from the petitioner as the promisor for the loss occasioned to
			<lb />
			the respondent by the failure to obtain the necessary approvals by the
			<lb />
			petitioner. The respondent has claimed the loss as stipulated and specified
			<lb />
			in Clause 18 of the Contract.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			81.
			<lb />
			Under the 3 rd part of Section 55 if the time was of the essence
			<lb />
			and the respondent as the promisee was entitled to avoid the contract upon
			<lb />
			the petitioner&apos;s failure to perform its promise within the agreed time, if the
			<lb />
			respondent accepted performance of the promise during the further later
			<lb />
			period of the agreement, then the respondent cannot claim compensation
			<lb />
			for the loss occasioned to the respondent by the non performance of the
			<lb />
			promise by the petitioner unless when the respondent accepted such late
			<lb />
			performance the respondent gave notice to the petitioner as the promisor
			<lb />
			of its intention to claim compensation.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			82.
			<lb />
			The notice that is contemplated is the notice to be given by the
			<lb />
			respondent to the petitioner that time was of the essence, that the contract
			<lb />
			was not performed within the specified time because of which the
			<lb />
			respondent suffered loss and for which it would claim compensation.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			83.
			<lb />
			Hence upon paraphrasing Section 55 it becomes clear that
			<lb />
			when time is of the essence, the contract can be avoided upon breach of
			<lb />
			performance within that time. When time is not of the essence the
			<lb />
			contract cannot be avoided for any breach within that time, but
			<lb />
			compensation is payable for the loss caused to the promisee. If time is of
			<lb />
			the essence and the contract is breached by the promisor within that time
			<lb />
			but the promisee allows the promisor to perform it outside that time then
			<lb />
			compensation could be claimed only upon notice in that behalf. The notice
			<lb />
			contemplated is to inform the promisor that he has not performed the
			<lb />
			contract within a specified time and that if he does not perform within any
			<lb />
			further time granted the promisee would claim compensation.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			84.
			<lb />
			It is contended by Mr. Andhyarujina on behalf of petitioner
			<lb />
			that the time was not of the essence of the contract, Clause 18
			<lb />
			notwithstanding. He argued that even if it was and the contract was to be
			<lb />
			completed within 12 months, the respondent continued to accept the
			<lb />
			approvals obtained by the petitioner and in fact called upon the petitioner
			<lb />
			to obtain further approvals and do further acts. Hence, he argued that,
			<lb />
			even if time was of the essence, the contract was allowed to be performed
			<lb />
			without insisting that the time was of the essence. However, the
			<lb />
			respondent has given notice on 6 th August, 1999 and called upon the
			<lb />
			petitioner to perform the remainder of the contract by 11 th August, 1999.
			<lb />
			It is not that the petitioner had obtained all the necessary remaining
			<lb />
			approvals within that period. It is not that the respondent has sought to
			<lb />
			enforce such a promise. It is only that the respondent has given notice
			<lb />
			contemplated in the 3 rd part of the section 55 of the ICA.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			85.
			<lb />
			Mr. Andhyarujina relied upon the judgment in the case of
			<lb />
			M/s. Hind Construction Contractors Vs. State of Maharashtra, AIR
			<lb />
			1979 Supreme Court 720 in that behalf. The judgment considers how
			<lb />
			time could be taken to be the essence of a given contract. It is held that it
			<lb />
			is the question of the intention of the parties to be gathered from the terms
			<lb />
			of the contract. Even if time is shown to be of the essence in the written
			<lb />
			contract if there are other stipulations in the contract such as fine or
			<lb />
			penalty per day or per week when the work remains unfinished it would
			<lb />
			exclude the inference that time was fundamental to the contract and so of
			<lb />
			the essence of the contract.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			In that case the contract was for the construction of an aqueduct.
			<lb />
			The period of the contract was for 12 months. The Court had to see
			<lb />
			whether the 12 month period so specified was of the essence of the
			<lb />
			contract. If it was not of the essence, as it would be in construction
			<lb />
			contracts, the Court had to see whether the contract had to be completed
			<lb />
			within a reasonable time.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			Referring to Halsbury&apos;s Laws of England, 4 th Edn. Vol.4 paragraph
			<lb />
			1179, the Court accepted that when time was of the essence, the breach
			<lb />
			would entitle the party aggrieved to repudiation. When a sum is payable
			<lb />
			for each week the work remains incomplete after the fixed date, the parties
			<lb />
			must be taken to have contemplated a postponement of the completion. In
			<lb />
			that case by reason of waiver the time which was fixed would cease to be
			<lb />
			applicable. The employer may by notice fix a reasonable time and if the
			<lb />
			contract was still not performed may dismiss the contractor.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			Paragraph 8 of the judgment further holds that the contract may
			<lb />
			exclude an inference of the completion of the contract by a particular date.
			<lb />
			Hence if the contract includes clauses for extension of time of payment by
			<lb />
			fine or penalty per day or per week of the work remaining unfinished it
			<lb />
			would mean that time was not of the essence.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			It cannot be seen how even if the time was not of the essence
			<lb />
			compensation cannot be claimed by the promisee (the respondent herein)
			<lb />
			upon notice being given.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			The judgment does not hold that if time is not of the essence no
			<lb />
			compensation can be claimed. In fact under the 3 rd part of Section 55 even
			<lb />
			after the extended period of time, compensation can be claimed once
			<lb />
			notice is given.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			86.
			<lb />
			The judgment in the case of Hind (Supra) has been followed
			<lb />
			in the case of McDermott International Inc. Vs. Burn Standar Co. Ltd &amp;
			<lb />
			Ors., 2006 Arb W L J 625 (SC) with regard to the aspect of time being of
			<lb />
			the essence. In paragraph 89 of the judgment the case of Arosan
			<lb />
			Enterprises Ltd. Vs. Union of India &amp; Anr., SCC 449 : 1999 Arb W L J
			<lb />
			732 (SC) has been cited showing that the extension of the contract for
			<lb />
			giving a goby to the stipulation as regards the time would require a future
			<lb />
			specified date for delivery or abandonment of the contract.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			It is argued on behalf of the petitioner that 5 days time given by the
			<lb />
			respondent is not reasonable. That would have been so if the petitioner
			<lb />
			was not paid for the approvals obtained by the petitioner during the
			<lb />
			extended period or at least from the date of the notice. That is not the
			<lb />
			case. The petitioner has been paid for the approvals obtained until 11 th
			<lb />
			August, 1999 i.e. after the petitioner had received the notice and also till
			<lb />
			the 5 day period of time expired. The petitioner obtained various
			<lb />
			approvals and charged the respondent for the same as per the terms of the
			<lb />
			contract (which has been considered hereinabove). The award does not
			<lb />
			show that the contention as to unreasonableness of the time granted after
			<lb />
			extension of the contract was argued by the petitioner.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			Section 55 of the ICA would show that the respondent would only be
			<lb />
			entitled to avoid the contract if the time was of the essence and that was so
			<lb />
			claimed by the respondent. The respondent was nevertheless entitled for
			<lb />
			compensation for the loss caused to the respondent by the failure to
			<lb />
			perform within time. If time was of the essence and the respondent
			<lb />
			accepted the performance outside the time period (as has been done in this
			<lb />
			case) the respondent would nonetheless be entitled to compensation from
			<lb />
			the petitioner for the loss occasioned by the failure to perform within the
			<lb />
			time agreed but only upon notice. The notice has been given. The
			<lb />
			respondent can, therefore, claim the compensation for the loss. Since the
			<lb />
			extent of the compensation is specified, the respondent can claim
			<lb />
			compensation only to that extent, without more and without further proof
			<lb />
			of loss. This having been done, the petitioner has been rightly held not
			<lb />
			entitled to be paid what had been withheld by the respondent. That part of
			<lb />
			the award deserves being upheld.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<head>
			Claim No.4 : Entries in the revenue record upon ROU permission for
			<lb />
			private lands
			<lb />
		</head>
		<p>
			87.
			<lb />
			It is the claim of the petitioner in Annexure C to the final bill
			<lb />
			that the petitioner was not required under the specific terms of the contract
			<lb />
			to get entered the respondent&apos;s name in the various revenue records but
			<lb />
			the respondent called upon the petitioner to do so. The petitioner claimed
			<lb />
			that it would charge the respondent for such claim. The respondent
			<lb />
			claimed that that was a part of the contract. The relevant part of the
			<lb />
			contract is shown in the Schedule of Rates titled ROU acquisition. Item
			<lb />
			No.1 of Schedule of Rates relating to ROU acquisition runs thus:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			To carry out coordination, liaison, followup and obtain ROU upto
			<lb />
			30 meters wide strip excluding cost of compensation, completion of
			<lb />
			all land acquisition, activities including manpower, vehicle
			<lb />
			deployment, survey equipment etc. and carrying out of all activities
			<lb />
			though specifically not mentioned here but required to be done for
			<lb />
			completion of ROU acquisition as per Pipeline Act.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			88.
			<lb />
			It is argued on behalf of the petitioner that these permissions
			<lb />
			would, therefore, have to be as per the agreement in terms of the Pipeline
			<lb />
			Act (The Petroleum Minerals and Pipelines (Acquisition of Right of User in
			<lb />
			Land) Act, 1962). The work was akin to acquisition of lands as per the
			<lb />
			Land Acquisition Act, 1882. The scope of work has been shown in Clause
			<lb />
			3.0 of Section 2A of the Contract.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			Clause 3.0 shows the contractor&apos;s scope of work for ROU acquisition
			<lb />
			activities.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			Clause 3.1 enumerates the activities/steps involved. These are
			<lb />
			preliminary scrutiny, verification of land records, publication of
			<lb />
			notification, filing of objections, personal hearing of objections, issue of
			<lb />
			notification, hearing of private parties, declaration of award, grant of
			<lb />
			compensation to land owners and issue of certificates in that behalf.
			<lb />
			Clause 3.1 does not expressly specify that after the land is acquired thus
			<lb />
			and so certified the revenue records would have to be altered to show the
			<lb />
			name of the respondent.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			However Clause 3.2 specifies that the activities/steps include jobs
			<lb />
			required to be completed directly or indirectly for completion of acquisition
			<lb />
			activities as per the Pipelines Act, though specifically not mentioned in the
			<lb />
			scope of the work.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			Under Clause 4.1 revenue charges, statutory fees, compensation
			<lb />
			charges etc. were payable by the respondent. Other expenditure in
			<lb />
			connection with ROU acquisition was to be borne by the petitioner. The
			<lb />
			necessary formalities and paper work was also to be done by the petitioner.
			<lb />
			This was to be as per the PP Act or the guidelines of the authorities or the
			<lb />
			respondent. It has to be seen whether the expenditure to be borne for
			<lb />
			entering the respondent&apos;s name in the revenue record would be &quot;other
			<lb />
			expenditure in connection with&quot; the ROU acquisition. Once it is seen that
			<lb />
			the necessary entries must be made in the government records as a
			<lb />
			condition subsequent to the acquisition for completing the acquisition
			<lb />
			activities, the expenditure incurred for that purpose would fall within the
			<lb />
			term &quot;all other expenditure in connection with&quot; the ROU acquisition.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			Clause 4.7 of the Contract also specifies that all infrastructural and
			<lb />
			administrative facilities would be provided by the contractor thought not
			<lb />
			specifically mentioned in the bid.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			Clause 4.8 amplifies this provision. It states that the scope of the
			<lb />
			work of the contractor includes all activities required to be done not only
			<lb />
			directly but also indirectly and includes the associated expenditure/ costs
			<lb />
			involved inter alia in item 4.1 which would in turn include the expenditure
			<lb />
			in connection with the ROU acquisition.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			89.
			<lb />
			Mr. Andhyarujina argued that the petitioner&apos;s work was only to
			<lb />
			obtain the ROU acquisition in terms of the Pipeline Act and not to deal
			<lb />
			with the title of the respondent. Mr. Sancheti argued that the acquisition
			<lb />
			would require the clearance of the title which can be reflected only in the
			<lb />
			government records and would, therefore, be included in the work of
			<lb />
			acquisition in the contract.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			90.
			<lb />
			The provision with regard to entering the name of the
			<lb />
			respondent in the government records is not a part of the acquisition under
			<lb />
			the PP Act. However any acquiring body would require, as a necessary
			<lb />
			condition subsequent to the acquisition, the government record showing its
			<lb />
			right. The pipeline is laid under the land. Mr. Sancheti stated that though
			<lb />
			the private owners would continue to have title in respect of the land, the
			<lb />
			fact of the pipeline being laid underneath the land would be required to be
			<lb />
			shown as a necessary incident of the land in case of any transfer for the
			<lb />
			knowledge of the subsequent transferee. Consequently even if the
			<lb />
			petitioner had not carried out any work in respect of the recording of the
			<lb />
			entries in the Khasaras with regard to the pipeline, the respondent itself
			<lb />
			would have had to do this within a reasonable time of acquisition and
			<lb />
			before third party rights could be created by the owners of the land
			<lb />
			through which the pipeline ran. Mr. Sancheti drew attention of the Court
			<lb />
			to the fact that in the government records (i.e. in Maharashtra) the other
			<lb />
			rights (brj gDd) are mentioned in the 7/12 extract. The entries were
			<lb />
			required to be made in that behalf. The purpose would be the information
			<lb />
			to all concerned in future about what the land contained within it.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			91.
			<lb />
			It would seem that the work in this behalf is rather huge. The
			<lb />
			petitioner would be entitled to payment in respect thereof at least in terms
			<lb />
			of quantum meruit if not otherwise provided in the contract. Mr. Sancheti,
			<lb />
			therefore, showed how it was provided under the aforesaid clauses of the
			<lb />
			contract that all such work would have to be done. Indeed the payment to
			<lb />
			be made to the petitioner under the contract also runs in crores of rupees.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			92.
			<lb />
			It would, therefore, have to be seen whether the terms of the
			<lb />
			contract notified the petitioner so as to include that in his bid. Clause 43
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			(ii) under the chapter of certificates and payment in Section VI with regard
			<lb />
			to the Schedule of Rates and payment shows this aspect. The Schedule of
			<lb />
			Rates showed the ambit of the work under the contract, the number of
			<lb />
			approvals required and called upon the petitioner to make his bid in that
			<lb />
			regard.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			Clause 43(ii) shows that the petitioner as the contractor would be
			<lb />
			taken to have known the nature, scope, magnitude and the expenditure of
			<lb />
			the work and materials required under the contract though the contract
			<lb />
			document may not fully and precisely furnish them. The petitioner has
			<lb />
			been specifically notified to make such provision in the Schedule of Rates
			<lb />
			as he may consider necessary to cover the costs of all such items of work
			<lb />
			which are reasonable and necessary to complete the works. Further the
			<lb />
			clause shows that the generality of the provision would not be deemed to
			<lb />
			limit what is not expressly stated as the work that the contractor shall do or
			<lb />
			perform without addition of payment and without extra charges and that
			<lb />
			all such work would be taken to be covered by the Schedule of Rates.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			93.
			<lb />
			The petitioner claimed extra payment for the work of updating
			<lb />
			the revenue records as per Clause 47 of the Contract. Clause 47 runs
			<lb />
			thus:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			NOTICE OF CLAIMS FOR ADDITIONAL PAYMENT :
			<lb />
			Should the contractor consider that he is entitled to any extra
			<lb />
			payment or compensation or to make any claims whatsoever in
			<lb />
			respect of the works, he shall forthwith give notice in writing to the
			<lb />
			EngineerinCharge that he claims extra payment and/or
			<lb />
			compensation. Such notice shall be given to the EngineerinCharge
			<lb />
			within two days from the ordering of any work of happening of any
			<lb />
			event upon which the contractor bases such claims and such notice
			<lb />
			shall contain full particulars of the nature of such claim with full
			<lb />
			details and amount claimed. Failure on part of the contractor to
			<lb />
			put forward any claim with the necessary particulars as above
			<lb />
			within the time above shall be an absolute waiver thereof. No
			<lb />
			omissions by the Owner to reject any such claim and no delay in
			<lb />
			dealing therewith shall be waiver by the Owner of any rights in
			<lb />
			respect thereof.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			94.
			<lb />
			Under Clause 47 of the Contract the petitioner had to give
			<lb />
			notice of carrying out any work for which he would claim extra payment or
			<lb />
			compensation within 2 days of the work being carried out to the engineer
			<lb />
			incharge, failing which the claim would be taken to be waived under
			<lb />
			Clause 29.2 of the Contract though failure by the owner or the contractor
			<lb />
			to enforce performance of the terms would not constitute a waiver.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			95.
			<lb />
			The petitioner has informed the respondent of the work in this
			<lb />
			behalf by its letter dated 18.07.1998. The letter shows that the ROU was
			<lb />
			to be recorded in Khasras of 253 villages in about 6000 survey numbers
			<lb />
			which was a tremendous job instructed to be carried out though not within
			<lb />
			the terms of the contract. The letter shows that the work was in progress
			<lb />
			and has been completed in 3 tehsils. The petitioner has at that juncture
			<lb />
			claimed an expenditure of Rs.5000/per km of the length of the pipeline
			<lb />
			route which was in Madhya Pradesh.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			96.
			<lb />
			Clause 47 relates to the additional payment of compensation
			<lb />
			sought by the contractor. In such a case the contractor is required to give
			<lb />
			notice in writing to the engineerincharge. The notice has to be given
			<lb />
			within two days from the date the work is ordered or when any event
			<lb />
			happens. If that is not made the claim for extra payment for compensation
			<lb />
			would be taken to be waived. Mr. Sancheti would argue that this is a
			<lb />
			specific clause for making extra payment. That would be the payment over
			<lb />
			and above the payment specified in the bid of the contractor. He argued
			<lb />
			that this kind of clause in contracts with government bodies would assume
			<lb />
			specific purpose and significance. It would put the government to notice of
			<lb />
			any claim which is sought to be made before it is made. It could result in
			<lb />
			proper supervision of the work for which the extra claim is made, so that
			<lb />
			the government has knowledge of the precise extra work which could be
			<lb />
			supervised upon a notice given. Mr. Sancheti argued that in such contract
			<lb />
			it cannot be that the contractor completes the entire work unknown to the
			<lb />
			government and than claims the amount for the work which cannot be
			<lb />
			inspected or investigated or supervised. He also argued that such a clause
			<lb />
			of contractual waiver should be construed strictly.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			97.
			<lb />
			Clause 29.2 relates to non waiver of defaults (which is not
			<lb />
			waiver of claims for extra payment of compensation). Under that clause
			<lb />
			failure of the contractor to enforce the performance of the contract or
			<lb />
			exercise the right would not constitute waiver. The clause does not show
			<lb />
			what is the part of the contract of which performance is sought or any
			<lb />
			specific right which is sought to be exercised. It is, therefore, a general
			<lb />
			clause relating to performance and exercise of right. The subtitle shows
			<lb />
			that it relates to defaults. It would, therefore, be default in performance or
			<lb />
			default in the right of the contractor. Mr. Andhyarujina rightly stated that
			<lb />
			there would be a number of trivial breaches and defaults for which there
			<lb />
			could be a right of enforcement of the contract by both the parties but
			<lb />
			which may not have been enforced. The mere non enforcement would not
			<lb />
			constitute waiver and such rights could be enforced under the other
			<lb />
			provisions of the contract. Both these contentions would show that Clause
			<lb />
			29.2 is a general clause. A specific clause would prevail over a general
			<lb />
			clause for granting rights to the contracting parties. Hence Clause 29.2
			<lb />
			cannot be taken to be an exception to Clause 47 because if it were, Clause
			<lb />
			47 would be entirely obliterated and this would be aside from the fact that
			<lb />
			both these clauses operate in different fields; Clause 29.2 for non waiver
			<lb />
			of defaults and Clause 47 being the claim for additional payment which
			<lb />
			would be waived if not made according to the strict terms of Clause 47.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			98.
			<lb />
			The petitioner&apos;s claim is made for the first time in the letter of
			<lb />
			the petitioner dated 18.07.1998. The letter shows that the ROU/ROW
			<lb />
			work of the contract was nearing completion. It shows that the right of use
			<lb />
			of land was to be recorded in the Khasaras of 253 villages in 6000 survey
			<lb />
			numbers. That work was completed in 2 regions and 3 tehasils. The
			<lb />
			remainder of the work was in progress. The letter related to the subject of
			<lb />
			fixation of rates for implementation of ROU/ROW in government records.
			<lb />
			Reading of the letter shows that the claim was made well after a lot of
			<lb />
			work in that behalf was done. The amount came to be crystallized by the
			<lb />
			petitioner. The claim was not made within 2 days or any time thereabouts.
			<lb />
			Mr. Sancheti rightly argued that it would appear that the claim was made
			<lb />
			months, or even years, after the work commenced and after the petitioner
			<lb />
			was instructed to carry out the work which the petitioner claimed was not
			<lb />
			covered in the contract. Further he argued that merely writing such a
			<lb />
			letter and relying upon such a letter would not constitute evidence or
			<lb />
			substantiation of what is stated in the letter. Hence though the petitioner
			<lb />
			stated that he had done such work, that work is not substantiated by oral
			<lb />
			or documentary evidence, the petitioner having led no evidence to state
			<lb />
			that he had indeed got the name of the respondent recorded in the
			<lb />
			government records in respect of lands through which the pipeline was laid
			<lb />
			and not even produced the documentary evidence contained in the record
			<lb />
			of rights itself of the survey numbers of the various regions and tehasils
			<lb />
			where the entries in the Khasaras were made.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			99.
			<lb />
			Clause 47 would contemplate only extra payment and
			<lb />
			compensation for the work which is ordered later or which arises upon the
			<lb />
			happening of any right. The payment for the remainder of the work which
			<lb />
			would be directly or indirectly as specified in the contract and which would
			<lb />
			be reasonable and necessary to be done to complete the contract would
			<lb />
			have to be included in the Schedule of Rates. Consequently it is for the
			<lb />
			Court to see what would be such reasonable and necessary work to be
			<lb />
			carried out upon the acquisition. The document of clear title would show
			<lb />
			only that the pipeline is running through the land, which aside from the
			<lb />
			title of the land owner, would be a necessary expedient to the contract.
			<lb />
			The test would be that even if it is not carried out by the petitioner, it
			<lb />
			would have to be carried out by the respondent. The ambit of the contract
			<lb />
			would, therefore, show that though the main work was specific in Clause
			<lb />
			3.1, the further work which is reasonable and necessary to complete the
			<lb />
			entire work of acquisition cannot be taken to be excluded. This would be
			<lb />
			apparent also from Clause 3.2 which immediately follows Clause 3.1 and
			<lb />
			specifies that the activities(steps) would include the jobs required to be
			<lb />
			completed directly or indirectly for completion of the ROU activities though
			<lb />
			specifically not mentioned in the scope of work. Consequently it is seen
			<lb />
			that the main activities are specified in Clause 3.1. The other indirect
			<lb />
			activities are included in Clause 3.2. Both are required for the completion
			<lb />
			of the acquisition activities. Reading this clause along with Clause 43(ii)
			<lb />
			would show that since the further indirect jobs are also included in the
			<lb />
			contract, the petitioner was required and specifically notified to include
			<lb />
			that in the schedule of payment at the time of the bid.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			100.
			<lb />
			Viewed from another angle also it may be stated that the fact
			<lb />
			that tenders were invited and the petitioner&apos;s bid was accepted, the parties
			<lb />
			would be bound by the offer and the acceptance. The petitioner&apos;s bid
			<lb />
			without the various claims now made would be taken to be grossly
			<lb />
			overrated. The bids of others which would have been higher may not have
			<lb />
			been accepted. It would be grossly unjust and unfair to the bidders who
			<lb />
			were not accepted if the respondent would have to pay much higher than
			<lb />
			what was thought to be the expenditure expected to be incurred under the
			<lb />
			contract. It would be improper if after a particular bid is accepted (which
			<lb />
			would be essentially dependent upon its quantum) the government
			<lb />
			corporation is required to incur far greater additional expenditure. Such
			<lb />
			act cannot be countenanced on the part of government body using public
			<lb />
			funds.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			101.
			<lb />
			Consequently though it is correct that the petitioner was to be
			<lb />
			paid and that work could not have been expected to be done gratis, the
			<lb />
			petitioner was indeed paid as per its own bid for the work that it did to the
			<lb />
			extent of Rs. 8.57 Cr.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			102.
			<lb />
			The learned Arbitrator has considered each of these
			<lb />
			contentions. He has concluded that the further amount is not payable
			<lb />
			because under the terms of the contract and the PP Act it was included.
			<lb />
			Hence the conclusion that the petitioner cannot be paid further is a very
			<lb />
			possible conclusion of the learned Arbitrator based upon reading and
			<lb />
			interpretation of the aforesaid clauses of the contract which cannot be
			<lb />
			interfered with in this petition.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			103.
			<lb />
			The learned Arbitrator has observed that the petitioner carried
			<lb />
			out the activity without raising the claim under Clause 47 and was,
			<lb />
			therefore, barred from making such a claim. Mr. Andhyarujina would
			<lb />
			argue that Clause 47 is void under Section 28(b) of the Indian Contract
			<lb />
			Act, 1872. Section 28 of the ICA runs thus:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			28. Agreements in restraint of legal proceedings, void. -Every
			<lb />
			agreement, -
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(a) by which any party thereto is restricted absolutely from enforcing
			<lb />
			his rights under or in respect of any contract, by the usual legal
			<lb />
			proceedings in the ordinary tribunals, or which limits the time within
			<lb />
			which he may thus enforce his rights; or
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(b) which extinguishes the rights of any party thereto, or discharges
			<lb />
			any party thereto from any liability, under or in respect of any contract
			<lb />
			on the expiry of a specified period so as to restrict any party from
			<lb />
			enforcing his rights, is void to that extent.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			It was argued that the amendment to section 28 of the ICA by Act I
			<lb />
			of 1997 dated 08.01.1997 incorporating clause &apos;b&apos; in Section 28 would
			<lb />
			govern the petitioner&apos;s case. Mr. Andhyarujina drew a comparison between
			<lb />
			Section 28(a) and 28(b).
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			Section 28 (a) applies when the time to enforce a right under a
			<lb />
			contract is limited.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			Section 28 (b) applies when the right of contractual party is
			<lb />
			extinguished which would restrict him from enforcing his rights under such
			<lb />
			contract or the other party to the contract is discharged.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			Both the aforesaid contracts are void to the extent of the limitation
			<lb />
			of time and the extinguishment of right or the discharge from liability.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			104.
			<lb />
			Section 28 as it was prior to the amendment of 1997 related to
			<lb />
			a complete ban on filing legal proceedings or limiting the time of
			<lb />
			limitation. In contracts where there is no complete ban or limiting the
			<lb />
			limitation period or suing also there were clauses relating to certain acts
			<lb />
			having to be done by certain parties to the contracts, failing which the right
			<lb />
			of that party would be extinguished and the liability of the other party
			<lb />
			would be discharged. Those kind of clauses which did not limit the
			<lb />
			limitation to sue were held to be valid in a number of judgments. The
			<lb />
			legislature sought to bring such transactions also within the purview of
			<lb />
			Section 28 of the ICA to declare them void. Why that was so done could be
			<lb />
			ascertained only from the Statement of Objects and Reasons (SOR). It
			<lb />
			would, therefore, be worthwhile to see SOR showing the gazetted
			<lb />
			amendment which came into force from 08.01.1997 under Act I of 1997.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			105.
			<lb />
			The Statement of Objects and Reasons runs thus:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			STATEMENT OF OBJECTS AND REASONS
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			The Law Commission of India has recommended in its 97 th report
			<lb />
			that section 28 of the Indian Contract Act, 1872 may be amended
			<lb />
			so that the anomalous situation created by the existing section may
			<lb />
			be rectified. It has been held by the courts that the said section 28
			<lb />
			shall invalidate only a clause in any agreement which restricts any
			<lb />
			party thereto from enforcing his rights absolutely or which limits
			<lb />
			the time within which he may enforce his rights. The courts have,
			<lb />
			however, held that this section shall not come into operation when
			<lb />
			the contractual term spells out an extinction of the right of a party
			<lb />
			to sue or spells out the discharge of a party from all liability in
			<lb />
			respect of the claim. What is thus hit by section 28 is an agreement
			<lb />
			relinquishing the remedy only i.e. where the timelimit specified in
			<lb />
			the agreement is shorter than the period of limitation provided by
			<lb />
			law. A distinction is assumed to exist between remedy and right
			<lb />
			and this distinction is the basis of the present position under which
			<lb />
			a clause barring a remedy is void, but a clause extinguishing the
			<lb />
			rights is valid. This approach may be sound in theory but, in
			<lb />
			practice it causes serious hardship and might even be abused.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			2. It is felt that section 28 of the Indian Contract Act, 1872 should
			<lb />
			be amended as it harms the interests of the consumer dealing with
			<lb />
			big corporations and causes serious hardship to those who are
			<lb />
			economically disadvantaged.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			3. The Bill seeks to achieve the above objects.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			106.
			<lb />
			This would show that there was an anomalous situation
			<lb />
			created upon the interpretation of Section 28 as it then prevailed. That
			<lb />
			was under Section 28(a) cited above. The SOR states that it has been held
			<lb />
			by the Courts that the unamended Section 28 would invalidate only a
			<lb />
			clause which would restrict the party from absolutely enforcing its rights or
			<lb />
			from limiting the time to sue. The SOR further states that the Courts have
			<lb />
			held that this section would not come into operation when any contractual
			<lb />
			term set out the extinction of right to sue or a discharge of a party from the
			<lb />
			liability when sued. The legislature considered that, therefore, only when
			<lb />
			a remedy was relinquished, the agreement would be hit by Section 28.
			<lb />
			This would be on the basis of reasonableness of agreements. However the
			<lb />
			legislature thought that though this would be sound in theory it caused
			<lb />
			serious hardship to parties and could be abused specially if they were
			<lb />
			consumers dealing with large corporations. The legislature, therefore, did
			<lb />
			the act of power balancing. The law came to be amended. The amended
			<lb />
			law, therefore, caused all contracts where the remedy was relinquished as
			<lb />
			also where the right to sue was extinguished or a discharge was claimed.
			<lb />
			All the aforesaid 3 types of agreements would be void and, therefore,
			<lb />
			unenforceable under the amended law.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			107.
			<lb />
			The law as amended came up for consideration in the case of
			<lb />
			M/s. Chander Kant &amp; Co. Vs. The Vice Chairman, DDA in Arbitration
			<lb />
			Petition No. 246 of 2005 by the Division Bench of the Delhi High Court
			<lb />
			considered this point of law. It considered the law pre and post
			<lb />
			amendment. That would indeed show the changed legal position and the
			<lb />
			extinction of the section to contracts extinguishing right and discharging
			<lb />
			the liability. In that case the period of limitation of 90 days was to be
			<lb />
			considered. The relevant clause runs thus:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			It is also a term of the contract that if the contractor (s) does/do
			<lb />
			not make any demand for arbitration in respect of any claim (s) in
			<lb />
			writing within 90 days of receiving the intimation from the
			<lb />
			EngineerinCharge that the Bill is ready for payment, the claim (s)
			<lb />
			of the contractor (s) will be deemed to have been waived and
			<lb />
			absolutely barred and the Delhi Development Authority shall be
			<lb />
			discharged and released of all liabilities under the contract in
			<lb />
			respect of those claims.
		</item>
		<lb />
		<p>
			It related to the demand for arbitration to be made within 90 days of
			<lb />
			receiving the intimation of the EngineerinCharge in respect of a bill which
			<lb />
			was ready for payment. The contractor would be taken to have waived his
			<lb />
			right to receive the payment thereafter which would be absolutely barred
			<lb />
			and the corporation would be discharged and released of all the liabilities
			<lb />
			in respect of those claims. The Court considered the legislation as also the
			<lb />
			precedents prior to the amendment in para 7 of the Judgment. The Court
			<lb />
			considered the amended law and the precedents after the amendment in
			<lb />
			para 8 of the judgment. It would be material to see that that law would
			<lb />
			apply post amendment. The Court has set out 4 specific cases in which
			<lb />
			clauses showing a period of time during which the right would be
			<lb />
			extinguished or the liability discharged have been held to be not valid in
			<lb />
			view of Section 28 (b) of the Contract Act. The Court followed the earlier
			<lb />
			decision in the case of Explore Computers Pvt. Ltd. Vs. Cals Ltd. 131
			<lb />
			(2006) DLT 477 which considered the preamendment Supreme Court
			<lb />
			decision in the case of National Insurance Co. Ltd. Vs. Sujir Ganesh
			<lb />
			Nayak &amp; Co. 1997 4 SCC 366 and held that the scope of Section 28 was
			<lb />
			widened and accordingly the distinction carved out by the earlier legal
			<lb />
			pronouncements was held not good law.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			That was a case of bank guarantee. That case set out a period of one
			<lb />
			month from the expiry of bank guarantee within which the right of the
			<lb />
			plaintiff to institute any legal proceeding would be extinguished. Hence in
			<lb />
			a case of a bank guarantee the Court held that such a plea would apply in
			<lb />
			the face of the amended Section 28 and the defendant could not be
			<lb />
			discharged from the liability nor could the right of the plaintiff be
			<lb />
			extinguished by such a clause.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			This judgment was followed by another Division Bench of the Delhi
			<lb />
			High Court in the case of DDA Vs. Pandit Construction Co.
			<lb />
			MANU/DEL/1714/2012. In that case Clause 25 of the Contract of DDA
			<lb />
			for appointment of the arbitrator within a period of 90 days from the date
			<lb />
			the dispute arose came to be considered. The Court considered the
			<lb />
			amended Section 28 in para 8 of the judgment holding that in both the
			<lb />
			instances under the section the contract would be void. In paragraph 11 of
			<lb />
			the judgment the Court considered the retroactivity of a legislation and
			<lb />
			referred the case of Chander Kant (Supra).
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			In that judgment the Court has also referred to the case of National
			<lb />
			Insurance (Supra) considered in the case of Chander Kant (Supra) and
			<lb />
			also the case of Continental Construction Ltd. Vs. Food Corporation of
			<lb />
			India, which shall be considered presently. The Court distinguished these
			<lb />
			cases in which the cause of action had arisen prior to the amendment and
			<lb />
			the amendment was not considered.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			108.
			<lb />
			The judgment has been further followed in the case of Avinash
			<lb />
			Sharam Vs. Municipal Corporation of Delhi, 2007 (4) ARBLR 147
			<lb />
			(Delhi) relating to the same clause by the learned Single Judge holding
			<lb />
			that the amended section deprived the party to the contract (in that case
			<lb />
			the contractor) of a very valuable right to claim the amount due to him and
			<lb />
			holding such a contract void.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			109.
			<lb />
			There has been a later Division Bench judgment of the Bombay
			<lb />
			High Court being the case of M/s. Indusing Bank Ltd. Vs. Union of India
			<lb />
			&amp; Ors. in Appeal No. 258 of 2008 dated 20 th April, 2011 in which the
			<lb />
			period of the validity of the bank guarantee was set out. In that case the
			<lb />
			claim was to be made within 3 months of the validity of the bank
			<lb />
			guarantee. The claim having not been made, the bank claimed to be
			<lb />
			relieved and discharged from its liability under the bank guarantee and
			<lb />
			claimed that nothing was payable to the plaintiff. The learned Single
			<lb />
			Judge considered the law under Section 28 and held that the bank
			<lb />
			guarantee was void as it laid down the period of 90 days during which a
			<lb />
			legal claim had to be made.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			The Court considered that the bank guarantee was to remain in force
			<lb />
			until a specific day and any claim under the bank guarantee had to be
			<lb />
			made within 3 months therefrom. If no demand was made, the claim
			<lb />
			under the bank guarantee could not be made. The Court observed that the
			<lb />
			respondent&apos;s right to make the claim or demand against the bank under the
			<lb />
			said bank guarantee was to be perfected only if the claim or demand was
			<lb />
			lodged before 90 days period.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			The Court considered the provision of unamended Section 28 and
			<lb />
			the judgment of the Supreme Court as also other Courts thereunder. The
			<lb />
			Court set out the judgment of the Supreme Court in the case of National
			<lb />
			Insurance (supra) which was also considered by the learned Division
			<lb />
			Bench of the Delhi High Court to set out and amplify the distinction that
			<lb />
			was carved out in that judgment pre amendment. Based upon the decision
			<lb />
			of the Supreme Court in the pre amendment case, the learned Division
			<lb />
			Bench of the Bombay High Court drew a parallel. The Supreme Court
			<lb />
			judgment set out the distinction between the right to enforce and the
			<lb />
			forfeiture or the waiver of rights as also the curtailment of limitation which
			<lb />
			was held to be not permissible and the extinction of the rights which was
			<lb />
			permissible and enforceable. The Division Bench of the Bombay High
			<lb />
			Court, therefore, considered the law before the amendment of 1997 and
			<lb />
			after the amendment. Having done so it set out the distinction between
			<lb />
			the right to adopt the remedy (the right to sue) and the restriction of
			<lb />
			enforcement of an accrued right. After observing that both were declared
			<lb />
			void, it drew the distinction and held that only the former was void and the
			<lb />
			latter was not affected by Section 28(b).
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			It further referred to the decision of the Supreme Court in the case of
			<lb />
			Food Corporation of India Vs. New India Assurance Co. Ltd. 1999 (3)
			<lb />
			SCC 324 which was also pre amendment and consequently showed the
			<lb />
			distinction. Extensively quoting the Supreme Court in the case of Food
			<lb />
			Corporation of India (supra) the Division Bench of the Bombay High
			<lb />
			Court held that such a clause did not affect &quot;the right of the respondents to
			<lb />
			enforce their rights&quot; by approaching a Court of Law within the normal
			<lb />
			period of limitation if the respondents assert their right or make a demand
			<lb />
			or claim with the bank within the period mentioned in the bank guarantee.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			Consequently it held that in a case of a bank guarantee the assertion
			<lb />
			of right must be within the period mentioned though the action in law may
			<lb />
			be taken as per the law of limitation. Thereupon the Division Bench of the
			<lb />
			Bombay high Court set aside the judgment of the Single Judge which had
			<lb />
			held that such a clause was void under Section 28(b) of the Contract Act.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			This judgment has not considered the judgment of the Delhi High
			<lb />
			Court in the case of Chander Kant (Supra) as also Avinash (Supra) and as
			<lb />
			per incurium to that extent.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			110.
			<lb />
			Consequently it can be seen that Clause 47 thus falls foul of
			<lb />
			Section 28(b) of the ICA and would be void to the extent it prescribes the
			<lb />
			time limit of 2 days to give notice for claiming any extra payment.
			<lb />
			Consequently the petitioner would be required to give notice but of a
			<lb />
			reasonable period to inform the respondent why he would need extra
			<lb />
			payment for any particular work done. Of course, the petitioner would
			<lb />
			have to prove the actual work done to be able to claim any extra payment.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			111.
			<lb />
			Mr. Andhyarujina drew my attention to the case of National
			<lb />
			Thermal Power Corporation Ltd. Vs. WIG Brothers Builders &amp;
			<lb />
			Engineers Ltd., ILR (2009) IV Delhi 663 which was the case of a contract
			<lb />
			between a government corporation and a private company in which an
			<lb />
			engineer had to be appointed. The parties had to first refer their dispute to
			<lb />
			the engineer. The decision of the engineer would become final and binding
			<lb />
			unless questioned by either party for which an arbitrator was provided.
			<lb />
			The engineer was never appointed. The condition precedent was not
			<lb />
			satisfied. It was held that when the appointment was not made by
			<lb />
			government authority which provided for the initial adjudication of the
			<lb />
			dispute by the engineer, the government undertaking could not take up a
			<lb />
			contention that the dispute could not be referred directly to an arbitrator
			<lb />
			and that a party cannot by its own act or omission prevent another from
			<lb />
			having the dispute resolved by arbitration. Upon the contention that the
			<lb />
			contract was frustrated, Mr. Andhyarujina would argue that since there was
			<lb />
			no engineer incharge, Clause 47 would not come into effect and the
			<lb />
			question of giving two days notice to the engineerincharge cannot be
			<lb />
			enforced.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			112.
			<lb />
			The real substance of Clause 47 is in view of the entire
			<lb />
			contract between the parties which required the petitioner to make a bid
			<lb />
			upon a tender floated by the respondent to give the allinclusive price for
			<lb />
			all the acts to be done directly or indirectly under the contract. Hence if
			<lb />
			the petitioner considered that an act which the petitioner was called upon
			<lb />
			by the respondent required any extra payment to be made, notice had to be
			<lb />
			given. It had to be given to the engineerincharge. If not, it had to be
			<lb />
			given to any other such officer or to the respondent itself. This would
			<lb />
			enable the respondent to know the kind of work that the petitioner was to
			<lb />
			do or had done and would be able to inspect it at the time it is done. It
			<lb />
			was, therefore, for the benefit of both the parties. The petitioner would be
			<lb />
			able to show the respondent what work it was to embark upon. The
			<lb />
			respondent would know the work was being done or which was to be done
			<lb />
			almost when it began. Consequently the petitioner would not be able to
			<lb />
			make a false claim upon work not done and stated to be done for which it
			<lb />
			considered that it was entitled to the extra payment and the respondent
			<lb />
			would not be able to refute the extra payment to be made if the work
			<lb />
			entitled the petitioner to such extra payment. Consequently in the absence
			<lb />
			of the engineerincharge the entire Clause 47 relating to claims for
			<lb />
			additional payment cannot be wiped off.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			113.
			<lb />
			Even its voidability is statutorily only to the extent the contract
			<lb />
			prescribed a time limit after which the petitioner&apos;s right would be
			<lb />
			extinguished and the respondent&apos;s liability would be discharged -the
			<lb />
			entire contract is not rendered void even under Section 28 of the ICA.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			114.
			<lb />
			This has been considered in the NTPC case itself to which my
			<lb />
			attention has been drawn by Mr. Sancheti. In paragraph 26 of the
			<lb />
			judgment upon holding the obligatory duty of party to the contract in not
			<lb />
			taking advantage of its own act or omission to claim frustration of the
			<lb />
			contract, it has been further observed that the remaining intention of the
			<lb />
			parties must be effectuated. The observation runs thus :
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			In the absence of the availability of the Engineer, the rest of the
			<lb />
			agreement must be given effect to, as that would be consistent with
			<lb />
			the intention of the parties. This interpretation is in accordance with
			<lb />
			the well accepted principle of interpretation of documents that the
			<lb />
			intention of the parties, to the extent possible, must be given effect to
			<lb />
			and each and every term of the contract must be implemented.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			115.
			<lb />
			In this case also even for want of an engineerincharge the
			<lb />
			remainder of Clause 47 would have to be effectuated. The petitioner
			<lb />
			would have to give notice to the respondent company. The respondent
			<lb />
			company would be put to the notice of the intended claim. The notice may
			<lb />
			not be of two days, but a reasonable notice. The petitioner has, in fact,
			<lb />
			notified the respondent albeit much after two days in making a claim for
			<lb />
			extra payment for obtaining the revenue records altered (as also for
			<lb />
			making the executive summary which shall be considered presently). The
			<lb />
			respondent has refuted that claim. The clause is reasonably complied by
			<lb />
			both parties. Consequently the adjudicating authority would decide
			<lb />
			whether the petitioner would be entitled to extra payment or not. The
			<lb />
			petitioner would be entitled to extra payment if the work did not fall
			<lb />
			within the scope of the contract; it would not be entitled for extra payment
			<lb />
			if the work was within the scope of the contract. The real determining
			<lb />
			aspect is, therefore, if the work is within the scope of the contract.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			116.
			<lb />
			Mr. Sancheti also argued that Clause 47 does not limit the
			<lb />
			time for limitation but is only to give notice. If the petitioner did not give
			<lb />
			notice, the petitioner would have to otherwise prove how it was entitled to
			<lb />
			extra payment. If the petitioner gave notice and the work merited extra
			<lb />
			payment respondent would have to make additional payment.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			117.
			<lb />
			Mr. Sancheti drew my attention to the judgment in the case of
			<lb />
			State of Madhya Pradesh Vs. Mittal &amp; Company, Dholpur, Rajasthan,
			<lb />
			MANU/MP/0037/1997. That was also a case of similar contract between
			<lb />
			state government and a private party. One of the clauses provided a time
			<lb />
			limit for unforeseen claims under which the claims which were not
			<lb />
			foreseen by the parties could not be made unless it was made in writing to
			<lb />
			that engineerincharge within one month of the cause for such a claim
			<lb />
			occurring. It was held that this would exclude claims arising out of the
			<lb />
			breach of the contract or claims flowing from the terms of the contract.
			<lb />
			Such clause was not held hit by the unamended section 28 of the ICA
			<lb />
			despite the period of one month granted to make the claim in writing in
			<lb />
			that case.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			A similar preamendment case of State of Rajasthan Vs. Chandra
			<lb />
			Mohan Chopra, AIR 1971 Rajasthan 229 (V 58 C 50) which was of a
			<lb />
			similar contract, such clause was interpreted. In that case also the chief
			<lb />
			engineer was to decide the amount if penalty levied. The Chief engineer
			<lb />
			did not determine the compensation. It was held that the right to fix the
			<lb />
			compensation was waived and hence no penalty could be recovered.
			<lb />
			Clause 47 could be similarly interpreted despite the amendment to Section
			<lb />
			28 of the ICA.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			118.
			<lb />
			It may be mentioned that Mr. Sancheti argued that if the
			<lb />
			petitioner is entitled to extra payment for having the revenue records
			<lb />
			altered (or for providing the executive summary of work done, which shall
			<lb />
			be considered later) it would be upon the fact that it was outside the scope
			<lb />
			of the contract. In that case the petitioner could not claim any amount
			<lb />
			within the contract. The petitioner would have to be granted such
			<lb />
			amounts only by way of quantum meruit. The petitioner would require to
			<lb />
			litigate to get such claims; they could not be granted in arbitration. The
			<lb />
			learned arbitrator would have to grant the claim only as per the contract
			<lb />
			and not claims outside the contract in arbitration. Having seen that the
			<lb />
			work forms the part of the contract, all those arguments and contentions
			<lb />
			became purely academic.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			119.
			<lb />
			The arbitrator has held that the respondent showed that the
			<lb />
			work fell within the contract. No further evidence was required. No
			<lb />
			further evidence was led. The claim has been considered upon the terms
			<lb />
			of the contract. Hence the award in this behalf cannot be interfered with.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<head>
			Claim No.5 : NOC for revenue forest (chhote bade zad ke jungle)
			<lb />
		</head>

		<p>
			120.
			<lb />
			This came to be defined, specified and considered in a
			<lb />
			judgment of the Supreme Court for permission being required if any kind
			<lb />
			of construction was to be put up in such forest claimed under Annexure D
			<lb />
			to the final bill dated 09.09.1999.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			121.
			<lb />
			The tender was floated for the contract between the parties on
			<lb />
			4 th October, 1996. The Supreme Court judgment is dated 12 th December,
			<lb />
			1996. The contract was entered into by the parties pursuant to the tender
			<lb />
			on 30 th December, 1996 (after the judgment was passed). The parties were
			<lb />
			yet unaware of the Supreme Court judgment and the requirement of
			<lb />
			obtaining NOC for what was termed as revenue forests. The parties
			<lb />
			obtained the intergovernmental letter of the Ministry of Environment and
			<lb />
			Forests (MEF) on 27 th October, 1997, consequent upon which they held
			<lb />
			meeting interalia for considering the requirement of the grant of NOC on
			<lb />
			13 th November, 1997. The petitioner has for the first time by its letter
			<lb />
			dated 25 th November, 1997 written about its claim, but not of a specified
			<lb />
			amount. The respondent has by its letter dated 3 rd December, 1997 refuted
			<lb />
			the claim on the ground that the work was within the scope of the
			<lb />
			contract. The petitioner has responded to this letter within two days on 5 th
			<lb />
			December, 1997. Upon the reiteration of the fact that the work was within
			<lb />
			the scope of the contract by the respondent in its letter dated 8 th December,
			<lb />
			1997, the petitioner (incorrectly) refuted that it could be so because it
			<lb />
			arose out of the judgment of the Supreme Court judgment dated 12 th
			<lb />
			December, 1996 which was after the award of the work, but claimed that
			<lb />
			the petitioner could be paid under Item No.1(I) of the Schedule of Rates
			<lb />
			and charged for 412 kms at the rate specified for Item No.1 being
			<lb />
			Rs.30,000/ per km length of the pipeline specified in its letters dated 15 th
			<lb />
			December, 1997 and 27 th January, 1998.
			<lb />
			Thereafter also further
			<lb />
			correspondence ensued but which the Court does not require to go into in
			<lb />
			a petition U/s.34 of the Act.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			122.
			<lb />
			The petitioner raised its claim upon the Supreme Court
			<lb />
			judgment dated 12 th December, 1997 with regard to the revenue forests for
			<lb />
			additional payment as work outside the contract. The claim is made that
			<lb />
			the work is outside the scope of the contract upon the fact that it arose
			<lb />
			from the Supreme Court judgment passed after the contract was executed.
			<lb />
			The aforesaid chronology showed that it was not. Of course, the parties
			<lb />
			came to know about Supreme Court judgment later and had to implement
			<lb />
			it. The case of the petitioner before learned arbitrator was that he was
			<lb />
			required to obtain certificate(s) from the Collector. The petitioner claimed
			<lb />
			that its claim would fall under Item No.1(I) of the Schedule of Rates. The
			<lb />
			petitioner claimed the amount for obtaining the certificates of the Collector
			<lb />
			per km of the pipeline which ran through such revenue forests as
			<lb />
			protected/reserved and other forests or as social forestry (and not per
			<lb />
			crossing as required under Item No.1). Though it is argued before this
			<lb />
			Court that the claim was made under the aforesaid provision, the fact
			<lb />
			remains that the petitioner obtained 9 certificates from the Collectors for
			<lb />
			the entire running length of the pipeline in the 9 districts through which
			<lb />
			the pipeline went. This is made clear from the contentions of the
			<lb />
			petitioner recited in Clause 5.1 of the award. Nevertheless the petitioner
			<lb />
			did make the claim for 412 running kms and claimed @ Rs.50,000/ per
			<lb />
			km in the Statement of Claim (in place of Rs.30,000/ claimed earlier in
			<lb />
			the correspondence) for the 9 certificates obtained by the petitioner.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			123.
			<lb />
			The very certificates would be circumstantial evidence in
			<lb />
			themselves to show that the claim could not fall under Item No.1 (H) or (I)
			<lb />
			but had to fall under Item No.II of the Schedule of Rates being the
			<lb />
			clearance / NOC to be obtained from the authority en route of the pipeline
			<lb />
			other than a crossing. Consequently, the mode for payment would be per
			<lb />
			approval, per district, per authority. The authority from which the 9
			<lb />
			certificates are obtained is the Collector. The other approvals with regard
			<lb />
			to various certificates in the 9 districts through which the pipeline ran are
			<lb />
			also approved by the same authority, the respective Collectors. As per the
			<lb />
			case of the respondent, if the petitioner had to obtain and had obtained
			<lb />
			permissions from any other authority to wit -the MEF, the petitioner
			<lb />
			would have been entitled to payment @ Rs.50,000/ for such 9 certificates.
			<lb />
			The respondent would contend that the petitioner having obtained the
			<lb />
			permission from the same authority was entitled to payment but once per
			<lb />
			district. That payment has been made. Hence the respondent rejected the
			<lb />
			petitioner&apos;s claim for additional payment.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			124.
			<lb />
			The contention of the respondent before the learned arbitrator
			<lb />
			was that obtaining various clearances was within the scope of the contract.
			<lb />
			The respondent has specified this in its letter dated 3 rd December, 1997.
			<lb />
			The petitioner accepted that position and hence obtained Collectors&apos;
			<lb />
			certificate(s) in March -May, 1998. The petitioner made its claim for the
			<lb />
			first time after completion of the entire work and had not claimed it so
			<lb />
			soon as the respondent directed the petitioner to produce the certificates.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			125.
			<lb />
			Mr. Sancheti on behalf of the respondent drew Court&apos;s
			<lb />
			attention to Clause 2.10 of the contract under which the petitioner as the
			<lb />
			contractor was enjoined to complete the work of obtaining statutory
			<lb />
			approvals and clearances and if during the execution of the project some
			<lb />
			more clearances were warranted, it was the obligation of the petitioner to
			<lb />
			discharge such responsibilities without extra compensation. Hence the
			<lb />
			respondent contended that obtaining additional certificate of the Collector
			<lb />
			for the revenue forest was other clearances which were warranted and
			<lb />
			hence fell within the scope of the contract. Consequently the respondent
			<lb />
			claimed in its letter dated 3 rd December, 1997 that for obtaining such
			<lb />
			certificates no additional payment was warranted.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			126.
			<lb />
			The petitioner in fact complied and obtained the required
			<lb />
			certificate(s) of the Collector in March -May, 1998.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			127.
			<lb />
			The petitioner claimed that it was entitled to additional
			<lb />
			payment for such work under Clause 47 of the Contract.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			128.
			<lb />
			The petitioner has notified its claim for additional to
			<lb />
			the respondent in the meeting held on 5 th December, 1997 which is Item
			<lb />
			No.8 in the minutes of the meeting. The item does show a claim made by
			<lb />
			the petitioner for additional time and payment to be considered by the
			<lb />
			respondent. It is not a claim specifically made by the petitioner for any
			<lb />
			specific amount. The claim of the specific amount is made for the first time
			<lb />
			after termination of the contract under the 18 th final bill of the petitioner.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			129.
			<lb />
			The learned arbitrator has considered whilst rejecting claim
			<lb />
			that the petitioner has not seriously disputed the stand of the respondent
			<lb />
			that this work is a part of the job which would mean that it would be
			<lb />
			within the scope of the contract for which the composite rate was agreed.
			<lb />
			Indeed the petitioner obtained the certificates between March and May,
			<lb />
			1998 itself which would justify the observation of the learned Arbitrator.
			<lb />
			The additional charges, if any, payable under Clause 47 would follow if the
			<lb />
			claim is seen to be seen to be such as would entail additional payment to
			<lb />
			be made upon a reasonable notice in that behalf and proof of the claim.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			130.
			<lb />
			The real reason for the petitioner not being given any extra
			<lb />
			payment is that the work did not fall under Item No. 1 and the petitioner
			<lb />
			could not have claimed at the exaggerated rate of Rs.50,000/ per km for
			<lb />
			412 kms of the length of the pipeline. The petitioner&apos;s claim would fall
			<lb />
			under Item No.2 upon the case of the respondent that it was covered in the
			<lb />
			9 approvals of the Collectors of the 9 district. Consequently it would have
			<lb />
			to be considered along with claim No.2 for payment for ROW.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			131.
			<lb />
			The specific case of the respondent under Clause 2.10 of the
			<lb />
			Contract is not reflected in the reasoning of the learned arbitrator and
			<lb />
			appears not to have been considered.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			132.
			<lb />
			What could be the reasons that the arbitrator would give has
			<lb />
			been set out in the judgment in the case of Jagmohan Singh Gujral of
			<lb />
			India Vs. Satish Ashok Sabnis &amp; Anr., 2004(1) Bom.C R 307 which has
			<lb />
			been relied upon by Mr. Andhyrujina. It has been held in the judgment
			<lb />
			that the reasons must be based on the material available to the tribunal. It
			<lb />
			must reflect the consideration of the relevant material and ignore all
			<lb />
			irrelevant material. If the material on record is not considered, the
			<lb />
			findings cannot be stated to be based on sound reasoning and would
			<lb />
			amount to being perverse and consequently be misconduct.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			133.
			<lb />
			This would stand to reason because the reasoning must show
			<lb />
			the mind of the adjudicating authority. The reasoning of claim No.5 does
			<lb />
			not show the consideration of the scope of the contract under Clause 2.10
			<lb />
			or the ambit of Clause 47. Further it ignores the later letters of the
			<lb />
			petitioner claiming that the work was outside the scope of the contract
			<lb />
			because it arose consequent upon the Supreme Court judgment which was
			<lb />
			itself delivered after the award of the work (which was erroneously
			<lb />
			stated). However it considers the petitioner&apos;s acceptance of the work as
			<lb />
			falling within the contract (by not seriously disputing it) as also that it is
			<lb />
			covered by Item No.2 of the Schedule of Rates.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			134.
			<lb />
			The reasoning of the learned arbitrator that the petitioner had
			<lb />
			&quot;not seriously disputed&quot; the stand of the respondent may, therefore, be a
			<lb />
			possible view. Indeed neither had the petitioner refused to act to obtain
			<lb />
			the further certificates nor had the petitioner made a claim of any specific
			<lb />
			amount for what it considered was the new &quot;job&quot;. The actual claim was
			<lb />
			made only in the final 18 th bill dated 09.09.1999. It having been seen to be
			<lb />
			falling under Item No.2 of the Schedule of Rates would be required to be
			<lb />
			considered along with Claim No.2 for payments in respect of ROW. The
			<lb />
			certificates obtained by the petitioner would be required to be seen to
			<lb />
			consider whether they were &quot;approvals&quot; and of which &quot;authority&quot; to
			<lb />
			consider them amongst the approvals obtained to be paid &quot;per approval,
			<lb />
			per authority, per district&quot; being a part of the approximate 475 approvals
			<lb />
			contemplated by the parties. Hence the award in respect of Claim No.5 is
			<lb />
			set aside to that extent.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<head>
			Claim No.6 : Preparation of executive summary
			<lb />
		</head>

		<p>
			135.
			<lb />
			The petitioner claims that the respondent directed the
			<lb />
			petitioner to prepare an executive summary which was outside the terms of
			<lb />
			the contract much later and after execution of a large part of the contract.
			<lb />
			The petitioner informed that it would prepare summary at an additional
			<lb />
			cost. The petitioner claims that this was a massive job relating to 250
			<lb />
			villages and was prepared villagewise and then tehsilwise. The petitioner
			<lb />
			would argue that under Clause 3.15 the progress reports were to be
			<lb />
			submitted fortnightly and what was called for as an executive summary is
			<lb />
			in addition to the progress report for which there is no mention in the
			<lb />
			contract and thus would merit additional payment.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			136.
			<lb />
			The respondent contends that the preparation of the execution
			<lb />
			summary is an integral part of the contract itself. It is argued on behalf of
			<lb />
			the respondent that the summary had to be prepared only for the sake of
			<lb />
			record and would be impliedly required to be prepared even if not
			<lb />
			expressly directed. It was for the petitioner itself to prepare such a
			<lb />
			summary to show the extent of the work done. The respondent relied
			<lb />
			upon the seminal clause in the contract signed by the parties which
			<lb />
			governs the payment to be made to the contractor as per the bid offered by
			<lb />
			the petitioner and accepted by the respondent. The contractor covenanted
			<lb />
			to execute and complete the work and do all other acts and things in the
			<lb />
			contract mentioned or described or which are to be implied therefrom or
			<lb />
			may be reasonably necessary for the completion of the work.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			137.
			<lb />
			The respondent has relied upon and drawn the Court&apos;s
			<lb />
			attention also to Clause 43(ii) which shows that the Schedule of Rates was
			<lb />
			to be inclusive. That clause states that the contractor shall be deemed to
			<lb />
			have known the nature, scope, magnitude and extent of the works and
			<lb />
			materials required, though the contract document may not fully and
			<lb />
			precisely furnished them. Hence he was to make such provision in the
			<lb />
			Schedule of Rates as he would consider necessary to govern all the items of
			<lb />
			work and materials as may be reasonable and necessary to complete the
			<lb />
			work. Further the clause states that the contractor shall do and perform all
			<lb />
			the work though not expressly stated in the contract without additional
			<lb />
			payment or extra charges and that all the charges were governed by the
			<lb />
			Schedule of Rates. Mr. Sancheti would argue that this specification was
			<lb />
			precisely to avoid the contingency of the contractor requiring additional
			<lb />
			payment when jobs specifically required to be done as conditions
			<lb />
			subsequent would arise. In fact it would stand to reason that when a
			<lb />
			tender is floated and bid is accepted, the contract would essentially govern
			<lb />
			all aspects which are reasonable and necessary to complete the work even
			<lb />
			though not stated. If for each aspect additional payment is required to be
			<lb />
			made, the purpose of submitting the bid would be frustrated.
			<lb />
			Consequently only the entirely different items of work if given to the
			<lb />
			contractor would merit additional payment.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			138.
			<lb />
			This aspect is made clear also under Clause 3.2 of the contract
			<lb />
			relating to the scope of work for ROU acquisition As aforesaid
			<lb />
			Clause 3.1 shows the main activities/steps which are required. This would
			<lb />
			show that there would be some ancillary activities or steps also for which
			<lb />
			provision has been made in Clause 3.2. It is specified that the activities
			<lb />
			included jobs required to be completed directly or indirectly for the ROU
			<lb />
			acquisition activities as per the Pipeline Act though not specifically
			<lb />
			mentioned in the scope of work. If there is any work which is to be done
			<lb />
			not for completion of ROU activities as per the Pipeline Act but for a
			<lb />
			completely different purpose, it would necessitate additional payment.
			<lb />
			Such additional payment could be made under Clause 47.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			139.
			<lb />
			The executive summary has been prepared. The petitioner has
			<lb />
			given 6 copies of the summary. The petitioner has charged Rs.1 lac for
			<lb />
			each copy. The learned arbitrator has essentially considered that it forms a
			<lb />
			part of the contract not meriting additional payment.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			140.
			<lb />
			It is contended on behalf of the petitioner that the approvals
			<lb />
			obtained and the jobs carried out were to be categorised in a particular
			<lb />
			manner. It was neither consequential nor necessary to do that job. Yet
			<lb />
			upon the respondent requiring it, the petitioner had done the job and,
			<lb />
			hence would merit additional payment as mentioned in the petitioner&apos;s
			<lb />
			letter dated 4 th March, 1999 in which the petitioner has stated that all
			<lb />
			documentation were handed over to the respondent by July, 1998. The
			<lb />
			petitioner would claim that the respondent has not commented until
			<lb />
			January, 1999 that that work was not as per contract. Consequently the
			<lb />
			specified summary later required by the respondent would be outside the
			<lb />
			scope of the contract for which the petitioner would charge Rs.1 lac for per
			<lb />
			set of documents.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			141.
			<lb />
			The learned Arbitrator has rejected this claim on the ground
			<lb />
			that the summary is not prepared to the satisfaction of the respondent by
			<lb />
			the petitioner and that it was a part of the composite job for which the
			<lb />
			fixed rate was paid by the respondent. The latter reason is in line with all
			<lb />
			the other such claims and must be accepted upon seeing the relevant
			<lb />
			clauses of the contract. Consequently the rejection of this claim is proper.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<head>
			Claim Nos.7 &amp; 8 : Overheads and loss of profits.
			<lb />
		</head>

		<p>
			142.
			<lb />
			The petitioner has accepted that the petitioner could not
			<lb />
			complete the work within stipulated time period and the work was delayed
			<lb />
			beyond the original period from 10 th October, 1997 until 11 th August, 1999.
			<lb />
			The petitioner has claimed the overheads and loss of profits on account of
			<lb />
			prolongation of the work by which the petitioner claims to have been put
			<lb />
			to an extra expenditure as per the details submitted by the petitioner in the
			<lb />
			last 18 th RA bill dated 9 th September, 1999. The petitioner has claimed
			<lb />
			Rs.7.48 Cr of account of overheads and Rs.6.95 Cr on account of loss of
			<lb />
			profits.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			143.
			<lb />
			It would be material to see the conduct of the petitioner in
			<lb />
			claiming the extension of the period in the first place. It was for the
			<lb />
			petitioner to obtain all the approvals within a period of one year. The
			<lb />
			petitioner had admittedly not obtained all the approvals. The petitioner
			<lb />
			itself had applied for extension of time from time to time under the
			<lb />
			correspondence with the respondent relied upon by the petitioner.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			In the letter dated 28 th May, 1997 which was within the specified
			<lb />
			period of the contract the petitioner accepted that it was its responsibility
			<lb />
			to carry out the activities within the time schedule, but for a certain illness
			<lb />
			of some one which was beyond its control.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			In the letter dated 5 th July, 1997 the petitioner has accepted the delay
			<lb />
			and given several reasons for the delay. The reasons set out by the
			<lb />
			petitioner showed the action of third parties for which the petitioner
			<lb />
			claimed no responsibility and sought an extension.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			In the letter dated 27 th September, 1997 the petitioner has again set
			<lb />
			out reasons for the delay of ROW cases which are all claimed to be due to
			<lb />
			acts of third parties.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			Again in the letter dated 28 th September, 1997 the petitioner has
			<lb />
			stated that the work was in progress, at an advanced stage and yet not
			<lb />
			entirely completed and hence would need extension of time limit. The
			<lb />
			petitioner has set out the specified dates of the delays for specific reasons
			<lb />
			which are not attributable to the respondent but to third parties. The
			<lb />
			petitioner has claimed the extension for further 285 days upon the causes
			<lb />
			of delay shown. These letters have been written within the contract period
			<lb />
			for extension of time beyond the contract period.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			144.
			<lb />
			The respondent granted a 45 days extension for the patwari
			<lb />
			strike which was one of the reasons why the petitioner had asked for
			<lb />
			extension of time. By its letter dated 17 th March, 1998 the respondent did
			<lb />
			not grant any further extension.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			145.
			<lb />
			After the contract was terminated on 11 th August, 1999 upon
			<lb />
			the notice dated 6 th August, 1999, the petitioner submitted the last bill on
			<lb />
			9 th September, 1999. Annexure A to that bill was the proposal for the time
			<lb />
			limit extension applied for in the letter dated 27 th September, 1997
			<lb />
			justifying an extension for 285 days. The petitioner stated in the Annexure
			<lb />
			that the work was completed on 11 th August, 1999 (which was as per the
			<lb />
			notice of termination). The petitioner submitted that the delay not due to
			<lb />
			petitioner was of 902 days which can be sanctioned up to 31 st March, 2000
			<lb />
			for which the petitioner claimed that the notice of termination was illegal.
			<lb />
			The petitioner set out 15 reasons and specified the days of delay for each
			<lb />
			of them, none of which is due to the respondent&apos;s acts or conduct.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			146.
			<lb />
			Hence the petitioner has claimed overheads and loss of profits
			<lb />
			on the ground that the contract was extended and the petitioner was
			<lb />
			allowed to perform the contract after the extended period which resulted
			<lb />
			in additional expenditure. This is wholly ignoring the fact that because the
			<lb />
			contract was extended beyond the contract period the petitioner was paid
			<lb />
			for the services rendered; the petitioner was paid for the approvals
			<lb />
			obtained by the petitioner not only within the period of the contract of one
			<lb />
			year but for all the approvals obtained for 34 months that the contract
			<lb />
			lasted until it was terminated on 11 th August, 1999. Hence it is seen that
			<lb />
			despite being paid as per the terms of the contract for the additional work
			<lb />
			done in the additional period which the petitioner took to perform that
			<lb />
			part of the contract, the petitioner claimed additional expenditure also.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			147.
			<lb />
			This claim is in the nature of damages. The damages are for
			<lb />
			the overheads incurred and loss of profits. A person who claimed damages
			<lb />
			must be the party to the contract which has not breached the contract.
			<lb />
			Damages cannot be claimed by the party in breach. Similarly damages
			<lb />
			cannot be claimed by the party who has been paid for the work done as per
			<lb />
			the contractual rate. Further a party can claim damages from the other
			<lb />
			party who is in breach. The party claiming damages must prove the
			<lb />
			damages. The petitioner, therefore, must prove the overheads incurred
			<lb />
			and the loss of profits consequent upon the respondent&apos;s breach. These
			<lb />
			must be attributable to the respondent. It need hardly be stated that the
			<lb />
			respondent would not be liable for the loss which is attributable to 3 rd
			<lb />
			parties or for the petitioner&apos;s delay even after paying the petitioner for the
			<lb />
			work done at the contractual rate. But such is the claim of the petitioner.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			148.
			<lb />
			Mr. Andhyarujina would argue that the time was not the
			<lb />
			essence of the contract and that even if it was the essence of the contract
			<lb />
			(per Clause 18) it was allowed to be extended. Once it was allowed to be
			<lb />
			extended the petitioner would be entitled to compensation for any loss.
			<lb />
			This would be a complete misreading of the provision of law contained in
			<lb />
			Section 55 of the ICA cited above in Claim No.3.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			149.
			<lb />
			Under Section 55 paraphrased above, the petitioner promised
			<lb />
			to obtain approvals within 12 months of the execution of the contract i.e.
			<lb />
			on or before 10 th October, 1997, the part of the contract for which the
			<lb />
			approvals were not obtained became voidable at the option of the
			<lb />
			respondent under the 1 st part of Section 55. Instead of avoiding the
			<lb />
			contract, the respondent accepted further approvals obtained by the
			<lb />
			petitioner for a further 22 months and paid the petitioner for the work
			<lb />
			done at the rate of the contract. The respondent gave notice on 6 th August,
			<lb />
			2011 to complete the contract by 11 th August, 2011 and claimed
			<lb />
			compensation at the rate specified in the contract (which has been
			<lb />
			considered under Claim No.3).
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			150.
			<lb />
			Rather than claiming compensation for the loss suffered by the
			<lb />
			respondent by non performance of the terms by the petitioner, the
			<lb />
			respondent has paid the petitioner for the work already done not only
			<lb />
			within the 12 months of the contract but also the later 22 months that the
			<lb />
			contract remained alive. The respondent&apos;s notice of termination was after
			<lb />
			34 months of the contract. The petitioner has accepted the termination
			<lb />
			and submitted its final bill. The petitioner has claimed for all the work
			<lb />
			done at the contractual rate during the entire period and the respondent
			<lb />
			has paid for such work as per the contract price, without more.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			151.
			<lb />
			Instead the petitioner would claim that because the time was
			<lb />
			not of the essence the petitioner would be entitled to compensation by the
			<lb />
			delay caused (by the petitioner itself !) for overheads incurred by and loss
			<lb />
			of profits caused to the petitioner. This contention is wholly esoteric. Mr.
			<lb />
			Sancheti would argue that the reliance upon Section 55 is itself self
			<lb />
			defeating. If the contract period is extended and time is made not of the
			<lb />
			essence there is no question of claiming overheads and loss of profits.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			152.
			<lb />
			In any event the petitioner has to prove the damages claimed.
			<lb />
			The petitioner has made two claims for the overheads in Annexure F to
			<lb />
			the petitioner&apos;s 18 th final bill. The first claim is for various equipments
			<lb />
			being computer with printers, ACs, jeeps, vehicles, furniture, generator,
			<lb />
			digital document system etc. The 2 nd claim is for establishment and
			<lb />
			employee costs and fees. The petitioner has made its claim on that ground
			<lb />
			under what is stated to be Hudson&apos;s formula. The petitioner claims that
			<lb />
			that is the accepted formula set out in the case of McDermott (Supra).
			<lb />
			Hudson&apos;s formula set out in paragraph 111 is as follows :
			<lb />
		</p>

		<table>
			&quot;Contract head office
			<lb />
			overhead &amp;
			<lb />
			X Contract sum
			<lb />
			X Period of
			<lb />
			profit percentage
			<lb />
			Contract period
			<lb />
			delay
		</table>
		<lb />
		<p>
			The percentage profit is taken by the petitioner to be 30% in its bill.
			<lb />
			How the petitioner has claimed 30% is not stated or justified. Mr. Sancheti
			<lb />
			rightly argued that this would be variable from contract to contract. The
			<lb />
			petitioner has not led evidence of why 30% is claimed.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			153.
			<lb />
			The claim of loss of profits is computable other than upon the
			<lb />
			Hudson&apos;s formula. This is set out in Annexure &apos;G&apos; to the final bill of the
			<lb />
			petitioner. The petitioner has set out why the amount is claimed but not
			<lb />
			shown how precisely 6.95 Cr is claimed. The petitioner has considered
			<lb />
			30% as profit. Why 30% is claimed as profit or not more or less is not
			<lb />
			shown and not justified either in that bill or in the claim or later in the
			<lb />
			evidence, if any, oral or documentary. No oral evidence is led. No
			<lb />
			document is produced in that behalf.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			154.
			<lb />
			The petitioner has claimed damages from the respondent. The
			<lb />
			petitioner has not shown the loss which was suffered to the petitioner by
			<lb />
			additional overheads or the loss of profits due to the breach of the
			<lb />
			respondent. Claim Nos.7 &amp; 8 of the petitioner in arbitration showed that
			<lb />
			because the work was delayed (for the various reasons shown in the earlier
			<lb />
			paras), the petitioner incurred extra expenditure and was deprived of its
			<lb />
			profitability which it considered at 30% and claimed damages.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			155.
			<lb />
			Mr. Sancheti drew the Court&apos;s attention to the claim made by
			<lb />
			the petitioner even in this petition. The claim Nos. 7 &amp; 8 on account of
			<lb />
			overheads and loss of profits showed that the work was delayed beyond
			<lb />
			the stipulated period and completed only on 11 th August, 1999. The
			<lb />
			extended period was due to various breaches of condition of the contract
			<lb />
			by the respondent. It is also stated that the petitioner was not responsible
			<lb />
			for the delay but the respondent committed several breaches of contract.
			<lb />
			The petitioner relied upon Section 55 and 73 of the Indian Contract Act in
			<lb />
			that behalf and made the aforesaid claims.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			156.
			<lb />
			Having seen the contract between the parties, the law relating
			<lb />
			to time being of the essence of the contract, the correspondence made by
			<lb />
			the petitioner to apply for extension of time giving the reasons for the
			<lb />
			delay in carrying out contract work within contract period and the claim
			<lb />
			made by the petitioner, the award would require to be analysed.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			157.
			<lb />
			The learned Arbitrator has set out that the petitioner has
			<lb />
			alleged breaches committed by the respondent for which the contract has
			<lb />
			been prolonged and correctly relied upon the legal principle that one who
			<lb />
			commits wrong must compensate the other side who has been put to loss
			<lb />
			due to such wrongful act. The learned arbitrator has further considered
			<lb />
			the case of the respondent that the statement of claim does not hold the
			<lb />
			respondent responsible for the delay. That case has been brought out only
			<lb />
			in the written arguments which is contrary to the case in the statement of
			<lb />
			claim. (It is thereafter been made out in this petition as aforesaid). It was
			<lb />
			also argued that for the tall claim of 7.5 Cr + 6.95 Cr there is no proof by
			<lb />
			way of documents. It is observed that the allegations about the delays
			<lb />
			attributable to the respondent are not proved and that case is contrary to
			<lb />
			the correspondence. The respondent also claimed that there was no logic in
			<lb />
			claiming loss of profits for 22 months when the contract was required to be
			<lb />
			completed in 12 months. How the profit of 30% claimed was also not
			<lb />
			shown.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			158.
			<lb />
			The learned arbitrator has held that the claim for the extended
			<lb />
			period could not be allowed, termination was not unlawful, the petitioner
			<lb />
			has failed to prove with evidence its claim which is of 7.5 Cr + 6.95 Cr, the
			<lb />
			petitioner has not completed work within contract period for reasons not
			<lb />
			attributable to force majeure or the respondent and hence disallowed the
			<lb />
			entire claim.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			159.
			<lb />
			Can the learned arbitrator be faulted in coming to the
			<lb />
			conclusion that nothing is proved by the petitioner and hence nothing can
			<lb />
			be granted? Indeed, the aforesaid discussion shows the extension applied
			<lb />
			for by the petitioner for the reasons of third parties&apos; acts or conduct for the
			<lb />
			delay and the total lack of any evidence to show how 30% of the contract
			<lb />
			price is taken as the base in the Hudson formula or how the various
			<lb />
			overheads for the various items in claim No.1 relating to overheads as also
			<lb />
			in the claim for loss of profits, which is not a part of the Hudson formula, is
			<lb />
			also proved.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			160.
			<lb />
			Mr. Andhyarujina argued that learned arbitrator did not
			<lb />
			consider the judgment in the case of McDermott (Supra) which was
			<lb />
			delivered well after the arguments were heard but before the award was
			<lb />
			passed. Nevertheless the claim of 30% made as per the Hudson formula
			<lb />
			has been seen by the arbitrator as devoid of proof. For claiming 30% in the
			<lb />
			formula Mr. Andhyarujina would claim that the question of law relating to
			<lb />
			time being the essence of the contract or not was not considered by the
			<lb />
			arbitrator. Seeing how Section 55 has been applied it becomes clear that it
			<lb />
			was not applicable to the petitioner&apos;s case at all and was not required to be
			<lb />
			considered in view of the total lack of any evidence and the very basis of
			<lb />
			making the claim against the party who has not been shown to be in
			<lb />
			breach and who is the promisee who would itself be entitled to
			<lb />
			compensation.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			161.
			<lb />
			Mr. Sancheti drew my attention to Clause 2 of the agreement
			<lb />
			between the parties which shows that the petitioner has inspected the site,
			<lb />
			satisfied himself about the quantity, nature and magnitude of the work,
			<lb />
			made legal and independent enquiries and obtained information as to all
			<lb />
			the probable and possible situations, delays hindrances or interference to
			<lb />
			or with the execution and completion of the work to be carried out by the
			<lb />
			petitioner. This would show the magnitude of the work to be done. The
			<lb />
			petitioner must anticipate various delays and accordingly put up his bill.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			162.
			<lb />
			Mr. Sancheti also drew my attention to Clause 15 of the
			<lb />
			contract relating to the time of performance which specifies that the
			<lb />
			contract shall be commenced within two weeks after the receipt of the
			<lb />
			letter of the acceptance of the tender and completed in the time schedule
			<lb />
			of the completion of the work. It is specified that the &quot;contractor should
			<lb />
			bear in mind that the time would be of the essence of the agreement&quot;
			<lb />
			unless it is extended under Clause 17.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			163.
			<lb />
			Clause 17 deals with extension of time. If the contractor is
			<lb />
			unavoidably hindered in the execution of the work on any ground, it is
			<lb />
			required to inform the Engineerincharge within 10 days of the hindrance
			<lb />
			to show reasonable grounds for authorising extension of time. The
			<lb />
			contract period expired on 10 th October, 1997. Had the contract period not
			<lb />
			been extended by the further 22 months and had the respondent not
			<lb />
			allowed the petitioner to obtain further sanctions or refused to pay the
			<lb />
			petitioner for the further approvals obtained, the petitioner could have
			<lb />
			claimed extension of time upon showing that it was unavoidably hindered
			<lb />
			in performing the contract. The petitioner was not disallowed to continue
			<lb />
			the contract after writing its letters showing the reasons for the delay till
			<lb />
			6 th August, 1999 after which no further extension was granted. It was not
			<lb />
			for the petitioner to apply for extension of time upon claiming that the
			<lb />
			contract could be extended but that the petitioner has not done its work.
			<lb />
			The petitioner has accepted termination despite calling it unlawful and
			<lb />
			stated that the contract was completed on 11 th August, 1999. The
			<lb />
			petitioner&apos;s claim is not also for extension of time. The petitioner knows
			<lb />
			well that the time has been very reasonably extended for 22 months after
			<lb />
			the completion of the period of the contract.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			164.
			<lb />
			The petitioner has also not shown force majeure. Hence clause
			<lb />
			in that behalf being Clause 16 also would not apply.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			165.
			<lb />
			Further Mr. Sancheti drew my attention to Clauses 43(v) and
			<lb />
			(vi) under which the schedule of the rates showing the rate claimed and
			<lb />
			charged by the petitioner would cover the risk of delay and which cannot
			<lb />
			be altered under the contract. This is in terms of a just tender. When
			<lb />
			tenders are invited parties are required to bid. The most attractive rate
			<lb />
			would be accepted. The petitioner&apos;s bid has been accepted. If the bid
			<lb />
			excludes various aspects relating to damages for overheads or loss of
			<lb />
			profits etc., the purpose of the bid would be frustrated. If any party has
			<lb />
			included this, as it should, as covering risk of delay based upon Clause 2 of
			<lb />
			the contract, by taking into account the magnitude of the work, its bid
			<lb />
			would have been rejected as less attractive than the petitioner&apos;s. After such
			<lb />
			express contract to include all such eventualities within the contract price,
			<lb />
			the petitioner cannot be made to rescind therefrom by being granted
			<lb />
			additional amounts which the petitioner may not have contemplated
			<lb />
			though the contract required him to do so.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			166.
			<lb />
			Mr. Sancheti would argue that only the respondent would be
			<lb />
			entitled compensation for delay in Clause 18 (which has been considered
			<lb />
			for Clause 3A and 3B relating to the liquidated damages). This clause
			<lb />
			shows the specified damages that would be claimed by the respondent as
			<lb />
			the owner and which would be payable by the petitioner as the contractor;
			<lb />
			it is not the other way round.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			167.
			<lb />
			Consequently considering the claim of the petitioner and
			<lb />
			despite the arguments for the first time in the written arguments and then
			<lb />
			in this petition, it is seen that the petitioner has not made out any case for
			<lb />
			being granted any damages by way of overheads or loss of profits and the
			<lb />
			entire claim is wholly misconceived and left totally unproved since there is
			<lb />
			no evidence of proof at all for the precise amount claimed by the petitioner
			<lb />
			and the petitioner has not shown how termination is unlawful whilst
			<lb />
			accepting completion of the contract on 11 th August, 1999. The conclusion
			<lb />
			by the learned arbitrator that the claim is not proved and hence cannot be
			<lb />
			granted cannot be faulted.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<head>
			Claim No.9A : Physical verification of the crossings and the ROU.
			<lb />
		</head>

		<p>
			168.
			<lb />
			The petitioner was to be paid for the various crossings as
			<lb />
			specified in the Schedule of Rates relating to ROW. The petitioner was to
			<lb />
			be paid for all the work done for acquisition of the relevant lands under the
			<lb />
			Pipeline Act for claiming payment for the ROU. The petitioner claimed for
			<lb />
			separate approvals with regard to various creeks/nallas, rastas, village
			<lb />
			roads etc. The respondent considered those claims erroneous and
			<lb />
			exaggerated. The petitioner submitted various RA bills from time to time.
			<lb />
			The respondent passed bills to a certain extent. The respondent claimed
			<lb />
			that the remainder of the petitioner&apos;s claim for various crossings separately
			<lb />
			shown by the petitioner under the approvals of the Collector of various
			<lb />
			districts could be granted as claims for nallas, rastas etc. only after physical
			<lb />
			verification of the crossings. This physical verification was to be done by
			<lb />
			the representative of the petitioner as also the respondent.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			169.
			<lb />
			The petitioner claimed that a lot of work went into such
			<lb />
			verification for a period of about 20 months at an expense of Rs.60,000/
			<lb />
			p.m. In the statement of claim the petitioner claimed Rs.12 lacs for such
			<lb />
			work. This would be 20 months from the date of the completion of the
			<lb />
			contract on 11.08.1999.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			170.
			<lb />
			The petitioner claimed for this work in its last bill dated
			<lb />
			09.09.1999. The petitioner had claimed for the voluminous work done by
			<lb />
			the petitioner for 20 months till 11.08.1999, the last day of the contract
			<lb />
			claiming Rs.50,000/ p.m. towards expenses for equipment and overheads
			<lb />
			and consequently claiming Rs.10 lacs therein.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			171.
			<lb />
			This claim has been enhanced to Rs.12 lacs in the statement of
			<lb />
			claim.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			172.
			<lb />
			The petitioner must show when the respondent demanded
			<lb />
			physical verification of the ROW crossings for the first time. The petitioner
			<lb />
			has shown the Court 4 letters in this behalf.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			The letter dated 11.06.1998 of the petitioner calls for payment to be
			<lb />
			made under the 5 th RA bill as per the number of crossings.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			The parties had a meeting on 12.08.1998 in which they decided that
			<lb />
			the payment for creeks/nallas/village roads could be made only after
			<lb />
			physical verification of those crossings at the site.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			This was set out in the respondent&apos;s letter dated 17.08.1998 in which
			<lb />
			the respondent called upon the petitioner to finalize the programme for
			<lb />
			physical verification of creeks/nallas/village roads in consultation with the
			<lb />
			Deputy Manager.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			By the letter dated 21.09.1998 the petitioner complained that
			<lb />
			despite his readiness the verification even on that date could not be done
			<lb />
			and was pending because of the respondent. Consequently the petitioner
			<lb />
			demanded certain adhoc payment.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			Under the further letter of the respondent dated 16.02.1999 the
			<lb />
			respondent again reiterated the physical verification is a must and called
			<lb />
			upon the petitioner to depute its staff along with their Deputy Manager to
			<lb />
			start the physical verification of crossings from 18.02.1999.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			These letters relied upon by the petitioner themselves show that the
			<lb />
			verification was not even commenced until after 16.02.1999.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			173.
			<lb />
			The respondent would contend that this claim is for the work
			<lb />
			covered under the scope of the contract. That has been specified in the
			<lb />
			letter dated 16.02.1999 in which the respondent has clarified that
			<lb />
			inspection of any work is a contractual obligation and consequently the
			<lb />
			petitioner cannot get any compensation for the crossings claimed by him
			<lb />
			unless physical verification was done. The petitioner would contend that it
			<lb />
			was work not within the scope of contract and, therefore, would merit
			<lb />
			additional payment under Clause 47 referred above.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			174.
			<lb />
			This was the case that the learned Arbitrator had to consider.
			<lb />
			He set out the case of the petitioner under claim No.9.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			175.
			<lb />
			The petitioner contended before the Arbitrator that the
			<lb />
			contract nowhere provided for verification after the entire work is over and
			<lb />
			that it could not pinpoint under which part of the contract the verification
			<lb />
			was required. It contended that the PP Act, 1962 pertains to notification
			<lb />
			only. The respondent contended that the petitioner claimed additional
			<lb />
			payment for creeks/nallas/roads which were not applicable and hence the
			<lb />
			verification was required to ascertain and prove the petitioner&apos;s claim. The
			<lb />
			petitioner agreed to the verification 11 months after the respondent sought
			<lb />
			verification. Indeed, this exercise was in the nature of proof of work. The
			<lb />
			petitioner would have to show precisely the places where there were
			<lb />
			&quot;crossings&quot;. It is much like making a report of the work done and taking
			<lb />
			inspection thereof for the satisfaction of the party to the contract who had
			<lb />
			to disburse payments upon inspecting the work done.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			176.
			<lb />
			The petitioner did not also provide any particulars of the
			<lb />
			quantum of the work done. The learned Arbitrator concluded that the
			<lb />
			petitioner had not provided clear particulars of the claim nor led any
			<lb />
			evidence to establish the claim and that it was hit by Clause 47 of the
			<lb />
			agreement, reenforcing the fact that the petitioner was aware that it was a
			<lb />
			part of the composite job.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			177.
			<lb />
			The petitioner indeed claimed additional amount for physical
			<lb />
			verification only much later in the contract. The petitioner claimed 20
			<lb />
			months of work done but the correspondence itself showed hardly 6
			<lb />
			months of such work, if any. No definite date of the commencement and
			<lb />
			completion of that work is shown. Arbitrary figures of Rs.50,000/ and
			<lb />
			Rs.60,000/ p.m. are claimed. The conclusion of the learned Arbitrator
			<lb />
			that the petitioner has not provided particulars or led any evidence would
			<lb />
			be enough to reject the claim. This is despite the invocation of Clause 47
			<lb />
			which is a purely academic exercise as in other claims.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			178.
			<lb />
			The rejection of the claim, therefore, cannot be interfered with
			<lb />
			and in fact nothing is shown as to how it could be granted.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<head>
			Claim No.9B : Compensatory land for afforestation
			<lb />
		</head>

		<p>
			179.
			<lb />
			Alternate land had to be provided where deforestation was
			<lb />
			done. The petitioner was required to buy suitable land on behalf of the
			<lb />
			respondent to be handed over to the Forest Department.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			180.
			<lb />
			The petitioner&apos;s last 18 th RA bill in this behalf makes a claim
			<lb />
			that the Ministry of Environment and Forests (MEF) was provided 15
			<lb />
			hectares of land. The petitioner claimed that that was done upon extra
			<lb />
			efforts put in by the petitioner. The petitioner&apos;s bill showed the market
			<lb />
			value of the land was estimated to be Rs.15 lacs. The petitioner claimed
			<lb />
			20% of the land costs towards its service being Rs.3 lacs.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			181.
			<lb />
			There are no documents showing transfer of 15 hectares of
			<lb />
			land to the Forest Department. The petitioner could have easily provided
			<lb />
			such documentary evidence, if any. There is no evidence showing the
			<lb />
			market value of the land. Claim of Rs.15 lacs is not shown to be for a
			<lb />
			particular area of the land.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			182.
			<lb />
			The petitioner&apos;s claim before the Arbitrator is much the same.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			183.
			<lb />
			The respondent would claim that there has been no basis
			<lb />
			shown by the petitioner for the value of the land or the percentage of his
			<lb />
			service charges in making this claim. No documents are produced showing
			<lb />
			the transfer.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			184.
			<lb />
			Mr. Sancheti on behalf of the respondent drew my attention to
			<lb />
			Clause 4.7 under which all infrastructural and administrative facilities
			<lb />
			required for completion of ROU activities were to be provided by the
			<lb />
			contractor though not mentioned in the bid documents.
			<lb />
			This would, therefore, include the transfer of alternate land for
			<lb />
			afforestation. Further under Clause 4.8 of the Contract the scope of work
			<lb />
			of the contractor included all activities required to be done directly or
			<lb />
			indirectly and also all associated expenses and costs to be incurred by the
			<lb />
			contractor.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			185.
			<lb />
			Under its letter dated 8 th May, 1997 the petitioner has notified
			<lb />
			the respondent that the approval required for the forest land was got
			<lb />
			prepared. However it could be passed only if a proposal for afforestation
			<lb />
			of the land was submitted along with application for the NOC/approval. It
			<lb />
			could be processed further only after land is allotted to the Forest
			<lb />
			Department where afforestation could be carried out. The petitioner called
			<lb />
			upon the respondent to suggest the alternate land. The respondent replied
			<lb />
			by its letter dated 16.05.1997 that there was no alternate land available
			<lb />
			and, therefore, the petitioner itself must pursue with the relevant Collector
			<lb />
			and make application to the Forest Authorities.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			186.
			<lb />
			The fact that the approval itself would not be granted unless
			<lb />
			such alternate land is transferred to the Forest Department would show
			<lb />
			that it was a condition precedent to the grant of the approval. The contract
			<lb />
			of the petitioner required him to obtain the necessary approvals and to do
			<lb />
			everything for such grant. Consequently the work of the petitioner in
			<lb />
			obtaining and transferring alternate land to the Forest Department would
			<lb />
			be a part of the contract as claimed by the respondent.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			187.
			<lb />
			The learned Arbitrator has considered the case of the
			<lb />
			petitioner that the contract pertains to the issue of the notification under
			<lb />
			the PP Act and that the requirement of obtaining alternate land for
			<lb />
			afforestation was not a part of the contract. The respondent contended
			<lb />
			that if the claim was not a part of the contract, Clause 47 would be
			<lb />
			attracted and which has not been followed. The respondent would
			<lb />
			contend that the petitioner&apos;s letter dated 08.05.1997 itself shows that the
			<lb />
			work for afforestation required was done before the approval could be
			<lb />
			obtained and consequently the work was included in the scope of work of
			<lb />
			the contract meriting no extra payment.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			188.
			<lb />
			The learned Arbitrator considered that the petitioner had not
			<lb />
			provided any evidence for this claim and was aware that it was a part of
			<lb />
			the composite job. He also claimed that the petitioner had not raised the
			<lb />
			claim as per the requirement of Clause 47.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			189.
			<lb />
			Once it was seen that the relevant documents and evidence
			<lb />
			was not produced which would be the document showing the transfer to
			<lb />
			the extent of the land claimed by the petitioner as also showing the market
			<lb />
			value of the land, the claim could not be accepted. Hence the rejection of
			<lb />
			the claim cannot be faulted.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<head>
			Claim No.10 : Compensation by way of interest for the delayed
			<lb />
			payment
			<lb />
		</head>

		<p>
			190.
			<lb />
			The petitioner&apos;s 8 th final RA bill shows 3 parts of the claim
			<lb />
			towards interest and other losses thus:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			(I)
			<lb />
			The petitioner&apos;s claim is for retention money retained by the
			<lb />
			respondent without reason. This is a reasonable claim of Rs.32,794/ and
			<lb />
			Rs.3440/ under the 9 th RA bill. The petitioner has explained that 15%
			<lb />
			mobilization advance was paid upon submission of bank guarantee by the
			<lb />
			petitioner. This was the payment of 15% of the entire contract value under
			<lb />
			Clause 6.0 of the Contract. The petitioner was to give bank guarantee
			<lb />
			which had to be released not upon any RA bill being submitted as claimed
			<lb />
			by the petitioner but upon Section 6(1) notification of ROU being issued on
			<lb />
			pro rata basis. The entire claim is based upon the RA bills presumably
			<lb />
			because some amount of the bank guarantee came to be released pro rata.
			<lb />
			A portion of the amount of the bank guarantee was, however, retained by
			<lb />
			the respondent. It could be released upon further notifications issued
			<lb />
			under Section 6(1) of the PP Act.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			191.
			<lb />
			The petitioner&apos;s claim was for late release of the bank
			<lb />
			guarantee. The petitioner claims that it was released late upon the dates
			<lb />
			shown in the 9 th RA bill submitted by the petitioner. The petitioner has
			<lb />
			calculated the dates between the 9 th RA bill and the release of the amount
			<lb />
			and claimed interest for wrongful retention @ 24% p.m.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			192.
			<lb />
			My attention has been drawn to Clause 6.0 which relates to
			<lb />
			15% mobilization advance which was to be released after Section 6(1)
			<lb />
			notification was issued on pro rata basis as mentioned therein.
			<lb />
			Consequently the date of the 9 th bill becomes wholly inconsequential to
			<lb />
			consider.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			193.
			<lb />
			The respondent would claim that the number of days would be
			<lb />
			erroneous because it was calculated from the wrong date which was
			<lb />
			irrelevant as per the terms of the contract. The respondent would argue
			<lb />
			the cost of keeping the bank guarantee alive was far less than 24% and
			<lb />
			consequently interest claimed @ 24% albeit of a reasonable amount was
			<lb />
			not grantable.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			194.
			<lb />
			The respondent would also claim that what the petitioner calls
			<lb />
			the amount released later was released when the further portion of the
			<lb />
			bank guarantee came to be repaid after the contract was completed on
			<lb />
			13.08.1998.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			195.
			<lb />
			The respondent has contended that the petitioner has not
			<lb />
			mentioned what amount was claimed as interest and for what period. The
			<lb />
			respondent claimed that when the bank guarantee was submitted on
			<lb />
			13.08.1998 the payment was immediately released. The petitioner must
			<lb />
			show that the amount retained was liable to be repaid to the petitioner
			<lb />
			earlier than was repaid. This the petitioner has not shown this in his claim.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			(II) The petitioner has claimed interest for the late release of the
			<lb />
			payment claimed in his RA bills by way of interest and loss suffered by it
			<lb />
			due to payment withheld for the work already done. The petitioner has
			<lb />
			submitted a statement of claim for such work done but for which payment
			<lb />
			was withheld. The claim shows a columnar statement reflecting amounts
			<lb />
			payable under the bills submitted, amounts actually paid, the difference,
			<lb />
			the delay for the number of days the amount was withheld and claimed
			<lb />
			interest @ 24% thereon.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			196.
			<lb />
			For each of these bills which the petitioner submitted but was
			<lb />
			not paid partly or fully, the petitioner must issue notice under Section 3(1)
			<lb />
			(b) of the Interest Act making a demand for charging interest at the rates
			<lb />
			specified in its notice from the date mentioned in the notice to the date of
			<lb />
			institution of the proceeding. The petitioner&apos;s claim under the RA bills is
			<lb />
			not for such period.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			197.
			<lb />
			The petitioner claims to have sent the notice to the respondent
			<lb />
			under its letter dated 29.04.1998. The letter shows the 8 th and 9 th RA bills
			<lb />
			dated 08.01.1998 and 23.03.1998 as the subject matter. The petitioner
			<lb />
			claims that the payment was not received by it. The letter further shows
			<lb />
			&quot;moreover the interest @ 24% and other losses for delay in payment will
			<lb />
			be payable to us&quot;. Such a letter cannot be construed as a notice under the
			<lb />
			Interest Act. The respondent would claim that for a mere statement given
			<lb />
			by the petitioner in its bill, the particulars of the number of days for which
			<lb />
			the payments are claimed by way of interest cannot be deciphered and the
			<lb />
			petitioner has not led any evidence or even explained the statement. The
			<lb />
			respondent would argue that the RA bills were required to be paid within 1
			<lb />
			month of the issue. The 8 th RA bill dated 08.01.1998 would be payable by
			<lb />
			08.02.1998. The 9 th RA bill dated 23.03.1998 would be payable by
			<lb />
			23.03.1998. The petitioner has not shown the dates when the amounts
			<lb />
			were released and the dates from when the interest was claimed in the
			<lb />
			columnar statement.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			198.
			<lb />
			Upon such a case the learned Arbitrator has considered that
			<lb />
			the petitioner&apos;s case was that it was deprived of its money and, therefore,
			<lb />
			required to be compensated since there was no bar to the payment of
			<lb />
			interest under the Contract. The respondent contended before the
			<lb />
			Arbitrator that the claim did not provide particulars of the amount due but
			<lb />
			simply took the difference between the amounts claimed and paid. The
			<lb />
			learned Arbitrator considered that the petitioner had not given notice
			<lb />
			claiming the interest at a particular rate from a particular date (which
			<lb />
			would be different for each of the bills). The learned Arbitrator considered
			<lb />
			that the petitioner has not provided particulars of the claim and led
			<lb />
			evidence to establish the claim. The columnar statement is rather
			<lb />
			unintelligible. The petitioner at least should have explained the period
			<lb />
			during which the claim was made at a particular rate but which has not
			<lb />
			been done.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			(III) This claim is also for interest and other losses for the delay in
			<lb />
			payment. The petitioner has shown the dates of the submission of the bills,
			<lb />
			the due date of the payment of the bill, the actual payment by the
			<lb />
			respondent and the days of delay in payments. It has claimed interest @
			<lb />
			24% p.a. on the bill amount. This statement indeed shows the period
			<lb />
			during which the amounts are claimed. The learned Arbitrator would
			<lb />
			otherwise require to only verify whether the dates of the bill and the
			<lb />
			payment and the extent of the payment could be made were correct.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			199.
			<lb />
			The respondent however relied upon the provisions of the
			<lb />
			Interest Act and claimed that no due notice was given to the respondent for
			<lb />
			such claim of interest. The learned Arbitrator has considered the aspect of
			<lb />
			the notice required to be given under the Interest Act which the petitioner
			<lb />
			was unable to show. On that singular aspect the claim could fail.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			Rejection of this claim, therefore, cannot be interfered with.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			LEGAL ASPECTS
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			Bias
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			200.
			<lb />
			The petitioner has claimed that the learned Arbitrator was
			<lb />
			biased against him, since he was the employee of the respondent. It is
			<lb />
			settled law that an employee of corporation of the respondent can be an
			<lb />
			Arbitrator. (See. M/s. Ladli Construction Co. (P) Ltd. Vs. Punjab Police
			<lb />
			Housing Corpn. Ltd. 2012 AIR SC 1580, Indian Oil Corporation Ltd. Vs.
			<lb />
			Raja Transport Pvt. Ltd. (2009) 8 SCC 520, Mussafar Shah Vs. MMTC
			<lb />
			83 2000 Delhi LT 514 and Saurabh Kalani Vs. Tata Finance Ltd.
			<lb />
			2003(3) Arb.LR 345 (Bom) (DB))
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			201.
			<lb />
			Hence the petitioner must show special bias in this claim. The
			<lb />
			filed their respective written arguments.
			<lb />
			The petitioner made an
			<lb />
			application on 11.03.2006 that the Arbitrator had to complete the
			<lb />
			arbitration within 3 years which had transpired since his argument
			<lb />
			commenced on 24.03.2003. This application of the petitioner was
			<lb />
			dismissed by the Arbitrator. The challenge to that order in this Court and
			<lb />
			thereafter in the Supreme Court has also been dismissed. The arbitration
			<lb />
			proceeded. Though the hearings were completed, the learned Arbitrator
			<lb />
			could not pronounce the award thanks only to the petitioner. After the
			<lb />
			SLP in the Supreme Court was disposed of, the petitioner made another
			<lb />
			application for further arguing the matter. The petitioner made yet another
			<lb />
			application under Sections 12 &amp; 13 of the Act alleging bias against the
			<lb />
			arbitrator. The learned Arbitrator has disposed of both the applications
			<lb />
			under a common order. My attention has been drawn to the application
			<lb />
			made by the petitioner. The application suggests how the arguments
			<lb />
			commenced on 24.03.2003 were completed on 14.05.2003 after which
			<lb />
			there were oral arguments and written arguments of the respondent
			<lb />
			including certain adjournments and which were completed after the lapse
			<lb />
			of 16 months. It alleges that the learned Arbitrator has not acted with the
			<lb />
			due diligence and hence favoured the respondent. The application also
			<lb />
			makes a reference to the fact that the Arbitrator become functus officio as
			<lb />
			claimed in earlier application which was rejected throughout till the
			<lb />
			Supreme Court order. It mentioned about another award passed by the
			<lb />
			same Arbitrator against the another contractor and in favour of the
			<lb />
			respondent. On the ground of bias the learned Arbitrator has held that the
			<lb />
			application is somewhat like the earlier application and hence has rejected
			<lb />
			it. It is indeed so. Para 3 as also 5 make this absolutely clear. Further
			<lb />
			allegations in para 4 are only a fall out of the case upon the allegations
			<lb />
			made in paras 3 &amp; 5. The petitioner could not be concerned with another
			<lb />
			award of the same Arbitrator against another party on totally different
			<lb />
			facts.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			202.
			<lb />
			Consequently it is seen that the claim of bias made out by the
			<lb />
			petitioner is frivolous. In fact it is counterproductive. The learned
			<lb />
			Arbitrator had to adjudicate upon the claim made by the petitioner himself.
			<lb />
			Even if the learned Arbitrator is held to be biased, another Arbitrator
			<lb />
			would be from the same corporation. It is in the petitioner&apos;s interest to put
			<lb />
			forward his case and to show on merits that the award is unsustainable.
			<lb />
			The ruling of the learned Arbitrator cannot be faulted.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			Mandate
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			203.
			<lb />
			Mr. Andhyarujina contended that the arbitrator did not have
			<lb />
			the mandate to pass the impugned award. This contention has been taken
			<lb />
			earlier. It has been rejected by this Court and Supreme Court. Mr.
			<lb />
			Andhyarujina would argue that this aspect would not make the petitioners
			<lb />
			contention hit by the provisions of res judicata when the law is amended
			<lb />
			after the earlier decision as shown in the case of Bharat Oman.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			204.
			<lb />
			Mr. Andhyarujina would argue that the aspect relating to the
			<lb />
			mandate of the arbitrator can be taken up whilst challenging the award
			<lb />
			because it is a jurisdictional fact. He has relied upon the judgment in the
			<lb />
			case of Arun Kumar &amp; Ors. Vs. Union of India &amp; Ors., (2007) 1
			<lb />
			Supreme Court Cases 732, in which the jurisdictional fact is explained in
			<lb />
			paragraphs 74 and 76 as a fact which must exist before the Court, Tribunal
			<lb />
			or Authority assumes jurisdiction over a particular matter. It is one of
			<lb />
			existence or nonexistence of a fact upon which depends the jurisdiction of
			<lb />
			a Court, Tribunal or Authority and its power to act. If the jurisdictional
			<lb />
			fact did not exist, the Court, Authority or Officer cannot act as no authority
			<lb />
			can act upon the jurisdiction which it otherwise does not possess. The
			<lb />
			essence of the jurisdictional fact is a sine qua non or condition precedent
			<lb />
			for the exercise of power by a Court of limited jurisdiction.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			205.
			<lb />
			The parties gave the arbitrator a time limit to decide. The
			<lb />
			arbitrator decided outside the time limit. The period for that decision was
			<lb />
			not extended by consent. The petitioner would rely upon the case of NBCC
			<lb />
			Ltd. Vs. J G Engineering Pvt. Ltd., (2010) 2 Supreme Court Cases 385
			<lb />
			to contend that the court could not extend the time in the absence of
			<lb />
			consent of the parties. However, in the Division Bench judgment of this
			<lb />
			Court followed in the case of M/s. Snehdeep Auto Centre Vs. Hindustan
			<lb />
			Petroleum Corporation Ltd. in Appeal No.143 of 2012 in Arbitration
			<lb />
			Petition No.430 of 2008 decided on 16 th April, 2012 and M/s. Mantech
			<lb />
			Consultants Vs. Bharat Oman Refineries Ltd. in Arbitration Petition
			<lb />
			No.477 of 2006 dated 2 nd September, 2011, the conduct of the parties
			<lb />
			amounting the clear waiver was considered. The presumption of waiver
			<lb />
			upon the conduct of the parties was made. It was held that when the
			<lb />
			conduct of the parties implied to mean that they have consented not to
			<lb />
			insist upon mandatory time limit, the award cannot be challenged. It was
			<lb />
			observed that when a party attended a number of meetings after the period
			<lb />
			expired, it would show a strong indication of waiver. If the party does not
			<lb />
			take a clear or unambiguous stand also it would tantamount to waiver.
			<lb />
			The petitioner would contend that his conduct would not tantamount to
			<lb />
			waiver because he has taken a clear stand that the arbitrator&apos;s mandate
			<lb />
			was over.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			206.
			<lb />
			Mr. Andhyarujina would argue that in the case of Bharat
			<lb />
			Oman Refineries Ltd. Vs. Mantech Consultants, 2012(3) Bom C R 754
			<lb />
			the Division Bench of this Court held that there can be no waiver after the
			<lb />
			period in the agreement expired. The arbitrator became functus officio
			<lb />
			and could not proceed with the award. This court is, however, bound by
			<lb />
			the decision of the Supreme Court in this case itself and consequently the
			<lb />
			question of mandate having been considered cannot be reconsidered.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			Reasons
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			207.
			<lb />
			It is contended by Mr. Andhyarujina that the award is a wholly
			<lb />
			unreasoned award because the reasons for rejecting each of the claims of
			<lb />
			the petitioner have not been given and mere conclusions are stated. Mr.
			<lb />
			Andhyarujina drew a parallel between reasons and conclusions. It is
			<lb />
			established not only by precedent but by legislation that awards must be
			<lb />
			reasoned awards. They would show the mind of the arbitrator. This would
			<lb />
			show lack of caprice much as in judgments of Courts. The award must,
			<lb />
			therefore, be intelligible as to why a particular claim is accepted or
			<lb />
			rejected. This proposition is too well settled to be at all refuted. What
			<lb />
			would constitute a reasoned judgment or award can be seen from various
			<lb />
			judgments.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			208.
			<lb />
			The requirement of giving reasons have been set out since well
			<lb />
			prior to the enactment of the 1996 Act as our justice system is based upon
			<lb />
			the requirement of giving reasoned orders and judgments. In the case of
			<lb />
			Messers Mahabir Prasad Santosh Kumar Vs. State of UP and Ors., 1970
			<lb />
			(1) Supreme Court Case 764 the worthiness of the reasoned judgment of
			<lb />
			the Tribunal has been set out for the quasi judicial determination. The
			<lb />
			reasons for the requirement of a reasoned judgment is shown thus :
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			It must appear not merely that the authority entrusted with quasi
			<lb />
			judicial authority has reached a conclusion on the problem before him :
			<lb />
			it must appear that he has reached a conclusion which is according to
			<lb />
			law and just, and for ensuring that end he must record the ultimate
			<lb />
			mental process leading from the dispute to its solution. Satisfactory
			<lb />
			decision of a disputed claim may be reached only if it be supported by
			<lb />
			the most cogent reasons that appeal to the authority. Recording of
			<lb />
			reasons in support of a decision on a disputed claim by a quasijudicial
			<lb />
			authority ensures that the decision is reached according to law and is
			<lb />
			not the result of caprice, whim or fancy or reached on grounds of policy
			<lb />
			or expediency. A party to the dispute is ordinarily entitled to know the
			<lb />
			grounds on which the authority has rejected his claim. If the order is
			<lb />
			subject to appeal, the necessity to record reasons is greater, for without
			<lb />
			recorded reasons the appellate authority has no material on which it
			<lb />
			may determine whether the facts were properly ascertained, the relevant
			<lb />
			law was correctly applied and the decision was just.
		</item>
		<lb />
		<p>
			This judgment has been applied by the Delhi High Court in the
			<lb />
			context of arbitration which shall be considered presently. The mental
			<lb />
			process from the dispute to the resolution as observed in this judgment has
			<lb />
			been also considered in a later case by the Supreme Court which shall be
			<lb />
			considered presently.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			209.
			<lb />
			Similarly in the case of in the case of S N Mukherjee Vs.
			<lb />
			Union of India, (1990) 4 Supreme Court Cases 594 the requirement of
			<lb />
			reasons to be given by an administrative authority governed by public law
			<lb />
			are stated to be an extension of rule of natural justice. The Court
			<lb />
			considered that the requirement of recording reasons would :
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			(I) guarantee consideration by the authority, (ii) introduce clarity in
			<lb />
			the decisions ; and (iii) minimise chances of arbitrariness in decision
			<lb />
			making.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			210.
			<lb />
			In the case of McDermott (Supra) what is &quot;reasoned&quot; has been
			<lb />
			explained from Bachawat&apos;s Law of Arbitration and Conciliation, 4 th Edn.,
			<lb />
			pp.85556 thus :
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			...Reason is a ground or motive for a belief or a course of action, a
			<lb />
			statement in justification or explanation of belief or action. It is in this
			<lb />
			sense that the award must state reasons for the amount awarded.
		</item>
		<lb />
		<item>
			The rationale of the requirement of reasons is that reasons assure that
			<lb />
			the arbitrator has not acted capriciously. Reasons reveal the grounds on
			<lb />
			which the arbitrator reached the conclusion which adversely affects the
			<lb />
			interests of a party. The contractual stipulation of reasons means, as
			<lb />
			held in Poyser and Mills&apos; Arbitration In Re, &quot;proper, adequate reasons&quot;.
			<lb />
			Such reasons shall not only be intelligible but shall be a reason
			<lb />
			connected with the case which the court can see is proper. Contradictory
			<lb />
			reasons are equal to lack of reasons.
		</item>
		<lb />
		<item>
			The meaning of the word &quot;reason&quot; was explained by the Kerala High
			<lb />
			Court in the context of a reasoned award....
		</item>
		<lb />
		<item>
			Reasons are the links between the materials on which certain
			<lb />
			conclusions are based and the actual conclusions....
		</item>
		<lb />
		<item>
			A mere statement of reasons does not satisfy the requirements of Section
			<lb />
			31(3). Reasons must be based upon the materials submitted before the
			<lb />
			arbitral tribunal. The tribunal has to give its reasons on consideration
			<lb />
			of the relevant materials while the irrelevant material may be
			<lb />
			ignored....
		</item>
		<lb />
		<item>
			Statement of reasons is mandatory requirement unless dispensed with
			<lb />
			by the parties or by a statutory provision.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			211.
			<lb />
			In the case of Jagmohan Singh Gujral Vs. Satish Ashok
			<lb />
			Sabnis 2004(1) Bom C R 307 the learned Single Judge of this Court
			<lb />
			considered various precedents and set out the mandatory reasons required
			<lb />
			under Section 31(3) of the Act. It was held that :
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			…. the reasons must be based on the material available to the
			<lb />
			Tribunal. The Tribunal has to give its reasons. On consideration of the
			<lb />
			relevant material and ignoring irrelevant material. This would be the
			<lb />
			relevant test. Findings based on the reasons not considering material
			<lb />
			on record and / or on appreciation of the evidence which the Court
			<lb />
			finds to be totally perverse can be said to be not a reasoned award.
		</item>
		<lb />
		<item>
			The purpose of giving reasons is to enable the Court to know that the
			<lb />
			arbitrator has correctly addressed himself to the controversy in issue or
			<lb />
			has considered the material on record or ignored irrelevant material or
			<lb />
			applied the correct principles and, therefore, on appreciation of the
			<lb />
			evidence has given reasons for the findings on the conclusions. This to
			<lb />
			my mind, would be the requirement of giving reasons. Any other
			<lb />
			manner of reading the expression to give reasons would defeat the
			<lb />
			mandate of law as contained in section 31(3) of the Act of 1996.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			212.
			<lb />
			Relying upon the same analogy it was held in the case of Jai
			<lb />
			Singh Vs. DDA, 2008 LawSuit (Del) 1781 that the arbitrator must
			<lb />
			indicate his mind and that award cannot be unintelligible. Consequently
			<lb />
			when the arbitrator has merely stated that the claim is not in accordance
			<lb />
			with the agreement or in accordance in terms of the contract or that the
			<lb />
			claim is not established or that no case is made out it tantamounts to not
			<lb />
			giving reasons as it would be unintelligible. At best such expressions could
			<lb />
			be conclusions. Therefore, conclusions must be based upon reasons and
			<lb />
			the conclusions must show how those conclusions have been arrived at.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			213.
			<lb />
			It is held in the case of Jai Singh (Supra) that if that is not
			<lb />
			done the Court would be compelled to peruse the record and determine
			<lb />
			whether the conclusions reached by the arbitrator are in accordance with
			<lb />
			law or not and this is not the scope of the enquiry whilst entertaining
			<lb />
			challenges and objections to arbitral awards.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			214.
			<lb />
			It may be mentioned that in this case this exercise was
			<lb />
			undoubtedly required to be undertaken by the Court, thanks to the tenacity
			<lb />
			and pursuasiveness of Mr. Andhyarujina. The learned Arbitrator has
			<lb />
			concluded that various claims cannot be entertained because they fell
			<lb />
			within the scope of the contract. Whereas the petitioner contended that
			<lb />
			there were additional matters outside the perview of the contract, the
			<lb />
			respondent pointed out how they were within the terms of the contract by
			<lb />
			the aforesaid clauses of the contract which have been reproduced. Though
			<lb />
			the learned arbitrator has not referred to those clauses of the contract by
			<lb />
			which he concluded that the work was within the scope of the contract,
			<lb />
			going through the contract would make that position clear.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			215.
			<lb />
			In the case of Madhok Construction Co. (P.) Ltd. Vs. Union
			<lb />
			of India, 71(1998) Delhi Law Times 599, when the arbitrator had dealt
			<lb />
			with the claims considering documents referring to the details of the claims
			<lb />
			it was held that the Court cannot reassess the evidence and arrive at
			<lb />
			contrary finding when the conclusions are supported by the material and
			<lb />
			evidence on record.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			216.
			<lb />
			In this case the arbitrator has held how various claims stated
			<lb />
			to merit extra payment were, in fact, within the scope of the contract. Mr.
			<lb />
			Sancheti having shown the Court the relevant clauses though not cited by
			<lb />
			the arbitrator, but seen by the Court, the inevitable conclusion would be
			<lb />
			that his conclusions are supported by the material on record, being the
			<lb />
			contract itself.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			217.
			<lb />
			What is a reasoned award has been explained by the Delhi
			<lb />
			High Court in the case of CMDR S.P. Puri Vs. Alankit Assignments Ltd.,
			<lb />
			2008 (3) Arb L R 465 (Delhi) to which my attention has been drawn by
			<lb />
			Mr. Sancheti. It is held that what the law requires under Section 31(3) of
			<lb />
			the Act is that the arbitrator must give reasons and nothing more. The
			<lb />
			reasons must be clear and indicate the basis of the decision. They must be
			<lb />
			intelligible and comprehensible and need not necessarily be lengthy and
			<lb />
			elaborate. They should indicate and provide a link between questions and
			<lb />
			issues and the conclusions reached. They should indicate the mind of the
			<lb />
			arbitrator. Hence it is held that arbitrators need not give an elaborate
			<lb />
			judgment dealing with each and every ground or reason. They have to
			<lb />
			consider the entire facts in proper perspective. The arbitrators are men
			<lb />
			from the trade or relatives and hence must have substantial latitude and
			<lb />
			flexibility in deciding matters in a just and equitable manner. They need
			<lb />
			not elaborately discuss all contentions raised by the parties.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			218.
			<lb />
			Similarly in the case of M/s. Ircon International Ltd. Vs.
			<lb />
			M/s. Arvind Construction Co. Ltd. &amp; Anr., 81(1999) Delhi Law Times
			<lb />
			268 it is observed in paragraph 11 that :
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			The arbitrator is not expected to write judgment like a Court of law
			<lb />
			but has only to state as to how he has come to the finding arrived at
			<lb />
			by him. No particular form is required for giving reasons. The
			<lb />
			arbitrator is not expected to record at great length the
			<lb />
			communications exchanged or submissions made by the parties nor he
			<lb />
			is expected to analyze the law and the authorities. It is sufficient for
			<lb />
			him to explain what his findings are and how he reached at the
			<lb />
			conclusions. Sufficiency of reasons is not to be gone into by the Court.
			<lb />
			The arbitrator in this case was an expert being a retired Financial
			<lb />
			Commissioner of the Railway Board and was appointed by the
			<lb />
			petitioner. He, after hearing the parties, has given his decisions and
			<lb />
			also recorded reasons. May be, in the opinion of the petitioner, the
			<lb />
			arbitrator has not analysed the law and has not elaborately discussed
			<lb />
			the various contentions of the parties, but that in itself, in my opinion,
			<lb />
			is not sufficient to set aside the award of the arbitrator. The arbitrator
			<lb />
			having given reasons for arriving at the decision taken in the award,
			<lb />
			there is no force in the submission of Mr. Singla that award is liable to
			<lb />
			be set aside on any alleged ground.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			219.
			<lb />
			In the case of International Airport Authority of India Vs. K
			<lb />
			D Bali &amp; Anr., 1988 Air 1099 1988 SCR (3) 370, it has been observed,
			<lb />
			albeit for a reasoned order which was demanded on the preliminary
			<lb />
			objections by a party challenging the award, that it was not necessary for
			<lb />
			the arbitrator to record a long reasoned order as &quot;indeed the law does not
			<lb />
			demand writing such a long order&quot;.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			220.
			<lb />
			What then would constitute an unreasoned award ?
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			221.
			<lb />
			The case of T N Electricity Board Vs. Bridge Tunnel
			<lb />
			Construction &amp; Ors., (1997) 4 Supreme Court Cases 121 was of a
			<lb />
			construction contract between a government body and private party.
			<lb />
			Various claims under certain clauses of the contract were made for material
			<lb />
			to be excavated, tunnel excavation etc. The rates payable under the
			<lb />
			contract were mentioned in the schedule to the contract. The respondent
			<lb />
			claimed at rates higher than the contract rates. These claims were made
			<lb />
			after expiry of the contract period. Objections were raised by the
			<lb />
			government body. The arbitrator without going into details passed the
			<lb />
			nonspeaking award awarding Rs.70.83 lacs in place of Rs.2.10 Cr. The
			<lb />
			award runs thus:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;I hereby award and direct as follows :
			<lb />
			(1) the respondent shall pay the claimant a sum of Rupees seventy
			<lb />
			lakhs eightythree thousand seven hundred and ninetythree only
			<lb />
			(Rs.70,83,793) and release the earnest money deposit and bank
			<lb />
			guarantees furnished by the claimant in lieu of security deposit, in full
			<lb />
			settlement of all claims and counterclaims.
		</item>
		<lb />
		<p>
			The Supreme Court held that the claim of excavation and damages
			<lb />
			were not considered in a nonspeaking award. It was difficult to discern to
			<lb />
			what extent the claims had been considered admissible and how the
			<lb />
			inadmissible claims were adjudged. Hence it could not be discerned to
			<lb />
			what extent the arbitrator had exercised his jurisdiction visavis the
			<lb />
			admissible claims and disallowed the nonarbitrable claims. Hence it was
			<lb />
			not clear whether he exercised his authority beyond his jurisdiction or in
			<lb />
			abdication thereof. In either case it was held that it would be an error of
			<lb />
			jurisdiction &quot;the very foundation of his decision&quot;. It was observed that in a
			<lb />
			nonspeaking award the Court cannot go through the reasoning of the
			<lb />
			award and correct wrong proposition of law or any error in law. It was
			<lb />
			observed that :
		</p>
		<lb />
		<item>
			It is not open to the Court to probe the mental process of the arbitrator
			<lb />
			and speculate, when no reasons have been given by the arbitrator, as to
			<lb />
			what impelled the arbitrator to arrive at his conclusion.
			<lb />
			Thus such a nonspeaking award was held liable to be set aside.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			222.
			<lb />
			In the case of Municipal Corporation of Delhi Vs. M/s.
			<lb />
			Jagan Nath Ashok Kumar &amp; Anr., AIR 1987 Supreme Court 2316, it was
			<lb />
			held and that when the germane and relevant reasons with a rational
			<lb />
			nexus to the claim were given to hold what arbitrators held, the award
			<lb />
			could not be challenged as unreasonable.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			223.
			<lb />
			In the case of Ravindra Kumar Gupta &amp; Co. Vs. Union of
			<lb />
			India, (2010) 1 Supreme Court Cases 409, the observation of the
			<lb />
			Supreme Court in paragraph 14 would show that there would be no
			<lb />
			interference with a reasoned award unless there is total perversity in the
			<lb />
			award or the judgment was based on the wrong proposition of law.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			224.
			<lb />
			Mr. Andhyarujina would argue that the reasonableness of the
			<lb />
			reasons must also be seen. He would contend that in claim No.4 with
			<lb />
			regard to the entries in the revenue records required to be obtained by the
			<lb />
			petitioner, the learned arbitrator made surmises and conjunctures upon his
			<lb />
			own imagination of what was the position with regard to the record of
			<lb />
			rights that he knew as a senior executive of the government and the citizen
			<lb />
			of this country. He contended that the learned arbitrator has only surmised
			<lb />
			that the names of all the parties who have right, title and interest in the
			<lb />
			property should be recorded in the revenue record and as such the work of
			<lb />
			obtaining such entries was within the scope of the work contractor.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			225.
			<lb />
			Mr. Andhyarujina relied upon the judgments in the case of
			<lb />
			Dhirajlal Girdharilal Vs. Commissioner of Income Tax, (S) AIR 1955 S
			<lb />
			C 271 (Vol 42 C N 47) and Ascu Arch Timber Protection Ltd Vs.
			<lb />
			Commissioner of Central Excise, Calcutta, (2004) 10 Supreme Court
			<lb />
			Cases 653 in which it has been held that upon the surmises of a Tribunal
			<lb />
			which was Court of fact arrived at by considering irrelevant material partly
			<lb />
			upon the conjectures, surmises and suspicions, an issue of law arose to
			<lb />
			reconsider the decision.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			That would be to frame a question of law upon which the Taxation
			<lb />
			Appeal could be admitted. What Mr. Andhyarujina calls surmises is the
			<lb />
			fact which merits judicial notice. It is a known fact that the revenue
			<lb />
			records do reflect the position of fact at site and its incorporation is
			<lb />
			mandatory. Stating the knowledge of such fact is not a surmise.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			226.
			<lb />
			Mr. Sancheti drew the attention of the Court to the case of
			<lb />
			Central Bank of India Vs. State of Gujarat &amp; Ors., AIR 1987 Supreme
			<lb />
			Court 2320 in which relying upon an English judgment in the case of
			<lb />
			Mediterranean &amp; Eastern Export Co. Ltd. Vs. Fortress Fabrics Ltd.
			<lb />
			(1948) 2 ALL ER 186 it was observed:
		</p>
		<lb />
		<item>
			A man in the trade who is selected for his experience would be likely to
			<lb />
			know and indeed to be expected to know the fluctuations of the market
			<lb />
			and would have plenty of means of informing himself or refreshing his
			<lb />
			memory on any point on which he might find it necessary so to do.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			227.
			<lb />
			It would have to be seen whether in this case sufficient reasons
			<lb />
			have been given by the learned arbitrator so as to make his award
			<lb />
			intelligible and so as to make the Court understand why the claims have
			<lb />
			been rejected. The reasons to be given, therefore, need not be scientifically
			<lb />
			made out or articulately enumerated and setting out each of the claims
			<lb />
			and the contentions. It would, therefore, have to be seen whether by a
			<lb />
			single reason in respect of each claim a rejection must be upheld, the other
			<lb />
			contentions of the parties and the considerations of the arbitrator
			<lb />
			notwithstanding.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			228.
			<lb />
			Upon such parameters the impugned award must be
			<lb />
			considered for the charge made against arbitrator that he has not given
			<lb />
			reasons for coming to any of the conclusions that he has.
			<lb />
			Mr.
			<lb />
			Andhyarujina took the Court through each of the claims considered by the
			<lb />
			learned arbitrator in which the entire case of both the parties has been
			<lb />
			succinctly set out followed by the consideration of the learned arbitrator
			<lb />
			himself. There are more than one reason shown in most of the claims to
			<lb />
			conclude why each of them is rejected even if the learned arbitrator has
			<lb />
			not gone into the specifics of the law cited by the parties with regard to
			<lb />
			some of the claims. It would have to be seen whether for the conclusions
			<lb />
			that he has come to the only reasons given by him would suffice. It may be
			<lb />
			mentioned that if a particular claim has to be rejected for single reason
			<lb />
			that it cannot be granted, it would matter little why the arbitrator has not
			<lb />
			given other reasons also for rejecting that claim. In short, therefore, a
			<lb />
			single apt reason for rejection of each of the claims must suffice.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			229.
			<lb />
			Separate claims may, therefore, be considered for seeing the
			<lb />
			reasons given by arbitrator thus :
			<lb />
		</p>

		<table>
			Claim
			<lb />
			Nos.
			<lb />
			Particulars of
			<lb />
			Claim
			<lb />
			Reasoning
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			the Arbitrator
			<lb />
			One reason sufficient
			<lb />
			to
			<lb />
			disentitle
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			Petitioner
			<lb />
			1(a)
			<lb />
			1(b)
			<lb />
			Loss caused by
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			illegal
			<lb />
			withholding of
			<lb />
			security deposit
			<lb />
			The
			<lb />
			security
			<lb />
			deposit had to
			<lb />
			be adjusted or
			<lb />
			refunded.
			<lb />
			It
			<lb />
			has
			<lb />
			been
			<lb />
			refunded.
			<lb />
			The due date
			<lb />
			was extended.
			<lb />
			The
			<lb />
			petitioner
			<lb />
			sought
			<lb />
			to
			<lb />
			complete the job
			<lb />
			and
			<lb />
			sought
			<lb />
			extension.
			<lb />
			The
			<lb />
			security
			<lb />
			deposit
			<lb />
			automatically
			<lb />
			got extended.
			<lb />
			Security deposit itself
			<lb />
			was
			<lb />
			not
			<lb />
			repayable
			<lb />
			before it was actually
			<lb />
			paid.
			<lb />
			No notice of demand
			<lb />
			under the Interest Act
			<lb />
			also given.
			<lb />
			2
			<lb />
			Payment
			<lb />
			for
			<lb />
			ROW under the
			<lb />
			Schedule
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			Rates.
			<lb />
			Petitioner
			<lb />
			has
			<lb />
			not proved the
			<lb />
			approvals
			<lb />
			obtained
			<lb />
			for
			<lb />
			nallas/crossings
			<lb />
			There was no
			<lb />
			evidence
			<lb />
			to
			<lb />
			support
			<lb />
			778
			<lb />
			approvals.
			<lb />
			Merely including
			<lb />
			numbers in the
			<lb />
			statement
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			claim does not
			<lb />
			entitle
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			petitioner
			<lb />
			for
			<lb />
			payment.
			<lb />
			The
			<lb />
			number
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			approvals claimed to
			<lb />
			have been obtained are
			<lb />
			not proved.
			<lb />
			(The award under this
			<lb />
			claim is set aside only
			<lb />
			to
			<lb />
			reconsider
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			purport of entire Item
			<lb />
			No.2 in the Schedule of
			<lb />
			Rates showing approx
			<lb />
			475 approvals.)
			<lb />
			3a
			<lb />
			&amp;
			<lb />
			3b
			<lb />
			Liquidated
			<lb />
			damages
			<lb />
			There
			<lb />
			was
			<lb />
			admittedly
			<lb />
			a
			<lb />
			delay of more
			<lb />
			than 10 weeks
			<lb />
			contemplated
			<lb />
			under
			<lb />
			Clause
			<lb />
			18. The amount
			<lb />
			withheld is the
			<lb />
			preestimated
			<lb />
			quantity of loss
			<lb />
			suffered.
			<lb />
			Reliance
			<lb />
			upon
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			case
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			ONGC Vs. Saw
			<lb />
			Pipes is made.
			<lb />
			Petitioner
			<lb />
			has
			<lb />
			only stated but
			<lb />
			not led evidence
			<lb />
			that
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			respondent has
			<lb />
			not suffered any
			<lb />
			loss.
			<lb />
			Upon the application of
			<lb />
			the principles laid down
			<lb />
			in Saw Pipes case, the
			<lb />
			respondent did not
			<lb />
			have to prove loss
			<lb />
			caused.
			<lb />
			The Petitioner had to
			<lb />
			prove that no loss was
			<lb />
			caused.
			<lb />
			That is not proved upon
			<lb />
			the general denial of
			<lb />
			the respondent.
			<lb />
			4
			<lb />
			Entries
			<lb />
			in
			<lb />
			revenue records
			<lb />
			The
			<lb />
			arbitrator
			<lb />
			has referred to
			<lb />
			his
			<lb />
			own
			<lb />
			experience
			<lb />
			relating
			<lb />
			to
			<lb />
			recording
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			names in the
			<lb />
			revenue records.
			<lb />
			The work is
			<lb />
			within the scope
			<lb />
			of the contract.
			<lb />
			It is in terms of
			<lb />
			PP Act.
			<lb />
			Claim has been
			<lb />
			not made as per
			<lb />
			Clause 47.
			<lb />
			The Work falls within
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			terms
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			contract.
			<lb />
			5
			<lb />
			NOC
			<lb />
			for
			<lb />
			revenue forests
			<lb />
			The petitioners
			<lb />
			work is for the
			<lb />
			job for which
			<lb />
			composite rate
			<lb />
			has been agreed.
			<lb />
			Clause 47 has
			<lb />
			not
			<lb />
			been
			<lb />
			complied.
			<lb />
			The work falls under
			<lb />
			Item 2 of the Schedule
			<lb />
			of Rates. (It must be
			<lb />
			reconsidered along with
			<lb />
			Claim No.2)
			<lb />
			6
			<lb />
			Preparation of
			<lb />
			executive
			<lb />
			summary
			<lb />
			It
			<lb />
			was
			<lb />
			not
			<lb />
			prepared to the
			<lb />
			satisfaction
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			the respondent.
			<lb />
			It was a part of
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			composite
			<lb />
			job for which
			<lb />
			the rate fixed
			<lb />
			has been paid.
			<lb />
			It is included in the
			<lb />
			terms of the Contract.
			<lb />
			7
			<lb />
			Additional
			<lb />
			overheads
			<lb />
			Termination of
			<lb />
			the agreement is
			<lb />
			not
			<lb />
			unlawful,
			<lb />
			hence additional
			<lb />
			overheads
			<lb />
			cannot
			<lb />
			be
			<lb />
			claimed.
			<lb />
			The
			<lb />
			petitioner
			<lb />
			has not led any
			<lb />
			evidence
			<lb />
			to
			<lb />
			prove
			<lb />
			any
			<lb />
			overheads
			<lb />
			or
			<lb />
			loss.
			<lb />
			No evidence to prove
			<lb />
			the extent of the
			<lb />
			overheads claimed.
			<lb />
			8
			<lb />
			Loss of profit.
			<lb />
			The
			<lb />
			petitioner
			<lb />
			has not been
			<lb />
			able to complete
			<lb />
			the work within
			<lb />
			No evidence to prove
			<lb />
			the extent of the loss
			<lb />
			claimed.
			<lb />
			12 months.
			<lb />
			That was not on
			<lb />
			account of force
			<lb />
			majeure
			<lb />
			or
			<lb />
			attributable to
			<lb />
			respondent.
			<lb />
			Hence loss of
			<lb />
			profit has to be
			<lb />
			borne by the
			<lb />
			petitioner.
			<lb />
			9A
			<lb />
			Physical
			<lb />
			verification
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			crossings
			<lb />
			The
			<lb />
			petitioner
			<lb />
			has not provided
			<lb />
			clear particulars.
			<lb />
			The
			<lb />
			petitioner
			<lb />
			has
			<lb />
			not
			<lb />
			led
			<lb />
			evidence
			<lb />
			to
			<lb />
			establish
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			verification
			<lb />
			done.
			<lb />
			Work is a part of the
			<lb />
			Contract.
			<lb />
			Verification
			<lb />
			for
			<lb />
			20
			<lb />
			months as claimed is
			<lb />
			not proved.
			<lb />
			9B
			<lb />
			Composite
			<lb />
			afforestation of
			<lb />
			land
			<lb />
			This was the
			<lb />
			part
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			composite job.
			<lb />
			No evidence of transfer
			<lb />
			of land or market value
			<lb />
			given.
			<lb />
			Work included in the
			<lb />
			terms of the Contract.
			<lb />
			10
			<lb />
			Withholding of
			<lb />
			retention money
			<lb />
			and
			<lb />
			delayed
			<lb />
			payments.
			<lb />
			The
			<lb />
			petitioner
			<lb />
			has not given
			<lb />
			notice claiming
			<lb />
			interest at a
			<lb />
			particular rate
			<lb />
			from a particular
			<lb />
			date.
			<lb />
			The
			<lb />
			petitioner
			<lb />
			has not led any
			<lb />
			evidence
			<lb />
			to
			<lb />
			Extent of the interest
			<lb />
			claimed is not proved.
			<lb />
			Statutory notice is not
			<lb />
			given.
			<lb />
			prove
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			particulars given
			<lb />
			by the petitioner.
			<lb />
			11 &amp;
			<lb />
			12
			<lb />
			Not pressed
		</table>
		<lb />
		<p>
			230.
			<lb />
			Upon the elaborate and detailed arguments of Mr.
			<lb />
			Andhyarujina it may be seen that several points of law as also questions of
			<lb />
			fact both have arisen under the aforesaid claims. Each of those detailed
			<lb />
			contentions have indeed not been considered. The arbitration is with
			<lb />
			regard to a commercial contract. The arbitrator is not a judicial officer. He
			<lb />
			is stated to be a retired IAS officer. He is a man from the trade and would
			<lb />
			see the contract commercially. &quot;The arbitrator is a man of trade.&quot; (See.
			<lb />
			Alankit (Supra)). He has considered the most pertinent contentions to
			<lb />
			reject the claims. The lack of proof by the petitioner by leading evidence in
			<lb />
			respect of the 778 approvals claimed upon 269 applications made, copies
			<lb />
			of which were also not produced would show that such a tall claim
			<lb />
			hitherto unproved could not be granted, the other questions of law is
			<lb />
			notwithstanding.
			<lb />
			Similarly when the petitioner claimed additional
			<lb />
			payment not under any particular clause of the contract but for what he
			<lb />
			claimed was additional work done e.g. the claims for updating the revenue
			<lb />
			records, afforestation, verification of crossings, preparation of executive
			<lb />
			summary etc. for all of which a composite rate was agreed and was held to
			<lb />
			have fallen within the terms of the Contract those clauses could not be
			<lb />
			entertained despite other contentions, however legally erudite, such as the
			<lb />
			voidability of Clause 47 under Section 28(b) of the ICA. Similarly if the
			<lb />
			learned arbitrator held that the clause relating to liquidated damages was
			<lb />
			applicable and no evidence was led to show no loss, the question of law
			<lb />
			relating to the subtle distinction between Sections 73 &amp; 74 of the ICA or
			<lb />
			the interpretation and analysis of Section 55 of the ICA relating to time
			<lb />
			being the essence of the contract would only follow as consequence and
			<lb />
			would be secondary. The claims would have to be rejected for the singular
			<lb />
			reasons stated above, the nuances of the law, notwithstanding. The
			<lb />
			arbitrator is not expected to analyse such law and authorities (See. M/s.
			<lb />
			Ircon (Supra)). When the petitioner applied for payment for what he
			<lb />
			considered was the additional work not within the scope of the contract
			<lb />
			but only submitted statements without leading evidence to prove the
			<lb />
			statements, the mere observation that no evidence was led would suffice.
			<lb />
			Further reasons to be given need not be gone into by probing the mental
			<lb />
			process of the arbitrator as required in T N Electricity Board (Supra). Of
			<lb />
			course, the learned arbitrator has not set out the precise clauses of the
			<lb />
			agreement under which the work done by the petitioner has fallen as a
			<lb />
			composite job. Yet these conclusions are supported by the material and
			<lb />
			evidence on record, clauses in the contract itself being shown to Court
			<lb />
			complying with Madhok (Supra).
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			231.
			<lb />
			Consequently it would suffice to state that the reasons given
			<lb />
			by the learned Arbitrator are sufficient.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<head>
			Public Policy
			<lb />
		</head>

		<p>
			232.
			<lb />
			Mr. Andhyarujina would argue that the award would be
			<lb />
			against public policy in view of what he stated were its deficiencies.
			<lb />
			However, he relied upon in the case of Simplex Concrete Pilies (I.) Ltd.
			<lb />
			Vs. Union of India, 2010 LawSuit(Del) 4632, in which the contract was
			<lb />
			held to be void under section 23 of the ICA as being against public policy of
			<lb />
			India. The case referred to the entitlement to claim damages under section
			<lb />
			17 read with section 55 of the ICA in view of it being void under Section
			<lb />
			23 of the Contract Act. The reliance upon that judgment is to show which
			<lb />
			are void contracts and to claim that the contract between the parties herein
			<lb />
			would be void at least so far as Clause 47 is concerned. That has not been
			<lb />
			the plea of the petitioner in the claim or even in this petition. It could not
			<lb />
			have been adjudicated in arbitration and cannot be considered in this
			<lb />
			petition.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			ORDER
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			(i)
			<lb />
			The rejection of all the claims of the petitioner, except Claims Nos.2
			<lb />
			&amp; 5 to the extent stated above, are upheld.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			(ii) Only Claim Nos. 2 &amp; 5 are set aside to the above extent.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			(iii) The arbitration petition with regard to the remaining claims stands
			<lb />
			dismissed.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			(iv) The Court is gratified to note that both Counsel argued different
			<lb />
			facets of the laws with depth and industry and had able, appropriate and
			<lb />
			immediate assistance from their junior colleagues.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>(ROSHAN DALVI J.)</p>
	</text>
</tei>