<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<p>Una, in Civil Suit No.99/2003 has been reversed, with a prayer to<lb/> set aside the same and to restore the judgment and decree passed<lb/> by the learned Trial Court.<lb/></p>

			<p>2.<lb/> The brief facts giving rise to the present appeal are:<lb/> that the Appellant/respondent (hereinafter to be<lb/> called as &quot;the appellant&quot;) maintained a suit for posession by way<lb/> of eviction and recovery of Rs.14,000/ on the contention that he<lb/> is the owner of the premises in the lis and the same was let out<lb/> by him to the respondent/plaintiff (hereinafter to be called as &quot;the<lb/> respondent&quot;) on a monthly rent of Rs.500/ in the month of June,<lb/> 1995. As per the plaintiff/respondent, the rent has not been paid<lb/> from June, 2001 to April, 2003 and, thus, the appellant is in<lb/> arrears of rent. Further, that the tenancy of the respondent was<lb/> terminated by a notice.<lb/></p>

			<p>3.<lb/> The defendant contested the suit and averred that the<lb/> land underneath the shop was given on lease on a monthly lease<lb/> money of Rs.10/ and the same was enhanced to Rs.50/. Further,<lb/> that after getting land on lease, the respondent raised super<lb/> structure with his own funds and at that time, it was agreed by<lb/> the predecessorininterest of the plaintiff/respondent that lease<lb/> is of permanent nature and so long the defendant pays the lease<lb/> money, he would not be evicted. As per the defendant, the<lb/> allegation of the plaintiff, that the shop in question was rented<lb/> out by the appellant on 01.6.1995, altogether is wrong and false.<lb/> It has been pleaded that the lease money has been paid to the<lb/> plaintiff till April, 2003.<lb/></p>

			<p>4.<lb/> The learned Trial Court, on completion of the<lb/> pleadings and after recording the evidence, dismissed the suit<lb/> holding that the plaintiff, though owner of the land, has failed to<lb/> prove that the premises was let out to the appellant on a monthly<lb/> rent of Rs.500/ w.e.f. 01.6.1995 and the termination of the<lb/> tenancy and the recovery of the arrears has been held to be not<lb/> tenable.<lb/></p>

			<p>5.<lb/> The learned District Judge, while setting aside the<lb/> reasoned and balanced judgment of the learned Trial Court,<lb/> decreed the suit. The learned District Judge has held that the<lb/> rent is Rs.100/ per month and the appellant is in arrears of rent<lb/> since 01.1.2001 and while passing the decree of possession by<lb/> eviction, a decree for recovery of Rs.9,600/ was also passed.<lb/></p>

			<p>6.<lb/> On the pleadings of the parties, the learned Trial<lb/> Court framed the following issues :<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot;1. Whether the shop doneted by letters ABCD<lb/> shown red in the site plan are owned by the<lb/> plaintiff as alleged?<lb/></item>

			<item>...<lb/> … OPP<lb/></item>

			<item>2.<lb/> Whether the defendant took aforesaid shops on<lb/> rent at the rat eof Rs.500/ per month from the<lb/> plaintiff since 1.6.1995, as alleged?<lb/></item>

			<item>...<lb/> … OPD<lb/></item>

			<item>3.<lb/> Whether the suit is not maintainable?<lb/></item>

			<item>...<lb/> … OPD<lb/></item>

			<item>4.<lb/> Whether the tenancy of the defendant has been<lb/> validly terminated by the plaintiff vide notice<lb/> dated 8.5.2003?<lb/> ...<lb/> … OPP<lb/></item>

			<item>5.<lb/> Whether the plaintiff is entitled to the relief of<lb/> possession, as claimed?<lb/></item>

			<item>...<lb/> … OPP<lb/></item>

			<item>6.<lb/> Whether the site underneath the shops was<lb/> taken on lease of Rs. 10/ per month, which<lb/> stands enhanced now to Rs.50/ per month, as<lb/> alleged. If so, its effect?<lb/></item>

			<item>...<lb/> … OPD<lb/></item>

			<item>7.<lb/> Whether there was an oral agreement between<lb/> the parties that defendant shall not be ejected<lb/> from the site underneath the shops so long as he<lb/> pays rent as alleged, If so, its effect?<lb/></item>

			<item>... … OPD<lb/></item>

			<item>8.<lb/> Relief.&quot;<lb/></item>

			<p>7.<lb/> The learned Trial Court decided Issue No.1 in favour<lb/> of the plaintiff and Issues No.2 to 5 against the plaintiff and<lb/> Issues No.6 and 7 against the defendants and dismissed the suit.<lb/></p>

			<p>8.<lb/> The defendants maintained the appeal before the<lb/> learned Lower Appellate Court, which was allowed and the<lb/> judgment and decree passed by the learned Trial Court was set<lb/> aside. Hence, the present regular second appeal, which was<lb/> admitted on 20.4.2010, on the following substantial question of<lb/> law:<lb/></p>

			<p>&quot;1. Whether the findings of the learned<lb/> trial Court as well as first Appellate Court<lb/> are result of complete misreading and<lb/> misinterpretation of the evidence and<lb/> material on record and against the settled<lb/> position of law?&quot;<lb/></p>

			<p>9.<lb/> I have heard the learned counsel for the parties and<lb/> have also gone through the record.<lb/></p>

			<p>10.<lb/> Learned Senior Counsel for the appellant/respondent<lb/> has argued that the judgment and decree passed by the learned<lb/> Lower Appellate Court is without appreciating the facts, which<lb/> have come on record to its true perspective and the same is<lb/> required to be set aside. He has further argued that it was<lb/> incumbent upon the learned Lower Appellate Court to give<lb/> findings on each and every aspect, but the learned Appellate<lb/> Court has failed to do so.<lb/></p>

			<p>11.<lb/> On the other hand, the learned Senior Counsel<lb/> appearing for the respondent/defendant has argued that the<lb/> judgment and decree passed by the learned Lower Appellate<lb/> Court is just and reasoned and requires no intereference. He<lb/> has further argued that the learned Trial Court has given its<lb/> findings on each and every aspect in detail and no interference is<lb/> required to be taken at this moment.<lb/></p>

			<p>12.<lb/> In rebuttal, the learned counsel for the<lb/> apellant/plaintiff has argued that there is substantial question of<lb/> law involved, which needs to be adjudicated upon. He has further<lb/> argued that the appeal be allowed.<lb/></p>

			<p>13.<lb/> To appreciate the arguments of the learned counsel<lb/> for the parties, I have gone through the record of the case, in<lb/> detail.<lb/></p>

			<p>14.<lb/> PW1 Piara Singh had stated that he had been the<lb/> owner of the shop in dispute and he had rented out the shop to<lb/> the defendant on monthly rent of Rs.500/ w.e.f. 01.06.1995 and<lb/> that the appellant/defendant had not paid the rent w.e.f.<lb/> 01.01.2001. He has further stated that his son was without any<lb/> job and he wanted to settle him and on this ground he had sought<lb/> eviction of the defendant. However, the defendant despite receipt<lb/> of notice, did not vacate the premises nor had paid any rent. The<lb/> evidence of this PW had been endorsed and supported by PW2<lb/> Bakhshish Singh and PW3 Darshan Singh.<lb/></p>

			<p>15.<lb/> PW4 had prepared the site plan of the premises,<lb/> Ext.PW4/A and against the said evidence of the plaintiff, the<lb/> defendant, including himself, had examined seven DWs.<lb/></p>

			<p>DW1 Ramesh Chand, MHC had tendered in evidence report,<lb/> Ext. DX, of Daily Diary of Police Post, Haroli on 24.01.1995. It<lb/> has been submitted that the premises in dispute had been<lb/> partially affected by fire on the night intervening 23.01.1995 and<lb/> 24.01.1995. DW2 Sarvan Singh was an official of HPSEB. During<lb/> his examination, he has stated that premises in dispute stood<lb/> provided power connection on and w.e.f. 20.07.1993. DW3,<lb/> Ramesh Kumar was an official of Weights and Measures<lb/> Department. DW3 had stated that the defendant had been issued<lb/> certificate/rectipt Ext. DW3/A on 17.05.1985 and the Weights of<lb/> the defendant had been certified by the then Inspector, Weights<lb/> and Measures Department. DW4 Pawan Kumar and DW7<lb/> Dharam Pal had stated that the defendant had been doing<lb/> business of food article and the local health authorities had issued<lb/> licence Ext.DW4/A and DW7/A in favour fo the defendant in the<lb/> year 198889. DW5 Bhajan Singh had stated that defendant had<lb/> construted the premises in dispute sometimes in the year 196667<lb/> and the defendant had been doing business. The defendant had<lb/> not taken the premises in question on rent from the plaintiff.<lb/></p>

			<p>DW6 Charna (appellant herein) had controverted the evidence of<lb/> the plaintiff.<lb/></p>

			<p>16.<lb/> When the notice was issued to the defendant by the<lb/> plaintiff, he has mentioned that the shop, in question, was given<lb/> to him on rent in the year 1995 at the rate of Rs.500/ per month,<lb/> but this fact found to be not correct as the defendant was running<lb/> the shop as per the witness of the plaintiff itself, i.e. PW4 from<lb/> the year 1985. The specific stand of the defendant that he had<lb/> constructed the shop consisting two rooms on the leased land<lb/> belonging to the plaintiff is not specifically controverted in the<lb/> replication. At the same point of time, the Government<lb/> Departments have given Licence Ext.DW7/A and Ext. DW7/B for<lb/> sale of food, Tea &amp; Sweets in the premises at Pubowal in the year<lb/> 198889. The Weights and Measures Department has certified<lb/> the weights and measures of the defendant in the year, 1985 vide<lb/> Ext.DW3/A.<lb/></p>

			<p>17.<lb/> Now, to the &apos;Rapt&apos; with regard to the fire. The<lb/> Rapat mark &apos;DX&apos; shows that on 23.01.1995, there was fire in the<lb/> shop, but after analysing mark DX, it is found that the fire<lb/> destroyed (Khahadposh) big grass roofed verandah of the shop<lb/> where the Benches were kept and on one side, was a &apos;Bhatti&apos; and<lb/> the loss was about to Rs.3,000/ only. It seems that the plaintiff<lb/> has taken the cause from this time onward, but the shop having<lb/> two rooms remained intact as per the perusal of mark DX. This<lb/> all shows that had the shop been given to the defendant on rent<lb/> prior to the year 1985, the plaintiff would have again asked the<lb/> defendant for the rent from the year 1985, if not paid, but he has<lb/> contested his case from the year 1995, but the facts on record<lb/> clearly shows that the shop having two rooms was with the<lb/> defendant prior to the year 1995. As per the defendant, he has<lb/> constructed the shop and there is no clear denial by the plaintiff<lb/> in the replication to this effect. The plaintiff has not stated that<lb/> when the shop was constructed; by whom shop was construcred<lb/> and who was keeping the shop in question before the year 1995.<lb/> In these circumstances, the version of the plaintiff is not reliable<lb/> at all and the version of the defendant is reliable. Hence, the<lb/> findings recorded by the learned Lower Appellate Court are, thus,<lb/> without any basis.<lb/></p>

			<p>18.<lb/> This Court finds that the findings recorded by the<lb/> learned Appellate Court are perverse and so, the findings as<lb/> recorded by the learned Appellate Court are not sustainable in<lb/> the eyes of law. In these circumstances, this Court comes to the<lb/> conclusion that the findings of the learned Lower Appellate Court<lb/> are perverse. So, the substantial question of law, as framed, is<lb/> answered accordingly.<lb/></p>

			<p>19.<lb/> The net result of the above discussion is that the<lb/> appeal is required to be allowed, which is allowed and the<lb/> judgment and decree passed by the learned Lower Appellate<lb/> Court is set aside and that of the learned Trial Court is affirmed.<lb/> Pending application(s) if any, also stands disposed of. No costs.<lb/></p>

			<p>(Chander Bhusan Barowalia)<lb/> Judge<lb/> September 10 , 2019.<lb/></p>

			<p>(M. gandhi)</p>


	</text>
</tei>
