<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<head>Coram<lb/> Ms. Jyotsna Rewal Dua, Judge<lb/> Whether approved for reporting? 1 Yes.<lb/></head>

			<p>For the Petitioners:<lb/></p>

			<p>Mr. Ajay Kumar, Senior Advocate with<lb/> Mr. Dheeraj K. Vashisht, Advocate.<lb/> For the Respondent: Mr. N.K. Thakur, Senior Advocate with<lb/> Mr. Karan Veer Singh, Advocate.<lb/> ------------------------------------------------------------------------------------<lb/>Jyotsna Rewal Dua, Judge<lb/> Defendants moved an application under Order 7<lb/> Rule 11 read with Section 151 of the Code of Civil<lb/> Procedure for rejection of plaint on account of filing less<lb/> amount of Court fee by the plaintiff. The application was<lb/> dismissed by the learned Trial Court on 31.01.2013. This<lb/> order of learned Trial Court has been questioned by the<lb/> 1 Whether reporters of print and electronic media may be allowed to see the order?<lb/> defendants in the instant petition preferred under Article<lb/> 227 of the Constitution of India.<lb/></p>

			<p>2.<lb/> Facts:-<lb/>2(i).<lb/> Civil Suit was filed by the respondent in the year<lb/> 2011 with the averments that:-<lb/></p>

			<item>(a). Suit land measuring 00-76-52 hectares was owned<lb/> and possessed by her father late Sh. Satdev, who was also<lb/> holder of account Nos. i.e. A/c No.492934 in Post Office,<lb/> Una having an amount of Rs.65,922/-and A/c No.367 in<lb/> Basoli Agricultural Service Co-operative Society having an<lb/> amount of Rs.7,64,471/-.<lb/></item>

			<p>(b).<lb/> Parents of the plaintiff were divorced. Though<lb/> the custody of the plaintiff remained with her father,<lb/> however, finding constant watch and care of the little<lb/> child/plaintiff difficult and owing to his strained relations<lb/> with other family members, Sh. Satdev had entrusted the<lb/> wellbeing of the plaintiff with her maternal uncle.<lb/></p>

			<p>(c).<lb/> Deceased Satdev had sufficient landed property<lb/> in his name and funds in his accounts. He developed<lb/> mental sickness and could not apprehend the things<lb/> properly. During the period of his mental illness, he was<lb/> looked after by the plaintiff and her maternal uncle. Sh.<lb/> Satdev passed away on 04.07.2010.<lb/></p>

			<p>(d).<lb/> After mourning the death of her father, when the<lb/> plaintiff approached the office of Basoli Agricultural Service<lb/> Co-operative Society for getting her name incorporated in<lb/> the account of her father, she became aware of the fact that<lb/> the amount lying in the account had been transferred to the<lb/> account of one of the defendants on the basis of a will<lb/> statedly executed by her late father. Subsequently, a<lb/> dispute with respect to attestation of mutation also arose<lb/> between the parties in respect of rights over the landed<lb/> property of the deceased.<lb/></p>

			<p>(e).<lb/> Father of the plaintiff had never executed the<lb/> alleged will during his lifetime in favour of the defendants.<lb/> The will is forged, fabricated, invalid, null and void. There<lb/> was no reason for plaintiff&apos;s father to disinherit her from his<lb/> estate as she was his only daughter and in good relations<lb/> with him. In any case, the land was Joint Hindu Family<lb/> Coparcenary property of plaintiff and her deceased father, it<lb/> could not be alienated in any manner save and except for<lb/> legal necessity.<lb/></p>

			<p>2(ii).<lb/> The plaintiff valued the suit for the purposes of<lb/> Court Fees and Jurisdiction at Rs.130/-and accordingly<lb/> affixed the Court Fees. In the relief clause, plaintiff sought a<lb/> declaration that the land measuring 00-76-52 hectares<lb/> (comprised in 14 different parcels/khasra numbers) is<lb/> owned and possessed by her and she is also entitled to<lb/> operate and receive the amount lying in two accounts of her<lb/> deceased father, being his daughter and natural heir. The<lb/> plaintiff also sought the relief of declaring the will dated<lb/> 09.05.2010 qua the estate of deceased Satdev in favour of<lb/> the defendants as fake, forged, fabricated, void ab-initio,<lb/> having no adverse effect upon the right, title and interest of<lb/> the plaintiff over the suit property as the same was Joint<lb/> Hindu Family Coparcenary property, which could not be<lb/> alienated except for legal necessity and without the consent<lb/> of other Co-parcener/plaintiff.<lb/> Alongwith the above declaratory reliefs, plaintiff<lb/> also sought consequential relief of permanent injunction for<lb/> restraining the defendants from getting the revenue entries<lb/> recorded in their names on the basis of alleged will, for<lb/> ousting the plaintiff from the joint possession, changing the<lb/> nature and character of the suit land till its partition and<lb/> for releasing the amount lying in the accounts of her father<lb/> in favour of the defendants. In the alternative, decree for<lb/> joint possession was also prayed for. It will be appropriate<lb/> to extract the relief clause:-<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot;It is therefore, prayed that a decree for declaration to the<lb/> effect that the land measuring 00-76-52 Hects detailed<lb/> below:-<lb/></item>

			<item>(i) to (xiv)<lb/> …………………<lb/> (xv)<lb/> …………………… is owned and possessed by the plaintiff and<lb/> she is also entitled to operate and receive the amount of about<lb/> Rs.65922/-laying in A/C No.492934 in the post office Una,<lb/> Div. Una (H.P.) as well as an amount of about Rs.7,64,471/-<lb/>laying in A/C No.367 in Basoli Agricultural Service Co-<lb/>operative Society, VPO Basoli Tehsil &amp; Distt. Una (H.P.), along<lb/> with interest being the only daughter as well as natural<lb/> heir/successor-in-interest of deceased Satdev S/O Jagan Nath<lb/> and the alleged WILL dated 09-05-2010 qua the estate of<lb/> deceased Satdev in favour of defts is fake, forged, fabricated,<lb/> invalid document and which is wrong, illegal, void ab-initio,<lb/> ineffective, inoperative, having no adverse effect upon the<lb/> right, title and interest of pelff over suit property, as the same<lb/> was joint Hindu family co-parcenary property of pelff and her<lb/> father which cannot be alienated in any manner by the<lb/> manager of joint Hindu family except for legal necessity and<lb/> without the consent of other co-parcener i.e. pelff, with<lb/> consequential relief of permanent injunction restraining the<lb/> defts from getting mutation/revenue entries in their names on<lb/> the basis of alleged will, ousting the pelff forcibly from joint<lb/> possession, changing nature and character in any manner<lb/> until final partition of suit land or making any kind of<lb/> alienation of specific khasra nos., getting release the amount<lb/> laying in aforesaid accounts and in the alternative decree for<lb/> joint possession and any other relief which this Hon&apos;ble court<lb/> may deems fit and just in the facts and circumstances of the<lb/> case may kindly be passed in favour of plaintiff and against<lb/> the defendants with costs in the interest of justice U/Ss 34 to<lb/> 38 of Specific Relief Act.&quot;<lb/></item>

			<p>2(iii).<lb/> Defendants No.1, 3 and 2, 4 filed their separate<lb/> written statements. In both the written statements, a<lb/> preliminary objection was taken that the suit had not been<lb/> valued properly for the purposes of Court Fee and<lb/> Jurisdiction. The reason assigned for taking this objection<lb/> was that the plaintiff had sought relief regarding Account<lb/> No.367, which had an amount of Rs.7,64,471/-, upon<lb/> which she was required to affix the Court Fee of<lb/> Rs.10,210/-, whereas she had valued the suit at Rs.130/-<lb/>and affixed court fee of Rs.23/-. It was asserted that the<lb/> Court below had no jurisdiction to try and entertain the<lb/> present suit.<lb/></p>

			<p>2(iv).<lb/> A separate application under Order 7 Rule 11 of<lb/> the Code of Civil Procedure was moved by the defendants<lb/> seeking rejection of plaint on following grounds:-<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot;2 That the plaintiff has filed the suit for declaration vide which<lb/> she is claiming herself to be owner in possession of the suit<lb/> land. The further relief claimed by the plaintiff is that she is<lb/> entitled to receive an amount of Rs.65922/-as well as<lb/> Rs.7,64,471/-.<lb/></item>

			<item>3<lb/> That the plaintiff-applicant wrongly valued the suit to the tune<lb/> of Rs.130/-and has affixed the court fee of Rs.23/-whereas<lb/> as per the pleadings particularly keeping in view the relief<lb/> claimed by the plaintiff she is require to affix the court fee on<lb/> the value of Rs.7,64,471/-which comes to Rs.10210/-.&quot;<lb/></item>

			<p>The application was dismissed by the learned<lb/> Trial Court vide order dated 31.01.2013. Aggrieved, the<lb/> defendants/petitioners have moved this Court by way of the<lb/> present petition.<lb/></p>

			<p>3.<lb/> Heard learned counsel for the parties and gone<lb/> through the record.<lb/> The contention raised on behalf of the<lb/> petitioners/defendants is that the suit filed by the plaintiff<lb/> was governed by Section 7(iv)(c) of the Himachal Pradesh<lb/> Court Fees Act, 1968 and ad valorem Court Fees on the<lb/> amount claimed was liable to be paid for the purpose of<lb/> Court Fee and Jurisdiction. It is further contended that the<lb/> learned Court below had no jurisdiction to try the suit on<lb/> account of lack of pecuniary jurisdiction to deal with the<lb/> matter. In support of his contention, learned Senior<lb/> Counsel has relied upon the judgments rendered in<lb/> 2006(3) Shim. LC 92, titled Devta Satya Narain and<lb/> another Versus Lal Chand and others and CMPMO<lb/> No.2012 &amp; CMP No.1396 of 2012, titled Khawaja<lb/> Khallilullah Versus Mrs. Shamem Butt and others,<lb/> decided on 01.04.2013.<lb/> Whereas on behalf of the respondent/plaintiff, it<lb/> is argued that affixation of Court Fee, in view of the reliefs<lb/> prayed for by the plaintiff, will be governed by Section<lb/> 7(iv)(c) first proviso of the Himachal Pradesh Court Fees<lb/> Act, 1968 and accordingly Court Fee of Rs.23/-has been<lb/> affixed. The suit is only for seeking a decree of declaration<lb/> alongwith consequential relief of permanent injunction.<lb/></p>

			<p>4.<lb/> Observations:-<lb/></p>

			<p>4(i).<lb/> Affixation of Court Fee in the instant case is<lb/> governed by the Himachal Pradesh Court Fees Act, 1968.<lb/> Section 7 whereof computes the fees payable in certain<lb/> suits. The relevant portion of this section is as follows:-<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot;7.<lb/> Computation of fees payable in certain suits-The amount of<lb/> fee payable under this Act in the suits next hereinafter<lb/> mentioned shall be computed as follows:-<lb/>(i) to (iii) ……………………………..<lb/></item>

			<item>(iv)<lb/> in suits-<lb/>(a)<lb/> …………………………………….<lb/></item>

			<item>(b)<lb/> …………………………………….<lb/></item>

			<item>(c)<lb/> for a declaratory decree and consequential relief; to obtain a<lb/> declaratory decree or order, where consequential relief is<lb/> prayed;<lb/></item>

			<item>(d)<lb/> …………………………………….<lb/></item>

			<item>(e)<lb/> …………………………………….<lb/></item>

			<item>(f)<lb/> …………………………………….<lb/> In all such suits the plaintiff shall state the amount at<lb/> which he values the relief sought;<lb/> Provided that the minimum court-fee in each case shall<lb/> be thirteen rupees:<lb/> Provided further that in suit coming under sub-clause<lb/> (c), in case where the relief sought is with reference to any<lb/> property such valuation shall not be less than the value of the<lb/> property calculated in the manner provided for by paragraph<lb/> (v) of this section;&quot;<lb/></item>

			<p>It is the case of both the parties that Court Fees<lb/> in the instant case will be determined in accordance with<lb/> Section 7(iv)(c) of the Himachal Pradesh Court Fees Act. The<lb/> only dispute is that according to the plaintiff/respondent, it<lb/> will be the first proviso of this section, which would govern<lb/> the determination of Court Fee, whereas according to the<lb/> defendants/petitioners, it is the second proviso which<lb/> would be applicable. In this regard, it will also be<lb/> appropriate to refer to Section 7(v), which provides for<lb/> computation of Court Fees for possession of land/houses<lb/> and gardens:-<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot;(v) for possession of land, houses and gardens; In suits for the<lb/> possession of land houses and gardens-according to the value of<lb/> the subject matter and such value shall be deemed to be-<lb/>where the subject matter is land, and -<lb/></item>

			<item>(a)<lb/> Where the land forms an entire estate, or a definite share of an<lb/> estate paying annual revenue to Government; or<lb/> forms part of such an estate and is recorded in the Collector&apos;s<lb/> register as separately assessed with such revenue,<lb/> and such revenue is permanently settled-ten times the revenue<lb/> so payable;<lb/></item>

			<item>(b)<lb/> where the land forms an entire estate, or a definite share of an<lb/> estate, paying annual revenue to Government or forms part of<lb/> such estate and is recorded as aforesaid;<lb/> and such revenue is settled, but not permanently-ten times the<lb/> revenue so payable;<lb/></item>

			<item>(c)<lb/> Where the land pays no such revenue, or has been partially<lb/> exempted from such payment, or is charged with any fixed<lb/> payment, in lieu of such revenue;<lb/> and net profits have arisen from the land during the year next<lb/> before the date of presenting the plaint fifteen times such net<lb/> profits, but where no such net profits have arisen therefrom-the<lb/> amount at which the court shall estimate the land with reference<lb/> to the value of similar land in the neighbourhood;<lb/></item>

			<item>(d)<lb/> where the land forms part of an estate paying revenue to<lb/> Government, but is not a definite share of such estate and is not<lb/> separately assessed as above mentioned-the market-value of<lb/> the land;<lb/> Explanation-The word &quot;estate&quot;, as used, in this paragraph<lb/> means any land subject to the payment of revenue, for which<lb/> the proprietor or a farmer or ryot shall have executed as<lb/> separate engagement to Government, or which, in the absence of<lb/> such engagement, shall have been separately assessed with<lb/> revenue;<lb/></item>

			<item>(e)<lb/> for houses and gardens; Where the subject matter is house or<lb/> garden-according to the market-value of the house or garden;&quot;<lb/></item>

			<p>4(ii).<lb/> Section 7(iv)(c) of the Himachal Pradesh Court<lb/> Fees Act is similar to Section 7(iv)(c) as applicable in the<lb/> State of Punjab. The provision of Section 7(iv)(c) of Court<lb/> Fees Act, 1870 as amended in Punjab reads as follows:-<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot;7. Computation of fees payable in certain suits.-The amount of fee<lb/> payable under this Act in the suits next hereinafter mentioned shall<lb/> be computed as follows:<lb/> *<lb/> *<lb/> *<lb/></item>

			<item>(iv) in suits-<lb/>*<lb/> *<lb/> *<lb/></item>

			<item>(c) for a declaratory decree and consequential relief.-to obtain a<lb/> declaratory decree or order, where consequential relief is prayed,<lb/> *<lb/> *<lb/> *<lb/> According to the amount at which the relief sought is valued in the<lb/> plaint or memorandum of appeal.<lb/> In all such suits the plaintiff shall state the amount at which he<lb/> values the relief sought:<lb/> Provided that the minimum court fee in each case shall be thirteen<lb/> rupees:<lb/></item>

			<item>Provided further that in suits coming under sub-clause (c), in cases<lb/> where the relief sought is with reference to any property such<lb/> valuation shall not be less than the value of the property calculated in<lb/> the manner provided for by clause (v) of this section.&quot;<lb/></item>

			<p>The above provision as existing in the State of<lb/> Punjab came for consideration of the Hon&apos;ble Apex Court in<lb/> (2010) 12 SCC 112, titled Suhrid Singh Alias Sardool<lb/> Singh Versus Randhir Singh and others. The plaint<lb/> therein contained following prayers:-<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot;(i) for a declaration that two houses and certain agricultural<lb/> lands purchased by his father, S. Rajinder Singh were<lb/> coparcenary properties as they were purchased from the sale<lb/> proceeds of ancestral properties, and that he was entitled to<lb/> joint possession thereof;<lb/></item>

			<item>(ii) for a declaration that the will dated 14-7-1985 with the codicil<lb/> dated 17-8-1988 made in favour of the third defendant, and<lb/> gift deed dated 10-9-2003 made in favour of the fourth<lb/> defendant were void and non est &quot;qua the coparcenary&quot;;<lb/></item>

			<item>(iii) for a declaration that the sale deeds dated 20-4-2001, 24-4-<lb/>2001 and 6-7-2001 executed by his father, S. Rajinder Singh<lb/> in favour of the first defendant and sale deed dated 27-9-2003<lb/> executed by the alleged power-of-attorney holder of S.<lb/> Rajinder Singh in favour of the second defendant, in regard to<lb/> certain agricultural lands (described in the prayer), are null<lb/> and void qua the rights of the &quot;coparcenary&quot;, as they were not<lb/> for legal necessity or for benefit of the family; and<lb/></item>

			<item>(iv) for consequential injunctions restraining Defendants 1 to 4<lb/> from alienating the suit properties.&quot;<lb/></item>

			<p>The question which arose for consideration<lb/> before the Hon&apos;ble Apex Court was that what should be the<lb/> Court Fee payable in regard to the prayer for a declaration<lb/> that sale deeds were void and not binding on the<lb/> Coparcenary and for the consequential relief of joint<lb/> possession and injunction. It was observed by the Court<lb/> that there was no prayer for cancellation of sale deeds. The<lb/> prayer was for declaration that the deeds do not bind the<lb/> Coparcenary and for joint possession. The plaintiff in the<lb/> suit was not the executant of sale deeds. Therefore, the<lb/> Court Fee was computable under Section 7(iv)(c) of the Act.<lb/> It was further held that the Trial Court and the High Court<lb/> were not justified in holding that the effect of prayer was to<lb/> seek cancellation of sale deeds or that the Court Fees had<lb/> to be paid on the sale consideration mentioned in the sale<lb/> deeds. Relevant paras from the judgment are extracted<lb/> hereinafter:-<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot;7.<lb/> Where the executant of a deed wants it to be annulled, he has<lb/> to seek cancellation of the deed. But if a non-executant seeks<lb/> annulment of a deed, he has to seek a declaration that the<lb/> deed is invalid, or non-est, or illegal or that it is not binding on<lb/> him. The difference between a prayer for cancellation and<lb/> declaration in regard to a deed of transfer/conveyance, can be<lb/> brought out by the following illustration relating to `A&apos; and `B&apos; -<lb/>-two brothers. `A&apos; executes a sale deed in favour of `C&apos;.<lb/> Subsequently `A&apos; wants to avoid the sale. `A&apos; has to sue for<lb/> cancellation of the deed. On the other hand, if `B&apos;, who is not<lb/> the executant of the deed, wants to avoid it, he has to sue for<lb/> a declaration that the deed executed by `A&apos; is invalid/void and<lb/> non-est/illegal and he is not bound by it. In essence both may<lb/> be suing to have the deed set aside or declared as non-<lb/>binding. But the form is different and court fee is also<lb/> different. If `A&apos;, the executant of the deed, seeks cancellation of<lb/> the deed, he has to pay ad-valorem court fee on the<lb/> consideration stated in the sale deed. If `B&apos;, who is a non-<lb/>executant, is in possession and sues for a declaration that the<lb/> deed is null or void and does not bind him or his share, he has<lb/> to merely pay a fixed court fee of Rs.19.50 under Article<lb/> 17(iii) of Second Schedule of the Act. But if `B&apos;, a non-<lb/>executant, is not in possession, and he seeks not only a<lb/> declaration that the sale deed is invalid, but also the<lb/> consequential relief of possession, he has to pay an ad-<lb/>valorem court fee as provided under Section 7(iv)(c) of the Act.<lb/></item>

			<item>8.<lb/> Section 7(iv)(c) provides that in suits for a declaratory decree<lb/> with consequential relief, the court fee shall be computed<lb/> according to the amount at which the relief sought is valued in<lb/> the plaint. The proviso thereto makes it clear that where the<lb/> suit for declaratory decree with consequential relief is with<lb/> reference to any property, such valuation shall not be less<lb/> than the value of the property calculated in the manner<lb/> provided for by clause (v) of Section 7.<lb/></item>

			<item>9.<lb/> In this case, there is no prayer for cancellation of the sale<lb/> deeds. The prayer is for a declaration that the deeds do not<lb/> bind the &quot;co-parcenery&quot; and for joint possession. The plaintiff<lb/> in the suit was not the executant of the sale deeds. Therefore,<lb/> the court fee was computable under section 7(iv)(c) of the Act.<lb/> The trial court and the High Court were therefore not justified<lb/> in holding that the effect of the prayer was to seek cancellation<lb/> of the sale deeds or that therefore court fee had to be paid on<lb/> the sale consideration mentioned in the sale deeds.&quot;<lb/></item>

			<p>4(iii).<lb/> In (2017) 11 SCC 852, titled J. Vasanthi and<lb/> Others Versus N. Ramani Kanthammal (Dead)<lb/> Represented by Legal Representative and Others, the<lb/> plaintiff filed the suit for declaration that the sale deeds<lb/> were fabricated and therefore, were void. Considering the<lb/> provisions of Tamil Nadu Court Fees and Suit Valuation<lb/> Act, it was held that suit for declaration for treating the<lb/> documents null and void amounts to seeking relief of<lb/> cancellation of documents. When plaintiff was party to such<lb/> transactions as in that case, then the Court Fee is to be<lb/> computed on the value of subject matter. Relevant para of<lb/> the judgment reads as under:-<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot;11. The singular issue that gains significance in this case is that<lb/> the original plaintiff was a party to the transaction. Section<lb/> 40 of the Act, as we notice, provides that in a suit for<lb/> cancellation of a document, the court fee has to be computed<lb/> on the value of the subject-matter of the suit and such value<lb/> shall be deemed to be the whole decree or other document<lb/> which is sought to be cancelled, the amount or value of the<lb/> property for which the decree was passed or other document<lb/> was executed. It also spelt out that a part of the decree or<lb/> other document is to be cancelled, such part of the amount or<lb/> value of the property. On a careful scrutiny of the provision, it<lb/> is limpid that it refers to the decree or other document and in<lb/> that context, it uses the word &quot;value&quot;. The stand of the<lb/> respondents before the High Court as well as before this Court<lb/> is that the documents were sought to be declared as null and<lb/> void on the ground of fraud and, therefore, Section 40 of the<lb/> Act would not be attracted. In this regard, we may notice<lb/> certain decisions of the High Court of Madras.&quot;<lb/></item>

			<p>The Apex Court noticed the decision in Suhrid<lb/> Singh&apos;s case, supra, as well as in Shailendra Bhardwaj<lb/> Versus Chandra Pal, (2013) 1 SCC 579 and observed that<lb/> these two decisions are in context of different situations<lb/> and based upon different enactments. Decision in Suhrid<lb/> Singh&apos;s case, supra, was based upon the Court Fees<lb/> provisions as they existed in the State of Punjab and the<lb/> judgment in Shailendra Bhardwaj&apos;s case was in reference to<lb/> the provisions as they existed in the State of U.P. Para 24 of<lb/> the judgment, being relevant in this regard, is extracted<lb/> hereinafter:-<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot;24. The decisions in Suhrid Singh and Shailendra Bhardwaj have<lb/> to be understood in their proper perspective. There was U.P.<lb/> Amendment in Shailendra Bhardwaj. In Suhrid Singh the<lb/> Court was dealing with a different situation. Be that as it may,<lb/> the valuation of a suit and payment of court fee shall depend<lb/> upon the special provision in a State if provided for. The view<lb/> taken by the Madras High Court in Chellakannu, in our<lb/> considered opinion, is the correct exposition of law.&quot;<lb/></item>

			<p>In respect of the Court Fee payable under the<lb/> relevant statute in State of Tamil Nadu, it was observed<lb/> that the view taken by the Madras High Court in<lb/> Chellakannu Versus Kolanji, 2005 SCC OnLine Mad<lb/> 390, was the correct opinion. This view as reproduced in<lb/> the judgment runs as follows:-<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot;16. Chellakannu v. Kolanji, dealt with a civil revision that was<lb/> filed by the plaintiff assailing the order of the trial court<lb/> directing the plaintiff to pay the court fee under Section<lb/> 6 2007 (1) CTC 300 7 AIR 2005 Mad 405 40 of the Act. The<lb/> narration of the facts in the plaint was adverted to by the High<lb/> Court and for proper appreciation of the controversy that has<lb/> been raised in the instant case, we may reproduce the same:<lb/></item>

			<item>&quot;2… the Suit Property belonged to his Father-Pichamuthu.<lb/> Pichamuthu had two wives, through whom he had Three Sons.<lb/> Earlier, there was Partition in the family of the Plaintiff on<lb/> 04.08.1971 wherein the Plaintiff and the Sons through the First<lb/> Wife have partitioned the family properties. There was further<lb/> partition between the Plaintiff and his Brothers in 1977. Item 1 of<lb/> the Suit Property was allotted to one Poomalai. Items 2 and 4 -<lb/>S.Nos.155/3 and 339/13A were allotted to the Plaintiff. First<lb/> Defendant is the Wife of Shanmugam. Third Defendant has been<lb/> keeping the First Defendant as his concubine. The Third Item<lb/> was allotted to the Plaintiff&apos;s Sister. The Third Defendant is the<lb/> Third Party. With the help of the First Defendant, the Third<lb/> Defendant secured the Suit Properties -Item Nos.1 to 3 under a<lb/> false representation that the Plaintiff is executing a Will in favour<lb/> of the First Defendant. On that mis-representation, Plaintiff&apos;s<lb/> thumb impression was obtained and two Sale Deeds dated<lb/> 05.06.1995 and 23.08.1995 are said to have been obtained.<lb/> Those Sale Deeds obtained from the Plaintiff under false<lb/> representation is not binding on the Plaintiff. Hence, the Plaintiff<lb/> has filed the Suit for Declaration that the Sale Deeds are not<lb/> binding on him and for Permanent Injunction, restraining the<lb/> Defendants from in any way interfering with the Plaintiff&apos;s<lb/> peaceful possession and enjoyment of the Plaint Schedule Items<lb/> I, II and IV.&quot;<lb/></item>

			<item>17. The further stand taken by the plaintiff was that the sale<lb/> deeds were obtained from him under fraud and hence, suit<lb/> had been filed for declaration that the sale deeds were not<lb/> binding on the plaintiff and since the suit was not filed for<lb/> cancellation of the sale deeds, the defendants could not insist<lb/> the plaintiff to pay the court fee under Section 40 of the Act.<lb/> The trial court recorded a find that the sale deeds had been<lb/> executed by the plaintiff himself and prima facie the sale<lb/> deeds were binding on the executants and when there is a<lb/> prayer to declare the sale deeds as invalid, it tantamounts to<lb/> seeking cancellation of sale deeds and therefore, court fee<lb/> payable would be governed by Section 40 of the Act.<lb/></item>

			<item>18. The High Court posed two questions, namely, (i) whether in<lb/> the Suit filed for Declaration that the Sale Deeds are invalid,<lb/> Court Fee paid under Section 25(d) of the Act is incorrect and<lb/> (ii) whether the impugned order directing the Plaintiff to pay<lb/> the Court Fee under Section 40 of the Act suffers from any<lb/> infirmity warranting interference. Dealing with the factual<lb/> matrix, the High Court observed:<lb/></item>

			<item>&quot;…Thus, the Plaintiff himself is a party to the Sale Deed; when<lb/> the Party himself seeks to get rid of the Sale Deeds in substance<lb/> it amounts to Cancellation of Decree. The Plaintiff might seek to<lb/> avoid the Sale Deeds if he is not a party to the Sale Deeds. But,<lb/> since the Plaintiff himself is a party to the Sale Deeds before he is<lb/> suing for any relief, the Plaintiff must first obtain the cancellation<lb/> of the Sale Deeds.&quot;<lb/> And again:<lb/></item>

			<item>&quot;12. The word &quot;Cancellation&quot; implies that the persons suing<lb/> should be a party to the document. Strangers are not bound by<lb/> the documents and are not obliged to sue for cancellation. When<lb/> the party to the document is suing, challenging the document, he<lb/> must first obtain cancellation before getting any further relief.<lb/> Whether cancellation is prayed for or not or even it is impliedly<lb/> sought for in substance, the Suit is one for cancellation. in the<lb/> present case, when the Plaintiff attacks the Sale Deeds as having<lb/> been obtained from him under fraud and misrepresentation the<lb/> Plaintiff cannot seek for any further relief without setting aside<lb/> the Sale Deeds.<lb/> *<lb/> *<lb/> *<lb/></item>

			<item>15. The allegation on the Plaint in substance mounts to<lb/> cancellation of the document. Though the prayer is couched in the<lb/> form of seeking declaration that the document is not valid and<lb/> not binding, the relief in substance indirectly amounts to seeking<lb/> for cancellation of the Sale Deed. Learned District Munsif was<lb/> right in ordering payment of Court Fee under Section 40 of the<lb/> Act. This Revision Petition has no merits and is bound to fail.&quot;<lb/> Being of this view, the High Court dismissed the civil<lb/> revision and directed the plaintiff to pay court fee with further<lb/> stipulation that unless paid, plaint would stand rejected.&quot;<lb/></item>

			<p>4(iv).<lb/> In AIR 2020 SC 1372, titled Agra Diocesan<lb/> Trust Association v. Anil David and others, the Hon&apos;ble<lb/> Apex Court again considered Suhrid Singh&apos;s case, supra, in<lb/> respect of the Court Fee provisions in the State of Punjab as<lb/> well as Shailendra Bhardwaj&apos;s case, supra, in respect of<lb/> Court Fee provisions in State of U.P. As Agra Diocesan case<lb/> pertained to State of U.P., therefore, the judgment in Suhrid<lb/> Singh&apos;s case was not applied. Paragraphs 13 to 15 of the<lb/> judgment, being relevant, are extracted hereinafter:-<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot;13. In Shailendra Bhardwaj &amp; Ors. v. Chandra Pal &amp; Anr. (2012<lb/> AIR SCW 6519) (supra), this court had to consider whether a<lb/> suit for declaration that a will and a sale deed are void<lb/> resulting in their cancellation, fell under Section 7(iv-A) of the<lb/> Court Fees Act, 1870 as amended by the U.P. Amendment<lb/> Act (Act 19 of 1938) or Article 17(iii) of Schedule II of the Court<lb/> Fees Act, 1870 for the purpose of valuation. The trial court had<lb/> held that the court fee had to be paid under Section 7(iv-A) and<lb/> the High Court affirmed that view. This court noted the<lb/> provisions of the Court Fees Act, 1870 as amended by the U.P.<lb/> Amendment Act (Act 19 of 1938) and held as follows:<lb/></item>

			<item>&quot;On comparing the above mentioned provisions, it is clear<lb/> that Article 17(iii) of Schedule II of the Court Fees Act is<lb/> applicable in cases where the Plaintiff seeks to obtain a<lb/> declaratory decree without any consequential relief and<lb/> there is no other provision under the Act for payment of fee<lb/> relating to relief claimed. Article 17(iii) of Schedule II of the<lb/> Court Fees Act makes it clear that this Article is applicable<lb/> in cases where the Plaintiff seeks to obtain a declaratory<lb/> decree without consequential reliefs and there is no other<lb/> provision under the Act for payment of fee relating to relief<lb/> claimed. If there is no other provision under the Court Fees<lb/> Act in case of a suit involving cancellation or<lb/> adjudging/declaring void or voidable a will or sale deed on<lb/> the question of payment of court fees, then Article 17(iii) of<lb/> Schedule II shall be applicable. But if such relief is covered<lb/> by any other provisions of the Court Fees Act, then Article<lb/> 17(iii) of Schedule II will not be applicable. On a<lb/> comparison between the Court Fees Act and the U.P.<lb/> Amendment Act, it is clear that Section 7(iv-A) of the U.P.<lb/> Amendment Act covers suits for or involving cancellation or<lb/> adjudging/declaring null and void decree for money or an<lb/> instrument securing money or other property having such<lb/> value.&quot;<lb/></item>

			<item>14. The Court observed that the suit was filed after the death of<lb/> the testator, and that the suit property covered by the will had<lb/> to be valued. The court felt that since Section 7(iv-A) of the U.P.<lb/> Amendment Act specifically provided that payment of court<lb/> fees in cases where the suit is for, or involving cancellation or<lb/> adjudging/declaring null and void a decree for money or an<lb/> instrument, Article 17(iii) of Schedule II of the Court Fees Act<lb/> was inapplicable. The U.P. Amendment Act, therefore, was<lb/> applicable despite the fact that no consequential relief had<lb/> been claimed. Consequently, in terms of Section 7(iv-A) of the<lb/> U.P. Amendment Act, court fees were to be computed<lb/> according to the value of the subject-matter. The trial court and<lb/> the High Court correctly held it to be so. The court<lb/> distinguished Suhrid Singh&apos;s case (supra) stating that:<lb/></item>

			<item>&quot;10. We are of the view that the decision of this Court in Suhrid<lb/> Singh (supra) is not applicable to the facts of the present<lb/> case. First of all, this Court had no occasion to examine the<lb/> scope of the U.P. Amendment Act. That was a case in<lb/> which this Court was dealing with Sections 7(iv)(c), (v) and<lb/> Schedule II Article 17(iii), as amended in the State of<lb/> Punjab. The position that we get in the State of Punjab is<lb/> entirely different from the State of U.P. and the effect of<lb/> the U.P. Amendment Act was not an issue which arose for<lb/> consideration in that case. Consequently, in our view, the<lb/> said judgment would not apply to the present case.<lb/></item>

			<p>11. The Plaintiff, in the instant case, valued the suit at Rs. 30<lb/> lakhs for the purpose of pecuniary jurisdiction. However,<lb/> for the purpose of court fee, the Plaintiff paid a fixed court<lb/> fee of Rs.200 Under Article 17(iii) of Schedule II of the<lb/> Court Fees Act. The Plaintiff had not noticed the fact that<lb/> the above mentioned Article stood amended by the State,<lb/> by adding the words &quot;not otherwise provided for by this<lb/> Act&quot;. Since Section 7(iv-A) of the U.P. Amended Act<lb/> specifically provides for payment of court fee in case where<lb/> the<lb/> suit<lb/> is<lb/> for<lb/> or<lb/> involving<lb/> cancellation<lb/> or<lb/> adjudging/declaring void or voidable an instrument<lb/> securing property having money value, Article 17(iii) of<lb/> Schedule II of the Court Fees Act shall not be applicable.&quot;<lb/></p>

			<p>15. It is evident from the above discussion that it is undisputed<lb/> that the point in issue was with respect to valuation for<lb/> purposes of court fee; equally, it is not in issue that since the<lb/> plaintiff (i.e. petitioner herein) sought, in addition to a<lb/> declaration, in both the suits, decrees of cancellation, the<lb/> crucial point was what the correct value for purposes of court<lb/> fee was. Now, market value has been specifically defined, in<lb/> the context of a litigation like the present one. According<lb/> to Section 7 (iv-A), in case the plaintiff (or his predecessor-in-<lb/>title) was not a party to the decree or instrument, the value<lb/> was to be according to one-fifth of the value of the subject<lb/> matter, &quot;and such value shall be deemed to be&quot; under Section<lb/> 7 (iv-A), &quot;if the whole decree or instrument is involved in the<lb/> suit, the amount for which or value of the property in respect of<lb/> which the decree is passed or the instrument executed&quot;.<lb/> Importantly, the explanation to Section 7 (iv-A) created a<lb/> deeming fiction as to what constitutes the &quot;value of the<lb/> property&quot; by saying that &quot;in the case of immovable property<lb/> shall be deemed to be the value as computed in accordance<lb/> with the sub-section (v), (v-A) or (v-B) as the case may be.&quot;<lb/></p>

			<p>4(v).<lb/> In the instant case, the plaintiff is seeking<lb/> declaration that she is owner in possession of the suit land<lb/> and she is entitled to operate and receive the amount lying<lb/> in the accounts of her deceased father. She has further<lb/> prayed for declaring the will allegedly executed by her late<lb/> father in favour of the defendants as fake, forged and not<lb/> binding upon her. Plaintiff has not claimed any amount<lb/> from the Court. In fact, the reliefs prayed by her practically<lb/> flow out from the declaration sought by her in respect of the<lb/> will allegedly executed by her late father. Plaintiff has also<lb/> not prayed for decree of possession. She has prayed for<lb/> consequential relief of permanent injunction for restraining<lb/> the defendants from mutating the land on the basis of<lb/> alleged will in their favour; for ousting her from joint<lb/> possession till the suit land is partitioned and for<lb/> restraining the defendants from getting the amount lying in<lb/> the accounts of her father released in their favour on the<lb/> basis of the will. The alternative decree prayed by her is<lb/> also for joint possession. In the instant case,<lb/> respondent/plaintiff is not even seeking cancellation of any<lb/> deed executed by her. The judgments cited on behalf of the<lb/> petitioners are not applicable to the fact situation of instant<lb/> case. Therefore, in light of the judgment passed by the<lb/> Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court in (2010) 12 SCC 112, titled<lb/> Suhrid Singh Alias Sardool Singh Versus Randhir<lb/> Singh and others, as considered in AIR 2020 SC 1372,<lb/> titled Agra Diocesan Trust Association v. Anil David<lb/> and others, in my considered view, the learned Trial Court<lb/> committed no error in rejecting the application moved by<lb/> the defendants praying for rejection of the plaint on account<lb/> of affixing less Court Fee. Plaintiff had neither claimed the<lb/> amount through the Court nor from the defendants or from<lb/> the Bank. Here it will also be appropriate to take note of<lb/> Order 7 Rule 11 of the Code of Civil Procedure, invoking<lb/> which, the defendants had prayed for rejection of the plaint.<lb/> Order 7 Rule 11 CPC reads as under:-<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot;Rejection of plaint<lb/> The plaint shall be rejected in the following cases:-<lb/></item>

			<item>(a)<lb/> where it does not disclose a cause of action;<lb/></item>

			<item>(b)<lb/> where the relief claimed is undervalued, and the plaintiff, on<lb/> being required by the court to correct the valuation within a<lb/> time to be fixed by the court, fails to do so;<lb/></item>

			<item>(c)<lb/> where the relief claimed is properly valued, but the<lb/> plaint is written upon paper insufficiently stamped, and<lb/> the plaintiff, on being required by the court to supply<lb/> the requisite stamp-paper within a time to be fixed by<lb/> the Court, fails to do so;<lb/></item>

			<item>(d)<lb/> where the suit appears from the statement in the plaint to be<lb/> barred by any law;<lb/></item>

			<item>(e)<lb/> where it is not filed in duplicate;]<lb/></item>

			<item>(f)<lb/> where the plaintiff fails to comply with the provisions of<lb/> rule 9;<lb/> Provided that the time fixed by the court for the<lb/> correction of the valuation or supplying of the requisite<lb/> stamp-papers shall not be extended unless the court, for<lb/> reasons to be recorded, is satisfied that the plaintiff was<lb/> prevented by any cause of an exceptional nature from<lb/> correcting the valuation or supplying the requisite stamp<lb/> papers, as the case may be, within the time fixed by the court<lb/> and that refusal to extend such time would cause grave<lb/> injustice to the plaintiff.&quot;<lb/></item>

			<p>A bare reading of the above provision makes it<lb/> amply clear that even if the plaint is not sufficiently<lb/> stamped, then also the plaintiff can be required by the<lb/> Court to supply the requisite stamp papers within a<lb/> timeline. There would be no occasion for rejection of the<lb/> plaint straightway on the ground that the same is<lb/> insufficiently stamped.<lb/> For all the aforesaid reasons, there is no merit<lb/> in the instant petition and the same is dismissed alongwith<lb/> pending miscellaneous application(s), if any. The parties<lb/> through their learned counsel are directed to appear before<lb/> the learned Court below on 08.04.2021.<lb/> The Registry is directed to return the records of<lb/> the case to the learned Trial Court forthwith.<lb/></p>

			<p>Jyotsna Rewal Dua<lb/> Judge<lb/> March 10, 2021<lb/> Mukesh</p>


	</text>
</tei>
