<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<head>CIVIL APPEAL NO.10226 OF 2017</head>

			<p>,<lb/> CIVIL APPEAL NO.12456 OF 2017,<lb/> CIVIL APPEAL NO. 198586 OF 2020,<lb/> [ARISING OUT OF SPECIAL LEAVE PETITION [C] NO.3631436315 OF 2017]<lb/> J U D G M E N T<lb/> VINEET SARAN, J.<lb/> Leave granted.<lb/></p>

			<p>2.<lb/> The reference made to this Constitution Bench relates<lb/> to the grant of time for filing response to a complaint under the<lb/> provisions of the Consumer Protection Act, 1986 (for short &apos;the<lb/> Act&apos;). The first question referred is as to whether Section 13(2)<lb/></p>

			<p>(a) of the Consumer Protection Act, which provides for the<lb/> respondent/opposite party filing its response to the complaint<lb/> within 30 days or such extended period, not exceeding 15 days,<lb/> should be read as mandatory or directory; i.e., whether the<lb/> District Forum has power to extend the time for filing the<lb/> response beyond the period of 15 days, in addition to 30 days.<lb/> The second question which is referred is as to what would be<lb/> the commencing point of limitation of 30 days stipulated under<lb/> the aforesaid Section.<lb/></p>

			<p>3.<lb/> The first question was referred by a two judge Bench of<lb/> this Court vide an Order dated 11.02.2016 passed in Civil Appeal<lb/> No(s).10831084 of 2016, M/s Bhasin Infotech and<lb/> Infrastructure Pvt. Ltd. versus M/s Grand Venezia Buyers<lb/> Association (Reg), the relevant portion of which is as under:<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot;There is an apparent conflict<lb/> between the decisions of this Court<lb/> in Topline Shoes Limited vs.<lb/> Corporation Bank [(2002) 6 SCC 33],<lb/> Kailash Vs. Nankhu [(2005) 4 SCC<lb/> 480],<lb/> Salem<lb/> Advocate<lb/> Bar<lb/> Association Vs. Union of India<lb/> [(2005) 6 SCC 344] on the one hand<lb/> and J.J. Merchant &amp; Ors. Vs.<lb/> Shrinath Chaturvedi [(2002) 6 SCC<lb/> 635 and NIA Vs. Hilli Multipurpose<lb/> Cold Storage [2014 AIOL 4615] on<lb/> the other in so far as the power of<lb/> the Courts to extend time for filing of<lb/> written<lb/> statement/reply<lb/> to<lb/> a<lb/> complaint is concerned. The earlier<lb/> mentioned line of decisions take the<lb/> view that the relevant provisions<lb/> including those of Order 8 Rule 1 of<lb/> the Civil Procedure Code, 1908 are<lb/> directory in nature and the Courts<lb/> concerned have the power to extend<lb/> time for filing the written statement.<lb/> The second line of decisions which<lb/> are also of coordinate Benches<lb/> however takes a contrary view and<lb/> hold that when it comes to power of<lb/> the Consumer Fora to extend the<lb/> time for filing a reply there is no<lb/> such power.<lb/></item>

			<item>Since the question that falls for<lb/> determination here often arises<lb/> before the Consumer Fora and<lb/> Commissions all over the country it<lb/> will be more appropriate if the<lb/> conflict<lb/> is<lb/> resolved<lb/> by<lb/> an<lb/> authoritative<lb/> judgment.<lb/> Further<lb/> since the conflict is between<lb/> Benches comprising three Judges<lb/> we deem it fit to refer these appeals<lb/> to a fiveJudge Bench to resolve the<lb/> conflict once and for all. While we do<lb/> so we are mindful of the fact that in<lb/> the ordinary course a twoJudge<lb/> Bench ought to make a reference to<lb/> a threeJudge Bench in the first<lb/> place but in the facts and<lb/> circumstances of the case and<lb/> keeping in view the fact that the<lb/> conflict is between coordinate<lb/> Benches comprising three Judges a<lb/> reference to three Judges may not<lb/> suffice.&quot;<lb/></item>

			<p>4.<lb/> The other question has been referred by another<lb/> Division Bench of this Court by an Order dated 18.01.2017<lb/> passed in this very appeal being Civil Appeal No(s).1094110942<lb/> of 2013, NIA Vs. Hilli Multipurpose Cold Storage Pvt. Ltd, the<lb/> relevant portion of the judgment is as under:<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot;……….what is the commencing<lb/> point of the limitation of 30 days<lb/> stipulated in Section 13 of the Act is<lb/> required<lb/> to<lb/> be<lb/> decided<lb/> authoritatively.<lb/> The<lb/> declaration<lb/> made in JJ Merchant&apos;s case that the<lb/> said period is to be reckoned from<lb/> the date of the receipt of the notice<lb/> by the opposite party or complaint<lb/> under the Act requires in our humble<lb/> opinion, a more critical analysis.&quot;<lb/></item>

			<p>5.<lb/> We have heard the learned Counsel for the parties at<lb/> length and have carefully gone through the records.<lb/></p>

			<p>6.<lb/> In the Statement of Objects and Reasons of the<lb/> Consumer Protection Act, in paragraph 4, it has been specifically<lb/> provided that the Consumer Protection Act is &quot;To provide speedy<lb/> and simple redressal to consumer disputes, a quasijudicial<lb/> machinery is sought to be set up at the district, State and Central<lb/> levels…….&quot;. The Preamble of the Consumer Protection Act also<lb/> mentions that the Act is &quot;to provide for better protection of the<lb/> interests of the consumers&quot;. The nomenclature of this Act also<lb/> goes to show that it is for the benefit or protection of the<lb/> consumer. From the above, it is evident that the Consumer<lb/> Protection Act has been enacted to provide for expeditious<lb/> disposal of consumer disputes and that, it is for the protection<lb/> and benefit of the consumer.<lb/></p>

			<p>7.<lb/> Before we proceed to analyse and determine the<lb/> questions referred, we may, for ready reference, reproduce the<lb/> relevant provisions of the Consumer Protection Act and its<lb/> Regulations.<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot;Section 13. Procedure on<lb/> admission of complaint. -<lb/></item>

			<item>(1) The District Forum shall, on<lb/> admission of a complaint, if it<lb/> relates to any goods,<lb/></item>

			<item>(a) refer a copy of the admitted<lb/> complaint, within twentyone days<lb/> from the date of its admission to<lb/> the opposite party mentioned in the<lb/> complaint directing him to give his<lb/> version of the case within a period<lb/> of thirty days or such extended<lb/> period not exceeding fifteen days<lb/> as may be granted by the District<lb/> Forum.<lb/></item>

			<item>(b)………………….<lb/></item>

			<item>(c)………………….<lb/></item>

			<item>(d)………………….<lb/></item>

			<item>(e)………………….<lb/></item>

			<item>(f)………………….<lb/></item>

			<item>(g)………………….<lb/></item>

			<item>(2) The District Forum shall, if the<lb/> complaints admitted by it under<lb/> section 12 relates to goods in<lb/> respect of which the procedure<lb/> specified in subsection (1) cannot<lb/> be followed, or if the complaint<lb/> relates to any services,<lb/></item>

			<item>(a)<lb/> refer a copy of such<lb/> complaint to the opposite party<lb/> directing him to give his version<lb/> of the case within a period of<lb/> thirty days or such extended<lb/> period not exceeding fifteen<lb/> days as may be granted by the<lb/> District Forum;<lb/></item>

			<item>(b) where the opposite party, on<lb/> receipt of a copy of the complaint,<lb/> referred to him under clause (a)<lb/> denies or disputes the allegations<lb/> contained in the complaint, or omits<lb/> or fails to take any action to<lb/> represent his case within the time<lb/> given by the District Forum, the<lb/> District Forum shall proceed to<lb/> settle consumer dispute,<lb/></item>

			<item>(i)<lb/> on the basis of evidence<lb/> brought to its notice by the<lb/> complainant and the opposite<lb/> party, where the opposite party<lb/> denies or disputes the allegations<lb/> contained in the complaint, or<lb/></item>

			<item>(ii)<lb/> ex parte on the basis of<lb/> evidence brought to its notice by<lb/> the complainant where the opposite<lb/> party omits or fails to take any<lb/> action to represent his case within<lb/> the time given by the Forum;<lb/></item>

			<item>(c) where the complainant fails to<lb/> appear on the date of hearing<lb/> before the District Forum, the<lb/> District Forum may either dismiss<lb/> the complaint for default or decide<lb/> it on merits.<lb/></item>

			<item>(3) No proceedings complying<lb/> with the procedure laid down in<lb/> subsections (1) and (2) shall be<lb/> called in question in any court<lb/> on<lb/> the<lb/> ground<lb/> that<lb/> the<lb/> principles of natural justice<lb/> have not been complied with.<lb/></item>

			<item>1<lb/> [(3A) Every complaint shall be<lb/> heard as expeditiously as<lb/> possible and endeavour shall be<lb/> made to decide the complaint<lb/> within a period of three months<lb/> from the date of receipt of<lb/> notice by opposite party where<lb/> the complaint does not require<lb/> analysis<lb/> or<lb/> testing<lb/> of<lb/> commodities and within five<lb/> months, if it requires analysis<lb/> or testing of commodities:<lb/></item>

			<item>Provided that no adjournment<lb/> shall be ordinarily granted by the<lb/> District Forum unless sufficient<lb/> cause is shown and the reasons for<lb/> grant of adjournment have been<lb/> recorded in writing by the Forum:<lb/></item>

			<item>Provided further that the<lb/> District Forum shall make such<lb/> orders as to the costs occasioned<lb/> by the adjournment as may be<lb/> provided in the regulations made<lb/> under this Act.<lb/></item>

			<item>Provided also that in the<lb/> event<lb/> of<lb/> a<lb/> complaint being<lb/> disposed of after the period so<lb/> specified, the District Forum shall<lb/> record in writing, the reasons for<lb/> the same at the time of disposing of<lb/> the said complaint.]<lb/></item>

			<item>2<lb/> [(3B) Where during the pendency<lb/> of any proceeding before the<lb/> District Forum, it appears to it<lb/> necessary, it may pass such<lb/> interim order as is just and proper<lb/> in the facts and circumstances of<lb/> the case.]<lb/></item>

			<item>(4) For the purposes of this section,<lb/> the District Forum shall have the<lb/> same powers as are vested in a<lb/> civil court under Code of Civil<lb/> Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908) while<lb/> trying a suit in respect of the<lb/> following matters, namely:-<lb/></item>

			<item>(i)<lb/> the<lb/> summoning<lb/> and<lb/> enforcing the attendance of any<lb/> defendant<lb/> or<lb/> witness<lb/> and<lb/> examining the witness on oath;<lb/></item>

			<item>(ii)<lb/> the discovery and production<lb/> of any document or other material<lb/> object producible as evidence;<lb/></item>

			<item>(iii)<lb/> the reception of evidence on<lb/> affidavits;<lb/></item>

			<item>(iv)<lb/> the requisitioning of the<lb/> report of the concerned analysis or<lb/> test from the appropriate laboratory<lb/> or from any other relevant source;<lb/></item>

			<item>(v)<lb/> issuing of any commission<lb/> for the examination of any witness,<lb/> and<lb/></item>

			<item>(vi)<lb/> any other matter which may<lb/> be prescribed.<lb/></item>

			<p>5……………….<lb/></p>

			<p>6……………….<lb/></p>

			<p>7……………….<lb/></p>

			<item>Section 15. Appeal. -Any<lb/> person aggrieved by an order made<lb/> by the District Forum may prefer<lb/> an appeal against such order to the<lb/> State Commission within a period<lb/> of thirty days from the date of the<lb/> order, in such form and manner as<lb/> may be prescribed:<lb/></item>

			<item>Provided that the State<lb/> Commission may entertain an<lb/> appeal after the expiry of the<lb/> said period of thirty days if it<lb/> is satisfied that there was<lb/> sufficient cause for not filing it<lb/> within that period;<lb/> Provided further that no<lb/> appeal by a person, who is<lb/> required to pay any amount in<lb/> terms of an order of the District<lb/> Forum, shall be entertained by the<lb/> State Commission unless the<lb/> appellant has deposited in the<lb/> prescribed manner fifty per cent. of<lb/> that<lb/> amount<lb/> or<lb/> twentyfive<lb/> thousand rupees, whichever is<lb/> less.&quot;<lb/></item>

			<item>Section19.<lb/> Appeals.-Any<lb/> person aggrieved by an order made<lb/> by the State Commission in<lb/> exercise of its powers conferred by<lb/> subclause (i) of clause (a) of<lb/> section 17 may prefer an appeal<lb/> against such order to the National<lb/> Commission within a period of<lb/> thirty days from the date of the<lb/> order in such form and manner as<lb/> may be prescribed:<lb/></item>

			<item>Provided that the National<lb/> Commission may entertain an<lb/> appeal after the expiry of the<lb/> said period of thirty days if it<lb/> is satisfied that there was<lb/> sufficient cause for not filing it<lb/> within that period:<lb/></item>

			<item>Provided further that no<lb/> appeal by a person, who is<lb/> required to pay any amount in<lb/> terms of an order of the State<lb/> Commission, shall be entertained<lb/> by the National Commission unless<lb/> the appellant has deposited in the<lb/> prescribed manner fifty per cent. of<lb/> the amount or rupees thirtyfive<lb/> thousand, whichever is less.<lb/></item>

			<item>Section24A. Limitation period.<lb/></item>

			<item>(1) The District Forum, the State<lb/> Commission<lb/> or<lb/> the<lb/> National<lb/> Commission shall not admit a<lb/> complaint unless it is filed within<lb/> two years from the date on which<lb/> the cause of action has arisen.<lb/></item>

			<item>(2) Notwithstanding<lb/> anything<lb/> contained in subsection (1), a<lb/> complaint may be entertained<lb/> after the period specified in<lb/> subsection<lb/></item>

			<item>(1),<lb/> if<lb/> the<lb/> complainant<lb/> satisfies<lb/> the<lb/> District<lb/> Forum,<lb/> the<lb/> State<lb/> Commission or the National<lb/> Commission, as the case may<lb/> be, that he had sufficient cause<lb/> for not filing the complaint<lb/> within such period:<lb/></item>

			<item>Provided<lb/> that<lb/> no<lb/> such<lb/> complaint shall be entertained<lb/> unless the National Commission,<lb/> the State Commission or the<lb/> District Forum, as the case may be,<lb/> records its reasons for condoning<lb/> such delay.&quot;<lb/></item>

			<item>(emphasis supplied)<lb/></item>

			<p>Relevant Provisions of the Consumer Protection Regulations,<lb/> 2005 are reproduced below:<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot;Reg.10. Issue of notice .(1)<lb/> Whenever the Consumer Forum<lb/> directs the issuance of a notice in<lb/> respect of a complaint, appeal or<lb/> revision petition, as the case may<lb/> be,<lb/> to<lb/> the<lb/> opposite<lb/> party(ies)/respondent(s),<lb/> ordinarily such notice shall be<lb/> issued for a period of 30 days<lb/> and<lb/> depending<lb/> upon<lb/> the<lb/> circumstances of each case<lb/> even for less than 30 days.<lb/></item>

			<item>(2) When there is a question of<lb/> raising presumption of service, 30<lb/> days notice shall be required.<lb/></item>

			<item>(3) Whenever notices are sought to<lb/> be effected by a courier service, it<lb/> shall be ascertained that the<lb/> courier is of repute.<lb/></item>

			<item>(4)<lb/> Whenever appointing the<lb/> courier for the purpose of effecting<lb/> service, security deposit may also<lb/> be taken.<lb/></item>

			<item>(5)<lb/> Along with the notice,<lb/> copies<lb/> of<lb/> the<lb/> complaint,<lb/> memorandum of grounds of<lb/> appeal, petitions as the case<lb/> may be and other documents<lb/> filed shall be served upon the<lb/> opposite<lb/> party(ies)/respondent(s).<lb/></item>

			<item>(6)<lb/> After the opposite party or<lb/> respondent has put in appearance,<lb/> no application or document shall be<lb/> received by the Registrar unless it<lb/> bears an endorsement that a copy<lb/> thereof has been served upon the<lb/> other side.&quot;<lb/></item>

			<item>Reg.14. Limitation.<lb/></item>

			<item>(1) Subject to the provisions of<lb/> sections 15, 19 and 24A, the period<lb/> of limitation in the following<lb/> matters shall be as follows:<lb/></item>

			<item>(i)<lb/> Revision Petition shall be<lb/> filed within 90 days from the date<lb/> of the order or the date of receipt of<lb/> the order as the case may be;<lb/></item>

			<item>(ii)<lb/> Application for setting aside<lb/> the ex parte order under section<lb/> 22A or dismissal of the complaint<lb/> in default shall be maintainable if<lb/> filed within thirty days from the<lb/> date of the order or date of receipt<lb/> of the order, as the case may be;<lb/></item>

			<item>(iii)<lb/> An application for review<lb/> under subsection (2) of section 22<lb/> shall be filed to the National<lb/> Commission within 30 days from<lb/> the date of the order or receipt of<lb/> the order, as the case may be;<lb/></item>

			<item>(iv)<lb/> The period of limitation for<lb/> filing any application for which no<lb/> period of limitation has been<lb/> specified in the Act, the rules of<lb/> these regulations shall be thirty<lb/> days from the date of the cause of<lb/> action or the date of knowledge.<lb/></item>

			<item>(2) Subject to the<lb/> provisions<lb/> of<lb/> the Act, the Consumer<lb/> Forum may condone the delay<lb/> in filing an application or a<lb/> petition referred to in sub<lb/> regulation (1) if valid and<lb/> sufficient<lb/> reasons<lb/> to<lb/> its<lb/> satisfaction are given.<lb/></item>

			<item>Reg.26. Miscellaneous.<lb/></item>

			<item>(1) In all proceedings before the<lb/> Consumer Forum, endeavour shall<lb/> be made by the parties and their<lb/> counsel to avoid the use of<lb/> provisions of Code of Civil<lb/> Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908):<lb/> Provided that the provisions<lb/> of the Code of Civil Procedure,<lb/> 1908 may be applied which have<lb/> been referred to in the Act or in the<lb/> rules made thereunder.<lb/></item>

			<item>(2)………………..<lb/></item>

			<item>(3)………………..<lb/></item>

			<item>(4)………………..<lb/></item>

			<item>(5)………………..<lb/></item>

			<item>(6)………………..&quot;<lb/> (emphasis supplied)<lb/></item>

			<p>Question No. 1:<lb/> Whether the District Forum has power to<lb/> extend the time for filing of response to<lb/> the complaint beyond the period of 15<lb/> days, in addition to 30 days, as envisaged<lb/> under Section 13(2)(a) of the Consumer<lb/> Protection Act?<lb/></p>

			<p>8.<lb/> A bare reading of Section 13(2)(a) of the Act makes it<lb/> clear that the copy of the complaint which is to be sent to the<lb/> opposite party, is to be with the direction to give his version of (or<lb/> response to) the case (or complaint) within a period of 30 days. It<lb/> further provides that such period of 30 days can be extended by<lb/> the District Forum, but not beyond 15 days.<lb/></p>

			<p>9.<lb/> SubSection 2(b)(i) of Section 13 of the Act provides for<lb/> a complaint to be decided on the basis of the response by the<lb/> opposite party and the evidence of the complainant and the<lb/> opposite party, where allegations contained in the complaint are<lb/> denied or disputed by the opposite party. SubSection 2(b)(ii) of<lb/> Section 13 of the Act provides that where no response is filed by<lb/> the opposite party, the complaint may be decided ex parte on the<lb/> basis of evidence brought forth by the complainant.<lb/></p>

			<p>10.<lb/> SubSection 2(c) of Section 13 of the Consumer<lb/> Protection Act further provides that where the complainant fails<lb/> to appear on the date of hearing before the District Forum, the<lb/> District Forum may either dismiss the complaint for default or<lb/> decide it on merits. The aforesaid provision [subSection 2(c)] was<lb/> inserted by Act 62 of 2002, w.e.f. 15.03.2003. Similarly, Section<lb/> (3A) of Section 13 of the Consumer Protection Act, which was also<lb/> inserted by Act 62 of 2002, provides for deciding every complaint<lb/> as expeditiously as possible and endeavour shall be made to<lb/> decide the complaint within a period of three months from the<lb/> receipt of notice by the opposite party, and within five months, if<lb/> the complaint requires analysis or testing of commodities. It also<lb/> provides that no adjournment shall ordinarily be granted by the<lb/> District Forum, and if the same is to be granted, costs may be<lb/> imposed, and further that reasons be recorded if the complaint is<lb/> disposed of after the time so provided.<lb/></p>

			<p>11.<lb/> From the above, it is clear that as mentioned in the<lb/> Statement of Objects and Reasons of the Consumer Protection<lb/> Act, the District Forum is to provide speedy disposal of consumer<lb/> disputes. The same has been further reiterated by the legislature<lb/> by insertion of Section 13(2)(c) and 13(3A) by Act 62 of 2002.<lb/></p>

			<p>12.<lb/> Section 13 of the Consumer Protection Act clearly<lb/> contemplates where time can be extended by the District Forum,<lb/> and where it is not to be extended. Like, under subSection (3A)<lb/> of Section 13, despite the best efforts of the District Forum, in<lb/> situations where the complaint cannot be decided within the<lb/> period specified therein, the same can be decided beyond the<lb/> specified period for reasons to be recorded in writing by the<lb/> District Forum at the time of disposing of the complaint. Meaning<lb/> thereby that the same would not be mandatory, but only<lb/> directory. The phrase &quot;endeavour shall be made&quot;, makes the<lb/> intention of the legislature evident that the District Forum is to<lb/> make every effort to decide the case expeditiously within time, but<lb/> the same can also be decided beyond the said period, but for<lb/> reasons to be recorded.<lb/></p>

			<p>13.<lb/> On the contrary, subSection (2)(a) of Section 13 of the<lb/> Consumer Protection Act provides for the opposite party to give<lb/> his response &apos;within a period of 30 days or such extended period<lb/> not exceeding 15 days as may be granted by the District Forum&apos;.<lb/> The intention of the legislature seems to be very clear that the<lb/> opposite party would get the time of 30 days, and in addition<lb/> another 15 days at the discretion of the Forum to file its<lb/> response. No further discretion of granting time beyond 45 days<lb/> is intended under the Act.<lb/> The question of natural justice is dealt with by the<lb/> legislature in subSection (3) of Section 13 of the Consumer<lb/> Protection Act, which clearly provides that &quot;No proceedings<lb/> complying with the procedure laid down in the subSection (1) and<lb/> (2) shall be called in question in any court on the ground that the<lb/> principles of natural justice have not been complied with.&quot; The<lb/> legislature was conscious that the complaint would result in<lb/> being decided ex parte, or without the response of the opposite<lb/> party, if not filed within such time as provided under the<lb/> Consumer Protection Act, and in such a case, the opposite party<lb/> will not be allowed to take the plea that he was not given<lb/> sufficient time or that principles of natural justice were not<lb/> complied with. Any other interpretation would defeat the very<lb/> purpose of subSection (3) of Section 13 of the Consumer<lb/> Protection Act.<lb/></p>

			<p>14.<lb/> The maximum period of 45 days, as provided under the<lb/> Consumer Protection Act, would not mean that the complainant<lb/> has a right to always avail such maximum period of 45 days to<lb/> file its response. Regulation 10 of the Consumer Protection<lb/> Regulations, 2005 clearly provides that ordinarily such notice to<lb/> the opposite party to file its response shall be issued for a period<lb/> of 30 days, but the same can be even less than 30 days,<lb/> depending upon the circumstances of each case.<lb/></p>

			<p>15.<lb/> Now, reverting back to the provisions of the Consumer<lb/> Protection Act to consider as to whether the provision of sub<lb/> Section 2(a) of Section 13 granting a maximum period of 15 days<lb/> in addition to 30 days has to be read as mandatory or not, we<lb/> may also consider the other provisions of the Consumer<lb/> Protection Act where the legislature intended to allow extension of<lb/> period of limitation.<lb/> Section 15 of the Consumer Protection Act provides for filing<lb/> of an appeal from the order of the District Forum to the State<lb/> Commission within a period of 30 days. However, it leaves a<lb/> discretion with the State Commission to entertain an appeal filed<lb/> after the expiry of the said period of 30 days, if it is satisfied that<lb/> there was sufficient cause for not filing it within the stipulated<lb/> period. Similarly, discretion for filing an appeal before the<lb/> National Commission beyond the period of 30 days has also been<lb/> provided under Section 19 of the Consumer Protection Act.<lb/> Section 24A provides for the limitation period of 2 years for<lb/> filing the complaint. However, subSection (2) of Section 24A<lb/> gives a discretion to entertain a complaint even after the period of<lb/> 2 years, if there is a satisfactory cause for not filing the complaint<lb/> within such period, which has to be recorded in writing.<lb/></p>

			<p>16.<lb/> Regulation 14 of the Consumer Protection Regulations,<lb/> 2005 also deals with limitation. In addition, the same provides for<lb/> limitation while dealing with appeals (under Section 15 and 19)<lb/> and complaint (under Section 24A).<lb/> SubRegulation (2) of<lb/> Regulation 14 provides for condonation of delay for sufficient<lb/> reasons to be recorded.<lb/></p>

			<p>17.<lb/> The legislature in its wisdom has provided for filing of<lb/> complaint or appeals beyond the period specified under the<lb/> relevant provisions of the Act and Regulations, if there is<lb/> sufficient cause given by the party, which has to be to the<lb/> satisfaction of the concerned authority. No such discretion has<lb/> been provided for under Section 13(2)(a) of the Consumer<lb/> Protection Act for filing a response to the complaint beyond the<lb/> extended period of 45 days (30 days plus 15 days). Had the<lb/> legislature not wanted to make such provision mandatory but<lb/> only directory, the provision for further extension of the period for<lb/> filing the response beyond 45 days would have been provided, as<lb/> has been provided for in the cases of filing of complaint and<lb/> appeals. To carve out an exception in a specific provision of the<lb/> statute is not within the jurisdiction of the Courts, and if it is so<lb/> done, it would amount to legislating or inserting a provision into<lb/> the statute, which is not permissible.<lb/> By specifically enacting a provision under subSection<lb/> (3) of Section 13, with a specific clarification that violation of the<lb/> principles of natural justice shall not be called in question where<lb/> the procedure prescribed under subSections (1) and (2) of<lb/> Section 13 of the Consumer Protection Act has been followed or<lb/> complied with, the intention of the legislature is clear that mere<lb/> denial of further extension of time for filing the response (by the<lb/> opposite party) would not amount to denial or violation of the<lb/> principles of natural justice. This provision of Section 13(3)<lb/> reinforces the time limit specified in Section 13(2)(a) of the Act.<lb/></p>

			<p>18.<lb/> This Court in the case of Lachmi Narain vs Union of<lb/> India (1976) 2 SCC 953 has held that &quot;if the provision is couched<lb/> in prohibitive or negative language, it can rarely be directory, the<lb/> use of peremptory language in a negative form is per se indicative<lb/> of the interest that the provision is to be mandatory&quot;. Further,<lb/> hardship cannot be a ground for changing the mandatory nature<lb/> of the statute, as has been held by this Court in Bhikraj<lb/> Jaipurai vs Union of India AIR 1962 SC 113=(1962) 2 SCR 880<lb/> and Fairgrowth Investments Ltd. Vs Custodian (2004) 11 SCC<lb/> 472. Hardship cannot thus be a ground to interpret the provision<lb/> so as to enlarge the time, where the statute provides for a specific<lb/> time, which, in our opinion, has to be complied in letter and<lb/> spirit.<lb/> This Court, in the case of Rohitash Kumar vs Om<lb/> Prakash Sharma (2013) 11 SCC 451 has, in paragraph 23, held<lb/> as under:<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot;23. There may be a statutory<lb/> provision, which causes great<lb/> hardship or inconvenience to either<lb/> the party concerned, or to an<lb/> individual, but the Court has no<lb/> choice but to enforce it in full rigor.<lb/> It is a well settled principle of<lb/> interpretation that hardship or<lb/> inconvenience caused, cannot be<lb/> used as a basis to alter the<lb/> meaning of the language employed<lb/> by the legislature, if such meaning<lb/> is clear upon a bare perusal of the<lb/> statute. If the language is plain<lb/> and hence allows only one<lb/> meaning, the same has to be given<lb/> effect to, even if it causes hardship<lb/> or possible injustice.&quot;<lb/> While concluding, it was observed &quot;that the hardship caused to an<lb/> individual, cannot be a ground for not giving effective and<lb/> grammatical meaning to every word of the provision, if the<lb/> language used therein, is unequivocal.&quot;<lb/></item>

			<p>Further, it has been held by this Court in the case of<lb/> Popat Bahiru Govardhane vs Special Land Acquisition<lb/> Officer (2013) 10 SCC 765 that the law of limitation may harshly<lb/> affect a particular party but it has to be applied with all its vigour<lb/> when the statute so prescribes and that the Court has no power<lb/> to extend the period of limitation on equitable grounds, even if the<lb/> statutory provision may cause hardship or inconvenience to a<lb/> particular party.<lb/></p>

			<p>19.<lb/> The contention of the learned Counsel for the<lb/> respondent is that by not leaving a discretion with the District<lb/> Forum for extending the period of limitation for filing the<lb/> response before it by the opposite party, grave injustice would be<lb/> caused as there could be circumstances beyond the control of the<lb/> opposite party because of which the opposite party may not be<lb/> able to file the response within the period of 30 days or the<lb/> extended period of 15 days. In our view, if the law so provides,<lb/> the same has to be strictly complied, so as to achieve the object of<lb/> the statute. It is well settled that law prevails over equity, as<lb/> equity can only supplement the law, and not supplant it.<lb/> This Court, in the case of Laxminarayan R. Bhattad<lb/> vs State of Maharashtra (2003) 5 SCC 413, has observed that<lb/> &quot;when there is a conflict between law and equity the former shall<lb/> prevail.&quot; In P.M. Latha vs State of Kerala (2003) 3 SCC 541,<lb/> this Court held that &quot;Equity and law are twin brothers and law<lb/> should be applied and interpreted equitably, but equity cannot<lb/> override written or settled law.&quot; In Nasiruddin vs Sita Ram<lb/> Agarwal (2003) 2 SCC 577, this Court observed that &quot;in a case<lb/> where the statutory provision is plain and unambiguous, the court<lb/> shall not interpret the same in a different manner, only because of<lb/> harsh consequences arising therefrom.&quot; In E. Palanisamy vs<lb/> Palanisamy (2003) 1 SCC 123, it was held that &quot;Equitable<lb/> considerations have no place where the statute contained express<lb/> provisions.&quot; Further, in India House vs Kishan N. Lalwani<lb/> (2003) 9 SCC 393, this Court held that &quot;The period of limitation<lb/> statutorily prescribed has to be strictly adhered to and cannot be<lb/> relaxed or departed from by equitable considerations.&quot;<lb/> It is thus settled law that where the provision of the Act<lb/> is clear and unambiguous, it has no scope for any interpretation<lb/> on equitable ground.<lb/></p>

			<p>20.<lb/> It is true that &apos;justice hurried is justice buried&apos;. But in<lb/> the same breath it is also said that &apos;justice delayed is justice<lb/> denied&apos;. The legislature has chosen the latter, and for a good<lb/> reason. It goes with the objective sought to be achieved by the<lb/> Consumer Protection Act, which is to provide speedy justice to<lb/> the consumer. It is not that sufficient time to file a response to<lb/> the complaint has been denied to the opposite party. It is just<lb/> that discretion of extension of time beyond 15 days (after the 30<lb/> days period) has been curtailed and consequences for the same<lb/> have been provided under Section 13(2)(b)(ii) of the Consumer<lb/> Protection Act. It may be that in some cases the opposite party<lb/> could face hardship because of such provision, yet for achieving<lb/> the object of the Act, which is speedy and simple redressal of<lb/> consumer disputes, hardship which may be caused to a party has<lb/> to be ignored.<lb/></p>

			<p>21.<lb/> It has been further contended that the language of<lb/> Section 13(2) of the Consumer Protection Act is pari materia to<lb/> Order VIII Rule 1 of the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (for short<lb/> &apos;the Code&apos;) and if time can be extended for filing of written<lb/> submission in a suit under the aforesaid provision of the Code,<lb/> the same would apply to the filing of response to complaint under<lb/> the Consumer Protection Act as well, and hence the provision of<lb/> Section 13(2)(a) of the Consumer Protection Act would be<lb/> directory and not mandatory.<lb/> In this regard, what is noteworthy is that Regulation 26 of<lb/> the Consumer Protection Regulation, 2005, clearly mandates that<lb/> endeavour is to be made to avoid the use of the provisions of the<lb/> Code except for such provisions, which have been referred to in<lb/> the Consumer Protection Act and the Regulations framed<lb/> thereunder, which is provided for in respect of specific matters<lb/> enumerated in Section 13(4) of the Consumer Protection Act. It is<lb/> pertinent to note that nonfiling of written statement under Order<lb/> VIII Rule 1 of the Code is not followed by any consequence of<lb/> such nonfiling within the time so provided in the Code.<lb/> Now, while considering the relevant provisions of the<lb/> Code, it is noteworthy that Order VIII Rule 1 read with Order VIII<lb/> Rule 10 prescribes that the maximum period of 120 days<lb/> provided under Order VIII Rule 1 is actually not meant to be<lb/> mandatory, but only directory. Order VIII Rule 10 mandates that<lb/> where written statement is not filed within the time provided<lb/> under Order VIII Rule 1 &quot;the court shall pronounce the judgment<lb/> against him, or make such order in relation to the suit as it thinks<lb/> fit&quot;. A harmonious construction of these provisions is clearly<lb/> indicative of the fact that the discretion is left with the Court to<lb/> grant time beyond the maximum period of 120 days, which may<lb/> be in exceptional cases. On the other hand, subSection (2)(b)(ii)<lb/> of Section 13 of the Consumer Protection Act clearly provides for<lb/> the consequence of the complaint to be proceeded ex parte<lb/> against the opposite party, if the opposite party omits or fails to<lb/> represent his case within the time given.<lb/> It may further be noted that in Order VIII Rule 10 of<lb/> the Code, for suits filed under the Commercial Courts Act, 2015,<lb/> a proviso has been inserted for &apos;commercial disputes of a specified<lb/> value&apos; (vide Act 4 of 2016 w.r.e.f. 23.10.2015), which reads as<lb/> under:<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot;Provided further that no Court<lb/> shall make an Order to extend the<lb/> time provided under Rule 1 of this<lb/> Order for filing the written<lb/> statement&quot;<lb/> From the above, it is clear that for commercial suits, time for<lb/> filing written statement provided under Order VIII Rule 1 is meant<lb/> to be mandatory, but not so for ordinary civil suits. Similarly, in<lb/> our considered view, for cases under the Consumer Protection Act<lb/> also, the time provided under Section 13(2)(a) of the Act has to be<lb/> read as mandatory, and not directory.<lb/></item>

			<p>Once consequences are provided for not filing the<lb/> response to the complaint within the time specified, and it is<lb/> further provided that proceedings complying with the procedure<lb/> laid down under sub Section (1) and (2) of Section 13 of the<lb/> Consumer Protection Act shall not be called in question in any<lb/> Court on the ground that the principles of natural justice have<lb/> not been complied with, the intention of the legislature is<lb/> absolutely clear that the provision of subSection 2(a) of Section<lb/> 13 of the Act in specifying the time limit for filing the response to<lb/> the complaint is mandatory, and not directory.<lb/></p>

			<p>22.<lb/> After noticing that there were delays in deciding the<lb/> complaints by the District Forum, the legislature inserted sub<lb/> Section (3A) of Section 13 of the Consumer Protection Act<lb/> providing for a time limit for deciding the complaints. From this it<lb/> is amply clear that the intention of the legislature was, and has<lb/> always been, for expeditious disposal of the complaints. By<lb/> providing for extension of time for disposal of the cases filed, for<lb/> reasons to be recorded, the legislature has provided for a<lb/> discretion to the Forum that wherever necessary, the extension of<lb/> the time can be provided for, and where such further extension is<lb/> not to be granted [as in the case of Section 13(2)(a)], the<lb/> legislature has consciously not provided for the same, so as to<lb/> achieve the object of the Act.<lb/></p>

			<p>23.<lb/> In SCG Contracts (India) Private Limited vs K.S.<lb/> Chamankar Infrastructure Private Limited (2019) 12 SCC<lb/> 210, this Court, was dealing with a case relating to the filing of<lb/> written statement under the Code, in respect of a case under the<lb/> Commercial Courts Act, 2015. After noticing the amendments<lb/> brought in Order V Rule 1, Order VIII Rule 1 and Order VIII Rule<lb/> 10 of the Code with regard to &apos;commercial disputes of specified<lb/> value&apos; under the Commercial Courts Act, 2015 by way of<lb/> insertion of the Provisos in the aforesaid provisions, this Court<lb/> held that &quot;….the clear, definite and mandatory provisions of Order<lb/> V read with Order VIII Rule 1 and 10 cannot be circumvented by<lb/> recourse to the inherent power under Section 151 to do the<lb/> opposite of what is stated therein&quot;. It was, thus, held that there<lb/> was no scope for enlarging the time for filing of written statement<lb/> beyond the period of 120 days in commercial suits, as the<lb/> provision with regard to such suits would be mandatory, and not<lb/> directory. The said judgment has been affirmed by a Bench of<lb/> three Judges in Desh Raj vs Balkishan decided on 20.01.2020<lb/> in Civil Appeal No.433 of 2020.<lb/></p>

			<p>24.<lb/> In Fairgrowth Investments Ltd. Vs Custodian<lb/> (2004) 11 SCC 472, this Court was dealing with the provisions of<lb/> the Special Court (Trial of Offences Relating to Transactions in<lb/> Securities) Act, 1992, and the question was whether the Special<lb/> Court has power to condone the delay in filing the petition under<lb/> Section 4(2) of the said Act. While holding, that the said<lb/> provision would be mandatory, it was held in paragraph 13 as<lb/> under:<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot;13. It is not for the courts to<lb/> determine whether the period of 30<lb/> days is too short to take into<lb/> account the various misfortunes<lb/> that may be faced by notified<lb/> persons who wish to file objections<lb/> under Section 4(2) of the Act nor<lb/> can the section be held to be<lb/> directory because of such alleged<lb/> inadequacy of time.&quot;<lb/></item>

			<p>Then, after considering the decisions of this Court in Topline<lb/> Shoes Ltd. vs. Corporation Bank (2002) 6 SCC 33 and Dr. J. J.<lb/> Merchant vs. Shrinath Chaturvedi (2002) 6 SCC 635, this<lb/> Court held that &quot;the period for filing an objection in Section 4(2) in<lb/> the Act is a mandatory provision given the language of the Section<lb/> and having regard to the objects sought to be served by the Act.&quot;<lb/></p>

			<p>25.<lb/> Certain other cases, which have been referred to by the<lb/> learned Counsel for the parties, have, in our considered opinion,<lb/> no direct bearing on the facts and issue involved in the present<lb/> case relating to the Consumer Protection Act, and thus, the same<lb/> are not being dealt with and considered here.<lb/></p>

			<p>26.<lb/> We may now deal with the decisions rendered by this<lb/> Court, which have been referred to in the Reference Order.<lb/></p>

			<p>27.<lb/> Division Bench of this Court has referred this<lb/> Question, after observing that there is an apparent conflict<lb/> between the decisions of this Court in Topline Shoes (supra);<lb/> Kailash Vs. Nanhku (2005) 4 SCC 480 and Salem Advocate<lb/> Bar Association vs. Union of India (2005) 6 SCC 344 on the one<lb/> hand; and Dr. J. J. Merchant (supra) and NIA vs. Hilli<lb/> Multipurpose Cold Storage (2015) 16 SCC 22, on the other<lb/> hand.<lb/></p>

			<p>28.<lb/> In Topline Shoes (supra), a Division Bench of this<lb/> Court, while dealing with the provisions of Section 13(2)(a) of the<lb/> Consumer Protection Act, has held that the said provision would<lb/> be directory and not mandatory. While holding so, the Bench<lb/> relied on the principles of natural justice, and also that no<lb/> consequence of nonfiling of the response to the complaint within<lb/> 45 days is provided for in the Consumer Protection Act.<lb/> In paragraph 8 of the said judgment, this Court held:<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot;It is for the Forum or the<lb/> Commission to consider all facts<lb/> and circumstances along with the<lb/> provisions of the Act providing time<lb/> frame to file reply, as a guideline<lb/> and then to exercise its discretion<lb/> as best as it may serve the ends of<lb/> justice and achieve the object of<lb/> speedy disposal of such cases<lb/> keeping in mind the principles of<lb/> natural justice as well&quot;.<lb/> (emphasis supplied)<lb/></item>

			<p>It is true that in Clause 4 of the Statement of Objects and<lb/> Reasons of the Consumer Protection Act, the legislature provided<lb/> that &quot;quasi-judicial bodies will observe the principles of natural<lb/> justice&quot;, however, the same is to be observed generally, and not<lb/> where the same is specifically excluded. In the said judgment,<lb/> subSection (3) of Section 13 has neither been referred, nor taken<lb/> note of. The same mandates that no proceedings complying with<lb/> the procedure laid down in subSections (1) and (2) of Section 13<lb/> shall be called in question in any Court on the ground that the<lb/> principles of natural justice have not been complied with. From<lb/> this it is evident that while considering the provisions of Section<lb/> 13(2)(a) of the Consumer Protection Act, the law mandates that<lb/> the principles of natural justice cannot be said to be violated by<lb/> adopting the said procedure and that the time of 30 days plus 15<lb/> days provided for filing the response to the complaint would be<lb/> sufficient and final.<lb/> In case of Topline Shoes (supra), this Court was also<lb/> of the view that in the Consumer Protection Act, &quot;no consequence<lb/> is provided in case the time granted to file reply exceeds the total<lb/> period of 45 days&quot;. While observing so, the Bench did not take<lb/> into account the provisions of Section 13(2)(b)(ii) of the Consumer<lb/> Protection Act, which provides that where the opposite party fails<lb/> to file response to the complaint within the specified time<lb/> provided in Clause (a), &quot;the District Forum shall proceed to settle<lb/> the consumer dispute……… on the basis of evidence brought to its<lb/> notice by the complainant……..&quot;. After the said judgment, by<lb/> Amendment Act 62 of 2002 (w.e.f. 15.03.2003), the legislature<lb/> has provided that the District Forum shall proceed to settle the<lb/> consumer dispute &quot;ex parte on the basis of the evidence&quot;. The<lb/> word &quot;ex parte&quot; has been added by the Amending Act. As we have<lb/> observed herein above, the consequence of not filing the response<lb/> to the complaint within the stipulated time is thus clearly<lb/> provided for in the aforesaid subSection, which has not been<lb/> noticed by the Bench while deciding the aforesaid case.<lb/></p>

			<p>29.<lb/> In the case of Kailash vs. Nanhku (supra), this Court<lb/> was dealing with an election trial under the Representation of<lb/> People Act, 1951, and while considering the provision under<lb/> Order VIII Rule 1 of the Code, it held the same to be directory,<lb/> and not mandatory. While holding so, the Court was of the view<lb/> that &quot;the consequences flowing from nonextension of time are not<lb/> specifically provided&quot; in the Code. The decision in the said case<lb/> has no bearing on the question under consideration, as the<lb/> present reference before us is under the Consumer Protection Act,<lb/> where, as we have already observed, consequences are specifically<lb/> provided for.<lb/> In passing, in paragraph 35 of the said judgment, the<lb/> Bench referred to the case of Topline Shoes (supra), where the<lb/> provision of Section 13 of the Consumer Protection Act was<lb/> considered to be directory, and not mandatory. In our view, the<lb/> same would not have the effect of affirming the decision of<lb/> Topline Shoes (supra) since the Court, in the aforesaid case, was<lb/> dealing with the provisions of the Code and not the specific<lb/> provisions of Consumer Protection Act.<lb/> We are thus of the opinion that Kailash vs Nanhku<lb/> (supra) has not overruled the decision in Dr. J. J. Merchant<lb/> (supra) with regard to the provision of the Consumer Protection<lb/> Act.<lb/></p>

			<p>30.<lb/> Again, in the case of Salem Advocates Bar<lb/> Association (supra), this Court was dealing with a case under<lb/> Order VIII Rule 1 of the Code and in paragraph 20, it has been<lb/> held as under:<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot;20.………The use of the word<lb/> &quot;shall&quot; is ordinarily indicative of<lb/> mandatory nature of the provision<lb/> but having regard to the context in<lb/> which it is used or having regard<lb/> to the intention of the legislation,<lb/> the same can be construed as<lb/> directory. The rule in question has<lb/> to advance the cause of justice<lb/> and not to defeat it. The rules of<lb/> procedure are made to advance<lb/> the cause of justice and not to<lb/> defeat it. Construction of the rule<lb/> or procedure which promotes<lb/> justice and prevents miscarriage<lb/> has to be preferred. The rules of<lb/> procedure are the handmaid of<lb/> justice and not its mistress. In the<lb/> present<lb/> context,<lb/> the<lb/> strict<lb/> interpretation<lb/> would<lb/> defeat<lb/> justice.&quot;<lb/> Thereafter, the Court proceeded to refer to the provisions of Order<lb/> VIII Rule 1, along with Order VIII Rule 10 of the Code. On a<lb/> harmonious construction of the said provision, it held that the<lb/> provisions of Order VIII Rule 1 of the Code would be directory,<lb/> and not mandatory. Relevant paragraph 21 of the said judgment<lb/> is below:<lb/></item>

			<item>&quot;21. In construing this provision,<lb/> support can also be had from<lb/> Order 8 Rule 10 which provides<lb/> that where any party from whom<lb/> a written statement is required<lb/> under Rule 1 or Rule 9, fails to<lb/> present the same within the time<lb/> permitted or fixed by the court, the<lb/> court shall pronounce judgment<lb/> against him, or make such other<lb/> order in relation to the suit as it<lb/> thinks fit. On failure to file written<lb/> statement under this provision,<lb/> the court has been given the<lb/> discretion either to pronounce<lb/> judgment against the defendant or<lb/> make such other order in relation<lb/> to the suit as it thinks fit. In the<lb/> context of the provision, despite<lb/> use of the word &quot;shall&quot;, the court<lb/> has been given the discretion to<lb/> pronounce or not to pronounce the<lb/> judgment against the defendant<lb/> even if the written statement is<lb/> not filed and instead pass such<lb/> order as it may think fit in relation<lb/> to the suit. In construing the<lb/> provision of Order 8 Rule 1 and<lb/> Rule<lb/> 10,<lb/> the<lb/> doctrine<lb/> of<lb/> harmonious<lb/> construction<lb/> is<lb/> required to be applied. The effect<lb/> would be that under Rule 10<lb/> Order 8, the court in its discretion<lb/> would have the power to allow the<lb/> defendant to file written statement<lb/> even after expiry of the period of<lb/> 90 days provided in Order 8 Rule<lb/> 1. There is no restriction in Order<lb/> 8 Rule 10 that after expiry of<lb/> ninety days, further time cannot<lb/> be granted. The court has wide<lb/> power to &quot;make such order in<lb/> relation to the suit as it thinks fit&quot;.<lb/> Clearly, therefore, the provision of<lb/> Order 8 Rule 1 providing for the<lb/> upper limit of 90 days to file<lb/> written statement is directory&quot;.<lb/></item>

			<p>As such in our view, the said judgment would hold the<lb/> field with regard to Order VIII Rule 1 of the Code and would not<lb/> be applicable to cases dealing with the provisions of Section 13(2)<lb/> of the Consumer Protection Act, or such other enactment wherein<lb/> a provision akin to Section 13(2) is there and the consequences<lb/> are also provided.<lb/></p>

			<p>31.<lb/> The case of Dr. J. J. Merchant (supra) is one relating<lb/> to the provisions of the Consumer Protection Act, and has been<lb/> decided by a Bench of three Judges of this Court (which is after<lb/> the decision in the case of Topline Shoes (supra) was rendered).<lb/> In this case it has been held that the time limit prescribed for<lb/> filing the response to the complaint under the Consumer<lb/> Protection Act, as provided under Section 13(2)(a), is to be strictly<lb/> adhered to, i.e. the same is mandatory, and not directory. In<lb/> paragraph 13 of the said judgment, it has been held that:<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot;For having speedy trial, this<lb/> legislative mandate of not giving<lb/> more than 45 days in submitting<lb/> the written statement or the<lb/> version of the case is required to<lb/> be adhered to.<lb/> If this is not<lb/> adhered<lb/> to,<lb/> the<lb/> legislative<lb/> mandate of disposing of the cases<lb/> within three or five months would<lb/> be defeated.<lb/></item>

			<p>In the said case of Dr. J. J. Merchant (supra), while<lb/> holding that the time limit prescribed would be mandatory and<lb/> thus be required to be strictly adhered to, this Court also<lb/> considered the Statement of Objects and Reasons of the<lb/> Consumer Protection (Amendment) Bill, 2002 (which was<lb/> subsequently enacted as Act 62 of 2002 and has come in force<lb/> w.e.f. 15.03.2003). The salient features of the same was &quot;to<lb/> provide simple, inexpensive and speedy justice to the<lb/> consumers……….&quot; and that &quot;the disposal of cases is to be faster&quot;<lb/> and after noticing that &quot;several bottlenecks and shortcomings<lb/> have also come to light in the implementation of various provisions<lb/> of the Act&quot; and with a view to achieve quicker disposal of<lb/> consumer complaints, certain amendments were made in the Act,<lb/> which included &quot;(iii) prescribing the period within which<lb/> complaints are to be admitted, notices are to be issued to opposite<lb/> party and complaints are to be decided&quot;. With this object in mind,<lb/> in subSection (2)(b)(ii) of Section 13, the opening sentence &quot;on<lb/> the basis of evidence&quot; has been substituted by &quot;ex parte on the<lb/> basis of evidence&quot;. By this amendment, consequences of not filing<lb/> the response to the complaint within the specified limit of 45 days<lb/> was to be that the District Forum shall procced to settle the<lb/> consumer dispute ex parte on the basis of evidence brought to its<lb/> notice by the complainant, where the opposite party omits or fails<lb/> to take action to represent his case within time. For achieving<lb/> the objective of quick disposal of complaints, the Court noticed<lb/> that subSection (3A) of Section 13 was inserted, providing that<lb/> the complaint should be heard as expeditiously as possible and<lb/> that endeavour should be made to normally decide the complaint<lb/> within 3 months, and within 5 months where analysis or testing<lb/> of commodities was required. The Provisos to the said sub<lb/> Section required that no adjournment should be ordinarily<lb/> granted and if granted, it should be for sufficient cause to be<lb/> recorded in writing and on imposition of cost, and if the<lb/> complaint could not be decided within the specified period,<lb/> reasons for the same were to be recorded at the time of disposing<lb/> of the complaint.<lb/> It was after observing so, and considering aforesaid<lb/> amendments, this Court held that the time limit of 30 plus 15<lb/> days in filing the response to the complaint, be mandatory and<lb/> strictly adhered to.<lb/></p>

			<p>32.<lb/> The decision of another Bench of three Judges in NIA<lb/> vs Hilli Multipurpose Coldstorage (supra), which has been<lb/> considered in the referring order was passed by a bench of two<lb/> Judges in the same case, after noticing a conflict of views in the<lb/> cases of Dr. J. J. Merchant (supra) and Kailash vs Nanhku<lb/> (supra).<lb/> After considering the provisions of the Code and<lb/> Consumer Protection Act, the reference was answered &quot;that the<lb/> law laid down by a three Judge Bench of this Court in Dr. J. J.<lb/> Merchant (supra) should prevail&quot;. In coming to this conclusion,<lb/> the following was observed in paragraphs 25 and 26 of the said<lb/> judgment:<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot;25. We are, therefore, of the<lb/> view that the judgment delivered<lb/> in J.J. Merchant holds the field<lb/> and therefore, we reiterate the<lb/> view that the District Forum can<lb/> grant a further period of 15 days<lb/> to the opposite party for filing his<lb/> version or reply and not beyond<lb/> that.<lb/></item>

			<item>26. There is one more reason to<lb/> follow the law laid down in J.J.<lb/> Merchant.<lb/> J.J. Merchant was<lb/> decided<lb/> in<lb/> 2002,<lb/> whereas<lb/> Kailash was decided in 2005.<lb/> As per law laid down by this<lb/> Court, while dealing Kailash, this<lb/> Court ought to have respected<lb/> the view expressed in J.J.<lb/> Merchant as the judgment<lb/> delivered in J.J. Merchant was<lb/> earlier in point of time.<lb/> The<lb/> aforesaid legal position cannot<lb/> be ignored by us and therefore,<lb/> we are of the opinion that the<lb/> view expressed in J.J. Merchant<lb/> should be followed.&quot;<lb/></item>

			<p>33.<lb/> Although, after the above decision, no further reference<lb/> was required to be made, but still we have proceeded to answer<lb/> the question referred to this Constitution Bench and are of the<lb/> considered opinion that the view expressed by this Court in the<lb/> case of Dr. J. J. Merchant (supra) is the correct view.<lb/> Question No. 2:<lb/> What would be the commencing point of<lb/> limitation of 30 days under Section 13 of<lb/> the Consumer Protection Act, 1986?<lb/></p>

			<p>34.<lb/> The question for determination is whether the<lb/> limitation under Section 13 of the Consumer Protection Act for<lb/> filing the response by the opposite party to the complaint would<lb/> commence from the date of receipt of the notice of the complaint<lb/> by the opposite party, or the receipt of notice accompanied by a<lb/> copy of the complaint.<lb/></p>

			<p>35.<lb/> In paragraph 12 of the judgment dated 04.12.2015, of<lb/> three Judge Bench of this Court, in this very case of NIA vs. Hilli<lb/> Multipurpose Cold Storage (supra), while referring to the<lb/> commencing point of limitation of 30 days under Section 13(2) of<lb/> the Consumer Protection Act, it has been held that &quot;The whole<lb/> issue centres round the period within which the opponent has to<lb/> give his version to the District Forum in pursuance of a complaint,<lb/> which is admitted under Section 12 of the Act. Upon receipt of a<lb/> complaint by the District Forum, if the complaint is admitted under<lb/> Section 12 of the Act, a copy of the complaint is to be served upon<lb/> the opposite party and as per the provisions of Section 13 of the<lb/> Act, the opposite party has to give his version of the case within a<lb/> period of 30 days from the date of receipt of the copy of the<lb/> complaint.&quot;<lb/></p>

			<p>36.<lb/> However, another two judge Bench of this Court, by an<lb/> Order dated 18.01.2017 passed in this very Appeal being Civil<lb/> Appeal No(s).1094110942 of 2013, NIA Vs. Hilli Multipurpose<lb/> Cold Storage, has expressed the view that the declaration made<lb/> in Dr. J. J. Merchant&apos;s case to the effect that the said period is<lb/> to be reckoned from the date of receipt of notice by the opposite<lb/> party or complaint under the Act, requires a more critical<lb/> analysis. The bench thus opined that &quot;what is the commencing<lb/> point of the limitation of 30 days stipulated in Section 13 of the Act<lb/> is required to be decided authoritatively&quot;. It is thus that this<lb/> question has been placed before us for an authoritative decision.<lb/></p>

			<p>37.<lb/> For deciding this question, we may first analyse the<lb/> relevant provisions of the Consumer Protection Act and the<lb/> Regulations framed thereunder. SubSections (2)(a) and (2)(b) of<lb/> Section13 of the Consumer Protection Act specify that it is the<lb/> copy of the complaint which is to given to the opposite party<lb/> directing him to give his version of the case within a period of 30<lb/> days or such extended period, not exceeding 15 days. As such,<lb/> from the aforesaid provision itself, it is clear that it is the copy of<lb/> the admitted complaint which is to be served, after which the<lb/> period to file the response would commence.<lb/> Further, Regulation 10 of the Consumer Protection<lb/> Regulations, 2005 also specifies the procedure of issuing notice,<lb/> which should be accompanied by copy of the complaint.<lb/> Regulation 10(5) clearly mentions that &quot;along with the notice,<lb/> copies of the complaint, memorandum of grounds of appeal,<lb/> petitions as the case may be and other documents filed shall be<lb/> served upon the opposite party(ies)/respondent(s)&quot;. The same<lb/> would also make it clear that it is on service of a copy of the<lb/> complaint that the period of limitation for filing the response by<lb/> the opposite party shall commence.<lb/></p>

			<p>38.<lb/> Even in the Code of Civil Procedure, Order VIII Rule 1<lb/> prescribes that the written statement shall be filed by the<lb/> defendant within 30 days from the receipt of the &quot;summons&quot;.<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot;Summons&quot; has been defined in Order V Rule 1 of the Code and<lb/> Rule 2 provides that &quot;Every summon shall be accompanied by a<lb/> copy of the plaint.&quot; While considering the aforesaid provisions, a<lb/> two judge Bench of this Court in the case of Nahar Enterprises<lb/> vs Hyderabad Allwyn Ltd. (2007) 9 SCC 466 has, in paragraph 8,<lb/> 9 and 10, held as under:<lb/></item>

			<item>(8) The learned counsel appears to<lb/> be correct. When a summons is<lb/> sent calling upon a defendant to<lb/> appear in the court and file his<lb/> written statement, it is obligatory<lb/> on the part of the court to send a<lb/> copy of the plaint and other<lb/> documents appended thereto, in<lb/> terms of Order 5 Rule 2 CPC.<lb/></item>

			<item>(9) Order 5 Rule 2 CPC reads as<lb/> under:<lb/></item>

			<item>&quot;2. Copy of plaint annexed to<lb/> summons. -Every summon shall<lb/> be accompanied by a copy of the<lb/> plaint.&quot;<lb/></item>

			<item>(10) The learned Judge did not<lb/> address itself the question as to<lb/> how a defendant, in absence of a<lb/> copy of the plaint and other<lb/> documents, would be able to file<lb/> his<lb/> written<lb/> statement…………………….……..&quot;<lb/></item>

			<p>39.<lb/> Even in Arbitration and Conciliation Act, 1996, sub<lb/> Section (5) of Section 31 provides that &quot;after the arbitral award is<lb/> made, a signed copy shall be delivered to each party&quot;.<lb/> An<lb/> application for setting aside the arbitral award is to be made<lb/> under Section 34 of the said Act. The delivery of the award sets in<lb/> motion the limitation for challenging the award under Section 34<lb/> of the said Act. While interpreting the nature and scope of Section<lb/> 31(5) of the said Act, a three Judge Bench of this Court in Union<lb/> of India vs Tecco Trichy Engineers &amp; Contractors, (2005) 4<lb/> SCC 239, has, in paragraph 6, held as under:<lb/></p>

			<p>(6)<lb/> Form and contents of the<lb/> arbitral award are provided by<lb/> Section 31 of the Act. The arbitral<lb/> award drawn up in the manner<lb/> prescribed by Section 31 of the Act<lb/> has to be signed and dated.<lb/> According to subsection (5), &quot;after<lb/> the arbitral award is made, a<lb/> signed copy shall be delivered to<lb/> each party&quot;. The term &quot;party&quot; is<lb/> defined by clause (h) of Section 2 of<lb/> the Act as meaning &quot;a party to an<lb/> arbitration<lb/> agreement&quot;.<lb/> The<lb/> definition is to be read as given<lb/> unless the context otherwise<lb/> requires. Under subsection (3) of<lb/> Section 34 the limitation of 3<lb/> months commences from the date<lb/> on which &quot;the party making that<lb/> application&quot; had received the<lb/> arbitral award. ……………&quot;<lb/> From the above, what we notice is that wherever limitation is<lb/> provided, either for filing response/written statement or filing an<lb/> appeal, it is the copy of the plaint or the order/award which is to<lb/> be served on the party concerned after which alone would<lb/> commence the period of limitation.<lb/></p>

			<p>40.<lb/> Now reverting to the provisions of the Consumer<lb/> Protection Act, a conjoint reading of Clauses (a) and (b) of sub<lb/> Section (2) of Section 13 would make the position absolutely clear<lb/> that the commencing point of limitation of 30 days, under the<lb/> aforesaid provisions, would be from the date of receipt of notice<lb/> accompanied by a copy of the complaint, and not merely receipt of<lb/> the notice, as the response has to be given, within the stipulated<lb/> time, to the averments made in the complaint and unless a copy of<lb/> the complaint is served on the opposite party, he would not be in a<lb/> position to furnish its reply. Thus, mere service of notice, without<lb/> service of the copy of the complaint, would not suffice and cannot<lb/> be the commencing point of 30 days under the aforesaid Section of<lb/> the Act. We may, however, clarify that the objection of not having<lb/> received a copy of the complaint along with the notice should be<lb/> raised on the first date itself and not thereafter, otherwise if<lb/> permitted to be raised at any point later would defeat the very<lb/> purpose of the Act, which is to provide simple and speedy<lb/> redressal of consumer disputes.<lb/></p>

			<p>41.<lb/> To conclude, we hold that our answer to the first<lb/> question is that the District Forum has no power to extend the<lb/> time for filing the response to the complaint beyond the<lb/> period of 15 days in addition to 30 days as is envisaged<lb/> under<lb/> Section<lb/> 13<lb/> of<lb/> the<lb/> Consumer<lb/> Protection<lb/> Act; and the answer to the second question is that the<lb/> commencing point of limitation of 30 days under Section 13 of the<lb/> Consumer Protection Act would be from the date of receipt of the<lb/> notice accompanied with the complaint by the opposite party, and<lb/> not mere receipt of the notice of the complaint.<lb/> This Judgment to operate prospectively.<lb/> The referred questions are answered accordingly.<lb/></p>

			<item>………………………………..J.<lb/> [Arun Mishra]<lb/></item>

			<item>………………………………..J.<lb/> [Indira Banerjee]<lb/></item>

			<item>………………………………..J.<lb/> [Vineet Saran]<lb/></item>

			<item>………………………………..J.<lb/> [M. R. Shah]<lb/></item>

			<item>………………………………..J.<lb/> [S. Ravindra Bhat]<lb/></item>

			<item>New Delhi<lb/> Dated: March 4, 2020</item>


	</text>
</tei>
