<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<p>
			1.
			<lb />
			Rule. Rule made returnable forthwith. Heard
			<lb />
			finally with the consent of the learned counsels for
			<lb />
			the parties.
			<lb />
			3 of 15
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			2.
			<lb />
			The petitioners are doctors in service. They
			<lb />
			are seeking directions against the respondents to
			<lb />
			allot them 10% marks for each year of the service
			<lb />
			rendered by them in difficult/hilly/rural area as an
			<lb />
			incentive as per the Government Resolution dated 20-
			<lb />
			05-2010 and 03-05-2011. Their further prayer is to
			<lb />
			hold that the cases of the petitioners will be
			<lb />
			governed by these two government resolutions and not
			<lb />
			by new policy framed vide two government resolutions
			<lb />
			dated 19-03-2019 read with Corrigendum dated 26-03-
			<lb />
			2020.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			3.
			<lb />
			The petitioners are seeking admission to the
			<lb />
			Postgraduate Medical Course under in service quota.
			<lb />
			According to the petitioners, Medical Council of
			<lb />
			India (for short &apos;MCI&apos;) has framed regulations
			<lb />
			namely
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			Postgraduate
			<lb />
			Medical
			<lb />
			Education
			<lb />
			Regulations 2000, which prescribed procedure for
			<lb />
			taking admission to the Postgraduate Medical Course.
			<lb />
			This regulation has been amended from time to time
			<lb />
			and lastly on or about May, 2018.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			4.
			<lb />
			Initially, there was 50% reservation in
			<lb />
			Postgraduate Course for the in service candidates.
			<lb />
			The said reservation has been modified in the year
			<lb />
			4 of 15
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			2009. The concerned State Government has been
			<lb />
			accorded power to allocate 10% additional marks for
			<lb />
			each year upto the maximum of 30% to the in service
			<lb />
			candidates who have worked in remote/difficult/rural
			<lb />
			area. The State Government, pursuant to 2009&apos;s
			<lb />
			amendment issued the Government Resolution dated 20-
			<lb />
			05-2010 and took a policy decision to allocate 10%
			<lb />
			additional marks to the in service candidates for
			<lb />
			each year. The said additional marks are to be added
			<lb />
			in the marks obtained by the concerned candidate in
			<lb />
			the NEET exam and after adding the said marks,
			<lb />
			candidate will be considered for the admission to
			<lb />
			the Postgraduate Course.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			5.
			<lb />
			The State Government, in order to give
			<lb />
			benefits of 10% additional marks has earmarked the
			<lb />
			area as remote area, difficult area and rural area
			<lb />
			as
			<lb />
			prescribed
			<lb />
			in
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			aforesaid
			<lb />
			government
			<lb />
			resolution. The Health Centres situated in 33
			<lb />
			districts have been notified as situated in remote
			<lb />
			area, difficult area and rural area. Thus, in
			<lb />
			service candidate who has served in the said areas
			<lb />
			would be entitled to the benefits under the 2010&apos;s
			<lb />
			Government Resolution.
			<lb />
			5 of 15
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			6.
			<lb />
			Another Government Resolution
			<lb />
			came to be
			<lb />
			issued on 03-05-2011 by the State Government laying
			<lb />
			down the procedure and the entitlement of the
			<lb />
			candidates for getting additional incentive marks.
			<lb />
			It is specifically mentioned in the said Government
			<lb />
			Resolution that the procedure would be applicable
			<lb />
			for the academic year 2011-2012 onwards.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			7.
			<lb />
			The said procedure laid down in 2011&apos;s
			<lb />
			Government Resolution was being followed till the
			<lb />
			year 2018. However, on 05-04-2018 the MCI has
			<lb />
			amended
			<lb />
			the regulation of
			<lb />
			2000.
			<lb />
			The State
			<lb />
			Government has been given authority to notify the
			<lb />
			remote/difficult/rural areas from time to time in
			<lb />
			order to give benefit of additional 10% marks per
			<lb />
			year to in service candidate. Accordingly, the State
			<lb />
			Government
			<lb />
			has issued the impugned
			<lb />
			Government
			<lb />
			Resolutions
			<lb />
			dated
			<lb />
			19-03-2019
			<lb />
			prescribing
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			procedure for allotting the additional marks on the
			<lb />
			basis of facilities available in the concerned area
			<lb />
			where Health Centres are situated. Marking system
			<lb />
			has
			<lb />
			been
			<lb />
			put
			<lb />
			in
			<lb />
			place,
			<lb />
			to
			<lb />
			define
			<lb />
			remote/difficult/rural area etc. For example, if
			<lb />
			Health Centre is situated in tribal area, 3 marks
			<lb />
			will be allotted. If it is situated in Naxalite
			<lb />
			6 of 15
			<lb />
			area, 2 marks will be allotted. If it is situated in
			<lb />
			hilly area, 2 marks will be allotted. If it is
			<lb />
			situated in rural area, 1 mark will be allotted etc.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			8.
			<lb />
			The area will be classified as remote area
			<lb />
			if overall marks fall between 6.1 to
			<lb />
			10. The in
			<lb />
			service candidates working in such Health Centres
			<lb />
			would be awarded 10% additional marks per year. The
			<lb />
			difficult area is the one where the marks fall
			<lb />
			between 3 to 6. The in service candidate working in
			<lb />
			such centre would be awarded 7% additional marks per
			<lb />
			year. The rural area is where the marks would be
			<lb />
			less than 3. The in service candidate working in
			<lb />
			such centre would be awarded 4% additional marks per
			<lb />
			year.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			9.
			<lb />
			On the basis of such marking, fresh centres
			<lb />
			have been notified under the impugned government
			<lb />
			resolutions. Primary Health Centre, Rayagaon where
			<lb />
			the petitioners in writ petition No.13949/2019 were
			<lb />
			working is notified under the category of rural
			<lb />
			area. Thus, the petitioners will now be entitled to
			<lb />
			get only 4% additional marks per year. Similar is
			<lb />
			the situation of the petitioner in writ petition No.
			<lb />
			5071/2020. The petitioner worked from 2016 as
			<lb />
			7 of 15
			<lb />
			Government Medical Officer Group-1, category of PHC
			<lb />
			of village Rajgad, Tq. Kinwat, Dist. Nanded. This
			<lb />
			centre would also fall under the category of rural
			<lb />
			area and thus he will now get only 4% additional
			<lb />
			marks per year.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			10.
			<lb />
			Thus, the State authorities have changed the
			<lb />
			earlier policy. In the previous policy there was no
			<lb />
			such bifurcation and all the candidates working
			<lb />
			under the remote/difficult/rural areas were entitled
			<lb />
			to get 10% additional incentive marks. However, the
			<lb />
			policy has been completely changed under the
			<lb />
			impugned Government Resolution.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			11. The grievance of the petitioners is that, this
			<lb />
			policy has been given retrospective effect vide
			<lb />
			Corrigendum dated 26-03-2020, and therefore, they
			<lb />
			have approached the court challenging the decision
			<lb />
			taken by the respondents.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			12.
			<lb />
			We have given thoughtful consideration to
			<lb />
			the submissions made by both the parties.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			13.
			<lb />
			Petitioner No.1 was initially appointed in
			<lb />
			Rural Hospital, Lonar vide order dated 06-10-2016.
			<lb />
			8 of 15
			<lb />
			However, on 29-04-2017 he was transferred to Primary
			<lb />
			Health Centre, Rayagaon which is remote area as
			<lb />
			defined in 2010&apos;s Government Resolution. Petitioner
			<lb />
			No.2
			<lb />
			has
			<lb />
			served
			<lb />
			at
			<lb />
			Primary
			<lb />
			Health
			<lb />
			Centre,
			<lb />
			Teerthpuri, Tq. Ghansawangi, Dist. Jalna from 2013
			<lb />
			to 2016. Thereafter, he came to be appointed as a
			<lb />
			Medical Officer, Group &apos;A&apos; at Primary Health Centre,
			<lb />
			Rayagaon a remote area. The petitioner in writ
			<lb />
			No. 5071/2020 was appointed in Primary
			<lb />
			Health Centre, Rajgad, Tq. Kinwat, Dist. Nanded vide
			<lb />
			order
			<lb />
			dated
			<lb />
			23-04-2016
			<lb />
			which
			<lb />
			comes
			<lb />
			under
			<lb />
			remote/difficult/hilly trival, naxalite undeveloped
			<lb />
			area.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			14.
			<lb />
			The petitioners claim that the policy
			<lb />
			prevailing at that time was to encourage the doctors
			<lb />
			like petitioners to serve in remote/difficult/rural
			<lb />
			areas. The petitioners have decided to join the
			<lb />
			Government service and to serve in the said areas in
			<lb />
			anticipation of getting 10% additional marks for
			<lb />
			each year&apos;s service. The petitioners have also
			<lb />
			executed necessary bonds to serve in the remote
			<lb />
			areas in order to get admission in the Postgraduate
			<lb />
			Course.
			<lb />
			Thus,
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			petitioners
			<lb />
			were
			<lb />
			otherwise
			<lb />
			entitled to get 10% additional incentive marks per
			<lb />
			9 of 15
			<lb />
			year up to maximum limit of 30% marks but by virtue
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			impugned
			<lb />
			government
			<lb />
			resolutions,
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			petitioners would now get only 4% additional
			<lb />
			incentive marks per year.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			15.
			<lb />
			There
			<lb />
			is
			<lb />
			no
			<lb />
			dispute
			<lb />
			that
			<lb />
			when
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			petitioners were appointed as Medical Officers, they
			<lb />
			were governed by the provisions of 2010&apos;s Government
			<lb />
			Resolution. In that sense, they were entitled to the
			<lb />
			benefits
			<lb />
			provided
			<lb />
			under
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			said
			<lb />
			Government
			<lb />
			Resolution for getting admission in the Postgraduate
			<lb />
			Course. There is further no dispute that the
			<lb />
			Government Resolution dated 19-03-2019 was issued
			<lb />
			pursuant to the amendment in MCI Regulations in the
			<lb />
			year 2018.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			16.
			<lb />
			The question is, whether the respondents
			<lb />
			were right in giving retrospective effect to the
			<lb />
			impugned government resolutions. The answer, would
			<lb />
			certainly be in the negative for the reasons to
			<lb />
			follow.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			17.
			<lb />
			The impugned government resolution dated 19-
			<lb />
			03-2019 would provide that the government resolution
			<lb />
			dated 19-06-2010 stands superseded. The second
			<lb />
			10 of 15
			<lb />
			government resolution of even date i.e. 19-03-2019,
			<lb />
			which laid down the procedure for granting benefits
			<lb />
			of marks would provide that the regulations would be
			<lb />
			applicable for the admissions for the year 2019-
			<lb />
			2020. The corrigendum dated 26-03-2020 provides,
			<lb />
			amongst others, that the provisions of government
			<lb />
			resolution dated 19-03-2019 will be applicable for
			<lb />
			in service doctors who have served at the rural
			<lb />
			areas during the period from 2010 to 2019. The
			<lb />
			petitioners therefore will be entitled only for 4%
			<lb />
			additional marks in terms of the impugned government
			<lb />
			resolutions read with corrigendum. The impugned
			<lb />
			government resolution, therefore, takes away all the
			<lb />
			benefits acquired by the petitioners.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			18.
			<lb />
			The law on the said point is well settled.
			<lb />
			The subsequent policy in the form of subordinate
			<lb />
			legislature or otherwise which is detrimental to the
			<lb />
			interest of citizens/ beneficiaries of earlier
			<lb />
			policy cannot be given retrospective effect. The
			<lb />
			Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court in the case of Dr. Dinesh
			<lb />
			Kumar and others Vs Motilal Nehru Medical College,
			<lb />
			Allahabad and others reported in (1985)3 SCC 22 and
			<lb />
			in the case of G. J. Raja Vs Tejraj Surana dated 30-
			<lb />
			07-2019, reported in 2019 (5) Mh.L.J. held that the
			<lb />
			11 of 15
			<lb />
			provisions which are in penal nature to the interest
			<lb />
			of person cannot be given retrospective effect.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			19.
			<lb />
			The impugned government resolutions are hit
			<lb />
			by
			<lb />
			principles of legitimate expectations. The
			<lb />
			petitioners have served at remote/difficult/rural
			<lb />
			locations with the legitimate expectation of getting
			<lb />
			additional
			<lb />
			benefits
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			10%
			<lb />
			marks
			<lb />
			per
			<lb />
			year.
			<lb />
			Therefore, the respondents, ought not to have issued
			<lb />
			impugned government resolutions giving retrospective
			<lb />
			effect.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			20.
			<lb />
			The
			<lb />
			petitioners
			<lb />
			have
			<lb />
			relied
			<lb />
			upon
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			judgment in writ petition No. 8268/2017 dated 05-07-
			<lb />
			2017 [Alia Kausar Mohammed Shafee Vs State of
			<lb />
			Maharashtra and others] with connected matters. The
			<lb />
			issue involved was in respect of eligibility of the
			<lb />
			candidates in getting admissions to the MBBS course
			<lb />
			from the Maharashtra State quota. The policy prior
			<lb />
			to 2017 was that the candidates who have passed 10 th
			<lb />
			std examination from the institution situated out
			<lb />
			side the Maharashtra but who have passed 12 th std
			<lb />
			examination from the institution situated in the
			<lb />
			State of Maharashtra and who are domicile of
			<lb />
			Maharashtra were eligible for getting admission
			<lb />
			12 of 15
			<lb />
			through the Maharashtra State quota. However, in the
			<lb />
			year 2017, the rule was changed. The modified clause
			<lb />
			was that the candidates who have passed 10 th and 12 th
			<lb />
			standard examination from the institution situated
			<lb />
			in the State of Maharashtra were also eligible for
			<lb />
			admission through the Maharashtra State quota. The
			<lb />
			amended policy was challenged before the Hon&apos;ble
			<lb />
			High Court. The High Court held that amended policy
			<lb />
			would not apply to the petitioners therein who have
			<lb />
			passed 10 th examination from outside Maharashtra
			<lb />
			prior to the year 2017.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			21.
			<lb />
			The petitioners have then referred to the
			<lb />
			writ petition No.3035/2019 dated 13-03-2019 [Ojas
			<lb />
			Devendra Shah Vs State of Maharashtra and ors] with
			<lb />
			connected petitions. The petitioners therein were
			<lb />
			admitted in the MBBS course between the period from
			<lb />
			01-11-2011 to 24-11-2017 and at that time, there was
			<lb />
			no policy of giving bond by them and the said policy
			<lb />
			was made applicable vide Government Resolution dated
			<lb />
			12-10-2017 and Government Resolution dated 24-11-
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			2017.
			<lb />
			The
			<lb />
			said
			<lb />
			Government
			<lb />
			Resolutions
			<lb />
			were
			<lb />
			challenged before the Principal Seat of High Court
			<lb />
			at Bombay. The High Court held that since the said
			<lb />
			policy was not in force when the petitioners therein
			<lb />
			13 of 15
			<lb />
			were admitted in MBBS course, the policy could not
			<lb />
			be made applicable subsequently.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			22.
			<lb />
			The
			<lb />
			respondents
			<lb />
			have
			<lb />
			submitted
			<lb />
			that
			<lb />
			Postgraduate Medical Education Regulations 2000 were
			<lb />
			amended in the year 2018 to include rural areas in
			<lb />
			the category of tribal difficult areas so as to
			<lb />
			extend benefit of additional incentive marks for the
			<lb />
			service extended in the rural areas as well. It is
			<lb />
			argued that the petitioners will also get benefits
			<lb />
			of the modified policy as they have worked in rural
			<lb />
			area. We are not convinced that said provision is
			<lb />
			beneficial to the petitioners. The overall effect of
			<lb />
			the policy is adverse to the interest of the
			<lb />
			petitioners. The petitioners will now get 4%
			<lb />
			additional marks as against 10% in terms of old
			<lb />
			policy.
			<lb />
			The
			<lb />
			modified
			<lb />
			policy
			<lb />
			if
			<lb />
			implemented
			<lb />
			retrospectively, will take away the benefits caused
			<lb />
			in favour of the petitioners. Therefore, the
			<lb />
			bifurcation of the areas envisaged in the impugned
			<lb />
			government resolution and it&apos;s benefits could only
			<lb />
			be made applicable with prospective effect.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			23.
			<lb />
			The
			<lb />
			sum
			<lb />
			and
			<lb />
			substance
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			above
			<lb />
			discussion is that, the policy decision taken by the
			<lb />
			14 of 15
			<lb />
			respondents through the two impugned government
			<lb />
			resolutions dated 19-03-2019 read with corrigendum
			<lb />
			dated 20-03-2020 will have prospective effect. The
			<lb />
			impugned government resolutions dated 19-03-2019 and
			<lb />
			corrigendum dated 20-03-2020 will not be applicable
			<lb />
			to the cases of the petitioners.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			24.
			<lb />
			The petitioners are, therefore, entitled to
			<lb />
			10% additional incentive marks per year as provided
			<lb />
			under the Government Resolution dated 20-05-2010 and
			<lb />
			03-05-2011. The petitions are partly
			<lb />
			allowed. Rule is made absolute in the above terms.
			<lb />
			No order as to costs.
			<lb />
			[ANIL L. PANSARE, J.]
			<lb />
			[RAVINDRA V. GHUGE, J.]
			<lb />
			VishalK/wp13949.19
			<lb />
		</p>
	</text>
</tei>
