<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<head>O R D E R<lb/></head>

			<p>This order has been divided into the following sections to facilitate analysis:<lb/></p>

			<p>A Introduction<lb/> B Outline of the Disaster Management Act<lb/> C Medical Infrastructure<lb/></p>

			<item>C</item>

			<head>.1 Submissions in UOI&apos;s Affidavits<lb/> C.2 National Policy for Admission in Hospitals<lb/> D Oxygen allocation and availability<lb/> E Vaccines<lb/></head>

			<p>E.1 Vaccine capacity and disbursal<lb/> E.2 Vaccine pricing<lb/> F Potentiality of Compulsory Licensing for vaccines and essential<lb/> drugs<lb/> G Supply of Essential Drugs<lb/> G.1 Submissions in the Central Government&apos;s Affidavits<lb/> G.2 Recommendations<lb/> G.3 Black Marketing<lb/> H Recommendations for augmenting healthcare workforce<lb/> I Epilogue<lb/> J Conclusion<lb/> A<lb/> Introduction<lb/> 1<lb/> The genesis of this suo motu writ petition is in an order dated 22 April<lb/> 2021. This Court took note of the unprecedented humanitarian crisis in the<lb/> country, following the outbreak of the COVID-19 pandemic. Notices were issued<lb/> to the Union of India 1 , the Governments of the States and Union Territories 2 , and<lb/> to several petitioners who were before the High Courts. The Court observed:<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot;the Union Government, the State Governments/Union<lb/> Territories and the parties, who appeared to have approached<lb/> the High Courts to show cause why uniform orders be not<lb/> passed by this Court in relation to<lb/> a) Supply of oxygen;<lb/></item>

			<item>b) Supply of essential drugs;<lb/> c) Method and manner of vaccination; and<lb/> d) Declaration of lockdown&quot;<lb/> The Court directed the Central Government to :<lb/></item>

			<item>&quot;1. Report on the existence or otherwise and requirement of<lb/> setting up of a coordinating body that would consider<lb/> allocation of the above resources in a consultative manner<lb/> (with the involvement of concerned States and Union<lb/> Territories).<lb/></item>

			<item>2. Consider declaration of essential medicines and medical<lb/> equipment including the above articles as essential<lb/> commodities in relation to COVID.<lb/></item>

			<item>3. In respect of coordination of logistical support for inter-State<lb/> and intra-State transportation and distribution of the above<lb/> resources.&quot;<lb/></item>

			<p>2<lb/> The Court also had appointed an Amicus Curiae to assist it. However, the<lb/> Amicus Curiae was, on his request, relieved of his position on 23 April 2021.<lb/> Hearings in the matter were then conducted on 27 April 2021, where the Court<lb/> appointed two new Amici: Mr Jaideep Gupta and Ms Meenakshi Arora, learned<lb/> Senior Counsel. They will be assisted by Mr Kunal Chatterjee and Mr Mohit Ram,<lb/> learned counsel and Advocate-on-Record. The Court began the hearing by<lb/> noting that the jurisdiction it assumed under Article 32 did not automatically lead<lb/> to the erosion of a High Court&quot;s jurisdiction under Article 226. Rather, the Court<lb/> stressed on the importance of the jurisdiction under Article 226, and how High<lb/> Courts may be better equipped to deal with issues within their own States.<lb/> However, this Court assumed jurisdiction over issues in relation to COVID-19<lb/> which traverse beyond state boundaries and affect the nation in its entirety.<lb/></p>

			<p>3<lb/> The Court noted that it was in receipt of an affidavit dated 23 April 2021<lb/> filed by the UOI. However, the Court directed the UOI to file an additional affidavit<lb/> and the respective governments of the States/Union Territories to file fresh<lb/> affidavits on four issues. The relevant extract of the order reads thus:<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot;(i) Supply of oxygen -The Court should be apprised by the<lb/> Union of India on<lb/></item>

			<item>(a) The projected demand for oxygen in the country at the<lb/> present point of time and in the foreseeable future;<lb/></item>

			<item>(b) The steps taken and proposed to augment the availability<lb/> of oxygen, meeting both the current and projected<lb/> requirements;<lb/></item>

			<item>(c) The monitoring mechanism for ensuring the supply of<lb/> oxygen, particularly to critically affected States and Union<lb/> Territories as well as the other areas;<lb/></item>

			<item>(d) The basis on which allocation of oxygen is being made<lb/> from the central pool; and<lb/></item>

			<item>(e) The methodology adopted for ensuring that the<lb/> requirements of the States are communicated to the Central<lb/> Government on a daily basis so as to ensure that the<lb/> availability of oxygen is commensurate with the need of each<lb/> State or, as the case may be, Union Territory.<lb/></item>

			<item>(ii) Enhancement of critical medical infrastructure, including<lb/> the availability of beds, Covid treatment centres with duly<lb/> equipped medical personnel on the basis of the projected<lb/> requirement of healthcare professionals and anticipated<lb/> requirements. The Union government will consider framing a<lb/> policy specifying the standards and norms to be observed for<lb/> admitting patients to hospitals and covid centres and the<lb/> modalities for admission;<lb/></item>

			<item>(iii) The steps taken to ensure due availability of essential<lb/> drugs, including Remdesivir and Favipiravir among other<lb/> prescribed drugs and the modalities which have been set up<lb/> for controlling prices of essential drugs, for preventing<lb/> hoarding and for ensuring proper communication of the<lb/> requirements at the level of each District by the District health<lb/> authorities or Collectors to the Health Departments of the<lb/> States and thereafter by the states to the Union Ministry of<lb/> Health and Family Welfare so that the projected requirements<lb/> are duly met and effectively monitored on a daily basis.<lb/></item>

			<item>(iv) Vaccination<lb/></item>

			<item>(a) Presently two vaccinations have been made available in<lb/> the country, namely, Covishield and Covaxin;<lb/></item>

			<item>(b) As of date, the vaccination programme has extended to all<lb/> citizens of the age of 45 years and above;<lb/></item>

			<item>(c) From 1 May 2021, the vaccination programme is to be<lb/> opened up also to persons between the age groups of 18 to<lb/> 45, in addition to the existing age group categories. The Union<lb/></item>

			<note type="other">of India shall clarify (i) the projected requirement of vaccines<lb/> as a result of the enhancement of coverage; (ii) the modalities<lb/> proposed for ensuring that the deficit in the availability of<lb/> vaccines is met; (iii) steps proposed for enhancement of<lb/> vaccine availability by sourcing stocks from within and outside<lb/> the country; (iv) modalities for administering the vaccines to<lb/> meet the requirements of those in the older age group (forty<lb/> five and above) who have already received the first dose; (v)<lb/> modalities fixed for administering the vaccine to meet the<lb/> additional demand of the 18-45 population; (vi) how the<lb/> supplies of vaccines will be allocated between various states if<lb/> each state is to negotiate with vaccine producers; and (vii)<lb/> steps taken and proposed for ensuring the procurement of<lb/> other vaccines apart from Covishield and Covaxin and the<lb/> time frame for implementation; and<lb/></note>

			<item>(d) The basis and rationale which has been adopted by the<lb/> Union government in regard to the pricing of vaccines. The<lb/> government shall explain the rationale for differential pricing in<lb/> regard to vaccines sourced by the Union government on one<lb/> hand and the states on the other hand when both sources<lb/> lead to the distribution of vaccines to citizens.&quot;<lb/></item>

			<p>4<lb/> This Court then received an additional affidavit dated 29 April 2021 from<lb/> the UOI, and fresh affidavits by the various States/UTs addressing the four issues<lb/> mentioned in its order dated 27 April 2021. In the hearing conducted on 30 April<lb/> 2021, this Court heard submissions by Mr Tushar Mehta, learned Solicitor<lb/> General of India, who was appearing on behalf of the Central Government.<lb/> Several other counsels have made brief interjections, including Mr Vikas Singh,<lb/> Senior Counsel and President of the Supreme Court Bar Association. This Court<lb/> also heard a presentation on oxygen supply in India by Ms Sumita Dawra,<lb/> Additional Secretary, Department of Promotion of Industry and International<lb/> Trade, Ministry of Commerce and Industry. As such, unless specified otherwise,<lb/> the directions and observations in the present order are limited to the UOI.<lb/></p>

			<p>5<lb/> During the course of the hearing, this Court directed that the individual<lb/> States/UTs shall be given an opportunity to discuss their affidavits at a later<lb/> hearing. Further, the Court also directed the learned Amici to prepare a tabular<lb/> compilation in relation to all the Interlocutory Applications which have been filed<lb/> in this petition. On the basis of the issues raised, they shall also be considered in<lb/> a later hearing. Before delving into a substantive discussion, we would like to<lb/> clarify that the jurisdiction exercised in this matter is merely to facilitate a dialogue<lb/> of relevant stakeholders, the UOI, the States and this Court, in light of the<lb/> pressing humanitarian crisis, and not with a view to usurp the role of the<lb/> executive and the legislature. This bounded-deliberative approach 3 is exercised<lb/> so that the UOI and States can justify the rationale behind their policy approach<lb/> which must be bound by the human rights framework which presently implicates<lb/> the right to life under Article 21 and right to equality under Article 14 of the<lb/> Constitution.<lb/></p>

			<item>3 Sandra Fredman, &quot;Adjudication as Accountability: A Deliberative Approach&quot; in Nicholas Bamforth and Peter<lb/> Leyland (eds), Accountability in the Contemporary Constitution (Oxford University Press, 2013)<lb/></item>

			<p>B<lb/> Outline of the Disaster Management Act<lb/></p>

			<p>6<lb/> The Disaster Management Act, 2005 4 came into effect on 26 December<lb/> 2005. The DMA provides for the effective management of disasters and matters<lb/> connected or incidental to such disasters. COVID-19 falls under the definition of a<lb/> disaster under Section 2(d) 5 of the DMA and the provisions of the DMA were<lb/> invoked for the first time to deal with the present pandemic. Under Section 6(2)(i)<lb/> of the DMA, the National Disaster Management Authority 6 issued an order dated<lb/> 24 March 2020 directing the Ministries, UOI, State/UTs and their authorities to<lb/> take effective measures to prevent the spread of COVID-19 in the country.<lb/> Thereafter, the Home Secretary, Ministry of Home Affairs as the Chairperson of<lb/> the National Executive Committee, which assists the NDMA in its functions, in an<lb/> order dated 24 March 2020 issued guidelines for the initial 21 days&quot; lockdown on<lb/> account of COVID-19.<lb/></p>

			<p>7<lb/> Section 2(e) defines disaster management as a continuous and integrated<lb/> process of planning, organizing, coordinating and implementing measures in<lb/> relation to the disaster. Section 2(e) provides:<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot;2…<lb/></item>

			<item>(e)&quot;disaster management&quot; means a continuous and integrated<lb/> process of planning, organizing, coordinating and<lb/> implementing measures&apos; which are necessary or expedient<lb/> for--<lb/></item>

			<item>(i) prevention of danger or threat of any disaster;<lb/></item>

			<item>(ii) mitigation or reduction of risk of any disaster or its&apos; severity<lb/> or consequences;<lb/></item>

			<item>(iii) capacity-building;<lb/></item>

			<item>(iv) preparedness to deal with any disaster;<lb/></item>

			<item>(v) prompt response to any threatening disaster situation or<lb/> disaster;<lb/></item>

			<item>(vi) assessing the severity or magnitude of effects of any<lb/> disaster;<lb/></item>

			<item>(vii) evacuation, rescue and relief;<lb/></item>

			<item>(viii) rehabilitation and reconstruction;..&quot;<lb/></item>

			<p>Section 2(n) of DMA defines a &quot;National Plan&quot; as the plan for disaster<lb/> management for the whole country prepared under Section 11 of DMA. Section 3<lb/> of the DMA constitutes the NDMA with the Prime Minister as the Chairperson, ex<lb/> officio. Section 6 lists down the powers and functions of the NDMA. Under<lb/> Section 6(2)(b), NDMA has the power to approve the National Plan. Section 11 of<lb/> the DMA provides the procedure for drawing up and implementation of the<lb/> National Plan in the following terms:<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot;11. National Plan<lb/> (1) There shall be drawn up a plan for disaster management<lb/> for the whole of the country to be called the National Plan.<lb/></item>

			<item>(2) The National Plan shall be prepared by the National<lb/> Executive Committee having regard to the National Policy and<lb/> in consultation with the State Governments and expert bodies<lb/> or organisations in the field of disaster management to be<lb/> approved by the National Authority.<lb/></item>

			<item>(3) The National Plan shall include--<lb/></item>

			<item>(a) measures to be taken for the prevention of<lb/> disasters, or the mitigation of their effects;<lb/></item>

			<item>(b) measures to be taken for the integration of<lb/> mitigation measures in the development plans;<lb/></item>

			<item>(c) measures to be taken for preparedness and<lb/> capacity building to effectively respond to any<lb/> threatening disaster situations or disaster;<lb/></item>

			<item>(d) roles and responsibilities of different Ministries or<lb/> Departments of the Government of India in respect of<lb/> measures specified in clauses (a), (b) and (c).<lb/></item>

			<item>(4) The National Plan shall be reviewed and updated annually.<lb/></item>

			<item>(5) Appropriate provisions shall be made by the Central<lb/> Government for financing the measures to be carried out<lb/> under the National Plan.<lb/></item>

			<item>(6) Copies of the National Plan referred to in sub-sections (2)<lb/> and (4) shall be made available to the Ministries or<lb/> Departments of the Government of India and such Ministries<lb/> or Departments shall draw up their own plans in accordance<lb/> with the National Plan.&quot;<lb/></item>

			<p>8<lb/> A National Plan includes, inter alia, measures for disaster prevention,<lb/> mitigation, preparedness and roles and responsibilities of different Ministries in<lb/> terms of Section 11(3) of DMA. A National Plan for the entire country was<lb/> prepared in the year 2016 and was revised and notified in November, 2019. The<lb/> National Plan, 2019 provides a framework to the Government agencies to deal<lb/> with different aspects of disaster management. Section 11(4) of the DMA<lb/> provides that the National Plan is to be revised and updated annually making it a<lb/> &quot;dynamic document&quot;. The executive summary of the National Plan succinctly<lb/> captures its purpose and contours in the below extract:<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot;...The National Disaster Management Plan (NDMP) provides<lb/> a framework and direction to the government agencies for all<lb/> phases of disaster management cycle. The NDMP is a<lb/> &quot;dynamic document&quot; in the sense that it will be periodically<lb/> improved keeping up with the emerging global best practices<lb/> and knowledge base in disaster management. It is in<lb/> accordance with the provisions of the DM Act, 2005, the<lb/> guidance given in the National Policy on Disaster<lb/> Management (NPDM) 2009, and the established national<lb/> practices...&quot;<lb/></item>

			<p>9<lb/> Section 12 of the DMA empowers the NDMA to recommend guidelines for<lb/> the minimum standard of relief to be provided to persons affected by disaster.<lb/> NDMA can create guidelines stipulating minimum standards of relief for providing<lb/> ex gratia assistance on account of loss of life and restoration of means of<lb/> livelihood in terms of Section 12(iii) of DMA. In light of the human suffering and<lb/> loss of livelihood that has accompanied this pandemic, NDMA may consider<lb/> laying down minimum standards of relief in this regard. We clarify that this is not<lb/> a direction of this Court, however a suggestion that can be looked into by the<lb/> NDMA. Under Section 12(iv) of the DMA, the NDMA has been given wide powers<lb/> to provide guidelines for any such relief that may be necessary.<lb/></p>

			<p>10<lb/> In addition to the above provisions, Section 35 of the DMA empowers the<lb/> Central Government to take measures which it deems to be necessary or<lb/> expedient for the purpose of disaster management. Section 35(2)(a) provides for<lb/> coordination of actions between the Central Government and State Governments<lb/> and their respective authorities in relation to disaster management. Section<lb/> 35(2)(e) obliges the Central Government to assist and cooperate with the State<lb/> Governments as requested by them or otherwise deemed appropriate by it.<lb/></p>

			<p>11<lb/> Section 36 of DMA provides for the responsibilities that have to be<lb/> undertaken by the Ministries or Departments of the Central Government. While<lb/> Section 36(h) empowers the Central Government to take any actions that it may<lb/> consider necessary for disaster management, Section 36(d) specifically enables<lb/> it to review its policies with a view to incorporate provisions necessary for<lb/> prevention of disaster, mitigation or preparedness. Under Section 36(f), it is the<lb/> responsibility of every Ministry or Department of Central Government to provide<lb/> assistance to the State Governments for (i) drawing up mitigation, preparedness<lb/> and response plans, capacity-building, data collection and identification and<lb/> training of personnel in relation to disaster management; (iii) carrying out rescue<lb/> and relief operations in the affected area; (iii) assessing the damage from any<lb/> disaster; and (iv) carrying out rehabilitation and reconstruction. Section 35(g)<lb/> provides that the Central Government is responsible for making available its<lb/> resources to the National Executive Committee or a State Executive Committee<lb/> for the purposes of, inter alia, transporting personnel and relief goods to and from<lb/> the affected area.<lb/></p>

			<p>12<lb/> The provisions of Sections 35 and 36 of the DMA that have been<lb/> discussed above have been enacted in the spirit of cooperative federalism in<lb/> order to ensure that Central Government can assist and enable the State<lb/> Governments to effectively tackle the disaster in question.<lb/></p>

			<p>13<lb/> The learned Solicitor General has submitted that the Central Government<lb/> is operating under the broad framework of the National Plan and the plan is<lb/> already in force. The plan specifically deals with &quot;Biological and Public Health<lb/> Emergencies&quot;. Further, different States have their own Disaster Management<lb/> Plans in place. It has been submitted that the National Plan does not and cannot<lb/> contain step by step instructions or specific directions for the day to day<lb/> management of the pandemic by the Government agencies. Such aspects are<lb/> kept open for executive decision, in view of the dynamic nature of the disaster in<lb/> question. Further, since COVID-19 is a novel virus, the knowledge in relation to<lb/> such a virus is contemporaneous in nature and is subject to constant<lb/> development. A three Judge bench of this Court in its judgement in Centre for<lb/> Public Interest Litigation vs Union of India 7 had noted that there was no need<lb/> to develop a fresh National Plan under Section 11 for COVID-19 since a National<lb/> Plan was already in place, which was being supplemented by various orders and<lb/> measures taken by competent authorities under DMA. Justice Ashok Bhushan,<lb/> speaking for this Court, observed that:<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot;40. The Disaster Management Act, 2005 contain ample<lb/> powers and measures, which could be taken by the National<lb/> Disaster Management Authority, National Executive<lb/> Committee and Central Government to prepare further plans,<lb/> guidelines and Standard Operating Procedure (SOPs), which<lb/> in respect to COVID-19 had been done from time to time.<lb/> Containment Plan for Novel Coronavirus, 2019 had been<lb/> issued by Ministry of Health and Family Welfare, Government<lb/> of India. There were no lack of guidelines, SOPs and Plan to<lb/> contain COVID-19, by Nodal Ministry had been brought on<lb/> record issued by Ministry of Health and Family Welfare,<lb/> Government of India, i.e., Updated Containment Plan for<lb/> Large Outbreaks Novel Coronavirus Disease, 2019 (COVID-<lb/>19).&quot;<lb/></item>

			<p>14<lb/> Therefore, the National Plan, 2019 can be supplemented by the issuance<lb/> of additional guidelines to tackle any aspect of disaster management including<lb/> the issue of admission to hospitals and access to essential drugs and vaccines in<lb/> respect of COVID-19.<lb/></p>

			<p>C<lb/> Medical Infrastructure<lb/> C.1 Submissions in UOI&apos;s Affidavits<lb/> 15<lb/> In relation to the broad issue of medical infrastructure, the Central<lb/> Government begins its affidavit dated 23 April 2021 and additional affidavit dated<lb/> 29 April 2021 by describing its &quot;three-tier setup&quot; of Covid Care Centers 8 ,<lb/> Dedicated COVID Health Centers 9 and Dedicated COVID Hospitals 10 which was<lb/> recommended to the States for tackling the COVID-19 pandemic, for which the<lb/> UOI also provided funds under an emergency response package from the<lb/> National Health Mission and State Disaster Response Fund.<lb/></p>

			<p>16<lb/> The present status of these is: (i) 2,084 DCH (of which 89 are under the<lb/> Central Government and the rest 1,995 with State Governments); (ii) 4,043<lb/> DCHC; and (iii) 12,673 CCC. Cumulatively, they have 18,52,265 beds in total, out<lb/> of which 4,68,974 beds are in DCH. It was also noted that Central Government<lb/> hospitals have also been converted into DCH.<lb/></p>

			<p>17<lb/> Further, tertiary care hospitals under ESIC, Defence, Railways,<lb/> paramilitary forces, Steel Ministry, et al, are also being leveraged for case<lb/> management. Even as many as 3816 railways coaches spread over 16 railway<lb/> zones have been converted into CCC. Finally, the DRDO has also set up large<lb/> field hospitals with capacities ranging from 1,000 to 10,000 isolation beds.<lb/></p>

			<p>18<lb/> It was noted that through coordination between Central Government and<lb/> State Governments, isolation beds (with/without oxygen) were increased to<lb/> around 15.7 lakhs, as compared to 10,180 before the first lockdown; similarly,<lb/> ICU beds were increased to more than 85,000, as compared to 2,168 before the<lb/> first lockdown. Similar upgrades were provided to necessary equipment such as<lb/> Ventilators, N95 masks and PPEs.<lb/></p>

			<p>19<lb/> The affidavit provides the following details of the efforts taken by UOI to<lb/> create projections for each State, and how it was communicated to them:<lb/></p>

			<p>(i)<lb/> It has developed an IT module for projections of expected cases based on<lb/> ongoing caseload, so as to alert States and districts to be prepared in<lb/> advance. The projections by the Central Government were regularly<lb/> shared in writing with the States, along with reports containing emergency<lb/> plans. This tool was also made available to States, to map their own<lb/> projections at the State level;<lb/></p>

			<item>(ii)<lb/> Details of the meetings conducted by the Prime Minister, the Minister of<lb/> Health and Family Welfare, the Cabinet Secretary, the Secretary (H) and<lb/> the DGHS were provided; and<lb/></item>

			<item>(iii)<lb/> Details of letters (which seem to have been sent on a monthly basis) sent<lb/> by the Central Government to the State Governments indicate that they<lb/> informed the State Governments of the projected cases for the coming<lb/> month, along with the number of Oxygen Supported Beds, ICU Beds and<lb/> of Ventilators that will be required to manage the projected cases.<lb/> Thereby, the State Governments which were found lacking in their<lb/> numbers were directed to ramp up their facilities.<lb/></item>

			<p>20<lb/> In relation to the preparedness for the second wave of the COVID-19<lb/> pandemic, the affidavits state that:<lb/></p>

			<p>(i)<lb/> After the first wave, the Central Government has been consistently writing<lb/> to the State Governments from 4 December 2020 with numbers of<lb/> projected cases, along with the directions requiring them to arrange the<lb/> necessary infrastructure which will be needed;<lb/></p>

			<item>(ii)<lb/> State Governments were requested by the UOI to formulate a<lb/> comprehensive plan in relation to:<lb/></item>

			<item>(a) Bed capacities, ICU beds, further identification of additional hospitals,<lb/> preparation of field hospital facilities, ensuring sufficient oxygen<lb/> supported beds and oxygen supplies;<lb/></item>

			<item>(b) Deployment of requisite HR training and mentoring of doctors and<lb/> nurses for management of patients, strengthen ambulance services and<lb/> centralized call center-based services for allocation of beds;<lb/></item>

			<item>(c) Suitable initiatives for (among other things) achieving and maintaining<lb/> adequate level of testing, surveillance and risk communication for<lb/> promoting wearing of masks, physical distancing, hand hygiene;<lb/></item>

			<item>(d) Sufficient referral linkages for districts with deficit infrastructure through<lb/> deployment of additional ambulances, wherever necessary; and<lb/></item>

			<item>(iii)<lb/> On 20 April 2021, the Ministry of Health and Family Welfare 11 wrote to the<lb/> State Governments with their projections and reminded them also of the<lb/> funding avenues being made available to all States under NHM funding,<lb/> State Disaster Response Fund, and other initiatives.<lb/></item>

			<p>21<lb/> The affidavits also note that the Central Government had developed a live<lb/> portal with all the States and districts where they were asked to feed in their data<lb/> of cases and details such as people under home isolation, on isolation beds (with<lb/> or without oxygen) and on ICU beds. Further, the State Governments were also<lb/> directed to feed in details of the COVID dedicated health care infrastructure<lb/> created by them, besides the details of containment zones so specified by them.<lb/> However, the Central Government has alleged that States and districts did not<lb/> upload their data regularly enough. Additionally, there was also a &quot;Facility App&quot;<lb/> which could be used by Covid Health facilities to monitor their patients as well as<lb/> the availability of logistics with their health facility. However, the Central<lb/> Government alleges that States, districts and facilities did not use this Facility<lb/> App.<lb/></p>

			<p>C.2 National Policy for Admission in Hospitals<lb/> 22<lb/> It has been submitted by the Central Government that health being a state<lb/> subject, the medical infrastructure is largely created and maintained by the<lb/> respective State Governments. Since we are yet to hear from the State<lb/> Governments, we shall not be issuing any directions or making comprehensive<lb/> observations in relation to this issue.<lb/></p>

			<p>23<lb/> However, based on the affidavits submitted by the Central Government<lb/> and the hearings which followed, we have come to understand that there is no<lb/> national policy on how admissions must take place in the various tiers of<lb/> hospitals (CCC, DCHC and DCH). Gaining admission into a hospital with a bed is<lb/> one of the biggest challenges being faced by most individuals during this second<lb/> wave of the COVID-19 pandemic. Left to their own devices, citizens have had to<lb/> suffer immeasurable hardship. Different states and local authorities follow their<lb/> own protocols. Differing standards for admission in different hospitals across the<lb/> nation leads to chaos and uncertainty. The situation cannot brook any delay.<lb/> Accordingly, we direct the Central Government to frame a policy in this regard, in<lb/> exercise of its statutory powers under the DMA, which will be followed nationally.<lb/> The presence of such a policy shall ensure that no one in need is turned away<lb/> from a hospital, due to no fault of their own. Such a policy should, inter alia,<lb/> address the following issues in relation to admission:<lb/></p>

			<p>(i)<lb/> Requirement of a positive test for COVID-19 virus, which may become<lb/> difficult for many individuals since testing facilities are overwhelmed, test<lb/> results are taking inordinately long time and the new strain of the COVID-<lb/>19 virus is sometimes not even picked up by a regular RT-PCR test;<lb/> (ii)<lb/> Some patients are being refused service based on arbitrary factors. For<lb/> example, the hospitals in Ahmedabad were initially refusing to take in<lb/> patients who did not arrive in the government-run &quot;108&quot; ambulances. While<lb/> this rule has now been removed, after objections were noted by the<lb/> Gujarat High Court during hearings in a suo motu public interest litigation 12 ,<lb/> we note that such rules cannot be allowed to crop up in other places;<lb/> (iii)<lb/> Some reports have also been brought to our attention that hospitals are<lb/> refusing to admit individuals who cannot produce a valid ID card which<lb/> shows that they belong to the city where the hospital is located. Given how<lb/> overstretched our hospitals are during the second wave of the COVID-19<lb/> pandemic, it is entirely plausible that individuals may travel to other cities in<lb/> desperation, since beds may not be available in their city. The rural health<lb/> infrastructure is seriously deficient. Hence, no hospital should be allowed<lb/> to deny them entry solely based on this reason or any other issues with<lb/> identity proofs;<lb/> (iv)<lb/> A related issue is when individuals often get their family member admitted<lb/> in a hospital in one city, but have to travel to another city to look for oxygen<lb/> or essential drugs and are denied their use because they are to be bought<lb/> for an individual admitted in a different city. As was true for the above such<lb/> rule, this is also unacceptable and should not be allowed;<lb/></p>

			<p>(v)<lb/> Admissions to hospital must be based on need. The Central Government,<lb/> in consultation with the respective State Governments, must formulate<lb/> guidelines on the stage at which hospitalization is required so as to ensure<lb/> that scarce hospital beds are not occupied by persons who do not need<lb/> hospitalization. This aspect should be based on the advice of medical<lb/> experts and can be suitably altered given the needs of each State (or<lb/> regions within the State) and in the course of the experiences gained<lb/> during the pandemic; and<lb/> (vi)<lb/> Directions are hereby issued to all States, Union Territories, and all public<lb/> agencies, to ensure that the above orders are implemented forthwith. The<lb/> Central, State and Union Territory governments shall issue necessary<lb/> orders and circulars, incorporating the above directions, within three days,<lb/> which shall be in force till replaced by an appropriate uniform policy,<lb/> devised by the central government, statutorily.<lb/></p>

			<p>D<lb/> Oxygen allocation and availability<lb/> 24<lb/> The Central Government has argued the following:<lb/></p>

			<item>(i)<lb/> By its order dated 11 September 2020, the Ministry of Home Affairs 13 , in<lb/> exercise of its powers under Section 10(2)(h) of the DMA had constituted<lb/> an Empowered Group-II as an inter-ministerial body to ensure availability of<lb/> essential medical equipment and oxygen management;<lb/></item>

			<item>(ii)<lb/> Medical oxygen is critical to treatment of COVID affected patients. The<lb/> entire available capacity of oxygen is used for supply for industrial and<lb/> medical use, which is in the form of Liquid Medical Oxygen 14 . The major<lb/> suppliers for both industrial and medical oxygen are steel plants in the<lb/> public and private sectors, and private entities;<lb/></item>

			<item>(iii)<lb/> Oxygen is not produced evenly in India. While some States may be oxygen<lb/> producing States such as Maharashtra, Rajasthan and Jharkhand; other<lb/> States/UTs such as Delhi, Goa and Madhya Pradesh, do not have<lb/> production capacity and rely on supply of oxygen from oxygen producing<lb/> States;<lb/></item>

			<item>(iv) For an estimation of the required oxygen supply, an Empowered Group I<lb/> was constituted which categorized patients into three categories:<lb/></item>

			<item> Class I comprising of 80% of the cases which are mild and do not<lb/> require oxygen;<lb/></item>

			<item> Class II comprising of 17% cases which are moderate and can be<lb/> managed on non-ICU beds and 50% of these may require oxygen<lb/> @10L/min; and<lb/></item>

			<item> Class III comprising of 3% of cases which are severe ICU cases<lb/> requiring approximately 24L/min oxygen.<lb/></item>

			<p>(v)<lb/> On the basis of the categorization provided by Empowered Group I, oxygen<lb/> requirement of different States on the basis of active cases is being<lb/> calculated which is around 8462 MT. Based on the trend of active cases,<lb/> the &quot;doubling rate of cases&quot; is calculated for each State, which implies, the<lb/> number of days in which COVID cases are likely to double. The number of<lb/> active cases are projected on the basis of the doubling rate and oxygen<lb/> requirement is calculated. These projections get changed daily on the basis<lb/> of real time change;<lb/></p>

			<p>(vi) In order to ensure supply of oxygen to all States, a mapping exercise of the<lb/> sources of supplies with the demand of medical oxygen to the critically<lb/> affected States was undertaken jointly by the Department of Promotion of<lb/> Industry and Internal Trade, MoHFW, Ministry of Steel, Petroleum and<lb/> Explosives Safety Organisation, oxygen manufacturers etc. During the<lb/> course of the mapping exercise, States were requested to indicate their<lb/> projections for requirement of medical oxygen based on expected active<lb/> case load. These projections were to be given as on 20 April, 25 April, and<lb/> 30 April 2021. The following was the forecast provided by the major States:<lb/> (vii) Based on these projections, an indicative mapping framework was drawn<lb/> up and approved by an order dated 15 April 2021, which provided the<lb/> name of the supply point, the State to which supply was allocated and the<lb/> quantity to be supplied. Subsequently, due to continuous changes in the<lb/> number of cases and the need for medical oxygen, a revised projection<lb/> was issued by States for 20 April 2021, which provided:<lb/> (viii) Following this, a revised supply plan for medical oxygen to 15 States for<lb/> meeting their demand was issued by an order dated 18 April 2021. Certain<lb/> States, such as Delhi, Rajasthan, Punjab, Uttar Pradesh, Uttarakhand and<lb/> Madhya Pradesh, faced challenges despite this allocation. Issues such as<lb/> logistical bottlenecks in transportation, incidents of local authorities in<lb/> disrupting supplies to other states were reported. Due to this, allocation<lb/> orders were further amended by orders dated 21 April 2021, 22 April 2021,<lb/> 24 April 2021, 25 April 2021 and 26 April 2021. The MHA also issued<lb/> orders dated 22 April 2021 and 25 April 2021 under the DMA to direct<lb/> States/UTs to ensure uninterrupted movement of medical oxygen;<lb/> (ix) The major principles on the basis of which the amendments were made<lb/> were to: (a) ensure that projected requirement of LMO is allocated as far as<lb/> possible; (b) allocate sources located within the State or closest to the<lb/> State while balancing requirements from States which have no/low internal<lb/> manufacturing capacity; (c) ensure feasible transportation; (d) ensure<lb/> minimum disruptions in existing supply chains;<lb/></p>

			<p>(x)<lb/> As an instance, the allocation summary for 28 April 2021 has been placed<lb/> on record:<lb/> (xi) After the Central Government procures and allocates the quantity of<lb/> medical oxygen to each State, it is the State Government&quot;s responsibility to<lb/> arrange transportation to pick up their allotted quantity from the supply<lb/> point;<lb/></p>

			<p>(xii) Given the fact that the mapping exercise has to be continuously updated<lb/> according to the need of the situation across States, the Central<lb/> Government also put in an interactive mechanism called the &quot;Virtual<lb/> Central Control Room&quot; consisting of senior officers of Additional/Joint<lb/> Secretary rank to monitor and find solutions to any problems that may arise<lb/> on a real time basis. We have been apprised that the daily allocation of the<lb/> supply of oxygen is sanctioned and uploaded on this virtual room, in which<lb/> the Chief Secretaries of all States/UTs are members;<lb/></p>

			<p>(xiii) In addition to the management of supply and demand of medical oxygen,<lb/> the Central Government has also taken the following steps to ensure<lb/> augmentation of supply in the country:<lb/></p>

			<p>(a) Licenses to industrial gas manufacturers: By an order dated 7 April<lb/> 2020, the Drug Controller General of India 15 allowed licenses to be<lb/> issued to industrial gas manufacturers for manufacturing medical<lb/> oxygen within 24 hours of receipt of the application by DCGI;<lb/></p>

			<p>(b) Enhanced production of LMO in steel plants and by private<lb/> manufacturers: Steps have been taken to reduce production of other<lb/> liquid products which are required for manufacturing steel (such as<lb/> argon and nitrogen) and enhance the capacity of liquid oxygen. This has<lb/> resulted in immediate enhancement of 293 MT. Additionally, the steel<lb/> sector has made available the liquid oxygen in its storage tanks (approx.<lb/> 16,000 MT as on 21 April 2021). Supplies have increased from 1000 MT<lb/> in the first week of April 2021 to 2600 MT on 21 April 2021. Moreover,<lb/> private manufacturers have also enhanced production of medical<lb/> oxygen;<lb/></p>

			<p>(c) Restrictions on use of industrial oxygen: By an order dated 18 April<lb/> 2021, the MoHFW restricted industrial use of oxygen. Supply of oxygen<lb/> for all industrial use was completely prohibited on 21 April 2021, except<lb/> for certain industries such as ampoules and vials; pharmaceuticals;<lb/> petroleum refineries; nuclear energy facilities; and oxygen cylinder<lb/> manufacturers. These have added 1000 MT of additional oxygen;<lb/></p>

			<p>(d) Augmentation in availability of tankers: India has 1224 oxygen<lb/> tankers (16732 MT capacity) and efforts are being made to increase this<lb/> capacity to 2000 tankers through conversion of nitrogen and argon<lb/> tankers and import of 138 cryogenic tankers;<lb/></p>

			<p>(e) Commissioning of PSA plants: Pressure Swing Absorption 16 is a<lb/> technology to generate oxygen at a local level. PSA plants established<lb/> in hospitals enable self-sufficiency in generation of oxygen. MoHFW is<lb/> in the process of commissioning 162 PSA Plants (154 MT capacity).<lb/> The following statistics have been furnished :<lb/> Number of plants installed:<lb/> 38<lb/> Number of plants to be installed by 30 April 2021<lb/> 21<lb/> Number of plants to be installed by 31 May 2021<lb/> 105<lb/> Number of plants to be installed by 30 June 2021 17<lb/> 51<lb/> Number of PSA Plants for district headquarters<lb/> (under planning)<lb/></p>

			<p>500<lb/></p>

			<p>(f) Import of medical oxygen: A global tender was floated to import<lb/> 50,000 MT of medical oxygen to be supplied in 90 days and quotations<lb/> have been received. As an interim measure, quotations from bidders<lb/> were called within 24 hours as to the quantities they could offer, prices<lb/> etc. Orders have been placed with 2 foreign suppliers, i.e., SSB<lb/> Cryogenic Equipment Ltd. for 200 MT and Gulf Industrial Gases Abu<lb/> Dhabi for 1800 MT. Another order is also being placed with M/s Ultra-<lb/>Pure Gases India for import of 500-1500 MT;<lb/></p>

			<p>(g) Augmentation of availability of cylinders: 1,02,400 oxygen cylinders<lb/> were procured in April and May 2020 and distributed to States. Orders<lb/> for additional 1,27,000 cylinders were placed on 21 April 2021. The<lb/> Central Government proposes to address the additional demand<lb/> through regulated portable oxygen system technology;<lb/></p>

			<p>(h) Setting up of jumbo container based COVID hospitals using<lb/> gaseous oxygen: Apart from LMO, the gaseous oxygen production<lb/> capacity in the steel sector is 43,000 MT per day against which 26,000<lb/> MT per day is being produced. Two private entities, AMNS and JSW are<lb/> setting up &quot;Jumbo&quot; COVID centres with 1000 bed oxygen facilities in<lb/> Hazira, Vijayanagar and Dolvi using gaseous oxygen; and<lb/> (i) Transportation by Air &amp; Rail: Railways are being used for long<lb/> distance transport of tankers through &quot;roll on roll off&quot; service and an<lb/> &quot;Oxygen Express&quot; -a double engine train which gets a green corridor -<lb/>is being run from supply point to destination. As an instance, the first<lb/> rake with 7 empty tankers reached Mumbai from Vizag to transport 105<lb/> MT from RINL Vizag to Kalamboli. In addition to this, defence aircraft for<lb/> carrying empty tankers to supply point are being deployed. However, it<lb/> is technically not possible to bring in oxygen filed tankers in an aircraft.<lb/></p>

			<p>25<lb/> During the course of the hearing, the Solicitor General has also sought to<lb/> lay down the facts and figures pertaining to production and supply of oxygen,<lb/> daily supply to States and challenges faced in supply chain logistics before the<lb/> Court by means of a power point presentation. We note the submission of the<lb/> Solicitor General that the figures given in the power point presentation are<lb/> revised on a daily basis and that the presentation is not to be treated as a<lb/> submission made on oath by the Solicitor General, which may give rise to a<lb/> cause of action for litigation in future either before this Court or the High Courts.<lb/> Ms Sumita Dawra, Additional Secretary, Department of Promotion of Industry and<lb/> Internal Trade, Ministry of Commerce and Industry, who is one of the senior<lb/> administrative officers in charge of oxygen procurement and supply coordination,<lb/> has given an overview of these issues and made a presentation before us. We<lb/> would like to record our appreciation for the contribution made by Ms Dawra and<lb/> her team, who despite being infected by the COVID-19 virus, has continued to<lb/> work and manage the supply of medical oxygen that the country so desperately<lb/> needs today. It is through the earnest contribution of officers such as Ms Dawra,<lb/> who are working round the clock, that the country is able to deal with the storm<lb/> created by one of the worst humanitarian crises we have seen.<lb/></p>

			<p>26<lb/> Based on the above facts and figures, the Solicitor General has stated that<lb/> there is no dearth of oxygen supply in the country as on date and steps are being<lb/> taken continuously to augment the supply of oxygen. Having said that, the<lb/> Solicitor General has also admitted that there has been a shortage of supply to<lb/> certain States and has attributed this shortage to various factors including the<lb/> failure of State Governments to lift the allocated quantity of oxygen from the<lb/> supply point; transportation bottlenecks caused by inter-State movement of<lb/> tankers; and technical failure of certain plants leading to reassessment of<lb/> allocation on a real time basis.<lb/></p>

			<p>27<lb/> Submissions have also been made on the issue of supply of oxygen by Mr<lb/> Rahul Mehra, learned Senior Counsel appearing for the Government of National<lb/> Capital Territory of Delhi 18 . Mr Rahul Mehra submits that the GNCTD is facing an<lb/> acute shortage of the supply of oxygen as it had been allocated a substantially<lb/> lower quantity of oxygen as against its projected demand. Mr Mehra pointed out<lb/> that initially as on 15 April 2021, the projected demand of GNCTD for 20 April<lb/> 2021 was 300 MT/day, for 25 April 2021 it was 349 MT/day, and for 30 April 2021<lb/> it was 445 MT/day. However, due to a surge in cases, the projected demand was<lb/> revised by GNCTD on 18 April 2021 to 700MT/day and this was immediately<lb/> communicated to the Central Government. Despite the increase in projected<lb/> demand, the supply of oxygen to GNCTD has continued in terms of the allocation<lb/> order dated 25 April 2021, in which 490 MT/day were allocated. As against this<lb/> as well, the manufacturers have only been able to supply 445 MT/day. Mr Mehra<lb/> has clarified that as on the date of the hearing their demand was 700MT/day,<lb/> however their projected demand for the coming days is stated to be 976 MT/day<lb/> as the GNCTD has planned an increase in medical infrastructure, including beds<lb/> with oxygen cylinders and beds for patients in intensive care unit.<lb/></p>

			<p>28<lb/> Opposing his submission, the Solicitor General and Ms Dawra stated that<lb/> no revised projections have been received from GNCTD till date. The Solicitor<lb/> General has also sought to highlight that the government of GNCTD has failed to<lb/> offtake the allocated quantity of oxygen from the supply point.<lb/></p>

			<p>29<lb/> Having heard the submissions of both counsels on the issues pertaining to<lb/> supply of oxygen to GNCTD, we note that the Central Government (on page 63)<lb/> in its affidavit dated 23 April 2021 has admitted that the projected demand for<lb/> GNCTD as of 20 April 2021 had increased by 133% from 300 MT/day to 700<lb/> MT/day. According to the figures of allocation given in the affidavit dated 23 April<lb/> 2021 and the presentation given by Ms Dawra, the existing allocation of GNCTD<lb/> remains at 490 MT/day. This situation must be remedied forthwith. The situation<lb/> on the ground in Delhi is heart rending. Recriminations between the Central<lb/> Government (which contends that GNCTD has not lifted its allocated quantity)<lb/> and GNCTD (which contends that despite its projected demand the quantity<lb/> allocated has not been enhanced) can furnish no solace to citizens whose lives<lb/> depend on a thin thread of oxygen being available. On the intervention of the<lb/> Court during the hearing, the Solicitor General states that he has instructions to<lb/> the effect that GNCTD&quot;s demand of medical oxygen will be met and that the<lb/> national capital will not suffer due to lack of oxygen. We issue a peremptory<lb/> direction in those terms. In the battle of shifting responsibility of supplying/off-<lb/>taking of oxygen, lives of citizens cannot be put in jeopardy. The protection of the<lb/> lives of citizens is paramount in times of a national crisis and the responsibility<lb/> falls on both the Central Government and the GNCTD to cooperate with each<lb/> other to ensure that all possible measures are taken to resolve the situation.<lb/> Learned Senior Counsel for GNCTD has assured the court after taking<lb/> instructions at the &quot;highest&quot; level that the issue will be resolved completely in a<lb/> spirit of co-operation. During the course of the hearing, the Solicitor General has<lb/> assured that henceforth he will ensure that the deficit of oxygen is rectified and<lb/> supply is made to the GNCTD according to their projected demand (which may<lb/> be revised in the future) on a day by day basis. We accept his submission and<lb/> direct compliance within 2 days from the date of the hearing, that is, on or before<lb/> midnight of 3 May 2021.<lb/></p>

			<p>30<lb/> With regard to the issue of the supply and availability of medical oxygen for<lb/> the entire country, we have noted that efforts are being made to augment the<lb/> availability of oxygen. While the Central and State Governments are in the<lb/> process of managing the supply of oxygen, at the same time, it is critical that a<lb/> buffer emergency stock of oxygen is created so that in the event that the supply<lb/> chain is disrupted to any one or more hospitals in an area for any reason, the<lb/> buffer or emergency stocks can be used to avoid loss of human lives. These<lb/> emergency stocks must be so distributed so as to be easily accessible without<lb/> delay in every local area. We have also seen the situation that has developed in<lb/> the last 24 hours in Delhi where patients, including among them medical<lb/> professionals, died because of the disruption of supplies and the time lag in the<lb/> arrival of tankers. This deficit shall be rectified immediately by the Central<lb/> Government by creating buffer stocks and collaborating with the States through<lb/> the virtual control room on a 24 by 7 basis. In view of the deaths which are being<lb/> caused daily by the disruption of supplies, this direction is more crucial than ever.<lb/> We therefore, direct the Central Government in collaboration with the States to<lb/> prepare a buffer stock of oxygen to be used for emergency purposes to ensure<lb/> supply lines continue to function even in unforeseen circumstances. The location<lb/> of the emergency stocks shall be decentralised so as to be immediately available<lb/> if the normal supply chain is disrupted to any hospital for any reason. The<lb/> emergency stocks shall be created within the next four days. The replenishment<lb/> of the emergency stocks will also be monitored on a real time basis through the<lb/> virtual control room in active consultation with each state/UT. This is in addition to<lb/> the day to day allocations.<lb/></p>

			<p>31<lb/> In addition to the above, we direct the Central Government to consider the<lb/> following suggestions, which may assist in increasing the availability of oxygen<lb/> and ensure transparency of demand-supply management, and provide a<lb/> clarification to this Court:<lb/></p>

			<p>(i)<lb/> We understand that the Virtual Central Control Room of the Central<lb/> Government displays the allocation of supply of oxygen by the Central<lb/> Government to each State/UT. By extension of this, a mechanism for<lb/> displaying real time updates of supply of oxygen from each State to<lb/> hospitals in each district, along with the remaining stock of oxygen with the<lb/> hospitals may be maintained and shared with the citizens to ensure<lb/> transparency. This will also ensure that citizens can easily identify the<lb/> hospitals where medical aid can be availed;<lb/></p>

			<p>(ii)<lb/> The government shall clarify the steps being taken on planning on the use<lb/> of oxygen concentrators to reduce the demand of LMO, such that LMO is<lb/> needed only for critical patients. A comprehensive plan on augmenting the<lb/> production/import of these oxygen concentrators may be considered;<lb/></p>

			<p>(iii) The expected supply of oxygen/containers to be received from outside<lb/> India should be suitably augmented to cater to anticipated increases in the<lb/> demand and shortfall of domestic availability. Pending the early finalization<lb/> of the global tender a decision may be taken on the need to continue<lb/> imports to bridge the gap in availability; and<lb/> (iv) A review shall be made of any restrictions on inter-State travel of trucks or<lb/> tankers carrying oxygen/other medical aid equipment (such as GST related<lb/> issues, documentation) which might cause a hindrance in their movement.<lb/> The Central Government may consider implementing a system to track and<lb/> map the supply tankers which would allow better management of resources<lb/> and allow diversion of resources from one State to the other in case of<lb/> emergencies.<lb/></p>

			<p>E<lb/> Vaccines<lb/> 32<lb/> The previous order of this Court dated 27 April 2021 directed the Central<lb/> Government to clarify, inter alia: (i) the projected availability of vaccines and<lb/> proposed steps to boost supply and distribution; and (ii) the vaccine pricing and<lb/> distribution among states. Upon perusing the affidavits filed by the Central<lb/> Government and after having the benefit of oral arguments of the Solicitor<lb/> General, we have arrived at the following understanding on the two broad issues<lb/> outlined above. We would once again re-iterate that we do not attempt to delve<lb/> into the role of the executive in designing policy choices. We are merely seeking<lb/> to enter into a dialogue with the relevant stakeholders in order to ensure probity<lb/> and transparency of the measures underway. We are cognizant that it is<lb/> ultimately up to the executive to frame and implement policies that it deems<lb/> appropriate, with the topmost regard to public interest.<lb/></p>

			<p>E.1 Vaccine capacity and disbursal<lb/></p>

			<p>33<lb/> The Central Government has apprised us of its constitution of a National<lb/> Expert Group on Vaccine Administration for COVID-19 19 on 7 August 2020 and<lb/> operationalization of the immunization programme from December 2020. It was<lb/> further stated that as of 26 April 2021, over 13.5 crore vaccine doses (approx. 9%<lb/> of the Indian population) have been administered to Frontline Workers,<lb/> Healthcare Workers and persons who are 45 years of age and higher in the 3<lb/> Phases of immunization. It was submitted that these vaccines have been<lb/> centrally procured and administered free of cost to the abovementioned groups<lb/> who were identified based on specific vulnerabilities and a higher mortality rate<lb/> on account of the COVID-19 infection.<lb/></p>

			<p>34<lb/> On 20 April 2021, the Central Government rolled out a revised strategy of<lb/> COVID-19 vaccination for all persons over 18 years of age, with effect from 1<lb/> May 2021. This new age group consists of approximately 59 crore people, which<lb/> would require 122 crore vaccine doses under the current two-dose vaccine<lb/> regime of Covishield and Covaxin which have been authorized for emergency<lb/> use in India. This revised strategy enables vaccine procurement by State<lb/> Governments and private hospitals, purportedly for accelerating the immunization<lb/> programme which is critical to curb the pandemic. In response to the query of this<lb/> Court on the necessity of the revised strategy, the Central Government furnished<lb/> the following justification:<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot;During the ongoing consultation with the states,<lb/> demands/concerns were raised by the various State<lb/> Governments to expand the scope of vaccination drive to<lb/> include the beneficiaries beyond the priority groups identified<lb/> by NEGVAC as approved by Central Government. As a matter<lb/> of co-operative federalism, it was felt necessary to allow play<lb/> in the joints and to de-centralize vaccine procurement and to<lb/> enable the States to expand vaccination drives to other<lb/> groups between the age of 18-44 years. However, since the<lb/> priority group as identified by Union of India (which had<lb/> more vulnerability) was not fully vaccinated, it was<lb/> considered imperative to carry out two drives separately<lb/> i.e. in a decentralized manner to achieve higher efficiency<lb/> and reach. Thus the States were given a participatory role<lb/> to undertake the procurement of vaccine and for<lb/> vaccination of any other &apos;groups identified drive&apos; for the<lb/> 18-44 age group. This would also keep the existing drive<lb/> of critical groups unobstructed as the 50 percent of the<lb/> vaccines procured through the GoI channel would<lb/> continue to support and provide free of cost vaccine to<lb/> the most vulnerable age groups of 45 years plus in the<lb/> country health care workers and frontline worker<lb/> identified by the Union of India who were entitled to get<lb/> vaccinated under Phase II.&quot;<lb/> (emphasis supplied)<lb/></item>

			<p>35<lb/> In response to the queries of the Court on how the supplies of vaccines will<lb/> be allocated between various states if each State Government is to negotiate with<lb/> vaccine producers, the Central Government has furnished the following<lb/> justification in order to iron out the inequities between States:<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot;For the remaining 50% non-government of India channel,<lb/> the states and the private hospitals are free to procure<lb/> vaccine for 18-44 years population, however, to have an<lb/> equitable distribution of vaccine across the country,<lb/> states have been allocated the available vaccine quantity<lb/> in proportion to the population between 18-44 years of<lb/> age of the respective state so as to ensure equitable<lb/> distribution of vaccine as there is a possibility of some<lb/> states having better bargaining power due to<lb/> geographical advantage etc.&quot;<lb/> (emphasis supplied)<lb/></item>

			<p>36<lb/> During the course of the hearing, this Court has expressed its reservations<lb/> prima facie on the validity of the revised policy under which the states and private<lb/> hospitals are to procure 50% of the vaccines in order to immunize persons in the<lb/> 18-44 years age group. For one thing, even this age group would consist of<lb/> persons who suffer from vulnerabilities. Once the vaccination programme has<lb/> been opened up for persons other than the 45 plus age group, it would not be<lb/> logical to impose the obligation to source vaccinations for the 18-44 age group on<lb/> the State Governments. This will, inter alia, leave each State Government to<lb/> negotiate supply schedules, delivery points and other logistical arrangements<lb/> with the manufacturers. At present, there are only two manufacturers for the<lb/> authorized vaccines (with one other vaccine -Sputnik V, in the process of<lb/> manufacture). The available stock of vaccines is not adequate to deal with the<lb/> requirements of both the categories. The Central Government must take the<lb/> responsibility of providing guidance to every State on the quantities to be<lb/> supplied to each State, the vaccine(s) being allocated, the period of delivery, and<lb/> the number of persons who can be covered for vaccination, among other details.<lb/> Leaving the State Governments to negotiate directly with manufacturers will<lb/> produce chaos and uncertainty. The object of vaccinating the 18-44 age group<lb/> cannot be achieved in the absence of stocks being available.<lb/></p>

			<p>37<lb/> Besides the above issues, the Central Government is directed to clarify the<lb/> following issues in order to ensure the protection of the fundamental rights to<lb/> equality and to life and personal liberty for all persons who will be eligible to take<lb/> the vaccine from 1 May 2021:<lb/></p>

			<p>(i)<lb/> Whether the Central and State Governments have introduced any<lb/> initiatives for ensuring the immunization of persons who do not have<lb/> access to digital resources as otherwise the mandatory requirement of<lb/> registration over the Co-WIN digital portal for persons in the age group of<lb/> 18-44 years will deprive a large class of citizens of vaccination;<lb/></p>

			<p>(ii)<lb/> Since the Central Government commits to vaccinating persons over 45<lb/> years, free of cost, in view of their vulnerability, whether walk-in facilities for<lb/> vaccination will continue for these persons after 1 May 2021;<lb/> (iii) Whether the Central or State Governments propose to undertake targeted<lb/> vaccination drives for persons who are providing on-ground assistance<lb/> during the second wave of the pandemic -such as crematorium workers,<lb/> who were not considered as Frontline or Healthcare workers for Phase 1 of<lb/> the vaccination drive;<lb/></p>

			<p>(iv) Whether, and if so what, steps being undertaken by INYAS, the nation-<lb/>wide mass awareness campaign for COVID-19 vaccination, for ensuring<lb/> outreach in rural areas and socio-economically underprivileged sections of<lb/> society including the possibility of using mobile vans, vehicles and railways<lb/> to vaccinate such people as well as those living in remote areas, near their<lb/> doorsteps so as to minimize their travel and potential infection with COVID-<lb/>2019. Efforts must also be made that a lack of an identity proof does not<lb/> create a hindrance in the process of immunization of all individuals,<lb/> specifically, the underprivileged;<lb/></p>

			<p>(v)<lb/> Whether the Central government will revisit its policy by procuring 100% of<lb/> the doses which can then be equitably disbursed to the State<lb/> Governments; and<lb/> (vi) Since the vaccine administration is now to be a shared responsibility of the<lb/> Union and the States, the Central Government and the State Governments<lb/> shall provide-(a) a breakup of the current and projected availability of<lb/> vaccine stocks for the next 6 months; and (b) a timeline for achieving<lb/> immunization of the newly eligible 59 crore persons who are aged between<lb/> 18-44 years.<lb/> These issues are of vital importance, since vaccination appears to be one of the<lb/> most important strategies to combat further spread of the pandemic, and would<lb/> also provide a measure of security and assure the people about their health and<lb/> well-being.<lb/></p>

			<p>E.2 Vaccine pricing<lb/> 38<lb/> Since the advent of the revised rollout strategy with effect from 1 May<lb/> 2021, only persons aged 45 years and above are guaranteed a free vaccine. The<lb/> reason of higher efficiency and speed has been furnished as a justification for<lb/> enabling State Governments and private hospitals to directly procure vaccines.<lb/> We have come to understand that a few State Governments have committed to<lb/> free immunization under the revised strategy. On specific enquiry on the rationale<lb/> in regard to the differential pricing for procurement by the Central Government<lb/> and the State Governments, the Central Government has furnished the following<lb/> justification:<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot;It is submitted that liberty to decide prices on arm&apos;s<lb/> length basis by and between the State Government and<lb/> hospitals is based on the concept of creating an<lb/> incentivized<lb/> demand<lb/> for<lb/> the<lb/> private<lb/> vaccine<lb/> manufacturers in order to instill a competitive market<lb/> resulting in increased production of vaccines and market<lb/> driven affordable prices for the same. Simultaneously, the<lb/> free vaccination by the Central Government for above referred<lb/> priority age groups would continue and it is always open for<lb/> each State Government either to offer free vaccination or<lb/> subsidise it for the additional identified earmarked priority<lb/> group identified by the State Governments [age 18-44 years].<lb/></item>

			<item>63. The new strategy was devised after multiple Inter-<lb/>Ministerial teams were deputed by Govt. of India to various<lb/> manufacturing sites to understand their requirement and to<lb/> provide pro-active and customized support to significantly<lb/> augment vaccine production capacities [which is the prime<lb/> priority of the Central Government at this juncture], in the form<lb/> of advance payments, facilitating more sites for production<lb/> etc. This approach, on the one hand, incentivizes vaccine<lb/> manufacturers to rapidly scale up their production and on<lb/> the other hand, it would also attract new vaccine<lb/> manufacturers. It would make pricing, procurement and<lb/> administration of vaccines more flexible and competitive<lb/> and would further ensure augmented vaccine production<lb/> as well as wider availability of vaccines in the country.&quot;<lb/> (emphasis supplied)<lb/></item>

			<p>39<lb/> Prima facie, there are several aspects of the vaccine pricing policy adopted<lb/> by the Central government which require that policy be revisited. All vaccines,<lb/> whether in the quantity of 50% purchased by the Central Government or the<lb/> remaining 50%, are to be used for vaccinating citizens. The end use is the same.<lb/> The Central Government proposes to purchase half of the total quantity falling<lb/> within its fifty per cent quota while for the rest, the manufacturers would declare in<lb/> advance the price to be fixed, allowing the State Governments to negotiate their<lb/> terms. As of date, the manufacturers have suggested two different prices, a lower<lb/> price which is applicable to the Central Government and a higher price which is<lb/> applicable to the quantities purchased by the State Governments. It is likely that<lb/> compelling the State Governments to negotiate with manufacturers on the ground<lb/> of promoting competition and making it attractive for new vaccine manufactures<lb/> will result in a serious detriment to those in the age group of 18 to 44 years, who<lb/> will be vaccinated by the State Governments. The social strata of this age group<lb/> also comprises persons who are Bahujans or belong to other under privileged<lb/> and marginalized groups, like many in the other population age groups. They<lb/> may not have the ability to pay. Whether or not essential vaccines will be made<lb/> available to them will depend upon the decision of each State Government,<lb/> based on its own finances, on whether or not the vaccine should be made<lb/> available free or should be subsidized and if so, to what extent. This will create<lb/> disparity across the nation. The vaccinations being provided to citizens constitute<lb/> a valuable public good. Discrimination cannot be made between different classes<lb/> of citizens who are similarly circumstanced on the ground that while the Central<lb/> government will carry the burden of providing free vaccines for the 45 years and<lb/> above population, the State Governments will discharge the responsibility of the<lb/> 18 to 44 age group on such commercial terms as they may negotiate. Prima<lb/> facie, the rational method of proceeding in a manner consistent with the right to<lb/> life (which includes the right to health) under Article 21 would be for the Central<lb/> Government to procure all vaccines and to negotiate the price with vaccine<lb/> manufacturers. Once quantities are allocated by it to each State Government, the<lb/> latter would lift the allocated quantities and carry out the distribution. In other<lb/> words, while procurement would be centralized, distribution of the vaccines<lb/> across India within the States/UTs would be decentralized. While we are not<lb/> passing a conclusive determination on the constitutionality of the current policy,<lb/> the manner in which the current policy has been framed would prima facie result<lb/> in a detriment to the right to public health which is an integral element of Article<lb/> 21 of the Constitution. Therefore, we believe that the Central Government should<lb/> consider revisiting its current vaccine policy to ensure that it withstands the<lb/> scrutiny of Articles 14 and Article 21 of the Constitution.<lb/></p>

			<p>40<lb/> In light of the justification offered for non-interference in the prices that are<lb/> set by the manufacturers, irrespective of their variance from the prices for<lb/> procurement of the Central Government, we would like to seek the following<lb/> clarifications:<lb/></p>

			<p>(i)<lb/> Whether any other alternatives were considered by the Central<lb/> Government for ramping up the immunization drive in India, particularly in<lb/> light of its initial strategy of a centralized free immunization drive;<lb/> (ii)<lb/> The methodology which the Central Government was envisaging to<lb/> procure adequate vaccine doses for the population prior to the revised<lb/> strategy which was announced amidst the second wave of COVID-19; and<lb/> (iii) Whether any studies and figures were relied upon in order to arrive at the<lb/> conclusion that decentralized procurement would spur competitive markets<lb/> to incentivize production and eventually drive down the prices of the<lb/> vaccines. Whether these studies are of relevance in a pandemic when<lb/> vaccines are a scarce and essential commodity which is being produced<lb/> by a limited number of manufacturers for a limited number of vaccines.<lb/></p>

			<p>41<lb/> The Central Government has submitted that the Finance Ministry has<lb/> sanctioned a credit of Rs 3000 crores for Covishield manufacturer -Serum<lb/> Institute of India 20 and Rs 1500 crores to Covaxin manufacturer -Bharat Biotech.<lb/> Additionally, another Rs 65 crores is stated to have been provided to Bharat<lb/> Biotech&quot;s production center at Bangalore. In bolstering its argument for<lb/> augmentation of vaccine production, the Central Government has provided the<lb/> Court with further information on advance funding (of unspecified amounts) that is<lb/> being provided to R&amp;D and manufacturing facilities. In light of this investment, the<lb/> Central Government should consider revisiting its policy bearing in mind what has<lb/> been stated above, the following issues and other relevant information:<lb/></p>

			<p>(i)<lb/> Whether, and if so, the Finance Ministry or any other funding organization<lb/> of the Government of India have made any grants/sanctions to Bharat<lb/> Biotech and the SII in the past, like the current infusion of Rs 1500 crores<lb/> and Rs 3000 crores, respectively. If so, breakup and corelation with the<lb/> total cost of development and production of the two vaccines;<lb/></p>

			<p>(ii)<lb/> Whether the current procurement prices for the Central Government<lb/> account for infusion of funds for production, infrastructure and other aid<lb/> provided by it. If so, the basis on which the same benefit is denied to<lb/> procurement by State Governments which equally service the needs of<lb/> citizens; and<lb/> (iii)<lb/> The full extent of direct and indirect grant/aid provided for research,<lb/> development and manufacture of all existing vaccines and future vaccines<lb/> that it proposes to authorize. For instance, the Central Government has<lb/> submitted in its affidavit that the Department of Biotechnology has<lb/> facilitated the trials for Sputnik V.<lb/></p>

			<p>F<lb/> Potentiality of Compulsory Licensing for vaccines and essential<lb/> drugs<lb/> 42<lb/> Several drugs that are at the core of the COVID treatment protocol are<lb/> under patents in India including Remdesivir, Tociluzumab and Favipiravir. On 2<lb/> October 2020, a communication was issued by the UOI, along with South Africa,<lb/> to the Council for Trade-Related Aspects of Intellectual Property which stated that<lb/> there were several reports about intellectual property rights hindering timely<lb/> provisioning of affordable medical products to patients 21 . The communication also<lb/> reported that some members of the World Trade Organization had carried out<lb/> urgent amendments to their national patent laws to expedite the process of<lb/> issuing compulsory/government use licenses.<lb/></p>

			<p>43<lb/> In India, the patent regime is governed by the Patents Act, 1970 22 , Section<lb/> 92 of which envisages the grant of a compulsory license, inter alia, in<lb/> circumstances of national emergency and extreme urgency. Once a declaration<lb/> of national emergency is made, and the relevant patents notified, any person<lb/> interested in manufacturing the drug can make an application to the Controller<lb/> General of Patents who can then issue a compulsory license. The patentee<lb/> would be paid a reasonable royalty as fixed by the Controller General of Patents.<lb/> Further, under Section 100 of the Patents Act, the Central Government can<lb/> authorize certain companies to use any patents for the &quot;purpose of the<lb/> government&quot;. Indian companies can begin manufacturing the drugs while<lb/> negotiating the royalties with the patentees. If the Central Government or its<lb/> authorized company is not able to reach an agreement with the patentee, the<lb/> High Court has to fix the reasonable royalty that is to be paid to the patentee.<lb/> Another alternative is for the Central Government to acquire the patents under<lb/> Section 102 from the patentees. If the Central Government and the patentee is<lb/> not able to reach a consensus on the price of the patents, it is up to the High<lb/> Court to fix the royalty. Additionally, under Section 66 of the Patents Act, the<lb/> Central Government is also entitled to revoke a patent in the public interest.<lb/> 21 Council for Trade-Related Aspects of Intellectual Property Rights, Waiver From Certain Provisions Of The Trips<lb/> Agreement For The Prevention, Containment And Treatment Of Covid-19, Communication From India And South<lb/> Africa,<lb/> IP/C/W/669,<lb/> 2nd<lb/> October,<lb/> 2020,<lb/> available<lb/> at<lb/> https://docs.wto.org/dol2fe/Pages/SS/directdoc.aspx?filename=q:/IP/C/W669.pdf&amp;Open=True<lb/> 22 &quot;Patents Act&quot;<lb/></p>

			<p>44<lb/> The utilization of these flexibilities has also been detailed in the Trade<lb/> Related Aspects of Intellectual Property Rights Agreement 23 . Even as TRIPS<lb/> obliges countries to ensure a minimum level of patent protection, it creates a<lb/> permissive regime for the carving out of exceptions and limitations that further<lb/> public health objectives 24 . This is evident from a conjoint reading of Articles 7, 8,<lb/> 30 and 31 of TRIPS. Article 7 outlines the objectives of the TRIPS as being to<lb/> ensure the effective enforcement of intellectual property in a way that, inter alia, is<lb/> &quot;conducive to social and economic welfare&quot;. Article 8 gives member countries the<lb/> freedom to take measures that protect public health and nutrition. Article 8(2)<lb/> allows for the taking of TRIPS-compatible measures aimed at preventing the<lb/> abuse of intellectual property rights. Articles 30 and 31 deal with exceptions to the<lb/> rights of patent owners, by allowing grant of compulsory licenses. It leaves<lb/> countries with significant breathing space to determine how the compulsory<lb/> licensing or government-use levers can be triggered. While such determinations<lb/> must be made on the individual merits of each case 25 , the aforesaid caveat does<lb/> not apply when the compulsory license grant is for national emergency, extreme<lb/> urgency or public non-commercial use 26 .<lb/></p>

			<p>45<lb/> According to the 2001 Doha Declaration, TRIPS should be interpreted in a<lb/> manner supportive of the right of members to protect public health and to promote<lb/> access to medicines 27 . It recognizes the right of WTO members to use the full<lb/> extent of the TRIPS flexibilities to secure this objective. Para 5(b) of the Doha<lb/> Declaration provides the freedom to each member to grant compulsory licenses<lb/> and to determine the grounds on which the licenses are granted. Para 5(c) leaves<lb/> it up to each nation to determine what constitutes a national emergency or<lb/> extreme urgency. In the context of the COVID-19 pandemic, we note that several<lb/> countries such as Canada and Germany have relaxed the legal regimes<lb/> governing the grant of compulsory licenses 28 .<lb/></p>

			<p>46<lb/> Whether and if so, the extent to which these provisions should be utilized is<lb/> a policy decision for the Central Government. We have flagged the issue for its<lb/> consideration. We have only outlined the legal framework within which the Central<lb/> Government can possibly consider compulsory licensing and government<lb/> acquisition of patents. The Central Government is free to choose any other<lb/> course of action that it deems fit to tackle the issue of vaccine requirements in an<lb/> equitable and expedient manner, which may involve negotiations with domestic<lb/> and foreign producers of vaccines. We clarify that it is up to the Central<lb/> Government to choose the best possible measures it can undertake during the<lb/> current crisis keeping in mind that public interest is of paramount importance.<lb/></p>

			<p>G<lb/> Supply of Essential Drugs<lb/> G.1 Submissions in the Central Government&apos;s Affidavits<lb/> 47<lb/> In relation to the broad issue of &quot;Supply of Essentials&quot;, in its affidavit dated<lb/> 23 April 2021 and additional affidavit 29 April 2021, with respect to Remdesivir,<lb/> the UOI urged that:<lb/></p>

			<p>(i)<lb/> Remdesivir is a patented drug which is being manufactured in India under<lb/> licensing agreements between the patent holder, M/s Gilead, a US based<lb/> company and seven Indian companies. Under such agreements, these<lb/> Indian companies are allowed to manufacture Remdesivir for distribution;<lb/> (ii)<lb/> In its affidavit dated 23 April 2021, it was submitted on behalf of the Central<lb/> Government that the current production is about 74 lakhs vials per month<lb/> and once the additional manufacturing sites of the seven manufacturers<lb/> become operational by May 2021, the production capacity will increase to<lb/> 90 lakhs vials per month. In its additional affidavit dated 29 April 2021, the<lb/> Central Government has submitted that as on 23 April 2021, the production<lb/> capacity has increased to 1.03 crore vials per month;<lb/></p>

			<p>(iii)<lb/> The Central Government allocated 11 lakhs vials of Remdesivir to nineteen<lb/> States with a high case load between 21 to 30 April through a letter issued<lb/> on 21 April 2021. This allocation was revised and expanded to all States<lb/> and UTs through a letter issued on 24 April 2021;<lb/></p>

			<p>(iv) The Central Government has directed the States to appoint nodal officers<lb/> to ensure unrestricted and timely movement of Remdesivir. A control room<lb/> has been set up in this regard by the National Pharmaceutical Pricing<lb/> Authority 29 which is monitoring supplies as allocated. A helpline has been<lb/> set up by NPPA and manufacturers have been directed to address the<lb/> hindrances in the movement of the drug. A WhatsApp group with nodal<lb/> officers has also been created to enable coordination and officials of MHA,<lb/> NPPA and CDSCO are also part of the group;<lb/></p>

			<item>(v)<lb/> Remdesivir, its Active Pharma Ingredients 30 and formulations have been<lb/> placed under export ban since 11 April 2021;<lb/></item>

			<item>(vi) The Ministry of Finance has issued a notification on 20 April 2021<lb/> exempting customs duty on the Remdesivir injection, and API of<lb/> Remdesivir and Betacyclodexterin, which are used in the manufacture of<lb/> the injection. All the SEZ/EOU manufacturing units of M/s Mylan and M/s<lb/> Honous Lab, who are manufacturing Remdesivir on behalf of some of the<lb/> seven manufacturers have also been directed to start manufacturing<lb/> Remdesivir for domestic supply;<lb/></item>

			<p>(vii) CDSCO has directed all State Drug Controllers on 10 April 2021 to conduct<lb/> a special investigation drive to prevent hoarding and black-marketing of<lb/> Remdesivir in the country. DCGI and State Drug Controllers have been<lb/> taking stringent action against such activities and enforcement action has<lb/> been taken in thirty-four cases across the country;<lb/></p>

			<p>(viii) MHA has issued an advisory on 22 April 2021 to States and Union<lb/> Territories to facilitate smooth movement of supplies. A &quot;Covid Drug<lb/> Management Cell&quot; consisting of the Department&quot;s Senior Officers and<lb/> others has been constituted on 26 April 2021 to oversee and identify<lb/> common concerns raised by States in relation to Remdesivir;<lb/></p>

			<p>(ix) NPPA has revised the maximum retail price of a 100 mg/vial of Remdesivir<lb/> to Rs 3500; and<lb/> (x)<lb/> The Central Government is also looking at the possibility of importing<lb/> Remdesivir.<lb/></p>

			<p>48<lb/> The UOI made the following submissions on the availability of Tociluzumab<lb/> injections:<lb/></p>

			<p>(i)<lb/> Tociluzumab is manufactured by a Swiss Company, M/s Roche, which<lb/> does not have any manufacturing facility in India or any agreements with<lb/> domestic pharma companies to manufacture the drug. It is imported in the<lb/> country by Cipla. India is completely dependent on imports;<lb/> (ii)<lb/> It is listed as an investigational therapy drug (off-label) under the National<lb/> Clinical Management Protocol for COVID-19 for severe cases. There are<lb/> domestically produced alternatives which are equivalent to or better than<lb/> Tociluzumab such as itulizumab, dexamethasone and methyl<lb/> prednisolone. However, an incorrect public perception has been created<lb/> that only Tociluzumab can treat the inflammatory burst condition in COVID-<lb/>19 patients since it is an imported drug. This has led to the acute shortage<lb/> in the availability of the drug and has created public panic; and<lb/></p>

			<item>(iii)<lb/> The supply of Tociluzumab is being monitored by NPPA and CDSCO.<lb/></item>

			<p>49<lb/> The UOI has made the following submissions on the availability of other<lb/> drugs:<lb/></p>

			<p>(i)<lb/> The National Clinical Management Protocol for COVID-19 does not include<lb/> Favipirarvir (popularly known as Fabiflu) due to insufficient peer reviewed<lb/> evidence to substantiate its use in mild to moderate cases of COVID-19.<lb/> However, it is being prescribed by certain doctors. The clinical<lb/> management protocol is a dynamic document which is reviewed<lb/> periodically and is subject to further evaluation based on medical research<lb/> and evidence that comes up in future; and<lb/> (ii)<lb/> On 24 April 2021, Department of Pharmaceuticals 31 , NPPA and DCGI had<lb/> reviewed the production and supply of other drugs such as Favipiravir,<lb/> Enoxaparin, Ivermectin, Methylprednisolone, Paracetamol and Hydroxy-<lb/>chloroquine. A meeting was conducted on 25 April 2021 by NPPA and<lb/> DCGI with manufacturers to review stock position, availability and<lb/> production plans.<lb/></p>

			<p>G.2 Recommendations<lb/> 50<lb/> In respect of the essential drugs, this Court has been informed that the<lb/> Central Government is taking steps to augment the production of Remdesivir. It<lb/> has been brought to our notice that seven Indian companies are manufacturing<lb/> this drug under a licensing agreement with a US based company, M/s Gilead. The<lb/> current production capacity as on 23 April 2021 is noted to be at 1.03 crores vials<lb/> per month. The Central Government should provide us with the details of the<lb/> actual rate of production and a breakup of demand for the drug from different<lb/> States. Further, while it has been submitted on behalf of the Central Government<lb/> that it is allocating the stocks based on a rational criterion of equitable distribution<lb/> keeping in mind the existing constraints on the availability of the drug, this Court<lb/> should be provided with details of the methodology used for such allocation.<lb/></p>

			<p>51<lb/> We have been informed by the Central Government in its affidavit that<lb/> NPPA has revised the maximum retail price of Remdesivir to Rs 3500. However,<lb/> it has come to our notice that several other drugs which are being prescribed by<lb/> doctors for treating COVID-19 patients like Favipiravir, Tociluzumab, Enoxaparin,<lb/> Ivermectin, Methylprednisolone, Paracetamol and Hydroxy-chloroquine are being<lb/> priced at exorbitant rates creating issues of access and affordability. While this is<lb/> not a direction of this Court, the Central Government can consider invoking its<lb/> statutory powers under paragraphs 19 and 20 of the Drugs Price Control Order,<lb/> 2013. Under paragraph 19 32 of the Drugs Price Control Order, 2013 the<lb/> Government in extraordinary circumstances, if it considers necessary in public<lb/> interest, can fix a ceiling price or retail price of the drug for a certain period.<lb/> COVID-19 is a crisis of an unprecedented nature and qualifies as an<lb/> extraordinary circumstance. It will be in public interest to ensure that the price of<lb/> essential drugs is fixed in such a manner that it is available even to the most<lb/> marginalized sections of the society. The Government can even monitor the<lb/> prices of the drugs under paragraph 20 33 of the Drugs Price Control Order, 2013<lb/></p>

			<item>32 &quot;19: Fixation of the Ceiling Price Under Certain Circumstances: Notwithstanding anything contained in this<lb/> order, the Government may, in case of extraordinary circumstances, if it considers necessary to do so in public<lb/> interest, fix the ceiling price or retail price of any drug, as it may deem fit and where the ceiling price or retail price<lb/> of the drug is already fixed and notified, the Government may allow an increase or decrease in the ceiling price or<lb/> the retail price, as the case may be, irrespective of annual wholesale price index of that year.&quot;<lb/></item>

			<item>33 &quot;20: Monitoring the Prices of Non-Scheduled Formulations: (1) the Government shall monitor the maximum<lb/> retail prices (MRP) of all the drugs, including the non-scheduled formulations and ensure that no manufacturer<lb/> increases the maximum retail price of a drug more than ten percent of maximum retail price during preceding<lb/> twelve months and where the increase is beyond ten percent of maximum retail price, it shall reduce the same to<lb/> and ensure that no manufacturer increases the prices of the drugs by more than<lb/> 10% of the maximum retail price during the preceding 12 months and where the<lb/> increase is beyond 10% of the maximum retail price, it can oblige the<lb/> manufacturer to reduce it to the level of 10% for the next 12 months.<lb/></item>

			<p>52<lb/> The Central Government has submitted that it plans to import Remdesivir.<lb/> It can also consider importing other essential drugs to meet the immediate<lb/> demand of the drug while the production is ramped up. We hasten to clarify that<lb/> this does not constitute a direction of this Court and ultimately this decision falls<lb/> under the domain of the executive.<lb/></p>

			<p>53<lb/> We note that there are certain medicines which are being prescribed by<lb/> doctors which are not mentioned in the National Clinical Management Protocol for<lb/> COVID-19 like Favipiravir. However, since these medicines are being prescribed<lb/> by doctors, people are facing significant inconvenience in obtaining them due to<lb/> their shortage in certain parts of the country. The Central Government should<lb/> consider whether the production of such medicines should be augmented to meet<lb/> the demand or instructions should be given to the doctors to not recommend such<lb/> medicines unless they have been included in the national protocol.<lb/></p>

			<p>54<lb/> It has been submitted on behalf of the Central Government that on 24 April<lb/> 2021, DoP, NPPA and DGCI reviewed the production and supply of drugs such<lb/> as Favipiravir, Enoxaparin, Ivermectin, Methylprednisolone, Paracetamol and<lb/> Hydroxy-chloroquine. The supply of Remdesivir and Tociluzumab is already<lb/> under the consideration of the Central Government. A meeting was also held on<lb/> the level of ten percent of maximum retail price for next twelve months. (2) The manufacturer shall be liable to<lb/> deposit the overcharged amount along with interest thereon from the date of the increase in price in addition to<lb/> the penalty.&quot;<lb/></p>

			<p>25 April 2021 by DoP, NPPA and DGCI with the manufacturers to review stock<lb/> position, availability and production plans. The Central Government should<lb/> provide details of estimated demand of essential drugs mentioned above,<lb/> production capacity, existing stocks, details of allocation and supply of such<lb/> drugs.<lb/></p>

			<p>55<lb/> As discussed in Section F, the Central Government can also consider<lb/> using its powers under Sections 92, 100 or 102 of the Patents Act to increase<lb/> production of essential drugs to ensure that it is commensurate to the demand.<lb/> The Central Government&quot;s affidavit testifies to existence of capacity of public<lb/> sector organizations and institutes, which can assist in augmenting production of<lb/> various drugs and formulations. The utilization of these capabilities to augment<lb/> production, once licensing is resorted to, will be in the interests of the general<lb/> public. This Court is further of the opinion that prima facie the present<lb/> circumstance warrant the government&quot;s examination of its the extraordinary<lb/> powers, meant to be used in extreme situations, such as the current pandemic,<lb/> for fixing drug prices, be it vaccines, or patented formulations, having regard to<lb/> the provisions of the Drugs and Cosmetics Act, 1940 and other provisions 34 . We<lb/> are cognizant that invocation of the above provisions, if any, is ultimately a policy<lb/> decision of the Central Government and may encompass negotiations with the<lb/> concerned stakeholders. We hope that the Central Government will adopt a route<lb/> that best serves the public interest.<lb/></p>

			<p>G.3 Black Marketing<lb/> 56<lb/> This Court would like to take judicial notice of the fact that several critical<lb/> drugs, used to treat COVID-19, such as Remdesivir and Tocilizumab, are being<lb/> sold at significantly inflated prices or in fake form. This is a condemnable attempt<lb/> to exploit people&quot;s misery and profit from their helplessness.<lb/></p>

			<p>57<lb/> In order to clamp down on this practice, the Central Government can<lb/> consider constituting a special team to identify and prosecute those who: (a) sell<lb/> medical grade oxygen/COVID-19 medicines at exorbitant prices; and (b) sell fake<lb/> substances and recover the concerned substances. A protocol for ambulances<lb/> must also be evolved to avoid citizens being exploited by extracting<lb/> unconscionable charges. The Central Government can consider creating a<lb/> platform for easy reporting and redressal of such cases.<lb/></p>

			<p>H<lb/> Recommendations for augmenting healthcare workforce<lb/> 58<lb/> It is common knowledge that a large number of medical, nursing and<lb/> pharmacy students, who graduated in 2020 and would be in the process of<lb/> graduating in 2021, would be available to augment the workforce in the health<lb/> sector. The Central Government should, we feel, look into this aspect, and ensure<lb/> the optimal manner of utilization of their services, regard being had, of course, to<lb/> their safety and well-being.<lb/></p>

			<p>59<lb/> The Central Government should also consider using health care workforce<lb/> available with the armed forces and para military forces for the purpose of<lb/> vaccination.<lb/></p>

			<p>I<lb/> Epilogue<lb/> 60<lb/> The World Health Organisation 35 , while discussing the rapid spread of<lb/> COVID-19 has not only labelled it an epidemic but also an &quot;infodemic&quot;, due to the<lb/> overabundance of information on the internet, which was riddled with<lb/> misinformation and disinformation 36 . This highlights the key role internet and<lb/> technology currently has in all our lives, as the COVID-19 pandemic rages on.<lb/> Indeed, the WHO recently also conducted a study to understand how individuals<lb/> between the ages of 18-40 years dealt with the ongoing pandemic using social<lb/> media 37 .<lb/></p>

			<p>61<lb/> It is only appropriate then that when many cities in India are suffering<lb/> through the second wave of the COVID-19 pandemic, many have turned to the<lb/> internet, using applications/websites to find critical support. On these platforms,<lb/> online communities led by members of the civil society and other individuals, have<lb/> assisted the needy in multiple ways -often by helping them procure oxygen,<lb/> essential drugs or find a hospital bed through their own networks or by amplifying<lb/> original requests, and even by offering moral and emotional support. However, it<lb/> is with deep distress that we note that individuals seeking help on such platforms<lb/> have been targeted, by alleging that the information posted by them is false and<lb/> has only been posted in social media to create panic, defame the administration<lb/> or damage the &quot;national image&quot;. We do not hesitate in saying that such targeting<lb/> shall not be condoned, and the Central Government and State Governments<lb/> should ensure that they immediately cease any direct or indirect threats of<lb/> prosecution and arrest to citizens who air grievances or those that are attempting<lb/> to help fellow citizens receive medical aid. If this does keep happening even after<lb/> the current order, this Court shall be constrained to use the powers available to it<lb/> under it contempt jurisdiction. We also direct that all Directors General of Police<lb/> shall ensure compliance down the ranks of the police forces within their<lb/> jurisdictions.<lb/></p>

			<p>62<lb/> In these trying times, those desperately seeking help for their loved ones<lb/> on these platforms should not have their misery compounded through the actions<lb/> of the State and its instrumentalities. Further, there are two more crucial reasons<lb/> why such a clampdown on information sharing must be absolutely stopped<lb/> immediately.<lb/></p>

			<p>63<lb/> The first reason is because sharing information widely is in itself an<lb/> important tool in combating public tragedies, like the current COVID-19 pandemic.<lb/> In K.S. Puttaswamy (Privacy-9J.) vs Union of India 38 , one of us (DY<lb/> Chandrachud, J) speaking for four Judges of a nine-Judge bench of this Court<lb/> noted academic literature documenting the widespread availability of information<lb/> and the resultant acknowledgement of the problem is what prevented the drought<lb/> in Maharashtra in 1973 from becoming as bad as the Bengal Famine of 1943,<lb/> where the British tried to deny the problem even existed. It was noted thus:<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot;267. Civil and political rights and socio-economic rights do<lb/> not exist in a state of antagonism. The conditions necessary<lb/> for realising or fulfilling socio-economic rights do not postulate<lb/> the subversion of political freedom. The reason for this is<lb/> simple. Socio-economic entitlements must yield true benefits<lb/> to those for whom they are intended. This can be achieved by<lb/> eliminating rent-seeking behaviour and by preventing the<lb/> capture of social welfare benefits by persons who are not<lb/> entitled to them. Capture of social welfare benefits can be<lb/> obviated only when political systems are transparent and<lb/> when there is a free flow of information. Opacity enures to the<lb/> benefit of those who monopolise scarce economic resources.<lb/> On the other hand, conditions where civil and political<lb/> freedoms flourish ensure that governmental policies are<lb/> subjected to critique and assessment. It is this scrutiny<lb/> which subserves the purpose of ensuring that socio-<lb/>economic<lb/> benefits<lb/> actually<lb/> permeate<lb/> to<lb/> the<lb/> underprivileged for whom they are meant. Conditions of<lb/> freedom and a vibrant assertion of civil and political<lb/> rights promote a constant review of the justness of<lb/> socio-economic programmes and of their effectiveness<lb/> in addressing deprivation and want. Scrutiny of public<lb/> affairs is founded upon the existence of freedom. Hence<lb/> civil and political rights and socio-economic rights are<lb/> complementary and not mutually exclusive.<lb/></item>

			<item>268. Some of these themes have been addressed in the<lb/> writings of the Nobel laureate, Amartya Sen. Sen compares<lb/> the response of many non-democratic regimes in critical<lb/> situations such as famine with the responses of democratic<lb/> societies in similar situations. [ Amartya Sen, Development as<lb/> Freedom (Oxford University Press, 2000) at pp. 178-79.]…<lb/></item>

			<p>269. In the Indian context, Sen points out that the Bengal<lb/> famine of 1943 &quot;was made viable not only by the lack of<lb/> democracy in colonial India but also by severe restrictions on<lb/> reporting and criticism imposed on the Indian press, and the<lb/> voluntary practice of &quot;silence&quot; on the famine that the British-<lb/>owned media chose to follow&quot; [ Amartya Sen, The Idea of<lb/> Justice (Penguin Books, 2009) at p. 339.] . Political liberties<lb/> and democratic rights are hence regarded as &quot;constituent<lb/> components&quot; of development. [Id, at p. 347] In contrast during<lb/> the drought which took place in Maharashtra in 1973, food<lb/> production failed drastically and the per capita food output<lb/> was half of that in sub-Saharan Africa. Yet there was no<lb/> famine in Maharashtra where five million people were<lb/> employed in rapidly organised public projects while there<lb/> were substantial famines in sub-Saharan Africa. This<lb/> establishes what he terms as &quot;the protective role of<lb/> democracy&quot;. Sen has analysed the issue succinctly:<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot;The causal connection between democracy and the non-<lb/>occurrence of famines is not hard to seek. Famines kill<lb/> millions of people in different countries in the world, but they<lb/> don&apos;t kill the rulers. The kings and the presidents, the<lb/> bureaucrats and the bosses, the military leaders and the<lb/> commanders never are famine victims. And if there are no<lb/> elections, no opposition parties, no scope for uncensored<lb/> public criticism, then those in authority don&apos;t have to suffer the<lb/> political consequences of their failure to prevent famines.<lb/> Democracy, on the other hand, would spread the penalty of<lb/> famines to the ruling groups and political leaders as well. This<lb/> gives them the political incentive to try to prevent any<lb/> threatening famine, and since famines are in fact easy to<lb/> prevent (the economic argument clicks into the political one at<lb/> this stage), the approaching famines are firmly prevented.&quot; [<lb/> Amartya Sen, Development as Freedom (Oxford University<lb/> Press, 2000) at p. 180.]...&quot;&quot;<lb/></item>

			<item>(emphasis supplied)<lb/></item>

			<p>As such, preventing clampdowns on sharing of information on online platforms is<lb/> not just in the interest of individuals sharing the information, but the larger<lb/> democratic structures of our nation. Without the ready availability of such<lb/> information, it is entirely possible that the COVID-19 pandemic may turn into a<lb/> tragedy worse than what it already is.<lb/></p>

			<p>64<lb/> The second reason is because sharing information widely will help in the<lb/> creation of a &quot;collective public memory&quot; of this pandemic. The presence of<lb/> collective public memory, which refers &quot;to an extant and taken-for-granted group<lb/> memory&quot; 39 , is important for the creation of knowledge of the problems plaguing us<lb/> today, so they may be passed on across time 40 . This is important since we do not<lb/> have to travel back too much in our past to realise that the pandemic caused by<lb/> the &quot;Spanish&quot; flu of 1918, which is said to have infected every third person in the<lb/> world and killed between 50-100 million individuals (compared to the 17 million<lb/> 39 Theodore O. Prosise, &quot;The collective memory of the atomic bombings misrecognized as objective history: The<lb/> case of the public opposition to the national air and space museum&apos;s atom bomb exhibit&quot;, (1998) 62 Western<lb/> Journal of Communication 3:316-347, pg 318<lb/> 40 Bryan Hubbard and Marouf A. Hasian, &quot;Atomic Memories of the &quot;Enola Gay&quot;: Strategies of Remembrance at<lb/> the National Air and Space Museum&quot; (1998) 1 Rhetoric and Public Affairs 3:363-385, pg 364<lb/> who died in World War I), has been almost entirely erased from our collective<lb/> public memory 41 . Therefore, the widespread sharing of information by individuals<lb/> living through the COVID-19 pandemic becomes crucial. Furthermore, the role of<lb/> Courts in creating and preserving this collective public memory cannot be<lb/> understated. Professors Austin Sarat and Thomas R. Kearns, in their book<lb/> History, Memory, and the Law, describe the function that is played by Courts in<lb/> the following terms 42 :<lb/></p>

			<p>&quot;Law in the modern era is, we believe, one of the most<lb/> important of our society&apos;s technologies for preserving<lb/> memory. Just as the use of precedent to legitimate legal<lb/> decisions fixes law in a particular relation to the past, memory<lb/> may be attached, or attach itself, to law and be preserved in<lb/> and through law. Where this is the case, it serves as one way<lb/> of orienting ourselves to the future. As Drucilla Cornell puts<lb/> it: &quot;Legal interpretation demands that we remember the<lb/> future.&quot; In that phrase, Cornell reminds us that there are,<lb/> in fact, two audiences for every legal act, the audience of<lb/> the present and the audience of the future. Law<lb/> materializes memory in documents, transcripts, written<lb/> opinions; it re-enacts the past, both intentionally and<lb/> unconsciously, and it is one place where the present<lb/> speaks to the future through acts of commemoration.<lb/> Because the litigated case creates a record, courts can<lb/> become archives in which that record serves as the<lb/> materialization of memory. Due process guarantees an<lb/> opportunity to be heard by, and an opportunity to speak<lb/> to, the future. It is the guarantee that legal institutions<lb/> can be turned into museums of unnecessary, unjust,<lb/> undeserved pain and death. The legal hearing provides<lb/> lawyers and litigants an opportunity to write and record<lb/> history by creating narratives of present injustices, and<lb/> to insist on memory in the face of denial. By recording<lb/> such history and constructing such narratives lawyers and<lb/> litigants call on an imagined future to choose Justice over the<lb/> &quot;jurispathic&quot; tendencies of the moment.&quot;<lb/></p>

			<p>(emphasis supplied)<lb/> Hence, in the present proceedings, we hope to not only initiate a dialogue so as<lb/> to better tackle the current COVID-19 pandemic but also to preserve its memory<lb/> in our public records, so that future generations may evaluate our efforts and<lb/> learn from them.<lb/></p>

			<p>65<lb/> We speak not only as members of this Court, but also as grateful citizens<lb/> of the country, and commend the outstanding work of our all healthcare<lb/> professionals (doctors, nurses, healthcare workers, laboratory technicians, ward<lb/> staff, ambulance drivers, crematorium workers etc.) during this crisis. They have<lb/> truly gone beyond their call of duty and toiled day in and day out, relentlessly<lb/> without rest amidst great challenges. It is absolutely necessary to take urgent<lb/> steps for their well-being to ensure that our appreciation for their tremendous<lb/> efforts is not reduced to rhetoric. This is especially important since another factor<lb/> which affects how collective public memory of any event is created is by the<lb/> rhetoric surrounding it 43 . As such, our public memory of this public event has to<lb/> transcend its conception as a &quot;war&quot; against the virus of COVID-19 itself, but rather<lb/> to remember that it is &quot;the complex epidemiological circumstances that promote<lb/> these outbreaks and the under-resourced health systems that are tasked with<lb/> disease containment&quot; 44 . While the healthcare professionals have been at the<lb/> forefront of tackling this crisis, we have to recognize their contribution as medical<lb/> healthcare professionals who have undertaken &quot;to protect public health using<lb/> proven scientific evidence and best practices and to serve to community at<lb/> large&quot; 45 , and not just as &quot;CORONA WARRIORS&quot;.<lb/></p>

			<p>66<lb/> We also do not hesitate to note that the treatment meted out to these public<lb/> healthcare professional during this COVID-19 pandemic has sometimes been<lb/> less than ideal. The following are some of the issues we wish to highlight:<lb/></p>

			<p>(i)<lb/> Recently, there were reports that the Pradhan Mantri Garib Kalyan<lb/> Package Insurance Scheme, an insurance scheme of Rs 50 lakhs which<lb/> had been extended to about 22 lakh healthcare professionals, was set to<lb/> expire on 24 March 2021 and would not be renewed. While we are happy<lb/> to note that UOI&quot;s affidavit of 23 April 2021 states that this Scheme has<lb/> been extended for one year starting April 2021, we have also been<lb/> informed that till date only 287 claims have been settled under it, which<lb/> includes claims from the families of 168 doctors who died after contracting<lb/> COVID-19 while treating patients. We direct the Central Government to<lb/> inform this Court as to how many claims are pending under the Scheme,<lb/> and the timeline within which the Central Government expects to settle<lb/> them;<lb/></p>

			<p>(ii)<lb/> Healthcare personnel are at an obvious heightened risk of contracting the<lb/> COVID-19 virus. However, we are aware of reports that indicate that<lb/> infected healthcare personnel are left to fend for themselves without<lb/> adequate availability of beds, oxygen or essential drugs. Further, some of<lb/> them have also often been asked to report back to duty within 10 days of<lb/> first testing positive for COVID-19 (provided they are asymptomatic), even<lb/> though a longer recuperation period is often recommended. While we are<lb/> dealing with a terrible second wave of the COVID-19 pandemic, there must<lb/> be an effective policy to ensure that the nation truly acknowledges their<lb/> effort and creates incentives for them. We hope it will be remedied soon by<lb/> the Central and State Governments through the introduction of appropriate<lb/> guidelines and measures;<lb/></p>

			<p>(iii)<lb/> It is unclear what measures are currently being taken to ensure that<lb/> healthcare personnel can continue to serve others while not risking the<lb/> health of their family members. We hope that the respective State<lb/> Governments, with necessary assistance from the Central Government,<lb/> can ensure this takes place; and<lb/> (iv) The Central Government should, we feel examine and ensure that in<lb/> addition to the schemes it has framed, other facilities such as availability of<lb/> food, resting facilities during intervals between work, transportation<lb/> facilities, non-deduction of salary or leave account, if afflicted by COVID<lb/> 2019 or related infection, overtime allowance, in both public and private<lb/> hospitals, and a separate helpline for doctors, and healthcare<lb/> professionals, in cases of COVID 2019 related emergencies, is provided.<lb/> All these, we feel, would show these professionals that we do not show our<lb/> appreciation in mere words, but also care for them.<lb/></p>

			<p>67<lb/> The issues mentioned above are only symptomatic of the other broader<lb/> issues that are being faced by healthcare professionals, who are instrumental in<lb/> combating the pandemic. Hence, we hope their welfare is considered seriously by<lb/> the Central and State Governments. Further, we would wish to use this order to<lb/> place on record our sincerest appreciation for all the public healthcare<lb/> professionals -not just limited to the doctors, but also nurses, hospital staff,<lb/> ambulance drivers, sanitation workers and crematorium workers. It is through<lb/> their dedicated efforts that the effect of COVID-19 pandemic is being currently<lb/> tackled in India.<lb/></p>

			<p>68<lb/> In light of the continuing surge of infections in the second wave of the<lb/> pandemic, we direct the Central Government and State Governments to put on<lb/> record the efforts taken to curb the spread of the virus and the measures that they<lb/> plan on taking in the near future. At the same time, we would seriously urge the<lb/> Central and State Governments to consider imposing a ban on mass gatherings<lb/> and super spreader events. They may also consider imposing a lockdown to curb<lb/> the virus in the second wave in the interest of public welfare. Having said that, we<lb/> are cognizant of the socio-economic impact of a lockdown, specifically, on the<lb/> marginalized communities. Thus, in case the measure of a lockdown is imposed,<lb/> arrangements must be made beforehand to cater to the needs of these<lb/> communities.<lb/></p>

			<p>J<lb/> Conclusion<lb/> 69<lb/> The present order has primarily considered the submissions (written and<lb/> oral) of the UOI. These submissions have been reproduced here as a matter of<lb/> public record and to contextualize the clarifications that are being sought by our<lb/> Court in order to serve its dialogic role. We reiterate, for abundant caution, that<lb/> the data and submissions reproduced above are not its endorsement or<lb/> acceptance. In terms of the above discussion, we hereby pass the following<lb/> directions:<lb/></p>

			<p>(i)<lb/> The UOI shall ensure, in terms of the assurance of the Solicitor General,<lb/> that the deficit in the supply of oxygen to the GNCTD is rectified within 2<lb/> days from the date of the hearing, that is, on or before the midnight of 3<lb/> May 2021;<lb/></p>

			<p>(ii)<lb/> The Central Government shall, in collaboration with the States, prepare a<lb/> buffer stock of oxygen for emergency purposes and decentralize the<lb/> location of the emergency stocks. The emergency stocks shall be created<lb/> within the next four days and is to be replenished on a day to day basis, in<lb/> addition to the existing allocation of oxygen supply to the States;<lb/></p>

			<p>(iii)<lb/> The Central Government and State Governments shall notify all Chief<lb/> Secretaries/Directors General of Police/Commissioners of Police that any<lb/> clampdown on information on social media or harassment caused to<lb/> individuals seeking/delivering help on any platform will attract a coercive<lb/> exercise of jurisdiction by this Court. The Registrar (Judicial) is also<lb/> directed to place a copy of this order before all District Magistrates in the<lb/> country;<lb/></p>

			<p>(iv) The Central Government shall, within two weeks, formulate a national<lb/> policy on admissions to hospitals which shall be followed by all State<lb/> Governments. Till the formulation of such a policy by the Central<lb/> Government, no patient shall be denied hospitalization or essential drugs<lb/> in any State/UT for lack of local residential proof of that State/UT or even in<lb/> the absence of identity proof;<lb/></p>

			<p>(v)<lb/> The Central Government shall revisit its initiatives and protocols, including<lb/> on the availability of oxygen, availability and pricing of vaccines, availability<lb/> of essential drugs at affordable prices and respond on all the other issues<lb/> highlighted in this order before the next date of the hearing, that is, 10 May<lb/> 2021. Copies of all affidavits to be served upon the Amici in advance; and<lb/> (vi) Several other suggestions have been made before this Court in IAs and<lb/> writ petitions filed by diverse parties. In order to streamline the further<lb/> course of hearing, we have requested the Amici to collate and compile<lb/> these suggestions which would be taken up later. The present order has<lb/> focused on certain critical issues in view of the urgency of the situation.<lb/></p>

			<p>……….….....................................................J.<lb/> [Dr Dhananjaya Y Chandrachud]<lb/> ……..….….....................................................J.<lb/> [L Nageswara Rao]<lb/> ……..….….....................................................J.<lb/> [S Ravindra Bhat]<lb/> New Delhi;<lb/> April 30, 2021</p>


	</text>
</tei>
