<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc xml:id="0" />
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <p>
            1. This instant batch of writ petitions assailing the impugned
            <lb />
            demand notices issued under Rules 11(2) and 11(4) of the Meghalaya Mineral
            <lb />
            Cess Rules, 1989, being similar and identical in facts and circumstances, are
            <lb />
            proposed to be disposed of by this common judgment and order.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            2.
            <lb />
            All the writ petitioners are holders of valid mining leases under
            <lb />
            the provisions of the Meghalaya Minor Mineral Concession Rules, 2016
            <lb />
            framed under Section 15 of the Mines and Minerals (Development and
            <lb />
            Regulation) Act, 1957. The writ petitioners produce and extract limestone for
            <lb />
            the manufacturing of lime and for raw limestone export to Bangladesh by
            <lb />
            paying the requisite royalty amount, reclamation fee as well as GST.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            3.
            <lb />
            The grievance of the petitioners is that the impugned demand
            <lb />
            notices had been served upon them, directing the submission of returns as per
            <lb />
            the rules, and also for payment of arrear cess charged under the Meghalaya
            <lb />
            Mineral Cess Rules, 1989 within a period of 60 days, from the date of the
            <lb />
            impugned demand notice. The grievance of the writ petitioners, is based on
            <lb />
            the pleading that the impugned demand notices, can never be construed as a
            <lb />
            statutory notice issued under Rule 11(2) in &apos;Form H&apos;, and that further, the tax
            <lb />
            liability period for filing of returns and the date for submission of the same
            <lb />
            under Rule 5, are completely absent in the impugned demand notices, which
            <lb />
            have been issued under the provisions of Meghalaya Mineral Cess Rules,
            <lb />
            1989. Further grievance is that the Director (Respondent No. 3) has already
            <lb />
            pre-determined the arrear cess payable, while at the same time directing the
            <lb />
            petitioners to submit the returns, which they assert, is in violation of the
            <lb />
            statutory requirements. As such, the writ petitioners are before this Court by
            <lb />
            way of these writ petitions.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            4.
            <lb />
            Before embarking upon the discussion on the matter, it is
            <lb />
            important to note that the writ petitions are in a manner, a continuation of an
            <lb />
            on-going dispute wherein the vires of the Meghalaya Mineral Cess Act, 1989
            <lb />
            has been put to challenge by an Association under the name of Limestone and
            <lb />
            Boulder Stone Miners Cum Exporters Forum, in WP(C) No. 454 of 2019, of
            <lb />
            which the writ petitioners are also members. A Misc. application in the writ
            <lb />
            petition being Misc. Case No. 244 of 2019, is also pending adjudication,
            <lb />
            wherein directions have been sought to command the respondents not to insist
            <lb />
            on the payment of cess retrospectively, pending the decision in WP(C) No.
            <lb />
            454 of 2019. Though, undoubtedly connected, the present writ petitions
            <lb />
            specifically assail only the demand notices, and as such the disposal of the
            <lb />
            instant writ petitions pending the adjudication of the challenge to the vires of
            <lb />
            the Act, will not impact, or be considered to have any bearing on WP(C) No.
            <lb />
            454 of 2019.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            5.
            <lb />
            Heard learned counsel for the parties.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            6.
            <lb />
            Mr. H.L. Shangreiso, learned counsel for the petitioners submits
            <lb />
            that the impugned demand notices assailed in these writ petitions, have been
            <lb />
            issued under Rule 11 (4) of the Meghalaya Mineral Cess Rules, 1989
            <lb />
            (hereinafter referred to as MMC Rules, 1989) quantifying the quantity of
            <lb />
            minerals, cess liability period and arrears of cess in &apos;Form J&apos;, after a unilateral
            <lb />
            assessment made by the Respondent No. 3 (Director) under Rule 11 (4)
            <lb />
            without issuing notice under Rule 11 (2) for filing of monthly returns, within
            <lb />
            30 days as provided in the MMC Rules, 1989. Learned counsel also contends
            <lb />
            that the respondent No. 3 by not adhering to the provisions of the Rules, has
            <lb />
            also violated the principles of natural justice and hence the impugned action
            <lb />
            and notices are unsustainable in law.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            7.
            <lb />
            Learned counsel submits that the impugned demand notice can
            <lb />
            never be construed as a valid statutory notice issued under Rule 11(2) in
            <lb />
            &apos;Form H&apos;, inasmuch as, the requirement on the issuance of the notice under
            <lb />
            Rule 11(2) is for submission of the returns under Rule 5 in &apos;Form A&apos;, a fact
            <lb />
            which he contends is absent in the demand notice. Learned counsel submits
            <lb />
            that a proper notice under Rule 11 (2) was not issued for the simple reason,
            <lb />
            that the respondent No. 3 had already determined the arrear cess payable,
            <lb />
            which is mentioned in the second page of the impugned demand notice. He
            <lb />
            submits therefore the statutory requirement of a notice under Rule 11(2) not
            <lb />
            having been met, the impugned demand notices are not sustainable in law.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            8.
            <lb />
            The learned counsel then submits that Rule 11(2) and Rule 11(4)
            <lb />
            are two distinct Rules with different objectives/purposes, which prescribes
            <lb />
            different procedures and powers. The assessing authority i.e. the Director he
            <lb />
            submits, exercises quasi-judicial functions, and is bound to adhere to the
            <lb />
            procedure as prescribed. He submits that these two Rules lay down two
            <lb />
            distinct jurisdictions under which the Director is to act and also states the
            <lb />
            remedy and compliance necessary on the part of the assesse miner or
            <lb />
            exporter. He contends that the issuance of the impugned demand notices,
            <lb />
            under the two provisions i.e. under Rule 11(2) and (4) in a form of a
            <lb />
            composite notice, is misconceived and against the statutory mandate of the
            <lb />
            MMC Act and Rules.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            9.
            <lb />
            Learned counsel while dwelling on this point, submits that had a
            <lb />
            proper notice been issued under Rule 11(2) and also opportunity given to file
            <lb />
            the returns, the amount assessed by the Director, as shown the demand notice
            <lb />
            purportedly under Rule 11(4) could not have been arrived at, inasmuch as,
            <lb />
            merely purchase of the challans in advance, does not automatically incur tax
            <lb />
            liability, unless the mineral is extracted or removed from the mines under
            <lb />
            Section 3 of the MMC Act, 1989. He further submits that had proper statutory
            <lb />
            notice under Rule 11(2) been issued upon the petitioners, they could have
            <lb />
            produced the records and materials to show the exact quantity of minerals
            <lb />
            extracted and removed from the mines commencing from the tax liability
            <lb />
            period, less the amount of cess already paid under protest. It is also contended
            <lb />
            that the mining lease executed by the parties and the State of Meghalaya
            <lb />
            under the Meghalaya Mineral Concession Rules, 2016 does not mention the
            <lb />
            fact they were liable to pay cess and further since the commencement of the
            <lb />
            operation they were never called upon to produce the transit or dispatch
            <lb />
            challan wherein the payment of cess was indicated. Learned counsel submits
            <lb />
            that the failure to submit the monthly returns owing to their ignorance, though
            <lb />
            ignorance of law is not an excuse, however cannot automatically allow the
            <lb />
            Director to avoid compliance of Rule 11(2) and instead issue a composite
            <lb />
            demand notice under Rule 11(4) for payment of the arrear cess amounts.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            10.
            <lb />
            Learned counsel in support of his arguments has placed reliance
            <lb />
            in the case of S.K. Bhargava vs. Collector, Chandigarh &amp; Ors. reported in
            <lb />
            (1998) 5 SCC 170, wherein it has been held that the principles of natural
            <lb />
            justice were not complied with, in the determination of sums due from the
            <lb />
            defaulter in the context of the Haryana Public Moneys (Recovery of Dues)
            <lb />
            Act, 1979, as no opportunity was afforded to the alleged defaulter to dispute
            <lb />
            the said sum, and that though there was no express provision for opportunity
            <lb />
            being given, the principles of natural justice must be read into it.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            11.
            <lb />
            Reliance has also been placed on the judgment dated 3 rd April,
            <lb />
            2020 of the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court in Civil Appeal No. 1008 of 2020 in the
            <lb />
            case of New Delhi Television Ltd. vs. Deputy Commissioner of Income Tax
            <lb />
            wherein it has been held that the manner of notice, and reasons given did not
            <lb />
            conform to the principles of natural justice and the assesse did not get a proper
            <lb />
            and adequate opportunity to reply to the allegations which were then being
            <lb />
            relied upon by the revenue authorities. The learned counsel has also cited the
            <lb />
            case of Sukhdev Singh &amp; Ors. vs. Bhagatram Sardar Singh Raghuvanshi
            <lb />
            &amp; Anr. reported in AIR 1975 SC 1331, to buttress his submissions of the duty
            <lb />
            to comply with the principles of natural justice and rules, whenever a man&apos;s
            <lb />
            rights are affected by a decision taken in exercise of statutory powers.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            12.
            <lb />
            In concluding his submissions, the learned counsel submits that
            <lb />
            the principles of waiver, acquiescence and estoppel as well as laches of delay
            <lb />
            come in the way of the respondents to claim the arrears in cess as non-
            <lb />
            submission of monthly returns creates a fresh cause of action. It is also prayed
            <lb />
            that the writ petitioners be given liberty to approach the respondents and
            <lb />
            allow them to raise their contentions on the assessment before any action is
            <lb />
            taken by them for recovery of the alleged arrears in cess. Lastly, it is
            <lb />
            submitted that the impugned notices being bad in law be set aside and
            <lb />
            quashed.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            13.
            <lb />
            In reply to the submissions made by the petitioners, Mr. A.
            <lb />
            Kumar, learned Advocate General, submits at the outset, that the writ
            <lb />
            petitions are liable to be dismissed on the ground of concealment of material
            <lb />
            facts, inasmuch as, the writ petitioners have simply disclosed information
            <lb />
            about the pending writ petition i.e. WP(C) No. 454 of 2019, without
            <lb />
            disclosing that at least two of the prayers are identical to the instant writ
            <lb />
            petitions, and further that the prayer in Misc. Application No. 244 of 2019 in
            <lb />
            the pending writ petition, is similar to the prayer made in the Misc.
            <lb />
            applications of the instant writ petitions. Learned Advocate General also
            <lb />
            submits, that second concealment is towards non-disclosure of the fact that
            <lb />
            this Court in a Coordinate Bench did not grant any interim relief even though
            <lb />
            the case was listed on numerous occasions. To substantiate his submissions,
            <lb />
            the learned counsel has made a chart in tabular form, which is reproduced
            <lb />
            herein below:
            <lb />
        </p>

        <table>
            Table showing identical reliefs claimed by the Petitioner
            <lb />
            Prayer in W.P. 454 of 2019 Prayer in M.C. No.244 of
            <lb />
            2019 in W.P. (C) No.454 of
            <lb />
            2019
            <lb />
            Prayer in W.P. No.112 of
            <lb />
            2020
            <lb />
            1. To withdraw, recall and
            <lb />
            otherwise forbear from
            <lb />
            giving
            <lb />
            effect
            <lb />
            to
            <lb />
            the
            <lb />
            Meghalaya Mineral Cess
            <lb />
            Act, 1988 after adjudging the
            <lb />
            same as ultra-vires the
            <lb />
            Constitution.
            <lb />
            1. The Respondent Forest
            <lb />
            Department to release the
            <lb />
            challan to the members of
            <lb />
            the
            <lb />
            Applicants/Writ
            <lb />
            Petitioners on payment of
            <lb />
            requisite fee to mine and
            <lb />
            transport
            <lb />
            the
            <lb />
            minor
            <lb />
            limestone as the existing
            <lb />
            mining lease agreement.
            <lb />
            1. Set aside and quash the
            <lb />
            impugned demand notice
            <lb />
            dated 11.2.2020(Annexure-
            <lb />
            9) issued by Director,
            <lb />
            Mineral Resource, Govt. of
            <lb />
            Meghalaya;
            <lb />
            2. Direct the Respondent
            <lb />
            State not to insist the writ
            <lb />
            petitioner
            <lb />
            to
            <lb />
            submit
            <lb />
            monthly return in &apos;Form-
            <lb />
            A&apos; under Rule 5 of MMC
            <lb />
            Rules, 1989 for payment of
            <lb />
            Cess.
            <lb />
            2. Direct the Respondent
            <lb />
            State to refund the collected
            <lb />
            cess to the members of the
            <lb />
            writ petitioner, including
            <lb />
            the writ petitioner no.2, at
            <lb />
            least with effect the date of
            <lb />
            filing the writ of (sic) their
            <lb />
            first representation dated 16th
            <lb />
            June, 2019.
            <lb />
            3. ……….
            <lb />
            4. ……..
            <lb />
            2. Allow the members of the
            <lb />
            applicants/writ petitioners
            <lb />
            to pay the current cess and
            <lb />
            District
            <lb />
            Mineral
            <lb />
            Foundation under protest
            <lb />
            by directing the State
            <lb />
            Respondent to refund the
            <lb />
            same depending on the
            <lb />
            final outcome of the writ
            <lb />
            petition.
            <lb />
            3. Direct the Respondent
            <lb />
            State to refund the current
            <lb />
            cess and DMF paid by the
            <lb />
            writ petitioner under
            <lb />
            protest
            <lb />
            during
            <lb />
            the
            <lb />
            pendency of connected
            <lb />
            W.P.(C) No.454 of 2019.
            <lb />
            3. The respondent state not be
            <lb />
            insist on the members of the
            <lb />
            applicants/writ petitioners to
            <lb />
            pay the cess retrospectively
            <lb />
            until the constitutionality of
            <lb />
            the impugned Meghalaya
            <lb />
            Mineral Act, 1988 as well as
            <lb />
            the
            <lb />
            Mine
            <lb />
            and
            <lb />
            Mineral
            <lb />
            Development
            <lb />
            Regulation
            <lb />
            (Amendment) Act, 2015 are
            <lb />
            finally adjudicated by this
            <lb />
            Hon&apos;ble Court in the pending
            <lb />
            writ petition.
            <lb />
        </table>

        <p>
            14.
            <lb />
            The learned Advocate General submits that the conduct of the
            <lb />
            petitioners, disentitles them from receiving any equitable relief under the
            <lb />
            extraordinary writ jurisdiction of this Court, as relief to be granted in writ
            <lb />
            jurisdiction is a matter of discretion and equity. He submits that the
            <lb />
            petitioners by not filing returns, are in gross violation of the MMC, Act and
            <lb />
            Rules 1989, since the commencement of production of limestone on
            <lb />
            23.01.2019. In support of his submissions, the learned Advocate General has
            <lb />
            placed reliance in the case of Udyami Evam Khad Gramodyog Welfare
            <lb />
            Sanstha &amp; Anr. vs. State of Uttar Pradesh &amp; Ors. reported in (2008) 1 SCC
            <lb />
            560, K.D. Sharma vs. Steel Authority of India Limited &amp; Ors. reported in
            <lb />
            (2008) 12 SCC and in the case of M. Lilly vs. The District Collector,
            <lb />
            Tiruvallur District, Tiruvallur W.A. No. 367 of 2017 (2017 SCC Online
            <lb />
            Mad 31311). The aforesaid judgments he urges, are all on the subject of writ
            <lb />
            remedy being an equitable one, and persons seeking relief should not
            <lb />
            suppress any material of facts and should come with clean hands before the
            <lb />
            Court.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            15.
            <lb />
            The learned Advocate General then submits that the fact that the
            <lb />
            vires of a law has been challenged, will not make that law cease to exist, and
            <lb />
            it continues to operate, till such time orders are passed to the contrary and it
            <lb />
            is set aside. The learned counsel submits that the writ petitioners therefore,
            <lb />
            cannot take the plea that they are not liable to pay cess on account of the
            <lb />
            challenge to the constitutional validity of the Meghalaya Mineral Cess Act,
            <lb />
            1988 and the Rules of 1989 made thereunder. In this regard, on the principles
            <lb />
            of the constitutionality of enactments, the learned counsel has placed reliance
            <lb />
            on the following judgments, People&apos;s Union for Civil Liberties &amp; Anr. vs.
            <lb />
            Union of India &amp; Ors. reported in (2004) 2 SCC 476 and Natural Resources
            <lb />
            Allocation, In Re, Special Reference No. 1 of 2012 reported in (2012) 10
            <lb />
            SCC 1. Learned counsel further submits that no direction can be sought
            <lb />
            contrary to prevailing Acts and Rules, as has been made by the writ
            <lb />
            petitioners, who have prayed for directions to command the State respondents
            <lb />
            to not make a demand, which is in violation of the statutory provision as laid
            <lb />
            down. To support his contentions, the learned counsel has relied on the
            <lb />
            following decisions; Maharshi Dayanand University vs. Surjeet Kaur
            <lb />
            reported in (2010) 11 SCC 159, State of Punjab &amp; Ors. vs. Renuka Singla
            <lb />
            &amp; Ors. reported in (1994) 1 SCC175 and Karnataka State Road Transport
            <lb />
            Corporation vs. Ashrafulla Khan &amp; Ors. reported in (2002) 2 SCC 560.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            16.
            <lb />
            Rebutting the submissions of the writ petitioners on the plea of
            <lb />
            ignorance of law, the learned Advocate General submits, that it is incorrect
            <lb />
            on the part of the writ petitioners to contend that they were not aware of their
            <lb />
            liability to pay cess under the MMC Act, 1988, and points out that the writ
            <lb />
            petitioners themselves have stated in their writ petitions, about their
            <lb />
            representation submitted to the Chief Minister, wherein they have expressed
            <lb />
            their inability to pay the cess. The learned counsel submits that the writ
            <lb />
            petitioners had complete knowledge of their liability, and it is in this context,
            <lb />
            that they have paid cess amounts on the periods commencing from
            <lb />
            31.01.2020, except for the writ petitioner in WP(C) No. 115 of 2020 who has
            <lb />
            not annexed any challan showing payment but has stated to have paid the
            <lb />
            same in para 16 of his writ petition, and as such the ground of ignorance as
            <lb />
            pleaded by the petitioners on the liability cannot be accepted. The learned
            <lb />
            counsel has cited the decision in the case of The Swadeshi Cotton Mills Co.
            <lb />
            Ltd. vs. The Government of U.P. &amp; Ors. reported in (1975) 4 SCC 378
            <lb />
            wherein it has been held that ignorance of law is no excuse. Reliance has also
            <lb />
            been placed in the case of State of A.P. &amp; Ors. vs. Twin City Jewellers Assn.
            <lb />
            &amp; Ors. reported in (2005) 13 SCC 552on this point.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            17.
            <lb />
            On the question, as to whether the composite nature of notices
            <lb />
            violated the procedure prescribed by the MMC Act, 1989, and whether there
            <lb />
            was any violation of the principles of natural justice, the learned Advocate
            <lb />
            General contends that the notice required the petitioner to file returns in
            <lb />
            &apos;Form A&apos; and the requirement of show cause format mentioned in &apos;Form H&apos;,
            <lb />
            is only limited to filing of returns. Learned counsel submits that the notice
            <lb />
            refers to the period, and the quantity is also mentioned therein, and as such
            <lb />
            the requirement of &apos;Form H&apos; has been fulfilled, and contends that the non-
            <lb />
            mentioning of the term &apos;Form H&apos; in the notice, will not vitiate the notice in
            <lb />
            any manner. Learned counsel contends that the knowledge of the contents of
            <lb />
            the notice is the requirement of law, and as such, the writ petitioners cannot
            <lb />
            plead that they have no knowledge of the period or their liability. He then
            <lb />
            further submits that the demand notices to all the writ petitioners were issued
            <lb />
            between 11.02.2020 to 27.02.2020, and it was only after a period of about a
            <lb />
            month, that the writ petitioners have approached this Court. He submits that
            <lb />
            this clearly illustrates the fact that the writ petitioners did not comply with
            <lb />
            the requirement of filing the returns in &apos;Form A&apos; as per the Rules of 1989,
            <lb />
            which as per Rule 11(2) requires that the returns be filed within a period of
            <lb />
            one month, which in turn made them liable to be proceeded under Rule 11
            <lb />
            (4) after the lapse of one month. Learned counsel contends that therefore in
            <lb />
            this backdrop, there has been no violation of the principles of natural justice.
            <lb />
            It is also argued by the learned counsel, that in fact and substance, the only
            <lb />
            ground assigned towards the non-payment of cess by the writ petitioners, is
            <lb />
            the pendency of WP(C) No. 454 of 2019 which he submits is untenable in
            <lb />
            law. He also submits that the application and receipt of transport challans for
            <lb />
            a specified quantity of minerals, extracted by the writ petitioners, positively
            <lb />
            indicates the quantity of production of minerals by the petitioners.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            18.
            <lb />
            The learned Advocate General has also drawn to the attention of
            <lb />
            this Court to the fact that the cess which is being collected, is in public
            <lb />
            interest, with 80% of the collection earmarked for primary education and 20%
            <lb />
            for development of mining regions, and that the non-payment of the cess by
            <lb />
            the petitioners, amounts to an evasion of social responsibility on their part.
            <lb />
            He further submits that the principles of taxation and requirement of notice
            <lb />
            as held by the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court, cannot be invalidated for mere non-
            <lb />
            adherence to procedural formality. Learned counsel in this context has placed
            <lb />
            reliance on the case of Dharampal Satyapal Limited vs. Deputy
            <lb />
            Commissioner of Central Excise, Gauhati &amp; Ors. reported in (2015) 8 SCC
            <lb />
            519 , MC Mehta vs. Union of India &amp; Ors. reported in (1999) 6 SCC 237
            <lb />
            and The Chairman Board of Mining Examination and Chief Inspector of
            <lb />
            Mines, &amp; Anr. reported in (1977) 2 SCC 256.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            19.
            <lb />
            The learned Advocate General in conclusion reiterates his
            <lb />
            submissions that there is no patent infirmity in the proceedings, and the
            <lb />
            issuance of the impugned notices and the process in question, is not vitiated
            <lb />
            in any manner, so as to render it arbitrary or considered to be in blatant
            <lb />
            violation of statutory rules. He submits that the petitioners being well aware
            <lb />
            of their liabilities, cannot escape the same by resorting to repeated writ
            <lb />
            petitions. He therefore, prays that the writ petitions be dismissed.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            20.
            <lb />
            Having heard learned counsels for the parties, and in
            <lb />
            consideration of all the arguments advanced and the connected materials
            <lb />
            placed before the Court, it is seen that the prayers of the writ petitioners is for
            <lb />
            quashing of the demand notices, not to insist on filing of monthly returns in
            <lb />
            &apos;Form A&apos; under Rule 5 of the Meghalaya Mineral Cess Rules, 1989 and for
            <lb />
            refund of current cess and District Mineral Foundation Fund (DMF) paid
            <lb />
            under protest during the pendency of WP(C) No. 454 of 2019 (wherein the
            <lb />
            vires of the Cess Act has been challenged). The petitioners have assailed the
            <lb />
            impugned notices, contending that the same are in violation of the Rules,
            <lb />
            1989, apart from the fact that the challenge to the validity of the Cess Act,
            <lb />
            1988, is pending adjudication.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            21.
            <lb />
            In this context, before coming to a final appreciation of the matter
            <lb />
            at hand, it would be apposite for the purposes of the instant case, to quote
            <lb />
            hereunder, the relevant sections and Forms of the Meghalaya Minerals Cess
            <lb />
            Rules, 1989 :-
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;MEGHALAYA MINERAL CESS RULES, 1989*
            <lb />
            CHAPTER I
            <lb />
            Preliminary
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            5.
            <lb />
            Submission of monthly returns. (1) Every lessee and every person
            <lb />
            referred to in sub-R. (2) of R. 4 shall submit in duplicate the monthly returns
            <lb />
            in Form &apos;A&apos; or Form &apos;B&apos;, as the case may be, to the Director so as to reach
            <lb />
            him on or before the fifteenth day of the month following the month to
            <lb />
            which the returns pertain:
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            Provided that the Director may permit any person referred to in sub-
            <lb />
            R. (2) of R. 4 to submit the returns in Form &apos;B&apos; for a consolidated period
            <lb />
            not exceeding twelve months. The consolidated returns shall reach the
            <lb />
            Director not later than the last day of the month following the period to
            <lb />
            which the returns pertain.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (2) In case no mineral is removed during the month or period, &apos;nil&apos;
            <lb />
            returns shall be submitted accompanied by a duly signed certificate to that
            <lb />
            effect within the time prescribed in this rule.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            11. Final assessment of the cess payable. (1)………..… ……………….
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (2) If the Director is not satisfied with the returns submitted under R.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            5 or if no returns are submitted he shall issue a notice in Form &apos;H&apos; requiring
            <lb />
            the lessee or the other person referred under sub-R. (2) of R. 4 to submit the
            <lb />
            returns or revised returns required in Form &apos;A&apos; or, as the case may be, Form
            <lb />
            &apos;B&apos; within a period of thirty days from the date of issue of the notice.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (3)…………………………
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (4) If no returns are submitted within the time specified in the notice
            <lb />
            issued under sub-R. (2) the Director shall assess the amount of cess due and
            <lb />
            payable to Government on the basis of records or other information
            <lb />
            available to him and intimate the lessee or the other person referred to in
            <lb />
            sub-R. (2) of R. 4 in Form &apos;J&apos; for payment of the sum within a period of
            <lb />
            sixty days from the date of issue of the notice.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            FORM H
            <lb />
            [See (Rule 11 (2)]
            <lb />
            Notice to the lessee or person referred to in sub-R. (2) of R. 4
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            To,
            <lb />
            …
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            …
            <lb />
            …
            <lb />
            …
            <lb />
            …
            <lb />
            …
            <lb />
            …
            <lb />
            …
            <lb />
            …
            <lb />
            …
            <lb />
            Whereas I am not satisfied with the Returns submitted by you in Form
            <lb />
            &apos;A&apos;/&apos;B&apos; of the Meghalaya Mineral Cess Rules, 1989 vide letter No…… dated
            <lb />
            .. .. .. .. in respect of …. .. … (name of the mining lease in case of leases)
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            for… .. ……. (minerals) for the period ending…
            <lb />
            …
            <lb />
            …
            <lb />
            …;
            <lb />
            You are hereby directed to submit revised returns in Form &apos;A&apos;/&apos;B&apos; for the
            <lb />
            period ending …….. …. ….. on or before ..
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            ..
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            ..
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            ..
            <lb />
            OR
            <lb />
            Whereas you have not submitted any returns in Form &apos;A&apos;/Form &apos;B&apos;
            <lb />
            as required under R. 5 of the Meghalaya Mineral Cess Rules, 1989 for …
            <lb />
            …
            <lb />
            …
            <lb />
            … (minerals) for the period ending…
            <lb />
            .. …. …
            <lb />
            …; you are hereby directed to submit the required returns on or
            <lb />
            before …… ..
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            ..
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            ..
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            ..
            <lb />
            In the event of your failure to comply with this notice I shall proceed
            <lb />
            to assess the amount of cess due and payable by you from records in my
            <lb />
            possession without further reference to you.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            Seal of the Director
            <lb />
            No. …
            <lb />
            …
            <lb />
            …
            <lb />
            Date …
            <lb />
            …
            <lb />
            …
            <lb />
            Director
            <lb />
            Place …
            <lb />
            …
            <lb />
            …
            <lb />
            FORM J
            <lb />
            [See Rule 11 (4)]
            <lb />
            Demand notice
            <lb />
            To,
            <lb />
            ..
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            ..
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            ..
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            ..
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            ..
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            ..
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            ..
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            ..
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            ..
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            ..
            <lb />
            Whereas no returns as required under R. 5 read with R. 11 (2) of the
            <lb />
            Meghalaya Mineral Cess Rules, 1989 have been submitted by you in respect
            <lb />
            of… … …
            <lb />
            …(name of mining lease in case of lessee) for……
            <lb />
            …
            <lb />
            …
            <lb />
            …,(minerals) for the month(s)/period… … …, I have,
            <lb />
            from records and other information available with me, assessed the amount
            <lb />
            of cess due and payable by you as detailed below not later than..
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            ..
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            .. ..failing which the amount will be recoverable from you as arrear
            <lb />
            of land revenue.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (a) Quantity of.. ..
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            ..
            <lb />
            ..(minerals) ....
            <lb />
            .. … …. … ……
            <lb />
            M. tonnes.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (b)Amount of cess due and payable
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            …. .… …per M.T.Rs…
            <lb />
            …… ………. ….. …… …..
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (c) Deduct amount already paid by you Rs…
            <lb />
            …
            <lb />
            ...
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            …..
            <lb />
            vide Treasury Receipt No.. ..
            <lb />
            ..dated..
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            ..
            <lb />
            ..
            <lb />
            ……
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (d)Net amount due and payable Rs…..
            <lb />
            …
            <lb />
            …
            <lb />
            …
            <lb />
            …….
            <lb />
            Seal of the Director
            <lb />
            No… …
            <lb />
            …
            <lb />
            …
            <lb />
            Date …
            <lb />
            …
            <lb />
            …
            <lb />
            Director
            <lb />
            Place …
            <lb />
            …
            <lb />
            …&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            22.
            <lb />
            The scheme of the Rules as can be discerned from above, is that
            <lb />
            it stipulates firstly, in Rule 5 the submission of monthly returns by a lessee or
            <lb />
            persons, referred to in Rule 4(2), who are to maintain a register to record the
            <lb />
            quantities of minerals removed. On non-filing of returns, recourse is to be
            <lb />
            taken to Rule 11(2) wherein the Director is enjoined, to issue notice in &apos;Form
            <lb />
            H&apos; requiring the lessee to submit the returns within a 30-day period. Rule
            <lb />
            11(4) comes into play, in the event no returns are submitted within the time
            <lb />
            specified, and the power then lies with the Director to assess the amount of
            <lb />
            cess payable on the basis of records, or other information available and
            <lb />
            intimate the lessee or other persons in &apos;Form J&apos;, for payment of the assessed
            <lb />
            sum within a period of 60 days. Thereafter, on still no payment being made,
            <lb />
            the provisions of Section 7 of the parent Act of 1988, will be applicable,
            <lb />
            which for convenience is quoted herein below:
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;Penalty for non-7
            <lb />
            payment of tax
            <lb />
            If any tax payable under this Act is not paid
            <lb />
            within such period as may be prescribed it shall
            <lb />
            be deemed to be in arrears and the authority
            <lb />
            prescribed in this behalf may impose on the
            <lb />
            person extracting or removing the minerals a
            <lb />
            penalty not exceeding the amount of tax in
            <lb />
            arrears;
        </item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            Provided that before imposing the penalty
            <lb />
            such person shall be given an opportunity of
            <lb />
            being heard and if the said authority is satisfied
            <lb />
            that the default was for good and sufficient
            <lb />
            reason, no penalty shall be imposed under this
            <lb />
            section.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            23.
            <lb />
            As noted earlier, this Court will confine itself only to the legality
            <lb />
            of the impugned notices, as to whether the procedure adopted in the manner
            <lb />
            of their issuance and their contents thereof, can be said to be in violation of
            <lb />
            statutory requirements and also the principles of natural justice. The
            <lb />
            composite notices under Rule 11(2) and (4) as served upon the petitioners, in
            <lb />
            this case WP(C) No. 112 of 2020 is reproduced herein under:-
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            &quot;GOVERNMENT OF MEGHALAYA
            <lb />
            DIRECTORATE OF MINERAL RESOURCES
            <lb />
            SHILLONG.
            <lb />
            No. DMR/R/3170/2020/4
            <lb />
            Dated Shillong, the 11.02.2020
        </p>
        <lb />
        <p>
            To,
            <lb />
            Shri. Marbat Dohkrut,
            <lb />
            Ri-Kaleng, Sohbar,
            <lb />
            East Khasi Hills
        </p>
        <lb />
        <p>
            Sub: Demand Notice</p>
        <lb />
        <p>
            Sir,
            <lb />
            Whereas no returns as required under Rule 5 read with Rule 11(2) of
            <lb />
            the Meghalaya Mineral Cess Rule (MMCR), 1989, have been submitted by
            <lb />
            you, Demand Notice in Form &quot;J&quot; of MMCR, 1989 along with the due
            <lb />
            statement for necessary payment is enclosed herewith for necessary
            <lb />
            compliance. You are also directed to furnish monthly return in Form &quot;A&quot;
            <lb />
            of the aforesaid Rule (copy enclosed).
        </p>
        <lb />
        <p>
            Enclo: As above
            <lb />
            Yours faithfully,
            <lb />
            (Arunkumar Kembhavi, IAS)
            <lb />
            Director of Mineral Resources
            <lb />
            Meghalaya ::: Shillong.
            <lb />
            Memo. No.DMR/R/3170/2020/4-A.
            <lb />
            Dated Shillong, the 11.02.2020
            <lb />
            Copy to:-
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            The Divisional Forest Officer, East Khasi Hills &amp;Ri-Bhoi (T) Division,
            <lb />
            Shillong.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            Director of Mineral Resources
            <lb />
            Meghalaya ::: Shillong.
            <lb />
            FORM &apos;J&apos;
            <lb />
            [See rule 11 (4)]
            <lb />
            DEMAND NOTICE
            <lb />
            To
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            Shri. Marbat Dohkrut,
            <lb />
            Ri-Kaleng, Sohbar,
            <lb />
            East Khasi Hills
        </p>
        <lb />
        <p>
            Whereas no returns as required under rule 5 read with rule 11 (2) of
            <lb />
            the Meghalaya Minerals Cess Rules, 1980 have been submitted by you in
            <lb />
            respect of Shri. Marbat Dohkrut, Ri-Kaleng, Sohbar, East Khasi Hills for
            <lb />
            Limestone for the month/ period from 28.01.2019 till date. I have from
            <lb />
            records and other information available with me, assessed the amount of
            <lb />
            cess due and payable by you as detailed below not later than 60 (sixty) days
            <lb />
            from the date of issue of this office failing which the amount will be
            <lb />
            recoverable from you as arrear of land revenue.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            (a) Quantity of Limestone: 53100M.T.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            (b) Amount of cess due and payable 60/-per M.T. Rs 3186000/-
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            (c) Deduct amount already paid by Rs. Nil you vide treasury receipt No. Nil
            <lb />
            dated Nil
            <lb />
            (d) Net amount due and payable Rs. Nil
            <lb />
            Seal of the Director
            <lb />
            Number _______________________
            <lb />
            Date __________________________
            <lb />
            Director
            <lb />
            Place _________________________&quot;
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            24.
            <lb />
            A perusal of the above quoted impugned notices reflect that on
            <lb />
            the same day itself, a composite notice both under Rule 11(2) and 11 (4) was
            <lb />
            issued. The contents in the first part, read that the petitioners have been
            <lb />
            directed to make the payment as per the demand notice in &apos;Form J&apos;, while at
            <lb />
            the same time asked to furnish monthly returns as per &apos;Form A&apos; as required
            <lb />
            by Rule 11(2). It is noted that there is no specific direction for furnishing the
            <lb />
            returns as per &apos;Form H&apos; which stipulates the periods for the returns, and the
            <lb />
            date for submission. The second part of the notice, in the form of Rule 11(4)
            <lb />
            quantifies the quantity of limestone and the amount of cess due, which has
            <lb />
            been assessed by the respondent No. 3, from records and other information
            <lb />
            available, raising a demand for payment as per &apos;Form J&apos;. As observed earlier,
            <lb />
            the writ petitioners have strongly contended that the notice was bad in law,
            <lb />
            inasmuch as, it was not in the form prescribed by the Rules. Contentions have
            <lb />
            also been raised, that the infraction of the stipulations, has resulted in the
            <lb />
            denial of adequate opportunity being afforded to the writ petitioners to present
            <lb />
            their case before the Assessing Authorities.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            25.
            <lb />
            A close scrutiny of the impugned notices, will no doubt reveal that
            <lb />
            there are discrepancies in the procedure adopted, and also the language used
            <lb />
            therein. However, in keeping with an overall view, we have to weigh the facts,
            <lb />
            and keep in mind as to whether this non-adherence to procedure, in the manner
            <lb />
            of issuance of notice, will be fatal to the case of the respondents. In this regard,
            <lb />
            the facts surrounding the entire matter need to be taken into consideration. The
            <lb />
            first prominent fact that cannot escape scrutiny, is that the writ petitioners are
            <lb />
            parties in WP(C) No. 454 of 2019, wherein the vires of the MM Cess Act,
            <lb />
            1988, has been put to challenge, and has also been taken as one of the main
            <lb />
            grounds in the instant writ petitions for non-payment of cess. This
            <lb />
            conclusively proves the fact that the writ petitioners, are well aware of their
            <lb />
            liability to submit returns and to pay the requisite cess. Another important
            <lb />
            factor that is to be considered, is the payment of the current cess amount by
            <lb />
            the writ petitioners to the respondents, which reinforces the above noted fact
            <lb />
            of the petitioners knowledge as to their liability under the MMC Rules.
            <lb />
            Though, for the failure of filing of the returns, a formal notice ought to have
            <lb />
            been served upon the writ petitioners, fault can also be pinned upon the writ
            <lb />
            petitioners, inasmuch as, they were duty bound as per the Act and Rules, to
            <lb />
            file their returns, a fact which by the actions show that they were well aware
            <lb />
            of, and had even filed a writ petition to avoid implementation of the same.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            26.
            <lb />
            The factum of knowledge and awareness of the writ petitioners
            <lb />
            as to their liability to pay cess, therefore cannot be denied. As such, the stand
            <lb />
            and pleading taken that there has been violation of the principles of natural
            <lb />
            justice in not issuing prior notice only under Rule 11(2) before issuance of
            <lb />
            notice under Rule 11(4), though an attractive argument, however, in the fact
            <lb />
            and circumstances of the present case, will in our opinion, not amount to
            <lb />
            denial of reasonable opportunity, as the outcome or conclusion will not be
            <lb />
            substantially different, even if the petitioners had been afforded opportunity.
            <lb />
            Compounded to this, is the fact that within 30 days of the notice, no returns as
            <lb />
            per &apos;Form A&apos;, nor any representations, were filed by the writ petitioners, but
            <lb />
            instead the instant writ petitions assailing the impugned notices, were filed
            <lb />
            directly before this Court, and that too around 30 days after their issuance,
            <lb />
            which corresponds to the notice period under the Rules. The element of notice,
            <lb />
            and its denial as projected by the writ petitioners in the backdrop of these
            <lb />
            circumstances, therefore loses its significance. It can be safely concluded
            <lb />
            therefore, that the absence of the word &apos;Form H&apos; in the notice under Rule 11(2)
            <lb />
            will not render the proceedings vitiated or invalid. Further the non-filing of
            <lb />
            returns by the petitioners in &apos;Form A&apos; within 30 days, rendered them liable to
            <lb />
            be proceeded with under Rule 11(4). As such, though there might be some
            <lb />
            procedural infirmity, looking at the totality of the objectives of the process
            <lb />
            and the proceedings itself, it cannot be held that the same is vitiated to render
            <lb />
            the notices void or illegal.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            27.
            <lb />
            In this context, it will be expedient to refer to the cited judgment
            <lb />
            in the case of Dharampal Satyapal Limited vs. Deputy Commissioner of
            <lb />
            Central Excise, Gauhati &amp; Ors. reported in (2015) 8 SCC 519 on the point
            <lb />
            exclusion or inapplicability of the principles of natural justice in Excise and
            <lb />
            Taxation matters the relevant paragraphs are quoted herein below:-
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;38. But that is not the end of the matter. While the law on the
            <lb />
            principle of audi alteram partem has progressed in the manner
            <lb />
            mentioned above, at the same time, the Courts have also
            <lb />
            repeatedly remarked that the principles of natural justice are
            <lb />
            very flexible principles. They cannot be applied in any
            <lb />
            straightjacket formula. It all depends upon the kind of
            <lb />
            functions performed and to the extent to which a person is
            <lb />
            likely to be affected. For this reason, certain exceptions to the
            <lb />
            aforesaid principles have been invoked under certain
            <lb />
            circumstances. For example, the Courts have held that it would
            <lb />
            be sufficient to allow a person to make a representation and
            <lb />
            oral hearing may not be necessary in all cases, though in some
            <lb />
            matters, depending upon the nature of the case, not only full-
            <lb />
            fledged oral hearing but even cross-examination of witnesses is
            <lb />
            treated as a necessary concomitant of the principles of natural
            <lb />
            justice. Likewise, in service matters relating to major
            <lb />
            punishment by way of disciplinary action, the requirement is
            <lb />
            very strict and full-fledged opportunity is envisaged under the
            <lb />
            statutory rules as well. On the other hand, in those cases where
            <lb />
            there is an admission of charge, even when no such formal
            <lb />
            inquiry is held, the punishment based on such admission is
            <lb />
            upheld. It is for this reason, in certain circumstances, even
            <lb />
            post-decisional hearing is held to be permissible. Further, the
            <lb />
            Courts have held that under certain circumstances principles
            <lb />
            of natural justice may even be excluded by reason of diverse
            <lb />
            factors like time, place, the apprehended danger and so on.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            39. We are not concerned with these aspects in the present
            <lb />
            case as the issue relates to giving of notice before taking action.
            <lb />
            While emphasizing that the principles of natural justice cannot
            <lb />
            be applied in straightjacket formula, the aforesaid instances
            <lb />
            are given. We have highlighted the jurisprudential basis of
            <lb />
            adhering to the principles of natural justice which are
            <lb />
            grounded on the doctrine of procedural fairness, accuracy of
            <lb />
            outcome leading to general social goals, etc. Nevertheless,
            <lb />
            there may be situations wherein for some reason -perhaps
            <lb />
            because the evidence against the individual is thought to be
            <lb />
            utterly compelling -it is felt that a fair hearing &quot;would make
            <lb />
            no difference&quot; -meaning that a hearing would not change the
            <lb />
            ultimate conclusion reached by the decision-maker -then no
            <lb />
            legal duty to supply a hearing arises. Such an approach was
            <lb />
            endorsed by Lord Wilberforce in Malloch v. Aberdeen Corpn.,
            <lb />
            who said that: (WLR p. 1595: All ER p. 1294)
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            &quot;… A breach of procedure...cannot give [rise to]
            <lb />
            a remedy in the courts, unless behind it there is
            <lb />
            something of substance which has been lost by the
            <lb />
            failure. The court does not act in vain. &quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            Relying on these comments, Brandon L.J. opined in
            <lb />
            Cinnamond v. British Airports Authority that: (WLR p. 593: All
            <lb />
            ER p. 377)
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            &quot;… no one can complain of not being given
            <lb />
            an opportunity to make representations if such an
            <lb />
            opportunity would have availed him nothing.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            In such situations, fair procedures appear to serve no purpose
            <lb />
            since &apos;right&apos; result can be secured without according such
            <lb />
            treatment to the individual.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            40. In this behalf, we need to notice one other exception
            <lb />
            which has been carved out to the aforesaid principle by the
            <lb />
            Courts. Even if it is found by the Court that there is a violation
            <lb />
            of principles of natural justice, the Courts have held that it may
            <lb />
            not be necessary to strike down the action and refer the matter
            <lb />
            back to the authorities to take fresh decision after complying
            <lb />
            with the procedural requirement in those cases where non-
            <lb />
            grant of hearing has not caused any prejudice to the person
            <lb />
            against whom the action is taken. Therefore, every violation of
            <lb />
            a facet of natural justice may not lead to the conclusion that
            <lb />
            order passed is always null and void. The validity of the order
            <lb />
            has to be decided on the touchstone of &apos;prejudice&apos;. The ultimate
            <lb />
            test is always the same, viz., the test of prejudice or the test of
            <lb />
            fair hearing.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            41. In ECIL, the majority opinion, penned down by Sawant,
            <lb />
            J., while summing up the discussion and answering the various
            <lb />
            questions posed, had to say as under qua the prejudice
            <lb />
            principle: (SCC pp. 756-58, para 30)
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            &quot;30. Hence the incidental questions raised above may be
            <lb />
            answered as follows:
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            *
            <lb />
            *
            <lb />
            *
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (v) The next question to be answered is what is the effect on
            <lb />
            the order of punishment when the report of the enquiry officer
            <lb />
            is not furnished to the employee and what relief should be
            <lb />
            granted to him in such cases. The answer to this question has
            <lb />
            to be relative to the punishment awarded. When the employee
            <lb />
            is dismissed or removed from service and the inquiry is set aside
            <lb />
            because the report is not furnished to him, in some cases the
            <lb />
            non-furnishing of the report may have prejudiced him gravely
            <lb />
            while in other cases it may have made no difference to the
            <lb />
            ultimate punishment awarded to him. Hence to direct
            <lb />
            reinstatement of the employee with back-wages in all cases is
            <lb />
            to reduce the rules of justice to a mechanical ritual. The theory
            <lb />
            of reasonable opportunity and the principles of natural justice
            <lb />
            have been evolved to uphold the rule of law and to assist the
            <lb />
            individual to vindicate his just rights. They are not incantations
            <lb />
            to be invoked nor rites to be performed on all and sundry
            <lb />
            occasions. Whether in fact, prejudice has been caused to the
            <lb />
            employee or not on account of the denial to him of the report,
            <lb />
            has to be considered on the facts and circumstances of each
            <lb />
            case. Where, therefore, even after the furnishing of the report,
            <lb />
            no different consequence would have followed, it would be a
            <lb />
            perversion of justice to permit the employee to resume duty and
            <lb />
            to get all the consequential benefits. It amounts to rewarding
            <lb />
            the dishonest and the guilty and thus to stretching the concept
            <lb />
            of justice to illogical and exasperating limits. It amounts to an
            <lb />
            &apos;unnatural expansion of natural justice&apos; which in itself is
            <lb />
            antithetical to justice.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            42. So far so good. However, an important question posed by
            <lb />
            Mr. Sorabjee is as to whether it is open to the authority, which
            <lb />
            has to take a decision, to dispense with the requirement of the
            <lb />
            principles of natural justice on the ground that affording such
            <lb />
            an opportunity will not make any difference? To put it
            <lb />
            otherwise, can the administrative authority dispense with the
            <lb />
            requirement of issuing notice by itself deciding that no
            <lb />
            prejudice will be caused to the person against whom the action
            <lb />
            is contemplated? Answer has to be in the negative. It is not
            <lb />
            permissible for the authority to jump over the compliance of the
            <lb />
            principles of natural justice on the ground that even if hearing
            <lb />
            had been provided it would have served no useful purpose. The
            <lb />
            opportunity of hearing will serve the purpose or not has to be
            <lb />
            considered at a later stage and such things cannot be presumed
            <lb />
            by the authority. This was so held by the English Court way
            <lb />
            back in the year 1943 in General Medical Council v.
            <lb />
            Spackman. This Court also spoke in the same language in
            <lb />
            Board of High School and Intermediate Education v. Chitra
            <lb />
            Srivastava, as is apparent from the following words: (SCC p.
            <lb />
            123, para 7)
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            &quot;7. The learned counsel for the appellant, Mr. C.B.
            <lb />
            Agarwala, contends that the facts are not in dispute and
            <lb />
            it is further clear that no useful purpose would have been
            <lb />
            served if the Board had served a show-cause notice on
            <lb />
            the petitioner. He says that in view of these
            <lb />
            circumstances it was not necessary for the Board to have
            <lb />
            issued a show-cause notice. We are unable to accept this
            <lb />
            contention. Whether a duty arises in a particular case to
            <lb />
            issue a show-cause notice before inflicting a penalty does
            <lb />
            not depend on the authority&apos;s satisfaction that the person
            <lb />
            to be penalised has no defence but on the nature of the
            <lb />
            order proposed to be passed.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            43. In view of the aforesaid enunciation of law, Mr. Sorabjee
            <lb />
            may also be right in his submission that it was not open for the
            <lb />
            authority to dispense with the requirement of principles of
            <lb />
            natural justice on the presumption that no prejudice is going to
            <lb />
            be caused to the appellant since judgment in R.C. Tobacco had
            <lb />
            closed all the windows for the appellant.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            44. At the same time, it cannot be denied that as far as Courts
            <lb />
            are concerned, they are empowered to consider as to whether
            <lb />
            any purpose would be served in remanding the case keeping in
            <lb />
            mind whether any prejudice is caused to the person against
            <lb />
            whom the action is taken. This was so clarified in ECIL itself
            <lb />
            in the following words: (SCC p. 758, para 31)
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            &quot;31. Hence, in all cases where the enquiry
            <lb />
            officer&apos;s report is not furnished to the delinquent
            <lb />
            employee in the disciplinary proceedings, the
            <lb />
            Courts and Tribunals should cause the copy of the
            <lb />
            report to be furnished to the aggrieved employee if
            <lb />
            he has not already secured it before coming to the
            <lb />
            Court/Tribunal and given the employee an
            <lb />
            opportunity to show how his or her case was
            <lb />
            prejudiced because of the non-supply of the report.
            <lb />
            If after hearing the parties, the Court/Tribunal
            <lb />
            comes to the conclusion that the non-supply of the
            <lb />
            report would have made no difference to the
            <lb />
            ultimate findings and the punishment given, the
            <lb />
            Court/Tribunal should not interfere with the order
            <lb />
            of punishment. The Court/Tribunal should not
            <lb />
            mechanically set aside the order of punishment on
            <lb />
            the ground that the report was not furnished as it
            <lb />
            regrettably being done at present. The courts
            <lb />
            should avoid resorting to short cuts. Since it is the
            <lb />
            Courts/Tribunals which will apply their judicial
            <lb />
            mind to the question and give their reasons for
            <lb />
            setting aside or not setting aside the order of
            <lb />
            punishment, (and not any internal appellate or
            <lb />
            revisional authority), there would be neither a
            <lb />
            breach of the principles of natural justice nor a
            <lb />
            denial of the reasonable opportunity. It is only if
            <lb />
            the Court/Tribunal finds that the furnishing of the
            <lb />
            report would have made a difference to the result
            <lb />
            in the case that it should set aside the order of
            <lb />
            punishment.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            45. Keeping in view the aforesaid principles in mind, even
            <lb />
            when we find that there is an infraction of principles of natural
            <lb />
            justice, we have to address a further question as to whether any
            <lb />
            purpose would be served in remitting the case to the authority
            <lb />
            to make fresh demand of amount recoverable, only after
            <lb />
            issuing notice to show cause to the appellant. In the facts of the
            <lb />
            present case, we find that such an exercise would be totally
            <lb />
            futile having regard to the law laid down by this Court in R.C.
            <lb />
            Tobacco.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            46. To recapitulate the events, the appellant was accorded
            <lb />
            certain benefits under Notification dated 8-7-1999. This
            <lb />
            Notification stands nullified by Section 154 of the 2003 Act,
            <lb />
            which has been given retrospective effect. The legal
            <lb />
            consequence of the aforesaid statutory provision is that the
            <lb />
            amount with which the appellant was benefitted under the
            <lb />
            aforesaid Notification becomes refundable. Even after the
            <lb />
            notice is issued, the appellant cannot take any plea to retain the
            <lb />
            said amount on any ground whatsoever as it is bound by the
            <lb />
            dicta in R.C. Tobacco. Likewise, even the officer who passed
            <lb />
            the order has no choice but to follow the dicta in R.C. Tobacco.
            <lb />
            It is important to note that as far as quantification of the
            <lb />
            amount is concerned, it is not disputed at all. In such a
            <lb />
            situation, issuance of notice would be an empty formality and
            <lb />
            we are of the firm opinion that the case stands covered by
            <lb />
            &quot;useless formality theory&quot;.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            47. In Escorts Farms Ltd.v. Commr., this Court, while
            <lb />
            reiterating the position that rules of natural justice are to be
            <lb />
            followed for doing substantial justice, held that, at the same
            <lb />
            time, it would be of no use if it amounts to completing a mere
            <lb />
            ritual of hearing without possibility of any change in the
            <lb />
            decision of the case on merits. It was so explained in the
            <lb />
            following terms: (SCC pp. 309-10, para 64)
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            &quot;64. Right of hearing to a necessary party is
            <lb />
            a valuable right. Denial of such right is serious
            <lb />
            breach of statutory procedure prescribed and
            <lb />
            violation of rules of natural justice. In these
            <lb />
            appeals preferred by the holder of lands and some
            <lb />
            other transferees, we have found that the terms of
            <lb />
            government grant did not permit transfers of land
            <lb />
            without permission of the State as grantor.
            <lb />
            Remand of cases of a group of transferees who
            <lb />
            were not heard, would, therefore, be of no legal
            <lb />
            consequence, more so, when on this legal question
            <lb />
            all affected parties have got full opportunity of
            <lb />
            hearing before the High Court and in this appeal
            <lb />
            before this Court. Rules of natural justice are to be
            <lb />
            followed for doing substantial justice and not for
            <lb />
            completing a mere ritual of hearing without
            <lb />
            possibility of any change in the decision of the case
            <lb />
            on merits. In view of the legal position explained
            <lb />
            by us above, we, therefore, refrain from
            <lb />
            remanding these cases in exercise of our
            <lb />
            discretionary powers under Article 136 of the
            <lb />
            Constitution of India.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            48. Therefore, on the facts of this case, we are of the opinion
            <lb />
            that non-issuance of notice before sending communication
            <lb />
            dated 23-6-2003 has not resulted in any prejudice to the
            <lb />
            appellant and it may not be feasible to direct the respondents to
            <lb />
            take fresh action after issuing notice as that would be a mere
            <lb />
            formality.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            28.
            <lb />
            Another judgment in the case of The Chairman, Board of
            <lb />
            Mining Examination and Chief Inspector of Mines &amp; Anr. vs. Ramjee
            <lb />
            reported 1977 2 SCC 256 at para 15, which is quoted herein below also covers
            <lb />
            this aspect;
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;15. These general observations must be tested on the concrete
            <lb />
            facts of each case and every miniscule violation does not spell
            <lb />
            illegality. If the totality of circumstances satisfies the Court that
            <lb />
            the party visited with adverse order has not suffered from denial
            <lb />
            of reasonable opportunity the Court will decline to be
            <lb />
            punctilious or fanatical as if the rules of natural justice were
            <lb />
            sacred scriptures.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            29.
            <lb />
            Apart from the above, it is settled law that no direction can be
            <lb />
            sought commanding the respondents to act contrary to prevailing statute or
            <lb />
            rules. The prayer of the writ petitioners to direct the respondents not to insist
            <lb />
            the submission of monthly returns in &apos;Form A&apos; under Rule 5 of the Rules,
            <lb />
            1989 is unsustainable. In the judgment of Maharshi Dayanand University vs.
            <lb />
            Surgeet Kaur reported in (2010) 11 SCC 159, the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court in
            <lb />
            para 11 has held as under:
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;11. It is settled legal proposition that neither the court nor any
            <lb />
            tribunal has the competence to issue a direction contrary to law
            <lb />
            and to act in contravention of a statutory provision. The Court
            <lb />
            has no competence to issue a direction contrary to law nor the
            <lb />
            court can direct an authority to act in contravention of the
            <lb />
            statutory provisions.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            30.
            <lb />
            The plea of the writ petitioners, in seeking refund of the current
            <lb />
            cess already paid during the pendency of WP(C) No. 454 of 2019 is also
            <lb />
            unsustainable in law. Challenge to the vires of an enactment cannot cease or
            <lb />
            suspend the operation or implementation of such an enactment unless the
            <lb />
            same is set aside in accordance with law. As held in Natural Resources
            <lb />
            Allocation, In Re, Special Reference No. 1 of 2012 reported in (2012) 10
            <lb />
            SCC 1 &quot;One of the most profound tenets of constitutionalism is a
            <lb />
            presumption of constitutionality assigned to each legislation enacted&quot;.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            31.
            <lb />
            The judgments relied upon by the petitioners though correct in
            <lb />
            their own perspective, stand on a different footing from the instant cases,
            <lb />
            inasmuch as, as observed, the petitioners herein were well aware of their
            <lb />
            liability. On the contentions raised by the respondents, with regard to the
            <lb />
            identical reliefs claimed by the writ petitioners in the prayers made in WP(C)
            <lb />
            No. 454 of 2019, Misc. Case No. 244 of 2019 in WP(C) No. 454 of 2019 and
            <lb />
            the present batch of petitions, as has been noted earlier, the issues being dealt
            <lb />
            with in this judgment will not intrude or have a bearing on WP(C) No. 454 of
            <lb />
            2019 wherein there is a challenge to the vires of the Act, but in our opinion
            <lb />
            will have a limited impact only on Misc. application No. 244 of 2019 which
            <lb />
            has sought for a direction not to insist for payment of cess until the
            <lb />
            constitutionality of the Meghalaya Mineral Cess Act, 1988 was adjudicated
            <lb />
            upon.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            32.
            <lb />
            As such, from the discussions and findings recorded above, the
            <lb />
            impugned proceedings and notices cannot be said to be vitiated, for not strictly
            <lb />
            adhering to procedure prescribed, as also the other prayers made in the writ
            <lb />
            petitions which are found to be unsustainable in law. However, an aspect
            <lb />
            which does not escape our notice, is the fact that the MMC Rules 1989 do not
            <lb />
            contain a provision for appeal against an order of assessment made under Rule
            <lb />
            11(4) of the Rules, and an opportunity of being heard, is only provided before
            <lb />
            the imposition of penalty for non-payment of tax or cess under Section 7 of
            <lb />
            the MMC Act, 1988. In our considered opinion, though this point has not been
            <lb />
            specifically pleaded, it was urged in the course of hearing, and reliance placed
            <lb />
            by the learned counsel for the petitioner in the case of S.K. Bhargava vs.
            <lb />
            Collector, Chandigarh &amp; Ors. reported in (1998) 5 SCC 170. Liberty was
            <lb />
            also prayed to allow the petitioners to represent before any further action is
            <lb />
            taken against them, in connection with the arrears in cess. This point in the
            <lb />
            interest of justice requires some deliberation.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            33.
            <lb />
            The order of assessment made under Rule 11(4) no doubt is an ex
            <lb />
            parte assessment, made on the failure of the writ petitioners to submit returns.
            <lb />
            In the absence of a provision to appeal against such assessment, or for that
            <lb />
            matter to prefer an appeal against any exercise of power under a statute by an
            <lb />
            authority the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court in the case of Organo Chemical
            <lb />
            Industries &amp; Anr. vs. Union of India &amp; Ors. reported in (1979) 4 SCC 573
            <lb />
            at para 15 has held as follows:-
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;15. In this connection, it was also urged that the absence of
            <lb />
            any provision for appeal, leaves the defaulting employer with
            <lb />
            no remedy. The conferral of arbitrary and uncontrolled powers
            <lb />
            on the Regional Provident Fund Commissioner to quantify
            <lb />
            damages, it is said, without a corresponding right of appeal or
            <lb />
            revision, makes the provision contained in Section 14-B per se
            <lb />
            void and illegal and it is liable to be struck down on that
            <lb />
            ground. We are afraid the contention is wholly devoid of
            <lb />
            substance. Mere absence of provision for an appeal does not
            <lb />
            imply that the Regional Provident Fund Commissioner is
            <lb />
            invested with arbitrary or uncontrolled power, without any
            <lb />
            guidelines. The conferral of power to award damages under
            <lb />
            Section 14-B is to ensure the success of the measure. It is
            <lb />
            dependent on existence of certain facts; there has to be an
            <lb />
            objective determination, not subjective. The Regional Provident
            <lb />
            Fund Commissioner has not only to apply his mind to the
            <lb />
            requirements of Section 14-B but is cast with the duty of
            <lb />
            making a &quot;speaking order&quot;, after conforming to the rules of
            <lb />
            natural justice.&quot; (Emphasis supplied)
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            Another ruling that comes to mind on this point, is the judgment rendered in
            <lb />
            the case of Chinta Lingam &amp; Ors. vs. Government of India &amp; Ors. and M/s
            <lb />
            Guggila Ramaiah etc. vs. The Union of India &amp; Ors. etc. reported in (1970)
            <lb />
            3 SCC 768 wherein in para 4, the extract of which is quoted herein below, the
            <lb />
            Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court held as follows:-
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;4.……We consider that there is no bar to any of the aggrieved
            <lb />
            parties approaching the State Government by means of a
            <lb />
            representation for a final decision even if the matter has been
            <lb />
            dealt with by the District Collector or the Deputy Commissioner
            <lb />
            of Civil Supplies in the first instance and the permit has been
            <lb />
            refused or wrongly withheld by those officers. In these
            <lb />
            circumstances the absence of a provision for appeal or revision
            <lb />
            can be of no consequence. At any rate it has been pointed out
            <lb />
            in more than one decision of this Court that when the power
            <lb />
            has to be exercised by one of the highest officers the fact that
            <lb />
            no appeal has been provided for is a matter of no moment;
            <lb />
            ……&quot; [Emphasis supplied]
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            The analogy of the cited case of S.K. Bhargava vs. Collector, Chandigarh &amp;
            <lb />
            Ors. reported in (1998) 5 SCC 170, in paras 8 and 9, which are reproduced
            <lb />
            herein below will also have a bearing in the formulation of this point in the
            <lb />
            present case:-
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;8. It is clear from the perusal of the above-quoted section that
            <lb />
            before a certificate can be issued by the Managing Director
            <lb />
            under sub-section (2) of Section 3, he must determine the &quot;sum
            <lb />
            due&quot; from the defaulter as enjoined upon him by Section 3(1)
            <lb />
            (b). It is difficult to appreciate the contention of the learned
            <lb />
            counsel for the respondent Financial Corporation that any
            <lb />
            such determination can take place without notice to the
            <lb />
            defaulter. The jurisdiction of the civil courts to go into the
            <lb />
            question as to what is the amount due is expressly ousted by
            <lb />
            sub-section (4) of Section 3. In its place, the power has been
            <lb />
            given to the Managing Director under Section 3 (1) (b) to
            <lb />
            determine as to what is the amount due from the defaulter.
            <lb />
            There can be no doubt that any such determination by the
            <lb />
            Managing Director will result in civil consequences ensuing.
            <lb />
            The determination being final and conclusive, would have the
            <lb />
            result of the passing of a final decree, inasmuch as the
            <lb />
            defaulters from whom any amount is found to be due, would
            <lb />
            become liable to pay the amount so determined and the
            <lb />
            Collector will have the right to recover the same as arrears of
            <lb />
            land revenue.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            9. In our opinion, even though Section 3 does not expressly
            <lb />
            provide for an opportunity being given to the alleged defaulter
            <lb />
            to explain as to whether any amount is due or not but in view
            <lb />
            of the nature of the said provision, the principles of natural
            <lb />
            justice must be read into it. The requirement of determination
            <lb />
            of the sum due by the Managing Director must be regarded as
            <lb />
            providing for the Managing Director hearing the alleged
            <lb />
            defaulter before coming to the conclusion as to what is the sum
            <lb />
            due. The very use of the word &quot;determine&quot; and &quot;sum due&quot;
            <lb />
            implies that there may be a lis between the parties and they have
            <lb />
            to be heard before a final conclusion is arrived at by the
            <lb />
            Managing Director. It is not a mere claim of the Corporation
            <lb />
            which is forwarded to the Collector for realisation, but it is the
            <lb />
            &quot;sum due&quot; as determined by the Managing Director which
            <lb />
            alone is recoverable. As already observed, this determination
            <lb />
            cannot be done without notice to the alleged defaulter.&quot;
            <lb />
            [Emphasis supplied]
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            34.
            <lb />
            From the discussions above, what follows is that though the
            <lb />
            assessment has been done by the competent authority, which is final as per the
            <lb />
            scheme of the MMC Rules, 1989, and the presumption is always that public
            <lb />
            officials discharge their duties in accordance with law, it would however, be
            <lb />
            just and proper and in the interest of justice if the writ petitioners be allowed
            <lb />
            to make a representation before the respondent No. 3, as to the assessment of
            <lb />
            cess made in the demand notices under Rule 11(4) before any further action
            <lb />
            that may follow, in proceedings under Section 7 of the Meghalaya Mineral
            <lb />
            Cess Act, 1988.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            35.
            <lb />
            The writ petitioners are therefore allowed to make
            <lb />
            representations within 10(ten) days from the date of this order and the
            <lb />
            respondent No. 3 to decide the same preferably within the period of 2(two)
            <lb />
            weeks thereafter on receipt of the said representations.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            36.
            <lb />
            For the reasons and circumstances discussed above, these writ
            <lb />
            petitions accordingly stand disposed of. No order as to costs.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            (W. Diengdoh)
            <lb />
            (H.S. Thangkhiew)
            <lb />
            Judge
            <lb />
            Judge
        </p>


    </text>
</tei>