<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc xml:id="0" />
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <p>
            1.
            <lb />
            The petitioner, who retired from the post of Executive Engineer
            <lb />
            (Electrical) on 31-01-2015, is aggrieved with the effect and consequences on
            <lb />
            his pensionary benefits caused by the Notification of the Meghalaya Energy
            <lb />
            Corporation Limited (Revision of Pay) Regulation, 2015, which was notified
            <lb />
            on 15-05-2017, which he alleges has resulted in Executive Engineers who
            <lb />
            were junior to the writ petitioner but who retired before 01-01-2015, drawing
            <lb />
            a higher pension.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            2.
            <lb />
            The writ petitioner retired from the post of Executive Engineer
            <lb />
            (Electrical) on 31-01-2015 when his basic pay was Rs. 56,330/-and the
            <lb />
            prevailing norm for fixation of pension was 50% of the average pay of the
            <lb />
            last 6 months, including Special Pay subject to a maximum of Rs. 27,380/-
            <lb />
            per month. After computation of the last 6 months pay of the petitioner, 50%
            <lb />
            of the average emolument worked out to Rs. 27,948.33/-and accordingly his
            <lb />
            pension was fixed at Rs. 27,380/-with effect 01-02-2015 which was the
            <lb />
            maximum amount payable.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            3.
            <lb />
            The respondent corporation vide Notification dated 15-05-2017,
            <lb />
            notified the Meghalaya Energy Corporation Limited (Revision of Pay)
            <lb />
            Regulation, 2015, revising the pay scale of its employees with effect 01-01-
            <lb />
            2015 and consequently by an Office Memorandum of the same day, the
            <lb />
            pensionary benefits of the employees stood revised with effect from 01-01-
            <lb />
            2015. Regulation/Paragraph 5 of the said OM dated 15-05-2017 dealt with
            <lb />
            the Revision of Pension/Family Pension and Principles of Fixation.
            <lb />
            Paragraph 5 (i) of the OM provided that Pension/Family Pension will be
            <lb />
            determined by multiplying the existing Basic Pension/Family Pension as on
            <lb />
            01-01-2015 by a factor of 1.82, whereas Paragraph 5(iv) of the OM provided
            <lb />
            the computation and fixation of the employees who retired within 6 months
            <lb />
            from the date of coming over to the revised scale of pay i.e., MeECL (RoP)
            <lb />
            Regulation, 2015.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            4.
            <lb />
            Mr. S.Sen, learned counsel for the petitioner submits that on the basis
            <lb />
            of the Revision of Pay implemented by the respondent corporation with
            <lb />
            effect from 01-01-2015, his revised pay for the month of January 2015, was
            <lb />
            fixed at Rs. 1,06,200/-and the respondent corporation relying on Paragraph
            <lb />
            5 (iv) of the OM dated 15-05-2017, revised the pension of the writ petitioner
            <lb />
            with effect from 01-01-2015. Learned counsel submits that taking into
            <lb />
            account the last 6 months including the last month at the revised pay, the
            <lb />
            petitioner&apos;s pension was fixed at Rs. 44,330/-. This, the learned counsel
            <lb />
            contends, has created an anomalous situation vis-a-vis the cases of the
            <lb />
            Executive Engineers who retired before 01-01-2015, as their pension has
            <lb />
            been revised by applying the principle contained in Paragraph 5 (i) of the
            <lb />
            OM i.e., by multiplying their existing basic pension by a factor of 1.82 which
            <lb />
            has resulted in them drawing a higher pension. The learned counsel submits
            <lb />
            that, as he received the benefit of the revised pay only for the month of
            <lb />
            January 2015, in comparison to other Executive Engineers who were getting
            <lb />
            the same pension earlier before the said revision, but retired before 01-01-
            <lb />
            2015, his basic pension is much lower than them. To illustrate this point, the
            <lb />
            learned counsel has referred to a chart which is annexed as Annexure-4 to
            <lb />
            the writ petition showing this anomaly.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            5.
            <lb />
            The learned counsel for the petitioner submits that the classification
            <lb />
            introduced by Paragraph 5 of the OM dated 15-05-2017, is unreasonable and
            <lb />
            unjustified and has no reasonable nexus with the objects sought to be
            <lb />
            achieved, as the same has resulted in discrimination in the revision of
            <lb />
            pension wherein, a junior is drawing higher pension than a senior, and as
            <lb />
            such he contends, the same is violative of Article 14 and 16 of the
            <lb />
            Constitution of India and is liable to be interfered with by this Court.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            6.
            <lb />
            Mr. S. Sen, in support of his arguments, has placed heavy reliance on
            <lb />
            the judgment of D.S. Nakara &amp; Ors. vs. Union of India. (1983)1 SCC 305
            <lb />
            and submits that as per this judgment, the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court has held
            <lb />
            that unequal treatment offends Article 14, if it appears that pensioners for the
            <lb />
            purpose of pension benefits who form a class are divided by arbitrarily fixing
            <lb />
            an eligibility criterion, and that any classification has to be based on some
            <lb />
            rational principle. The following decisions have also been placed by the
            <lb />
            learned counsel for consideration by this Court:
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            (i)
            <lb />
            AIR 1989 SC 669 M.L.Jain Vs. Union of India &amp; Ors.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (ii) (2006) 11 SCC 709 Col. B.J. Akkara (Retd.) Vs. Govt. of India
            <lb />
            &amp; Ors.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (iii) (2021) 11 SCC 543 State of Andhra Pradesh &amp; Anr. Vs.
            <lb />
            Dinavahi Lakshmi Kameswari.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            7.
            <lb />
            Mr. S. Sahay, learned counsel for the respondent corporation in reply,
            <lb />
            has firstly submitted that the writ petition is not maintainable as the petitioner
            <lb />
            has not been able to disclose any legal or fundamental right which has been
            <lb />
            violated. He also submits that the petitioner is receiving pensionary benefits
            <lb />
            in accordance with the applicable terms and conditions as provided by the
            <lb />
            OM dated 15-05-2017, which has been given effect to without any deviation
            <lb />
            and that the petitioner has no vested right to claim pensionary benefits at an
            <lb />
            amount of his choosing. It is contended that the amount to be disbursed as
            <lb />
            pension is a matter of policy, and that the pay and emoluments of the
            <lb />
            employees of the corporation, are determined on the recommendations of the
            <lb />
            Pay Committee, which is an expert body constituted for the purpose.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            8.
            <lb />
            Learned counsel submits that the writ petition is also barred by laches
            <lb />
            as the re-fixation of Pay and Pension, had been carried out by the respondent
            <lb />
            corporation vide the OM dated 15-05-2017, whereas the petitioner has
            <lb />
            chosen to approach this Court only on October 2021, without explaining the
            <lb />
            inordinate delay, when even the representations of the petitioner were
            <lb />
            rejected in 2017-2018 itself. On this ground alone, it is submitted the writ
            <lb />
            petition deserves no consideration and is liable to be dismissed.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            9.
            <lb />
            On merits, learned counsel contends that the writ petition is
            <lb />
            unsustainable. It is submitted that the OM dated 15-05-2017, in respect of
            <lb />
            Revised Pension was introduced keeping in view the interest of the
            <lb />
            employees, but however due to the method of calculation wherein, in most
            <lb />
            cases the date of retirement plays a vital role, there cannot be parity in respect
            <lb />
            of a quantum of pensionary benefits to all its employees. It is further
            <lb />
            submitted by learned counsel that there are no Pension Protection Rules to
            <lb />
            protect the pension of an employee from their respective juniors and no
            <lb />
            provision for one rank one pension under the respondent corporation.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            10. In support of his arguments, learned counsel has cited the following
            <lb />
            cases:
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            (i)
            <lb />
            (1993) 4 SCC 62 State of West Bengal vs. Ratan Behari Dey
            <lb />
            &amp; Ors.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (ii) (2002) 2 SCC 179 State of W.B. &amp; Anr. Vs. W.B. Govt.
            <lb />
            Pensioners&apos; Associations &amp; Ors.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (iii) (1990) 4 SCC 207 Krishena Kumar Vs. Union of India &amp; Ors.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (iv) (1994) 4 SCC 68 Union of India Vs. P.N.Menon &amp; Ors.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (v) (2006) 5 SCC 65 State of Bihar &amp; Ors. Vs. Bihar Pensioners
            <lb />
            Samaj.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            11. The learned counsel has sought to distinguish the judgment of
            <lb />
            D.S.Nakara (supra) and submits that the principle enunciated therein is not
            <lb />
            applicable to the facts of this case and has referred to State of West Bengal
            <lb />
            vs. Ratan Behari Dey (supra) wherein the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court has held
            <lb />
            that terminal benefits and also pensionary benefits constitute conditions of
            <lb />
            service and the employee is vested with the right to revise salaries as also
            <lb />
            terminal/pensionary benefits and also to specify a date from which the
            <lb />
            revision of pay scales, terminal/pensionary benefits shall take effect, and as
            <lb />
            long as such dates specified in a reasonable manner without discriminating
            <lb />
            between similarly situated persons, no interference is called for. Reference
            <lb />
            has also been made to the case of Krishena Kumar vs. Union of India &amp;
            <lb />
            Ors. (supra) wherein learned counsel submits the Constitution Bench of the
            <lb />
            Supreme Court held that notification setting a cut-off date could not be struck
            <lb />
            out by applying the ratio of Nakara (supra) and that a cut-off date for
            <lb />
            granting service benefits may not necessarily tantamount to a violation of
            <lb />
            Article 14 and will be upheld by Courts if there is some reasonable
            <lb />
            explanation in support of that date.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            12. I have heard learned counsel for the parties and have perused the
            <lb />
            materials on record. Firstly, it is to be noted that on the date of retirement of
            <lb />
            the writ petitioner, the prevailing norm was that pension was fixed at 50% of
            <lb />
            the average of the last 6 months of emoluments including Special Pay subject
            <lb />
            to a maximum of Rs.27,380/-. Accordingly, the petitioner&apos;s pension was
            <lb />
            worked out as follows: -
        </p>
        <lb />
        <table>
            i. Pay for August 2014
            <lb />
            Rs.55360/-+ Spl. Pay Rs. 375/-= Rs. 55,735/-
            <lb />
            ii. Pay for September, 2014 Rs.55360/-+ Spl. Pay Rs. 375/-= Rs. 55,735/-
            <lb />
            iii Pay for October, 2014
            <lb />
            Rs.55360/-+ Spl. Pay Rs. 375/-= Rs. 55,735/-
            <lb />
            iv. Pay for November, 2014 Rs.55360/-+ Spl. Pay Rs. 375/-= Rs. 55,735/-
            <lb />
            v. Pay for December, 2014 Rs.55360/-+ Spl. Pay Rs. 375/-= Rs. 55,735/-
            <lb />
            vi. Pay for January, 2015
            <lb />
            Rs.56330/-+ Spl. Pay Rs. 375/-= Rs. 56,705/-
            <lb />
            Total
            <lb />
            = Rs.3,35,380/-
            <lb />
            Average emolument Rs.3,35,380 ÷ 6 = Rs.55,896.66
            <lb />
            50% of 55,896.66 = 27,948.331
            <lb />
            Pension was fixed w.e.f. 1.2.2015 at Rs.27,380/-(this being the maximum limit).
            <lb />
        </table>

        <p>
            13. On coming into effect of the Office Memorandum dated 15-05-2017,
            <lb />
            the petitioner came to be governed by paragraph 5 (iv) of the OM which
            <lb />
            provided as follows:-
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;MEGHALAYA ENERGY CORPORATION LIMITED
            <lb />
            Corporate Affairs
            <lb />
            Corporate
            <lb />
            Identification
            <lb />
            No.
            <lb />
            U40101ML2009SGC008374
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            LUM JINGSHAI, SHORT ROUND ROAD, SHILLONG 793 001,
            <lb />
            MEGHALAYA
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            Fax: 0364-2590355: Website address: www.meecl.nic.in
            <lb />
            No. MeECL/CA/PB/77/2017/42 Dated 15 th May,2017.
            <lb />
            OFFICE MEMORANDUM
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            5.
            <lb />
            Revision of Pension/Family Pension and
            <lb />
            Principle of Fixation.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (iv) In the case of Corporation&apos;s employees
            <lb />
            who retire within 6(six) months from the
            <lb />
            date of
            <lb />
            coming over to the revised
            <lb />
            scale of pay in
            <lb />
            terms of the Meghalaya
            <lb />
            Energy
            <lb />
            Corporation
            <lb />
            Limited
            <lb />
            (Revision of Pay) Regulations 2011 (sic)
            <lb />
            average
            <lb />
            emoluments for 6(six) months
            <lb />
            period
            <lb />
            preceding the
            <lb />
            date
            <lb />
            of
            <lb />
            retirement shall be
            <lb />
            calculated
            <lb />
            by
            <lb />
            taking into account pay as
            <lb />
            follows:-
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (a) For the period during which pay is
            <lb />
            drawn in pre-revised scale -Basic
            <lb />
            Pay multiplied by a factor of 1.53.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (b) For the period during which pay is
            <lb />
            drawn in the revised scale -Basic
            <lb />
            Pay in the Revised Scale.
            <lb />
            NOTE -(1) In the case of employees
            <lb />
            in receipt of Special Pay, the same
            <lb />
            shall be taken into account for the
            <lb />
            purpose of calculating average
            <lb />
            emoluments.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (2) The Pension/Family
            <lb />
            Pension in terms of these orders shall
            <lb />
            qualify for
            <lb />
            Dearness Allowance
            <lb />
            as per rates revised from time
            <lb />
            to
            <lb />
            time.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (Note: It appears that 2011 has been
            <lb />
            inadvertently referred to instead of 2015.)
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            14. On the basis of the revision of pay with effect 01-01-2015, the revised
            <lb />
            pay of the petitioner for the month of January, 2015 was fixed at Rs.
            <lb />
            1,06,200/-. Accordingly, by application of paragraph 5 (iv) of the OM dated
            <lb />
            15-05-2017, the revised pension of the petitioner with effect from 01-02-
            <lb />
            2015 was as follows:
        </p>
        <table>
            <lb />
            Pre Revised Pay for August 2014 Rs. 55360 × 1.53 + Spl. Pay Rs. 375 = 85075.80
            <lb />
            Pre Revised Pay for September
            <lb />
            2014
            <lb />
            Rs. 55360 × 1.53 + Spl. Pay Rs. 375 = 85075.80
            <lb />
            Pre Revised Pay for October
            <lb />
            2014
            <lb />
            Rs. 55360 × 1.53 + Spl. Pay Rs. 375 = 85075.80
            <lb />
            Pre Revised Pay for November
            <lb />
            2014
            <lb />
            Rs. 55360 × 1.53 + Spl. Pay Rs. 375 = 85075.80
            <lb />
            Pre Revised Pay for December
            <lb />
            2014
            <lb />
            Rs. 55360 × 1.53 + Spl. Pay Rs. 375 = 85075.80
            <lb />
            Revised Pay for January 2015
            <lb />
            Rs.106200 × 1 + Spl. Pay Rs. 375 = 106575.00
            <lb />
            Total
            <lb />
            = 531954.00
            <lb />
            A.E. 531,954.00 ÷ 6 = Rs. 88,659.00
            <lb />
            (B) S/Pension Admissible:
            <lb />
            50% of 88659.00 × (30÷30) = Rs.44329.50 Say 44330.00
            <lb />
        </table>

        <p>
            15. In contrast, as projected by the writ petitioner in the case of Executive
            <lb />
            Engineers who retired before 01-01-2015, their pension has been revised by
            <lb />
            application of paragraph 5 (i) of the OM dated 15-05-2017, which was by
            <lb />
            multiplying their existing basic pension by a factor of 1.82, which has
            <lb />
            resulted in them drawing higher pension, even though they were junior to the
            <lb />
            writ petitioner but retired before 01-01-2015. This Court is therefore to
            <lb />
            examine as to whether the fixation of the cut-off date has been done
            <lb />
            arbitrarily bringing about a discrimination between similarly situated person
            <lb />
            or whether the said specification of the date was reasonable.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            16. The fixation and revision of pension in the respondent corporation as
            <lb />
            can be seen from the materials is as per rules, terms and conditions laid down
            <lb />
            by the corporation in the Office Memorandums from time to time. By OM
            <lb />
            dated 15-05-2017, revision of pensionary benefits was with effect from 01-
            <lb />
            01-2015 upto 31-12-2019 and by OM dated 11-12-2019, revision of
            <lb />
            pensionary benefits was with effect from 01-01-2020 onwards. In the case
            <lb />
            of the writ petitioner as noted above, OM dated 15-05-2017 had prescribed
            <lb />
            the computation of revised pension in the case of employees who retired
            <lb />
            within six months from the date of coming over to the revised scale of pay
            <lb />
            of 2017. The effect of this OM is that due to the peculiar situation of the
            <lb />
            petitioner, inasmuch as, he enjoyed the benefit of revised pay only for a
            <lb />
            month i.e., January 2015, his revised pension would therefore be less in
            <lb />
            comparison with the employees retired prior to 01-01-2015. No arbitrariness,
            <lb />
            irregularity or illegality can be attributed to the respondent corporation for
            <lb />
            fixation of the cut-off date which has resulted in the alleged anomaly.
            <lb />
            Moreover, it is to be noted that there are no Pensionary Protection Rules in
            <lb />
            place to protect the pension of the employee from that of his junior
            <lb />
            employees and further there is no provision for one rank one pension. As the
            <lb />
            discrepancy is not between similarly situated classes, the petitioner cannot
            <lb />
            be said to have been discriminated against.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            17. In this context, it would be apposite to refer to the judgments of the
            <lb />
            Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court as cited by the parties which have been pronounced
            <lb />
            in such matters:-
        </p>
        <lb />
        <p>
            In the case of State of West Bengal &amp; Ors. Vs. Ratan Behari Dey &amp;
            <lb />
            Ors. (1993) 4 SCC 62, at paras 7, 8, 9 &amp; 10 it was held as follows:
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;7.
            <lb />
            In our opinion, the principle of Nakara
            <lb />
            has no application to the facts of this case. The
            <lb />
            precise principle enunciated in Nakara has been
            <lb />
            duly explained in Krishena Kumar by a
            <lb />
            coordinate Bench. For reasons to be assigned
            <lb />
            hereinafter, it cannot be said that prescribing
            <lb />
            April 1, 1977 as the date from which the new
            <lb />
            Regulations were to come into force is either
            <lb />
            arbitrary or discriminatory. Now, it is open to the
            <lb />
            State or to the Corporation, as the case may be,
            <lb />
            to change the conditions of service unilaterally.
            <lb />
            Terminal benefits as well as pensionary benefits
            <lb />
            constitute conditions of service. The employer
            <lb />
            has the undoubted power to revise the salaries
            <lb />
            and/or the pay scales as also terminal
            <lb />
            benefits/pensionary benefits. The power to
            <lb />
            specify a date from which the revision of pay
            <lb />
            scales or terminal benefits/pensionary benefits,
            <lb />
            as the case may be, shall take effect is a
            <lb />
            concomitant of the said power. So long as such
            <lb />
            date is specified in a reasonable manner, i.e.,
            <lb />
            without bringing about a discrimination between
            <lb />
            similarly situated persons, no interference is
            <lb />
            called for by the Court in that behalf….
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            8.
            <lb />
            In this context, it may be remembered that
            <lb />
            the power of the State to specify a date with effect
            <lb />
            from which the Regulations framed, or amended,
            <lb />
            as the case may be, shall come into force is
            <lb />
            unquestioned. A date can be specified both
            <lb />
            prospectively as well as retrospectively. The only
            <lb />
            question is whether the prescription of the date is
            <lb />
            unreasonable or discriminatory. Since we have
            <lb />
            found that the prescription of the date in this case
            <lb />
            is neither arbitrary nor unreasonable, the
            <lb />
            complaint of discrimination must fail.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            9.
            <lb />
            Now coming to the argument of Sri P.P.
            <lb />
            Rao that the Regulations bring about an
            <lb />
            unreasonable classification between similarly
            <lb />
            placed employees, we must say that we are not
            <lb />
            impressed by it. It is not submitted that the
            <lb />
            Corporation had no power to give retrospective
            <lb />
            effect to the Regulations. It was within the power
            <lb />
            of the Corporation to enforce the Regulations
            <lb />
            either prospectively or with retrospective effect
            <lb />
            from such date as they might specify. Of course,
            <lb />
            as repeatedly held by this Court, in such cases the
            <lb />
            State cannot, as the expression goes, pick a date
            <lb />
            out of its hat. It has to prescribe the date in a
            <lb />
            reasonable manner, having regard to all the
            <lb />
            relevant facts and circumstances. Once this is
            <lb />
            done, question of discrimination does not arise.
            <lb />
            Reference in this behalf may also be had to the
            <lb />
            decision of this Court in Sushma Sharma v. State
            <lb />
            of Rajasthan a decision of the Division Bench
            <lb />
            comprising E.S. Venkataramiah and Sabyasachi
            <lb />
            Mukherji, JJ.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            10. As rightly pointed out in Krishena Kumar,
            <lb />
            Nakara was a case where an artificial date was
            <lb />
            specified classifying the retirees, governed by the
            <lb />
            same Rules and similarly situated, into two
            <lb />
            different classes, depriving one such class of the
            <lb />
            benefit of liberalized Pension Rules. It was found
            <lb />
            in that case that the specification of the date
            <lb />
            (from which the liberalised Rules were to come
            <lb />
            into force) was arbitrary. Whereas in this case,
            <lb />
            the employees retiring prior to April 1, 1977 and
            <lb />
            those retiring thereafter were governed by
            <lb />
            different sets of rules. The argument to the
            <lb />
            contrary may mean that the Government can
            <lb />
            never change the conditions of service relating to
            <lb />
            retiral benefits with effect from a particular date.
            <lb />
            No such absolute proposition can be stated that
            <lb />
            while effecting any such change, no date from
            <lb />
            which such change will come into force can be
            <lb />
            specified. As stated above, a date can be
            <lb />
            prescribed but such date should not be drawn in
            <lb />
            such a manner as to bring about discrimination
            <lb />
            between persons situated similarly i.e., in a
            <lb />
            manner violative of Article 14. This aspect has
            <lb />
            been elaborately dealt with and explained in
            <lb />
            Krishena Kumar and we do not think it necessary
            <lb />
            to repeat the same.&quot;
            <lb />
            (Emphasis supplied)
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            In the case of State of W.B. &amp; Anr. Vs. W. B. Govt. Pensioners&apos;
            <lb />
            Associations &amp; Ors. (2002) 2 SCC 179, at paras 20 and 21 it was held as
            <lb />
            follows:
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;20. What is noticeable is that the definition of
            <lb />
            the word &quot;emoluments&quot; in the 1971 Rules was
            <lb />
            not amended. As such pension continued to be
            <lb />
            calculated on the basis of emoluments as defined
            <lb />
            in the 1971 Rules namely the last pay drawn
            <lb />
            immediately prior to retirement. The pay of the
            <lb />
            pre-1986 pensioners was not revised. The Third
            <lb />
            Pay Commission had given a reason for choosing
            <lb />
            1-1-1986, as the cut-off date. As held in Krishena
            <lb />
            Kumar v. Union of India and Union of India v.
            <lb />
            P.N. Menon merely because a cut-off date is
            <lb />
            fixed would not make the exercise invalid
            <lb />
            although persons in the service immediately
            <lb />
            before the cut-off date would be deprived of the
            <lb />
            benefit of the revised scales of pay. It would
            <lb />
            depend upon the relevancy of the consideration
            <lb />
            underlying the choice of such date. The reason
            <lb />
            stated by the Third Pay Commission cannot be
            <lb />
            said to be arbitrary or irrelevant.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            21. Because the scales of pay had been revised
            <lb />
            from 1-1-1986, the recomputation of pension for
            <lb />
            such employees as had been granted the revised
            <lb />
            scales of necessity was limited to the same cut-off
            <lb />
            date. All that the impugned Memorandum No.
            <lb />
            4056-F dated 25-4-1990 did was to recompute the
            <lb />
            benefits in favour of post 1-1-1986 retirees
            <lb />
            according to the existing formula as provided by
            <lb />
            the Memorandum No. 7530-F and No. 7531-F
            <lb />
            both dated 6-7-1988. The same formula
            <lb />
            continues to be applied to the pre-1986 retirees.
            <lb />
            The difference between pre-1986 pensioners and
            <lb />
            the post-1986 pensioners is only on account of
            <lb />
            the revision of pay scales and not account of
            <lb />
            failure of State Government to equitably apply
            <lb />
            the liberalised pension scheme formula. The
            <lb />
            quantum of the emoluments formed no part of
            <lb />
            the formula for grant of pension during 1986 to
            <lb />
            1995.&quot;
        </item>
        <lb />
        <p>
            In the case of Union of India Vs. P. N. Menon &amp; Ors. (1994) 4 SCC
            <lb />
            68, at para 8 it was held as follows:
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;8. Whenever the Government or an authority,
            <lb />
            which can be held to be a State within the
            <lb />
            meaning of Article 12 of the Constitution, frames
            <lb />
            a scheme for persons who have superannuated
            <lb />
            from service, due to many constraints, it is not
            <lb />
            always possible to extend the same benefits to one
            <lb />
            and all, irrespective of the dates of
            <lb />
            superannuation. As such any revised in
            <lb />
            respect of post-retirement benefits, if
            <lb />
            implemented with a cut-off date, which can be
            <lb />
            held to be reasonable and rational in the light
            <lb />
            of Article 14 of the Constitution, need not be held
            <lb />
            to be invalid. It shall not amount to &quot;picking out
            <lb />
            a date from the hat&quot;, as was said by this Court in
            <lb />
            the case of D.R.Nim v. Union of India (AIR 1967
            <lb />
            SC 1301: (1967) 2 SCR 325: (1968) 1 LLJ 264) in
            <lb />
            connection with fixation of seniority. Whenever
            <lb />
            a revision takes place, a cut-off date becomes
            <lb />
            imperative because the benefit has to be allowed
            <lb />
            within the financial resources available with the
            <lb />
            Government.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            In the case of State of Bihar &amp; Ors. Vs. Bihar Pensioners Samaj
            <lb />
            (2006) 5 SCC 65, at para 17 it was held as follows:
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;17. We think that the contention is well
            <lb />
            founded. The only ground on which Article
            <lb />
            14 has been put forward by the learned counsel
            <lb />
            for the respondent is that the fixation of the cut-
            <lb />
            off date for payment of the revised benefits under
            <lb />
            the two notifications concerned was arbitrary
            <lb />
            and it resulted in denying arrears of payments to
            <lb />
            certain sections of the employees. This argument
            <lb />
            is no longer res integra. It has been held in a
            <lb />
            catena of judgments that fixing of a cut-off date
            <lb />
            for granting of benefits is well within the powers
            <lb />
            of the Government as long as the reasons
            <lb />
            therefor are not arbitrary and are based on some
            <lb />
            rational consideration.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            18. From the facts of the case and from the pronouncements of the
            <lb />
            judgments that have been quoted above, apart from the fact that the writ
            <lb />
            petition has been filed after a considerable delay, no unreasonableness can
            <lb />
            be discerned from the actions of the respondent corporation in fixing the cut-
            <lb />
            off date to warrant any sort of interference by this Court. In the circumstances
            <lb />
            therefore, this writ petition is accordingly dismissed, but however, the parties
            <lb />
            are to bear their own cost.
        </p>
        <p>
            Judge
            <lb />
            Meghalaya
            <lb />
            26.07.2022
            <lb />
            “Samantha PS”
            <lb />
        </p>

    </text>
</tei>