<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc xml:id="0" />
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <p>
            1. The petitioner before this Court is serving as a Supervisor (Design) in
            <lb />
            the establishment of the respondent North Eastern Electric Power
            <lb />
            Corporation Limited (NEEPCO) and is aggrieved with the impugned
            <lb />
            transfer order dated 26-11-2021 which had been issued by the respondent
            <lb />
            No.4. The reasons for assailing the transfer order are that the same had been
            <lb />
            made in a colourable and malafide exercise of power by the respondents in
            <lb />
            view of the fact that the writ petitioner is a trade union leader and under the
            <lb />
            collective banner of the three Trade Unions in NEEPCO had filed a writ
            <lb />
            petition being No. WP(C). 367 of 2021 on 18-11-2021, wherein the vires of
            <lb />
            Rule 8 (iii) of the North Eastern Electric Power Corporation Limited
            <lb />
            (NEEPCO) Conduct, Discipline and Appeal Rules, 1980 have been
            <lb />
            challenged. The writ petitioner has alleged that his transfer is a form of
            <lb />
            punishment for his involvement in trade union activities. Personal
            <lb />
            allegations of malafide have also been levelled against the respondent No.5
            <lb />
            who is made a party respondent by name.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            2.
            <lb />
            Mr. H.L.Shangreiso, learned Senior counsel assisted by Ms.
            <lb />
            A.Kharshiing, learned counsel submits that the transfer order suffers from
            <lb />
            grave illegalities, firstly, in the speed and haste with which the petitioner
            <lb />
            was transferred which was at the behest of the respondent No.5, to Kurung
            <lb />
            Project Arunachal Pradesh from Mawsynram Project, Meghalaya without
            <lb />
            allowing him to complete his assignment and that the same is a clear
            <lb />
            violation of the stated Transfer Policy of NEEPCO. Learned Senior counsel
            <lb />
            also asserts that the impugned transfer was made at the behest and on the
            <lb />
            recommendation of the respondent No.5 who is the petitioner&apos;s controlling
            <lb />
            officer and also the competent recommending authority for transfer of
            <lb />
            subordinate technical staff, and as such the transfer order was issued by the
            <lb />
            respondent No.4 (H.R.Department). The learned Senior counsel in his
            <lb />
            allegations of malafide against the respondent No.5 has submitted that the
            <lb />
            said respondent was inimical to the petitioner and had warned him with the
            <lb />
            threat of transfer to a far-flung area for his union activities. In this context,
            <lb />
            he has drawn the attention of the Court to Annexure-5 of the writ petition
            <lb />
            which is a show cause notice dated 11-10-2021 issued by the respondent
            <lb />
            No.5, wherein the petitioner was warned and was called upon to explain as
            <lb />
            to why necessary action was not to be initiated against him. The learned
            <lb />
            Senior counsel has pointed out that in this letter itself, reference is made to
            <lb />
            a verbal warning by the respondent No.5, which was made on 09-08-2021.
            <lb />
            Learned Senior counsel further submits immediately after the explanation
            <lb />
            had been given, the petitioner was sent to Wah Umiam HeP Stage III (85
            <lb />
            MW) Mawsynram, Meghalaya vide letter dated 15-11-2021 issued by the
            <lb />
            respondent No.3, for collection of data and he was to submit the same on or
            <lb />
            before 1 st December, 2021, even though such assignment is hardly
            <lb />
            connected with the petitioner&apos;s normal official duty which is drawing of
            <lb />
            projects as Supervisor (Design). Thereafter, learned Senior counsel submits
            <lb />
            when the vires of Rule 8 (iii) of the North Eastern Electric Power
            <lb />
            Corporation Limited (NEEPCO) Conduct, Disciplinary and Appeal Rules,
            <lb />
            1980 came to be challenged by way of WP(C). No. 367 of 2021 on 18-11-
            <lb />
            2021 by the three Trade Unions of NEEPCO, at the behest of respondent
            <lb />
            No.5, the impugned transfer order dated 26-11-2021 was passed hastily,
            <lb />
            transferring the petitioner from Guwahati to Kurung Dam, Arunachal
            <lb />
            Pradesh. The transfer, the learned Senior counsel asserts was made with the
            <lb />
            view to disable the petitioner from discharging his responsibilities as a Trade
            <lb />
            Union leader and as such the same was not done in the ordinary course of
            <lb />
            business but solely with an ulterior motive to punish the petitioner.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            3.
            <lb />
            The learned Senior counsel submits that the transfer of the petitioner
            <lb />
            is also in violation of Rule 6.2 of the Transfer Policy of NEEPCO which
            <lb />
            stipulates that an employee will be considered for transfer from Location
            <lb />
            Category-I to Location Category-II or vice versa or within the same category
            <lb />
            after completion of the tenure of 4(four) years in one location. He submits
            <lb />
            that though a representation against the transfer has been filed as provided
            <lb />
            under Rule 17, the petitioner has been compelled to approach this Court due
            <lb />
            to the nature of the case where he cannot expect justice from the respondents.
            <lb />
            In this regard the learned Senior counsel has referred to a judgment and order
            <lb />
            dated 27-08-2019 passed by this Court in WP(C). No. 258 of 2018 and
            <lb />
            WP(C). No. 319 of 2018 (Shri. Devapriya Choudhury vs. Union of India
            <lb />
            and Shri. Subir Sircar vs. NEEPCO &amp; Ors.) especially para 18 wherein it
            <lb />
            has been held that though the Transfer Policy does not have the force of
            <lb />
            statutory rules but as the guidelines had been framed by the NEEPCO itself,
            <lb />
            an obligation was cast upon them to follow these norms and to justify any
            <lb />
            deviation therefrom.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            4.
            <lb />
            The learned Senior counsel then submits that the writ petitioner
            <lb />
            holding the post of Supervisor (Design) in NEEPCO, his service is not one
            <lb />
            of private employment or contract of personal service, as NEEPCO is a
            <lb />
            government company and as such it would fall within the meaning of State
            <lb />
            under Article 12 of the Constitution. He further submits that NEEPCO in
            <lb />
            performing governmental functions and public duty has public law character
            <lb />
            and would fall under the exception given in para 45 and para 52 of the
            <lb />
            judgment in the case of K.K.Saksena vrs. International Commission on
            <lb />
            Irrigation and Drainage &amp; Ors. reported in (2015) 4 SCC 670. Learned
            <lb />
            Senior counsel on this point has also relied upon the following judgments:
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            i)
            <lb />
            Central Inland Water Transport Corporation vrs. Brojo Nath
            <lb />
            Ganguly (1986) 3 SCC 156.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            ii)
            <lb />
            Ajay Hasia &amp; Ors. vrs. Khalib Mujib Sehravardi &amp; Ors.
            <lb />
            (1981) 1 SCC 722.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            iii) Ramana Dayaram Shetty vrs. International Airport Authority
            <lb />
            of India (1979) 3 SCC 489.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            iv) Delhi Transport Corporation vrs. D.T.C. Mazdoor Congress
            <lb />
            &amp; Ors. (1991) Supp. (1) SCC 600.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            v)
            <lb />
            Zee Telefilms Ltd. vrs. Union of India (2005) 4 SCC 649.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            vi) Kishore Madhukar Pinglikar vrs. Automative Research
            <lb />
            Association of India.
            <lb />
            Learned Senior counsel in concluding his arguments submits that the
            <lb />
            case is a fit case for interference by this Court, inasmuch as, malafide is writ
            <lb />
            large in the conduct of the respondents and NEEPCO being a public
            <lb />
            government company, the employment of the petitioner cannot be taken to
            <lb />
            be a contract of personal service.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            5.
            <lb />
            Mr. V.K.Jindal, learned Senior counsel assisted by Ms. E.Marwein,
            <lb />
            learned counsel at the outset submits that it is not the case of the petitioner
            <lb />
            that the impugned transfer order dated 26-11-2021 is vitiated by malafide on
            <lb />
            the part of the authority making the order. He submits that the transfer order
            <lb />
            was issued by the General Manager (H.R.) by which the petitioner was
            <lb />
            posted to Kurung Dam site, and that as per Rule 9 of the NEEPCO Transfer
            <lb />
            Policy, the authority for the transfer is the Functional Director, in this case
            <lb />
            the Director (Technical) and the Director (Personnel). He further submits
            <lb />
            that the petitioner has not made any allegation of malafide or otherwise
            <lb />
            against the said authorities, and instead has levelled allegations against the
            <lb />
            respondent No.5, who has nothing to do with the impugned transfer order.
            <lb />
            The learned Senior counsel has invited the attention of this Court to the
            <lb />
            pleadings in the writ petition, wherein the petitioner has made allegations of
            <lb />
            malafide against the respondent No.5 accusing him of being vindictive
            <lb />
            because of the petitioner&apos;s involvement in Trade Union activities and the
            <lb />
            transfer order being at the behest of the respondent No.5. Learned Senior
            <lb />
            counsel submits that the respondent No.5 has no role to play and is only
            <lb />
            responsible for maintaining the discipline in the wing under his control and
            <lb />
            that the show cause notice dated 11-10-2021 had been issued by him as per
            <lb />
            instructions received from the Industrial Relation and Disciplinary Section
            <lb />
            of NEEPCO. He further submits that the respondent No. 5 has no interest or
            <lb />
            anything to do with Rule 8 (iii) which is a subject of WP(C). No. 367/2021
            <lb />
            before the Division Bench, and as such there is no question of the respondent
            <lb />
            No.5 acting in a malafide manner against the petitioner. Learned Senior
            <lb />
            counsel strongly contends that the facts as projected by the petitioner does
            <lb />
            not make out a case of malafide or of malice in law or in fact.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            6.
            <lb />
            The learned Senior counsel then contends that the transfer of the
            <lb />
            petitioner has been occasioned not due to his involvement in Trade Union
            <lb />
            activities, but the same was done in the exigency of service, as the petitioner
            <lb />
            is specially trained to take up the initial stages of survey of the project and
            <lb />
            his services were therefore urgently required. The transfer order he argues,
            <lb />
            was issued to meet the urgent operational requirements at the project site
            <lb />
            and the allegation that respondent No.5, or any other official respondent had
            <lb />
            acted in a malafide manner, or that the impugned transfer is a case of
            <lb />
            colourable exercise of power, has no legs to stand on and have been made
            <lb />
            with the intention to unnecessarily harass the respondent No.5.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            7.
            <lb />
            The learned Senior counsel has also raised a point on the
            <lb />
            maintainability of the writ petition by arguing that the service of the
            <lb />
            petitioner is purely a contract of personal service which cannot be
            <lb />
            specifically enforced in view of the bar created by the Specific Relief Act.
            <lb />
            Learned Senior counsel to substantiate this contention has drawn the
            <lb />
            attention of this Court to the proposal made to the petitioner for his
            <lb />
            appointment as Draftsman (Civil) Grade III under NEEPCO made vide
            <lb />
            appointment order dated 27-10-1989 (Annexure-1 to the petition). He
            <lb />
            submits that in conditions No. 2 and 3, it has been provided that the
            <lb />
            petitioner is liable to be posted in any office of the Corporation in India and
            <lb />
            that his conditions of service will be governed by the existing Rules which
            <lb />
            are in force, at that relevant point of time. It is submitted that the order of
            <lb />
            appointment with the said conditions was accepted by the petitioner when
            <lb />
            he joined the service of NEEPCO and as such the aforesaid order of
            <lb />
            appointment constitutes a contract of personal service, which governs the
            <lb />
            service condition of the petitioner and the same can be specifically enforced,
            <lb />
            in view of the bar created by the Specific Relief Act, 1963.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            8.
            <lb />
            On the issue of the Transfer Policy of NEEPCO which had been
            <lb />
            formulated by the Board of Directors, the learned Senior counsel submits
            <lb />
            that the said Transfer Policy are mere guidelines and not statutory rules, and
            <lb />
            that they are also in the nature of a contract entered into between the Trade
            <lb />
            Unions of the employees of NEEPCO and its management. Rule 18, he
            <lb />
            submits vests the management with the right to modify and amend any
            <lb />
            provision in the Transfer Policy. On the allegation that Rule 6.2 and Rule 9
            <lb />
            (column 3) has been violated as the transfer of the petitioner has sought to
            <lb />
            be made prior to the completion of the tenure of four years` and that the
            <lb />
            transfer was not by the competent authority (Functional Director) but
            <lb />
            effectuated by the respondent No.5, learned Senior counsel submits that
            <lb />
            Rule 8.1 cloaks the management with enough power to transfer or retain any
            <lb />
            employee at any place, irrespective of the tenure at a particular location to
            <lb />
            meet the organizational requirements. Learned Senior counsel submits that
            <lb />
            the transfer of the petitioner having been done to meet organizational
            <lb />
            requirements, the allegations that the Transfer Policy has been violated is
            <lb />
            not sustainable. It is further submitted that the petitioner has also taken
            <lb />
            recourse to Rule 17 of the Transfer Policy and has filed a representation on
            <lb />
            29-11-2021 but before the same could be disposed of, the petitioner has
            <lb />
            come before this Court.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            9.
            <lb />
            Reiterating the stand that NEEPCO is not a statutory authority,
            <lb />
            learned Senior counsel submits that though NEEPCO may be considered a
            <lb />
            state within the meaning of &apos;other authorities&apos;, it is not a statutory authority,
            <lb />
            and though amenable to writ jurisdiction, in view of the nature of
            <lb />
            employment of the writ petitioner, the service of the petitioner is purely a
            <lb />
            contract of personal service and is also in the nature of private rights and as
            <lb />
            such, cannot be specifically enforced. The learned Senior counsel also
            <lb />
            touched upon the points that the writ petitioner is not a workman but is
            <lb />
            serving in a supervisory capacity, and also that the petitioner is not a
            <lb />
            protected workman or a protected key official to be eligible for any special
            <lb />
            treatment.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            10. The learned Senior counsel has placed the following decisions in
            <lb />
            support of his arguments which are as follows:
            <lb />
            i)
            <lb />
            S.C.Saxena vs. Union of India &amp; Ors. (2006) 9 SCC 583, para
            <lb />
            6 and 7.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            ii)
            <lb />
            Union of India vs. S.L.Abbas (1993) 4 SCC 357, para 6 and
            <lb />
            7.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            iii) Rajneesh Khajuria vs. Wockhardt Limited &amp; Anr. (2020) 3
            <lb />
            SCC 86, para 16 to 22.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            iv) Executive Committee UP Warehousing Corporation vs.
            <lb />
            Chandra Kuran Tyagi (1969) 2 SCC 838, para 13, 14, 20, 23
            <lb />
            &amp; 28.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            v)
            <lb />
            E.P.Royappa vs. State of Tamil Nadu, AIR 1974 SC 555, para
            <lb />
            92 and 93 (Five Judge Bench).
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            vi) T. Natarajan vs. Indian Oxygen Limited (2003) SCC Online
            <lb />
            775 (Madras) para 22.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            vii) Pearlite Liners (Pvt) Ltd. vs. Manorama Sirsi (2004) 3 SCC
            <lb />
            172 para 7.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            viii) K.K.Saksena vs. International Commission on Irrigation and
            <lb />
            Drainage (2015) 4 SCC 670, para 43 to 45, 50, 51.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            ix) WP(C). No. 258 and 319/2018 (Shri Devapriya Choudhury vs.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            UOI) date of order 27/8/2019 by Justice H.S.Thangkhiew.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            x)
            <lb />
            Executive Committee of Vaish Degree College, Shamli and
            <lb />
            Ors. vs. Lakshmi Narain &amp; Ors. (1976) 2 SCC 58, para 18.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            11. Having heard learned Senior counsel for the parties, the points that
            <lb />
            have risen for consideration are, whether the respondent corporation though
            <lb />
            amenable to writ jurisdiction under Article 226 will come within the purview
            <lb />
            of Article 12 and whether the employment of the petitioner constitutes a
            <lb />
            contract of personal service, which would make the instant writ petition not
            <lb />
            maintainable, as it would be an issue of seeking enforcement of private
            <lb />
            rights.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            12. In examining as to whether NEEPCO is a body that will come within
            <lb />
            the meaning of Article 12, certain factors have to be considered such as, the
            <lb />
            formation of the body, the objects and functions, the management and
            <lb />
            control the authorized share capital etc. Article 12 of the Constitution of
            <lb />
            India in its definition of &apos;State&apos;, has included in its ambit local or other
            <lb />
            authorities within the territory of India or under the control of the
            <lb />
            Government of India. As held in the case of Pradeep Kumar Biswas vs.
            <lb />
            Indian Institute of Chemical Biology &amp; Ors. (2002) 5 SCC 111 at paras 5
            <lb />
            and 6, the inclusive definition of &apos;State&apos; as given in Article 12, is not
            <lb />
            exhaustive and is &quot;among the great generalities of the Constitution the
            <lb />
            content of which has been and continues to be supplied by Courts from time
            <lb />
            to time&quot;. In this backdrop therefore, the nature of NEEPCO as a corporation
            <lb />
            has to be considered as the determination of a body as a &apos;State&apos; is not a rigid
            <lb />
            set of principles.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            13. An important indicator is the existence of deep and pervasive state
            <lb />
            control over a corporation to determine its character. In the case of Kishor
            <lb />
            Madhukar Pinglikar vs. Automotive Research Association of India in SLP
            <lb />
            No. 6637 of 2019 decided on 10 th February, 2022, the Supreme Court at
            <lb />
            para 5 had observed as follows:
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;5. An earlier judgment of this Court in Ramana
            <lb />
            Dayaram Shetty v. International Airport Authority of
            <lb />
            India and others, (1979) 3 SCC 489 had received the
            <lb />
            imprimatur of Ajay Hasia (supra) as to when a
            <lb />
            corporation can be said to be an instrumentality or
            <lb />
            agency of the government.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            &quot;(1) One thing is clear that if the entire share
            <lb />
            capital of the corporation is held by Government,
            <lb />
            it would go a long way towards indicating that
            <lb />
            the corporation is an instrumentality or agency
            <lb />
            of Government. (SCC p. 507, para 14).
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (2) Where the financial assistance of the State
            <lb />
            is so much as to meet almost entire expenditure
            <lb />
            of the corporation, it would afford some
            <lb />
            indication of the corporation being impregnated
            <lb />
            with governmental character. (SCC p.508, para
            <lb />
            15).
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (3) It may also be a relevant factor…..whether
            <lb />
            the corporation enjoys monopoly status which is
            <lb />
            State-conferred or State-protected. (SCC p. 508,
            <lb />
            para 15).
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (4)
            <lb />
            Existence of deep and pervasive State
            <lb />
            control may afford an indication that the
            <lb />
            corporation is a State agency or instrumentality.
            <lb />
            (SCC p. 508, para 15).
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (5) If the functions of the corporation are of
            <lb />
            public importance and closely related to
            <lb />
            governmental functions, it would be a relevant
            <lb />
            factor in classifying the corporation as an
            <lb />
            instrumentality or agency of Government. (SCC
            <lb />
            p. 509, para 16).
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (6) &apos;Specifically, if a department of
            <lb />
            Government is transferred to a corporation, it
            <lb />
            would be a strong factor supportive of this
            <lb />
            inference&apos; of the corporation being an
            <lb />
            instrumentality or agency of Government. (SCC
            <lb />
            p. 510, para 18)&quot;.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            14. The aforementioned case has also discussed the other judgments of
            <lb />
            the Supreme Court such as, Zee Telefilms Limited &amp; Anr. vs. Union of
            <lb />
            India &amp; Ors. (2005) 4 SCC 649, Ajay Hasia &amp; Ors. vs. Khalid Mujib
            <lb />
            Sheravardi &amp; Ors. (1981) 1 SCC 722 which have been also relied upon by
            <lb />
            the petitioner. The factors as to when a corporation can be said to come
            <lb />
            within the meaning of Article 12 as enumerated in the judgments quoted
            <lb />
            above will therefore necessarily have to be examined.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            15. From a perusal of the Memorandum and Articles of Association of
            <lb />
            the respondent corporation, it is firstly noted that it is a government company
            <lb />
            within the meaning of Section 2(45) of the Companies Act, 2013 (as
            <lb />
            amended), and the entire authorized share capital of the corporation is held
            <lb />
            by the Government of India. The main objects of the corporation are to plan,
            <lb />
            promote and organize an integrated and efficient development of electric
            <lb />
            power through conventional and non-conventional sources. Apart from the
            <lb />
            development of electric power, the corporation is also authorized to engage
            <lb />
            in manufacturing, trading and other businesses for the purpose of disposal,
            <lb />
            generation, operation and maintenance of electric power stations and
            <lb />
            projects apart from transmission, distribution, purchase and sale of electric
            <lb />
            power.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            16. It is also noted that there is deep and pervasive state control in the
            <lb />
            management of the corporation, the President of India an expression which
            <lb />
            also includes the Government of India and vice versa, is defined in the
            <lb />
            Memorandum of Association at clause 3(xiii). Extracts from the
            <lb />
            Memorandum of Association which are reproduced herein below leave no
            <lb />
            doubt as to the role the government has in the management and affairs of the
            <lb />
            corporation including the appointment of the Directors who are to run the
            <lb />
            company.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <table>
            Sr.No.
            <lb />
            BOARD OF DIRECTORS
            <lb />
            President to Appoint
            <lb />
            Directors and Determine
            <lb />
            their Remuneration
            <lb />
            75.
            <lb />
            The Chairman of the Board of
            <lb />
            Directors and the Government
            <lb />
            representatives on the Board of
            <lb />
            Directors shall be appointed by the
            <lb />
            President. Other members of the
            <lb />
            Board of Directors shall be
            <lb />
            appointed or reappointed by the
            <lb />
            President.
            <lb />
            The Whole-time Directors shall be
            <lb />
            paid such remuneration as the
            <lb />
            President may, from time to time,
            <lb />
            determine.
            <lb />
            Chairman and Managing
            <lb />
            Director
            <lb />
            76.
            <lb />
            The President at his discretion may
            <lb />
            appoint the same persons or two
            <lb />
            different persons as the Chairman
            <lb />
            of the Board of Directors and the
            <lb />
            Managing Director of the Company
            <lb />
            for such period and on such terms
            <lb />
            and conditions as he may think fit
            <lb />
            and may revoke such appointment.
            <lb />
            The Chairman and the Managing
            <lb />
            Directors so appointed shall be
            <lb />
            entitled to hold office till the expiry
            <lb />
            of his tenure unless removed earlier
            <lb />
            by the President and any vacancy
            <lb />
            arising either by death, removal,
            <lb />
            resignation or otherwise may be
            <lb />
            filled by fresh appointment by the
            <lb />
            President.
            <lb />
            Determination of period of
            <lb />
            appointment
            <lb />
            by
            <lb />
            the
            <lb />
            President
            <lb />
            77.
            <lb />
            The Directors appointed shall be
            <lb />
            entitled to hold office for such
            <lb />
            period as the President may
            <lb />
            determine. Further, the President
            <lb />
            may from time to time or at any time
            <lb />
            remove any part-time Director,
            <lb />
            from office at his absolute
            <lb />
            discretion.
            <lb />
            Chairperson
            <lb />
            87.
            <lb />
            (a) The President and/or the Board
            <lb />
            may
            <lb />
            elect a chairperson of its
            <lb />
            meetings and determine the period
            <lb />
            for which is to hold office.
            <lb />
            (b) All meetings of the Directors
            <lb />
            shall be presided over by the
            <lb />
            Chairperson or the Chairman and
            <lb />
            Managing Director if present. If no
            <lb />
            such Chairperson is elected, or if at
            <lb />
            any meeting of the Board, the
            <lb />
            Chairperson is not present within
            <lb />
            five minutes after the time
            <lb />
            appointed for holding the same, the
            <lb />
            Directors present may choose one
            <lb />
            of the Directors then present to
            <lb />
            preside at the meeting.
            <lb />
            (c) Subject to Section 203 of the Act
            <lb />
            and rules made there under, one
            <lb />
            person can act as the Chairman as
            <lb />
            well as the Managing Director or
            <lb />
            Chief Executive Officer at the same
            <lb />
            time.
            <lb />
            GENERAL POWERS OF THE
            <lb />
            BOARD
            <lb />
            Powers of the Board
            <lb />
            97.
            <lb />
            (a) Subject to the provisions of the
            <lb />
            Act and to such directive and or
            <lb />
            instructions as the President may
            <lb />
            issue from time to time under these
            <lb />
            Articles, the business of the
            <lb />
            Company shall be managed by the
            <lb />
            Board of Directors who may
            <lb />
            exercise all such powers and do all
            <lb />
            such acts and things as the
            <lb />
            Company is authorized to exercise
            <lb />
            and do and who may, from time to
            <lb />
            time delegate such powers to the
            <lb />
            Chairman
            <lb />
            and/or
            <lb />
            Managing
            <lb />
            Director or whole time Director
            <lb />
            exercisable by them, upon such
            <lb />
            terms and conditions and with such
            <lb />
            restrictions, as they may think fit
            <lb />
            and either collaterally with or to the
            <lb />
            exclusion of their own powers and
            <lb />
            may, from time to time, revoke,
            <lb />
            withdraw or alter or vary all or any
            <lb />
            of such powers as may be necessary
            <lb />
            for the proper conduct of the
            <lb />
            business of the Company.
            <lb />
            (b) Provided that the Board of
            <lb />
            Directors shall not exercise any
            <lb />
            powers or do any act or thing which
            <lb />
            is directed or required, whether by
            <lb />
            this or any other Act or by the
            <lb />
            Memorandum or Articles of the
            <lb />
            Company or otherwise to be
            <lb />
            exercised or done by the Company
            <lb />
            in the Annual General Meeting.
            <lb />
            (c) The Chairperson shall reserve
            <lb />
            for decision of the President any
            <lb />
            proposals or decisions of the Board
            <lb />
            or any matter brought before the
            <lb />
            Board which raises in the opinion of
            <lb />
            the Chairperson, an important issue
            <lb />
            and which is on that account fit to
            <lb />
            be reserved for the decision of the
            <lb />
            President and no decision on such
            <lb />
            an important issue shall be taken in
            <lb />
            the absence of the Chairperson
            <lb />
            appointed by the President.
            <lb />
        </table>

        <p>
            17. It is thus clear from the recitals of the Memorandum of Association
            <lb />
            that the respondent corporation is under deep and pervasive control of the
            <lb />
            Government of India. The activities of the respondent corporation which is
            <lb />
            the generation and distribution of power is also an activity of great public
            <lb />
            importance and is closely related to governmental function, policy and
            <lb />
            planning. The indicators as have been illustrated above are decisive factors
            <lb />
            that supports the inference that the respondent corporation is an
            <lb />
            instrumentality of the government and therefore not only amenable to
            <lb />
            Article 226, but is an entity or authority within the meaning of Article 12 of
            <lb />
            the Constitution of India.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            18.
            <lb />
            Coupled with the discussions above as to the characteristics of the
            <lb />
            respondent corporation, a recent development that would reinforce the
            <lb />
            inference, is that as per the website of the respondent corporation, it is now
            <lb />
            shown that NEEPCO is a wholly owned subsidiary of NTPC (National
            <lb />
            Thermal Power Corporation) Limited and 100% of the equity shares are now
            <lb />
            held by NTPC Limited. This observation is made in view of the fact that the
            <lb />
            NTPC Limited as reflected in several judgments passed by various High
            <lb />
            Courts that being an undertaking of the Government of India it is considered
            <lb />
            a &apos;State&apos; for the purposes of Article 12 of the Constitution of India. This
            <lb />
            view is evident even from a decision rendered as far back on 26-09-1989 in
            <lb />
            the case of Navranglal Mittal Vs. National Thermal Power Corporation
            <lb />
            Ltd. &amp; Ors. passed by the High Court of Madhya Pradesh (Jabalpur
            <lb />
            Bench) M.P.No. 4004 of 1989. The position being thus situated, the
            <lb />
            respondent corporation (NEEPCO) for all purposes, is therefore to be
            <lb />
            considered to be an authority within the meaning of Article 12 of the
            <lb />
            Constitution of India.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            19. Coming to the other aspect of the matter as to the nature of
            <lb />
            employment and whether a mandamus would lie to enforce a contract of
            <lb />
            personal service in view of the stand of the respondents that the appointment
            <lb />
            of the petitioner constitutes a contract of personal service, in the nature of
            <lb />
            private right and therefore cannot be specifically enforced; however, in view
            <lb />
            of the finding that the NEEPCO as per discussions above is deemed to be a
            <lb />
            &apos;State&apos; or authority under the sweep of Article 12, the exceptions to the Rule
            <lb />
            of non-enforceability will therefore be attracted. In this context, the
            <lb />
            employment of the petitioner though contended to be a contract of personal
            <lb />
            service can be a subject for judicial review. In the case of K.K.Saksena
            <lb />
            (supra), three exceptions to the Rule of non-enforceability of contract of
            <lb />
            personal service have been laid down in para 52 of the judgment which is
            <lb />
            quoted herein below:
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;52. It is trite that contract of personal service cannot
            <lb />
            be enforced. There are three exceptions to this rule,
            <lb />
            namely:
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (i)
            <lb />
            when the employee is a public servant working
            <lb />
            under the Union of India or State;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (ii) when such an employee is employed by an
            <lb />
            authority/body which is a State within the
            <lb />
            meaning of Article 12 of the Constitution of
            <lb />
            India; and
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (ii) when such an employee is &quot;workmen&quot; within the
            <lb />
            meaning of Section 2(s) of the Industrial
            <lb />
            Disputes Act, 1947 and raises a dispute regarding
            <lb />
            his termination by invoking the machinery under
            <lb />
            the said Act.
        </item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            In the first two cases, the employment ceases to have
            <lb />
            private law character and &quot;status&quot; to such an
            <lb />
            employment is attached. In the third category of cases,
            <lb />
            it is the Industrial Disputes Act which confers
            <lb />
            jurisdiction on the Labour Court/Industrial Tribunal to
            <lb />
            grant reinstatement in case termination is found to be
            <lb />
            illegal.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            20. In this background therefore, it will be open for this Court to examine
            <lb />
            the transfer order and whether the same is vitiated by malafides or arbitrary
            <lb />
            which will involve the violation of Article 14 as well. Further, it is to be
            <lb />
            examined whether the said transfer has been made in violation of the
            <lb />
            Transfer Policy of the NEEPCO. This Court in the decision rendered in the
            <lb />
            case of Devapriya Choudhury vs. Union of India &amp; Ors. (WP(C). No. 258
            <lb />
            of 2018) and Subir Sircar vs. North Eastern Electric Power Corporation
            <lb />
            Ltd. &amp; Ors. (WP(C). No. 319 of 2018) dated 27-08-2019 which were matters
            <lb />
            involving transfer has held at para 18 as follows:
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;18. Admittedly, NEEPCO is a public sector
            <lb />
            undertaking and has framed the Transfer Policy to
            <lb />
            regulate the transfer and posting of employees of
            <lb />
            NEEPCO. The Policy framed by NEEPCO cannot be
            <lb />
            said to have the status of statutory rules framed under
            <lb />
            proviso to Article 309. However, once NEEPCO has
            <lb />
            laid down well thought out norms and policy, there
            <lb />
            must be valid reasons to deviate therefrom. It is true
            <lb />
            that these guidelines do not have the force of statutory
            <lb />
            Rules, and as such they do not confer any right on the
            <lb />
            employee, but it is also equally true that since NEEPCO
            <lb />
            has laid down norms and policy for transfer and policy,
            <lb />
            there must be valid and justifiable reasons for
            <lb />
            NEEPCO to deviate from the same in any particular
            <lb />
            case of transfer and posting. The norms and policy
            <lb />
            which have been framed by NEEPCO have obviously
            <lb />
            been framed for the purpose that they be followed and
            <lb />
            naturally have not been framed for the purpose that
            <lb />
            they be violated. As such though these guidelines do not
            <lb />
            confer a right on the employee, but definitely these
            <lb />
            Guidelines cast an obligation on NEEPCO to follow
            <lb />
            these norms and policy and justify with valid reasons
            <lb />
            why the set norms and policy of transfer cannot be
            <lb />
            followed in the case of a particular employee.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            The petitioner has alleged that his transfer is in violation of clause 6.2
            <lb />
            of the Transfer Policy of NEEPCO which stipulates that an employee will
            <lb />
            be considered for transfer from Location Category-I to Location Category-
            <lb />
            II or vice versa or within the same category after completion of the tenure
            <lb />
            of 4(four) years in one location. It is noted therefore, that notwithstanding
            <lb />
            the overriding powers of the corporation as given in clause 8.1, it is
            <lb />
            incumbent upon the respondent corporation to keep the Transfer Policy in
            <lb />
            mind while making such decisions.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            21. A more serious challenge that can be made out against the impugned
            <lb />
            transfer order is the allegation of colourable exercise of power, arbitrariness
            <lb />
            and malafide apart from the haste in which the transfer order was passed. It
            <lb />
            is noted from the sequence of events that firstly, the petitioner was given a
            <lb />
            show cause dated 11-10-2021 under the hand of respondent No.5 for
            <lb />
            indulging in trade union activities and in the said show cause itself, reference
            <lb />
            was also made to a verbal warning which had been given by respondent No.5
            <lb />
            on 09-08-2021 in his office chamber. Secondly, it is noted that the petitioner
            <lb />
            who was posted at Guwahati had then been tasked to complete an
            <lb />
            assignment in Wah Umiam HeP Stage-III (85 MW) Mawsynram,
            <lb />
            Meghalaya for collection of data/information and to submit the same on or
            <lb />
            before 01-12-2021, which is evidenced by letter dated 15-11-2021.
            <lb />
            However, the respondents issued the impugned transfer order on 26-11-2021
            <lb />
            transferring the petitioner to Kurung Dam Site in Arunachal Pradesh even
            <lb />
            before the allotted period given by the respondents to complete the
            <lb />
            assignment in Meghalaya was to expire.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            22. Another factor which deserves attention as contended by the
            <lb />
            petitioner, is the collective decision of three Trade Unions in NEEPCO, to
            <lb />
            approach this Court wherein its leaders, including the writ petitioner had
            <lb />
            jointly filed WP(C). No. 367 of 2021 on 18-11-202,1 whereby the vires of
            <lb />
            Rule 8(iii) which was inserted as a new provision in the North Eastern
            <lb />
            Electric Power Corporation Ltd. (NEEPCO) Conduct, Discipline and
            <lb />
            Appeal Rules, 1980 was put to challenge. The said Rule 8(iii) stipulates that
            <lb />
            employees to whom these Conduct, Discipline and Appeal Rules, 1980
            <lb />
            apply, are not to seek membership of any registered trade union or indulge
            <lb />
            in trade union activities.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            23. All the circumstances as narrated above point towards only one
            <lb />
            possible conclusion, that is, the transfer of the petitioner was not in normal
            <lb />
            course of his duties or in the exigencies of service. Even if the fact that the
            <lb />
            respondent No. 5 was the petitioner&apos;s Controlling officer who had issued the
            <lb />
            show cause notice dated 11-10-2021, apart from the verbal warning and
            <lb />
            even if the allegation of malafide against the said respondent is disregarded
            <lb />
            by this Court, the course of events and the very fact that the petitioner was
            <lb />
            sought to be transferred in such a manner, can squarely be attributed to his
            <lb />
            involvement in trade union activities, and the filing of WP(C). No. 367 of
            <lb />
            2021 before this Court. From the action of the respondent corporation, it is
            <lb />
            clear the impugned transfer order has been passed as a punitive measure
            <lb />
            against the petitioner for such activities. The haste and speed in which the
            <lb />
            transfer order was passed, also speaks volumes about the arbitrary nature of
            <lb />
            the same.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            24. As held in the case of Ajay Hasia &amp; Ors. vs. Khalid Mujib Sehravardi
            <lb />
            &amp; Ors. (1981) 1 SCC 722, any arbitrary or unreasonable action of an
            <lb />
            authority would be violative of Article 14. Para 16 which has illustrated this
            <lb />
            principle is reproduced hereinbelow:
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;16. If the Society is an &apos;authority&apos; and therefore
            <lb />
            &apos;State&apos; within the meaning of Article 12, it must follow
            <lb />
            that it is subject to the constitutional obligation
            <lb />
            under Article 14. The true scope and ambit of Article
            <lb />
            14 has been the subject matter of numerous decisions
            <lb />
            and it is not necessary to make any detailed reference
            <lb />
            to them. It is sufficient to state that the content and
            <lb />
            reach of Article 14 must not be confused with the
            <lb />
            doctrine of classification. Unfortunately, in the early
            <lb />
            stages of the evolution of our constitutional law, Article
            <lb />
            14 came to be identified with the doctrine of
            <lb />
            classification because the view taken was that that
            <lb />
            Article forbids discrimination and there would be no
            <lb />
            discrimination where the classification making the
            <lb />
            differentia fulfils two conditions, namely, (i) that the
            <lb />
            classification is founded on an intelligible differentia
            <lb />
            which distinguishes persons or things that are grouped
            <lb />
            together from others left out of the group; and (ii) that
            <lb />
            that differentia has a rational relation to the object
            <lb />
            sought to be achieved by the impugned legislative or
            <lb />
            executive action. It was for the first time in E.P.
            <lb />
            Royappa v. State of Tamil Nadu that this Court laid
            <lb />
            bare a new dimension of Article 14 and pointed out that
            <lb />
            that Article has highly activist magnitude and it
            <lb />
            embodies a guarantee against arbitrariness. This Court
            <lb />
            speaking through one of us (Bhagwati, J.) said: [SCC
            <lb />
            p.38 : SCC (L&amp;S) p. 200, para 85]
        </item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            The basic principle which therefore informs both
            <lb />
            Articles 14 and 16 is equality and inhibition against
            <lb />
            discrimination. Now, what is the content and reach of
            <lb />
            this great equalising principle? It is a founding faith,
            <lb />
            to use the words of Bose, J., &quot;a way of life&quot;, and it must
            <lb />
            not be subjected to a narrow pedantic or lexicographic
            <lb />
            approach. We cannot countenance any attempt to
            <lb />
            truncate its all-embracing scope and meaning, for to do
            <lb />
            so would be to violate its activist magnitude. Equality is
            <lb />
            a dynamic concept with many aspects and dimensions
            <lb />
            and it cannot be &quot;cribbed, cabined and confined&quot;
            <lb />
            within traditional and doctrinaire limits. From a
            <lb />
            positivistic point of view, equality is antithetic to
            <lb />
            arbitrariness. In fact, equality and arbitrariness are
            <lb />
            sworn enemies; one belongs to the rule of law in a
            <lb />
            republic while the other, to the whim and caprice of an
            <lb />
            absolute monarch. Where an act is arbitrary it is
            <lb />
            implicit in it that it is unequal both according to
            <lb />
            political logic and constitutional law and is therefore
            <lb />
            violative of Article 14, and if it affects any matter
            <lb />
            relating to public employment, it is also violative
            <lb />
            of Article 16. Articles 14 and 16 strike at arbitrariness
            <lb />
            in State action and ensure fairness and equality of
            <lb />
            treatment.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            This vital and dynamic aspect which was till then
            <lb />
            lying latent and submerged in the few simple but
            <lb />
            pregnant words of Article 14 was explored and brought
            <lb />
            to light in Royappa&apos;s case and it was reaffirmed and
            <lb />
            elaborated by this Court in Maneka Gandhi v. Union
            <lb />
            of India where this Court again speaking through one
            <lb />
            of us (Bhagwati, J.) observed: (SCC pp.283-84, para 7)
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            Now the question immediately arises as to what
            <lb />
            is the requirement of Article 14: What is the content
            <lb />
            and reach of the great equalising principle enunciated
            <lb />
            in this Article? There can be no doubt that it is a
            <lb />
            founding faith of the Constitution. It is indeed the
            <lb />
            pillar on which rests securely the foundation of our
            <lb />
            democratic republic. And, therefore, it must not be
            <lb />
            subjected to a narrow, pedantic or lexicographic
            <lb />
            approach. No attempt should be made to truncate its
            <lb />
            all-embracing scope and meaning, for to do so would
            <lb />
            be to violate its activist magnitude. Equality is a
            <lb />
            dynamic concept with many aspects and dimensions
            <lb />
            and it cannot be imprisoned within traditional and
            <lb />
            doctrinaire limits...............Article 14 strikes at
            <lb />
            arbitrariness in State action and ensures fairness and
            <lb />
            equality of treatment. The principle of reasonableness,
            <lb />
            which legally as well as philosophically, is an essential
            <lb />
            element
            <lb />
            of
            <lb />
            equality
            <lb />
            or
            <lb />
            non-arbitrariness
            <lb />
            pervades Article 14 like a brooding omnipresence.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            This was again reiterated by this Court in
            <lb />
            International Airport Authority&apos;s case at page 1042
            <lb />
            (SCC p. 511) of the Report. It must therefore now be
            <lb />
            taken to be well settled that what Article 14 strikes at is
            <lb />
            arbitrariness because any action that is arbitrary, must
            <lb />
            necessarily involve negation of equality. The doctrine
            <lb />
            of classification which is evolved by the courts is not
            <lb />
            paraphrase of Article 14 nor is it the objective and end
            <lb />
            of that Article. It is merely a judicial formula for
            <lb />
            determining whether the legislative or executive action
            <lb />
            in question is arbitrary and therefore constituting
            <lb />
            denial of equality. If the classification is not reasonable
            <lb />
            and does not satisfy the two conditions referred to
            <lb />
            above, the impugned legislative or executive action
            <lb />
            would plainly be arbitrary and the guarantee of
            <lb />
            equality under Article 14 would be breached. Wherever
            <lb />
            therefore there is arbitrariness in State action whether
            <lb />
            it be of the legislature or of the executive or of an
            <lb />
            &apos;authority&apos; under Article 12, Article 14 immediately
            <lb />
            springs into action and strikes down such State action.
            <lb />
            In fact, the concept of reasonableness and non-
            <lb />
            arbitrariness pervades the entire constitutional scheme
            <lb />
            and is a golden thread which runs through the whole
            <lb />
            of the fabric of the Constitution.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            25.
            <lb />
            For the foregoing reasons and circumstances, without further
            <lb />
            dwelling on any other aspects, the impugned transfer order dated 26.11.2021
            <lb />
            passed by the Respondent No.4 being found to be arbitrary and
            <lb />
            unsustainable, is hereby set aside and quashed.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            26.
            <lb />
            The writ petition is accordingly allowed and disposed of, however,
            <lb />
            leaving the parties to bear their own costs.
        </p>
        <p>
            Judge
            <lb />
            Meghalaya
            <lb />
            12.05.2022
            <lb />
            “Samantha PS
            <lb />
        </p>


    </text>
</tei>