<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<p>4. Bank of Baroda through its Branch Manager, Branch<lb/> Jagdalpur, District Bastar Chhattisgarh.<lb/></p>

			<p>5. Union of India, through the Secretary, Ministry of Railways,<lb/> Rail Bhawan, New Delhi-1.<lb/></p>

			<p>6. Bastar Railway Private Limited (Joint venture Of NMDC,<lb/> IRCON, SAIL and CMDC) through its Chief Executive<lb/> Officer, having its office at Global Exploration Centre,<lb/> NMDC, Green Valley City, Housing Board Colony,<lb/> Boriyakala, Raipur, District-Raipur Chhattisgarh.<lb/> ----Respondents<lb/> WA No. 77 of 2022<lb/> • Smt. Neelima Belsaria, W/o Shri T.V. Ravi, Aged 36 Years,<lb/> R/o Village-Pallai, Tahsil Jagdalpur, District Bastar<lb/> Chhattisgarh.<lb/> ----Appellant<lb/> Versus<lb/> 1. Bastar Railway Private Limited Through Chief Executive<lb/> Officer Bastar Railway Private Limited Global Exploration<lb/> Centre, NMDC Green Valley City, Housing Board Colony,<lb/> Boriyakala, Raipur, District Raipur Chhattisgarh.<lb/></p>

			<p>2. State of Chhattisgarh Through The Secretary To The<lb/> Government of Chhattisgarh Department of Revenue and<lb/> Disaster Management: Mahanadi Bhawan, Atal Nagar,<lb/> Raipur, District-Raipur Chhattisgarh.<lb/></p>

			<p>3. Union of India Through The Secretary to the Department of<lb/> Railway, Raisina Road, Rail Bhawan, 1, New Delhi<lb/> 4. The Commissioner-Cum-Arbitrator Bastar Division, Bastar<lb/> District Bastar Chhattisgarh.<lb/></p>

			<p>5. The Collector Jagdalpur, District Bastar Chhattisgarh.<lb/></p>

			<p>6. Additional Collector-cum-Land Acquisition Officer /<lb/> Competent Authority Bastar, District-Bastar Chhattisgarh.<lb/></p>

			<p>7. Bali Nagwanshi, S/o Shri Buter Nagwanshi, R/o Sun City,<lb/> Jagdalpur Chhattisgarh.<lb/></p>

			<p>8. Smt. Pakli, W/o Shri Maniram, R/o Palli Village, Jagdalpur<lb/> Chhattisgarh.<lb/></p>

			<p>9. Nitya Gopal, S/o Shitij Chand, R/o Reena Village Kangoli,<lb/> District Bastar Chhattisgarh.<lb/></p>

			<p>10. Seema Rathi, W/o Shri Ajay Rathi, R/o Village-Palli,<lb/> Jagdalpur , District-Bastar, Chhattisgarh.<lb/></p>

			<head>----Respondents<lb/></head>

			<p>4. Station House Officer, Police Station Jagdalpur, District<lb/> Jagdalpur Chhattisgarh.<lb/> ----Respondents<lb/> WA No. 119 of 2022<lb/> 1. Suresh B. Matali, S/o Shri B.S. Matali, Aged About 52 Years<lb/> Addl. General Manager (Civil), R/o House No. 10, Aashoka<lb/> Lifestyle, Dharampura-3, Police Station City Kotwali,<lb/> Jagdalpur, District Bastar Chhattisgarh. Permanent R/o<lb/> H.No.-MIG-39, Jalanagar, Vijayapura, 586101, Karnatka,<lb/> 2. A.V.R. Murty, S/o Shri A. Krishna Murty, Aged About 54<lb/> Years, Joint General Manager (Civil), R/o House No. 69,<lb/> Ashoka Lifestyle, Dharampura-3, Police Station City Kotwali,<lb/> Jagdalpur, District Bastar Chhattisgarh. Permanent R/o<lb/> H/No. 12-2-16/2, Chinna Veedhi, Samalkot, 533440, East<lb/> Godawari District, Andhra Pradesh.<lb/> ----Appellants<lb/> Versus<lb/> 1. State of Chhattisgarh, Through The Secretary to the<lb/> Government of Chhattisgarh Department of Revenue and<lb/> Disaster Management Mahanadi Bhawan, Atal Nagar,<lb/> Raipur District Raipur Chhattisgarh.<lb/></p>

			<p>2. Union of India Through The Secretary to the Department of<lb/> Railway, Raisina Road, Rail Bhawan, 1, New Delhi, District<lb/> New Delhi, Delhi.<lb/></p>

			<p>3. The Collector Jagadalpur, District Bastar, Chhattisgarh.<lb/></p>

			<item>4. Station House Officer, Police Station Jagdalpur, District-<lb/>Bastar, Chhattisgarh.<lb/> ----Respondents<lb/></item>

			<item>(Cause-title taken from Case Information System)<lb/> _________________________________________________<lb/></item>

			<item>For Appellants<lb/> : Heard Mr. Prashant Bhushan, learned<lb/> senior<lb/> counsel<lb/> (through<lb/> video-<lb/>conferencing) assisted by Mr. Amit<lb/> Verma, learned counsel, appearing for the<lb/> appellant in WA No. 81/2022 and WA No.<lb/> 64/2022, Mr. Anurag Dayal Shrivastava,<lb/> learned counsel, appearing for the<lb/> appellant, in WA No. 77/2022, 83/2022<lb/> and 129/2022, Mr. Siddharth Shukla,<lb/> learned counsel, appearing for the<lb/> appellant in WA No. 115/2022, Mr. Arvind<lb/> Shrivastava, learned counsel, appearing<lb/> for the appellant, in WA No. 119/2022, Mr.<lb/> Varun<lb/> Sharma,<lb/> learned<lb/> counsel,<lb/> appearing for the appellants, in WA No.<lb/> 144/2022.<lb/></item>

			<p>For Respondents<lb/> : Mr. Vikas Singh, learned senior counsel<lb/> (through video-conferencing), assisted by<lb/> Mr. Vaibhav Shukla, Mr. Ujjwal Choubey<lb/> and Mr. Chandradeep Prasad, learned<lb/> counsel, appearing for the respondent-<lb/>Bastar Railway Private Limited, Ms. Astha<lb/> Shukla, learned Government Advocate<lb/> and Mr. Vikram Sharma, learned Deputy<lb/> Government Advocate for the State and<lb/> Mr. Ramakant Mishra, learned Assistant<lb/> Solicitor General for the Union of India.<lb/> Date of hearing<lb/> : 13-05-2022<lb/> Date of Judgment<lb/> : 28-06-2022<lb/> Hon&apos;ble Shri Arup Kumar Goswami, Chief Justice<lb/> Hon&apos;ble Shri Rajendra Chandra Singh Samant, Judge<lb/> C.A.V. Judgment<lb/> Per R.C.S. Samant, J.<lb/></p>

			<p>1.<lb/> Writ Appeal No.64/2022 has been preferred challenging the<lb/> order dated 10.01.2022 passed in Writ Petition(Civil) No.<lb/> 3355/2019 by which the petition was allowed and the award<lb/> dated 12.02.2018 passed by the Competent Authority and<lb/> the Arbitration Award passed by the Commissioner,<lb/> Jagdalpur dated 11.7.2019 were set aside.<lb/> Writ Appeal No.81/2022 has been preferred against<lb/> the order dated 10.1.2022 in Writ Petition(Cr.)<lb/> No.1031/2019. Writ Appeal No.81/2022 is preferred against<lb/> the same order by which the order dated 10.1.2022 in WPC<lb/> No.3355/2019 has been challenged.<lb/> In Writ Appeal No.119/2022 the order of Single Bench<lb/> in Writ Petition(Cr.)No.828/2019 passed on 10.1.2022,<lb/> dismissing the petition is under challenge.<lb/> In Writ Appeal No.144/2022 the order of Single Bench<lb/> dated 10.1.2022 dismissing the Writ Petition(Cr.)<lb/> No.1096/2019 has been challenged.<lb/> Writ Appeal No.129/2022 has been preferred against<lb/> the same order dated 10.1.2022 by which the Writ<lb/> Petition(Cr.) No.674/2019 preferred by the appellants, was<lb/> dismissed.<lb/> Writ Appeal No.83/2022 has been preferred by the<lb/> appellants against the order dated 10.1.2022 of Single<lb/> Bench dismissing the Writ Petition(Cr.) No.751/2019.<lb/> Writ Appeal No.115/2022 has been preferred against<lb/> the order dated 10.1.2022 of Single Bench by which the Writ<lb/> Petition(Cr.) No.1037/2019 has been dismissed.<lb/> Writ Appeal No.77/2022 has been preferred against<lb/> the judgment dated 10.1.2022 by which the Writ<lb/> Petition(Civil) No.3355/2019, was allowed.<lb/></p>

			<p>2.<lb/> A project for construction of single railway line of length of<lb/> 140km named as Rowghat, Jagdalpur broad-gauge single<lb/> railway line was declared as Special Railway Project by<lb/> Gazette Notification dated 4.4.2016. For execution of this<lb/> railway project, 1863 hectares of land was proposed to be<lb/> acquired, out of which 140.233 hectares were private lands.<lb/> A notification dated 21.8.2017 was issued under Section 20A<lb/> of the Railways Act, 1989 (for short &apos;the Act, 1989&apos;), by the<lb/> competent authority declaring the intention to acquire the<lb/> lands for the execution of the Special Railway Project. After<lb/> granting time for objections, the notification for acquisition of<lb/> lands was issued under Section 20E of the Act, 1989, on<lb/> 21.12.2017. The appellants in Writ Appeal No.64/2022,<lb/> 81/2022, 77/2022 and 83/2022 were the land owners, whose<lb/> land was situated in Village-Palli. They were the affected<lb/> persons as their lands were acquired for this Special<lb/> Railway Project. The Additional Collector District-<lb/>Bastar/Competent Authority, proceeded for determination of<lb/> the award in application No.34/2017 and passed the award<lb/> date 12.2.2018 granting compensation of Rs.188.83 crores.<lb/> Khasra No.123/1 of area 7000 sq. meter and khasra<lb/> No.123/2 of area 19900 sq.meter was acquired from<lb/> appellant Bali Nagwanshi. Plot bearing Khasra No.125/1 to<lb/> 125/29, 125/31, 125/33 to 125/37, which were plots situated<lb/> in the colony developed in the name of &quot;Neelima Spandan&quot;<lb/> were also acquired for this project. Compensation for land<lb/> acquired from Bali Nagwanshi was determined as 70.62<lb/> Crores for the total area of the land which was acquired<lb/> being 2.69 hectares. Similarly, the compensation was<lb/> determined in favor of appellant Neelima Belsariya to the<lb/> tune of Rs.25.19 Crores for the total area of the land which<lb/> was acquired being 1.040 hectares.<lb/></p>

			<p>3.<lb/> Appellant Bali Nagwanshi in WA No.81/2022 &amp; 64/2022, not<lb/> being satisfied with the compensation determined, preferred<lb/> arbitration reference before the Commissioner, Bastar<lb/> Division, on which vide order dated 11.7.2019, the<lb/> Arbitration Award was given, by enhancing the<lb/> compensation and granting additional amount of<lb/> Rs.7,79,04,091/-.<lb/></p>

			<p>4.<lb/> The arbitration reference was also made by appellant-<lb/>Neelima Belsariya in WA No.83/2022 &amp; 77/2022 before<lb/> Additional Commissioner, Bastar Division, which was<lb/> decided by order dated 11.7.2019 and she got an<lb/> enhancement of Rs.98,39,610/-.<lb/></p>

			<p>5.<lb/> The Collector District-Bastar took cognizance of a news item<lb/> published in daily newspaper-Navbharat dated 19.7.2019<lb/> about discrepancies and scam in the acquisition matter and<lb/> he constituted a Committee of three members to inquire into<lb/> the matter.<lb/></p>

			<p>6.<lb/> The Committee made an inquiry and submitted a report. The<lb/> Collector District-Bastar, by a memo dated 30.7.2019, by<lb/> relying upon the report of the Committee, came to the<lb/> conclusion that the determination of compensation by the<lb/> Competent Authority and the Arbitrator was erroneous and<lb/> that the Railway Officials, the then Additional Collector, SDM<lb/> and others were involved in the conspiracy for determination<lb/> of huge compensation in favor of Bali Nagwanshi and<lb/> Neelima Belsariya beyond their entitlement and on this<lb/> basis, he directed lodging of FIR. The FIR was lodged as<lb/> Crime No.409/2019 against the Dharmnarayan Sahu<lb/> (Patwari), Arjun<lb/> Shrivastava<lb/> (Revenue<lb/> Inspector),<lb/> Deendayal Mandavi (Tahsildar), Siyaram Kurre (SDO,<lb/> Revenue), Heeralal Nayak (Additional Collector cum<lb/> Competent Authority), Kaushal Thakur (in-charge sub-<lb/>Registrar), Officer from IRCON Suresh B. Mitali, Officer from<lb/> IRCON A.R. Murthy, Range Officer G.R. Rao, Bali<lb/> Nagwanshi and Neellima Belsariya. Various writ petitions<lb/> have been disposed off by the Single Bench by the<lb/> impugned order and they are the appellants before this<lb/> Court in their respective writ appeals.<lb/></p>

			<p>7. The petitioners in Writ Petition(Cr.) 674/2019 Siyaram and<lb/> others are the Revenue Officers. The petitioners in Writ<lb/> Petition(Cr.) No.1027/2019, Heeralal Nayak was Competent<lb/> Authority, the petitioner in Writ Petition(Cr.) No.1096/2019<lb/> Kaushal Kumar Thakur was the Clerk/In-Charge of Sub-<lb/>Registrar Office, Neelima Belsariya and one another<lb/> petitioner in Writ Petition(Cr.) No.97/2019. Neelima Belsariya<lb/> again the petitioner in Writ Petition(Cr.) No.751/2019, Bali<lb/> Nagwanshi the petitioner in Writ Petition(Cr.) No.1031/2019<lb/> and Suresh B. Mitali and another petitioner in Writ<lb/> Petition(Cr.) No.828/2019 had preferred the writ petitions<lb/> praying for quashment of the FIR lodged against them. The<lb/> Bastar Railway Pvt. Ltd. (for short &apos;BRPL&apos;), petitioner in Writ<lb/> Petition(Civil) No.3355/2019 had preferred the petition<lb/> praying for quashment of the compensation award of the<lb/> Competent Authority and also the Arbitration Award given by<lb/> the Arbitrator / Commissioner, Bastar Division. The learned<lb/> Single Bench has by the detailed order allowed the Writ<lb/> Petition(Civil) No.3355/2019, by setting aside the Award<lb/> passed by the Competent Authority dated 12.2.2018 and by<lb/> the Commissioner dated 11.7.2019. All the other writ<lb/> petitions(criminal) preferred were dismissed.<lb/></p>

			<p>8.<lb/> Mr. Prashant Bhushan, learned counsel for the petitioner Bali<lb/> Nagwanshi submits, that Writ Petition(Civil) No.3355/2019<lb/> was not maintainable, as there was remedy available under<lb/> Section 34 of the Arbitration and Conciliation Act, 1996., (for<lb/> short, &apos;the Act, 1996&apos;). Such an application has also been<lb/> preferred by the respondent Bastar Railway Pvt. Ltd, before<lb/> the Court of District Judge, Bastar. Hence, the petition was<lb/> not maintainable on this ground. It is further submitted, that<lb/> according to the reliefs that were claimed by the petitioner<lb/> BRPL in Writ Petition(Civil) No.3355/2019, initially, the<lb/> petition was not maintainable. An application for amendment<lb/> was filed by which additional relief, which was prayer for<lb/> setting aside the award dated 11.7.2019 passed by the<lb/> Commissioner was allowed at the final hearing stage and<lb/> then the same relief was granted to the petitioner BRPL. It<lb/> is further submitted that after filing of an application under<lb/> Section 34 of the Act, 1996, such a prayer for setting aside<lb/> the Award of the Arbitrator under Article 226 Constitution<lb/> was not maintainable. Reliance was placed on judgment of<lb/> Supreme Court in SBP &amp; Co. Vs. Patel Engg. Ltd.,<lb/> reported in (2005) 8 SCC 618 and Haryana Urban<lb/> Development Authority, Karnal Vs. Mehta Construction<lb/> Company, reported in 2022 SCC OnLine SC 396. This<lb/> objection was raised by the petitioner side, but the same<lb/> was not decided. Hence, the order allowing the Writ<lb/> Petition(Civil) No.3355/2019, is erroneous. The learned<lb/> Single Judge has made an erroneous mention in the<lb/> paragraph No. 117 of the impugned order, that no one has<lb/> raised objection about maintainability of the writ petition at<lb/> the initial stage, which is not a correct statement and hence,<lb/> the order of the learned Single Bench in Writ Petition(Civil)<lb/> No.3355/2019, is liable to be set aside.<lb/></p>

			<p>9.<lb/> It is submitted by Mr. Prashant Bhushan, learned counsel for<lb/> the petitioner, that the land of the petitioner Bali Nagwanshi<lb/> that was acquired was urban land, which was situated<lb/> adjacent to the main road and the compensation was<lb/> determined in accordance with guidelines of 2017-2018, by<lb/> the Inspector General Registrar and Superintendent(Stamp),<lb/> Raipur. There was provision of compensation in accordance<lb/> with per square meter market value of the plot situated<lb/> within the depth of 20 meters from the main road and<lb/> accordingly, compensation was determined by the<lb/> Competent Authority and was enhanced by the<lb/> Commissioner, Bastar Division / Arbitrator.<lb/></p>

			<p>10. The guidelines of 2017-2018 specifically mentions in Serial<lb/> No.34 &amp; 37, that for the land situated on the way from MGM<lb/> School to Palli Naka, the compensation was to be<lb/> determined at the rate of Rs.13,800/-per sq. meter, for such<lb/> lands which are situated within the 20 meters depth from the<lb/> main road.<lb/></p>

			<p>11. By the Government Notification dated 2.7.2014, the State<lb/> Government determined the Extent of Wards of Nagar<lb/> Nigam, Jagdalpur. According to the Schedule, the Serial<lb/> No.37 mentions of Lokmanya Tilak Ward, which includes the<lb/> Palli area. In the details of the Ward No.37, there is mention<lb/> of Palli Naka. Clause No.10 of the guidelines itself mentions,<lb/> that the urban residential area which is situated adjacent the<lb/> main road, being used for Commercial/Industrial purpose for<lb/> that, the market price was to be calculated at the enhanced<lb/> rate upto 25% of the compensation for that area. Clause<lb/> No.11 further provides, that the locality/colony/route in the<lb/> urban area, which has been shown in the guidelines, in that<lb/> place, the market price will be calculated according to the<lb/> rate of the locality/colony/route, which has been followed in<lb/> determining the compensation. It is submitted that the<lb/> Collector is bound to follow the provision under Section 26 of<lb/> the Right to Fair Compensation and Transparency in Land<lb/> Acquisition, Rehabilitation and Resettlement Act, 2013 (for<lb/> short, &apos;the Act, 2013&apos;) and, therefore, there is no error<lb/> committed by the Competent Authority, in determining the<lb/> compensation and, further, the Commissioner also has not<lb/> committed any error in enhancing the compensation in favor<lb/> of the appellant Bali Nagwanshi. The Award of the<lb/> Competent Authority and the Arbitrator both are sustainable.<lb/> The land that had been acquired by the respondent<lb/> authorities was purchased by the petitioner Bali Nagwanshi<lb/> about nine years prior to its acquisition. On these grounds,<lb/> the impugned order is challenged and he contends that the<lb/> FIR is baseless and vexatious.<lb/></p>

			<p>12. Mr. Anurag Dayal Shrivastava, learned counsel in Writ<lb/> Appeal No.77/2022, 129/2022 &amp; 83/2022 submits, that Writ<lb/> Petition(Civil) No.3355/2019 was not maintainable as it was<lb/> based only on the report of the Collector. The Collector has<lb/> no authority to inquire into the matter under the provisions of<lb/> the Act, 1989. The whole procedure of acquisition has taken<lb/> place under the provisions of the Act, 1989. The Additional<lb/> Collector was notified as Competent Authority. The<lb/> notification dated 21.8.2007 issued under Section 20A of the<lb/> Act, 1989, can neither be challenged in any Court nor can it<lb/> be examined by a Criminal Court. It is submitted that the<lb/> petitioners filed a Writ Petition(Civil) No.3355/2019 after long<lb/> delay and hence it was not maintainable. On the basis of the<lb/> prayer clause which was initially present the petition was not<lb/> maintainable. The learned Single Bench has allowed the<lb/> amendment in prayer clause, which was included later on,<lb/> regarding which the objection was raised, that when an<lb/> application under Section 34 of the Act, 1996, was pending,<lb/> prayer for setting aside the award of the arbitrator should not<lb/> have been entertained by this Court in the writ petition.<lb/> Hence, the order of Single Bench in Writ Petition(Civil)<lb/> No.3355/2019 is not sustainable.<lb/></p>

			<p>13. It is further submitted by Mr. Shrivastava, learned counsel<lb/> that the land belonging to the appellant-Neelima Belsaria<lb/> was urban land situated in Ward No.37 and there was a<lb/> diversion order for the same regarding land use. This land<lb/> was present in the colony developed and styled as &quot;Neelima<lb/> Spandan&quot;. The State Government had passed the order<lb/> restraining transfer/ sale of land in the project area for the<lb/> Railway construction. The appellant-Neelima Belsaria had<lb/> challenged this order in Writ Petition(227) No.238/2012<lb/> which was disposed off on 07.08.2014 by the learned Single<lb/> Judge partly allowing the petition. It was held in that order<lb/> that the diversion for the land use was just and proper and in<lb/> accordance with law.<lb/> He endorses the submissions made by the learned<lb/> counsel for Bali Nagwanshi, that the land in question is<lb/> situated in the urban area under the municipal limits of<lb/> Municipal<lb/> Corporation,<lb/> Jagdalpur.<lb/> Therefore,<lb/> the<lb/> determination of compensation as per the guidelines, was<lb/> proper. It is again submitted that in the Collector report,<lb/> suspicion has been raised on the notification itself regarding<lb/> which the Collector has no authority or jurisdiction and,<lb/> therefore, the notification concerned cannot be examined by<lb/> a criminal Court. Hence, the order in Writ Petition(Civil)<lb/> No.3355/2019 is not sustainable and also the FIR lodged<lb/> against the petitioner is liable to be quashed.<lb/></p>

			<p>14. Mr. Arvind Shrivastava, learned counsel in Writ Appeal<lb/> no.119/2022 submits, that the appellants are not the<lb/> employees of Bastar Railway Private Limited. They are<lb/> employees of the IRCON International Limited(Government<lb/> of India undertaking under the Ministry of Railways). These<lb/> appellants have nothing to do with the acquisition process or<lb/> determination of compensation. There had been no<lb/> involvement of these appellants in whatsoever manner. In<lb/> the FIR lodged, the offence under Section 109 of IPC has<lb/> been added to show a conspiracy and that these appellants<lb/> were the part of the conspiracy. It is submitted that the<lb/> proposal for construction of Railway Station in Palli, was not<lb/> given by these appellants. In the report of the Collector<lb/> dated 30.7.2019, it is mentioned in Clause F , that there is<lb/> requirement for inquiry by Competent Railway Authorities,<lb/> regarding the involvement of Railway Officers and necessity<lb/> of criminal action against them. Therefore, it was not a<lb/> recommendation for making any inquiry against the<lb/> appellants, who are not the railway employees. The learned<lb/> Single Bench has very cursorily decided this point raised by<lb/> the appellants/petitioners holding, that the ground raised<lb/> cannot be examined by the Writ Court, which is erroneous,<lb/> therefore, the appellants in this case are entitled for grant of<lb/> relief as prayed in this writ appeal.<lb/></p>

			<p>15. Mr. Varun Sharma, learned counsel for the appellant in Writ<lb/> Appeal No.144/2022 submits, that the appellant in this case<lb/> was Registration Clerk and his only role was to provide the<lb/> calculation sheet as per the guidelines, which was laid down<lb/> under the provisions of Stamp Act. A departmental action<lb/> was initiated against this appellant which was withdrawn<lb/> later on. It is further submitted that under Section 186 of the<lb/> Act, 1989, immunity has been granted to the public servant<lb/> under which this appellant is also protected, hence, the<lb/> lodging of FIR against him was liable to be quashed, it is<lb/> prayed that this writ appeal be allowed and relief be granted.<lb/></p>

			<p>16. Mr. Siddharth Shukla, learned counsel for the appellant in<lb/> Writ Appeal No.115/2022 submits, that the appellant in this<lb/> case was the Competent Authority and he has not played<lb/> any role in the said conspiracy as alleged in the Collector&apos;s<lb/> report. The award was passed on the basis of the<lb/> documents that were supplied, which included the guidelines<lb/> of 2017-2018. The appellant has performed his duty strictly<lb/> in accordance with law. Therefore, there is no criminality<lb/> present on the part of this appellant. The learned Single<lb/> Judge has erred in holding, that the case requires<lb/> investigation. Whereas the FIR lodged was liable to be<lb/> quashed, hence, it is prayed that this writ appeal be allowed<lb/> and the appellant may be granted relief as prayed.<lb/></p>

			<p>17. Ms. Astha Shukla, learned State counsel, representing State<lb/> of Chhattisgarh, Collector, Bastar and the S.H.O. of the<lb/> Police Station, Kotwali, Jagdalpur, submits that the Collector<lb/> had the authority to make an inquiry into the allegation of<lb/> corruption and fraud, in determination of compensation by<lb/> the concerned authority and also against the persons hugely<lb/> benefited, without there being any entitlement of them. As<lb/> soon as the matter came to the notice of Collector from the<lb/> news reports published regarding large scale irregularity and<lb/> illegality committed in land acquisition proceeding for Bastar<lb/> Railway project, inquiry has been ordered and on the basis<lb/> of the inquiry report the F.I.R. has been lodged. The learned<lb/> Single Judge has very correctly held that Collector is<lb/> competent to make such an inquiry and that the lodging of<lb/> F.I.R. is a correct step taken. It is further submitted that the<lb/> land belonging to the appellant Bali Nagwanshi and Neelima<lb/> Belsariya was clearly situated in the rural areas, which has<lb/> been erroneously considered as urban area for determining<lb/> enhanced compensation in favour of these appellants,<lb/> therefore, there is no error in the impugned order passed by<lb/> the learned Single Judge. Therefore, all the Writ Appeals are<lb/> liable to be dismissed.<lb/></p>

			<p>18. Shri Vikas Singh, learned Senior Counsel for respondent<lb/> BRPL, firstly submits on the ground of maintainability of<lb/> WPC No.3355/2019, that the High Court is empowered<lb/> under Article 226 of the Constitution to entertain the petition<lb/> regarding which he has placed reliance on the judgments of<lb/> Hon&apos;ble the Supreme Court in the cases of Andi Mukta<lb/> Sadguru Shree Muktajee Vandas Swami Suvarna Jayanti<lb/> Mahotsav Smarak Trust Vs. V.R. Rudani, (1989) 2 SCC<lb/> 691, PRP Exports &amp; Ors. Vs. Chief Secretary,<lb/> Government of Tamil Nadu &amp; Ors., (2014) 13 SCC 692,<lb/> State of U.P. Vs. Mahindra &amp; Mahindra Ltd., (2011) 13<lb/> SCC 77. It is submitted that it is a case of large scale<lb/> corruption and huge discrepancy in the determination of the<lb/> compensation in the acquisition process. Therefore, it is an<lb/> exceptional case which was required to be challenged under<lb/> Article 226 of the Constitution of India. Therefore, invoking of<lb/> Section 34 of the Act, 1996 is not adequate remedy. It is<lb/> further submitted that at the time of filing of WPC<lb/> No.3355/2019 on 12-09-2019, no proceeding was initiated<lb/> under Section 34 of the Act, 1996. However, an application<lb/> under Section 34 of the Act, 1996 had been filed on 18-02-<lb/>2021, which is not yet registered by the court concerned.<lb/> Hence, it is only under Article 226 of the Constitution, the<lb/> efficacious remedy can be sought. Hence, for these reasons<lb/> WPC No.3355/2019 was maintainable and the question of<lb/> maintainability has been correctly decided by the learned<lb/> Single Bench.<lb/></p>

			<p>19. Countering the submissions made by learned counsel for the<lb/> appellants it is submitted that the acquired lands are situated<lb/> in village Palli which is a panchayat area and is not notified<lb/> so far as municipal area. The last notification including<lb/> villages in the limits of the municipal council Jagdalpur of<lb/> Bastar District is dated 03-09-2002, by which Village Palli<lb/> was not included as the municipal area. Claim of the<lb/> appellants that village Palli is included in the Ward No.37,<lb/> that is Lokmanya Tilak ward, is without any basis. The<lb/> description of the Ward No.37 Lokmanya Tilak ward<lb/> mentions that the western boundary of the ward is shared<lb/> with the eastern boundary of Village Palli. The description of<lb/> northern boundary mentioning Palli Naka is not to be<lb/> understood as Palli Village. It is further submitted that the<lb/> appellants, namely, Bali Nagwanshi and Neelima Belsaria<lb/> have made purchase of agricultural lands, regarding which<lb/> description of area given is in hectares and the stamp duty<lb/> was affixed accordingly. There is no notification present<lb/> under Section 5(A) of the Chhattisgarh Municipalities Act,<lb/> 1961 (for short &apos;the Act, 1961) for inclusion of Village-Palli<lb/> as municipal area. The notification dated 22-07-2014 on<lb/> which the appellants&apos; side is placing reliance was issued<lb/> under Section 29(1) of the Act, 1961 only for the election<lb/> purposes and no inference can be drawn that villages<lb/> included in the extension of ward under Section 29 of the<lb/> Act, 1961 are municipal areas. The last notification for the<lb/> inclusion in municipal areas was dated 03-09-2002. It is<lb/> further submitted that by notification dated 21-07-2014,<lb/> Gram Panchayat area has been constituted by the State of<lb/> Chhattisgarh (C.G.) in which serial No.23 shows, that Gram<lb/> Panchayat Kumhraband includes Village Palli, which<lb/> confirms that Village Palli is a notified Gram Panchayat area.<lb/></p>

			<p>The guidelines of 2017-18 issued by the IG and<lb/> Superintendent of Stamps, C.G. very clearly shows Village<lb/> Palli was an area for which determination of market price of<lb/> agricultural lands was to be done on hectare basis and not<lb/> on the basis of per square meter. It is submitted that land<lb/> acquisition was made from 9 other persons apart from the<lb/> petitioners/appellants Bali Nagwanshi and Neelima Belsaria<lb/> and the compensation for their land has been determined on<lb/> hectare basis, whereas, the compensation of lands<lb/> belonging to Bali Nagwanshi and Neelima Belsaria has been<lb/> determined on per square meter basis, which shows gross<lb/> irregularity committed to bestow undue favour to them as<lb/> also the conspiracy involved.<lb/></p>

			<p>20. It is submitted that in the order passed by the competent<lb/> authority dated 12-02-2018, it is mentioned in paragraph 4<lb/> that claim of Bali Nagwanshi regarding assessment of<lb/> compensation at enhanced rate was accepted, whereas,<lb/> claim of other three claimants, namely, Paramjeet Jaswal,<lb/> Onkar Singh and Mohd. Abu Natik were rejected and then<lb/> the Commissioner by following the same guidelines has<lb/> ordered for enhancement of the compensation. Whereas,<lb/> the similarly placed other land oustees have not been<lb/> compensated on equal terms. Hence, it is clearly a case of<lb/> fraud, which was committed through a conspiracy hatched<lb/> between appellants Bali Nagwanshi and Neelima Belsaria<lb/> and the officials involved in determination of the<lb/> compensation. It is submitted that learned Single Bench has<lb/> noticed fraud and mentioned about the same in the<lb/> impugned order.<lb/></p>

			<p>21. It is submitted that the Collector has jurisdiction and power to<lb/> inquire into the allegations of corruption, fraud etc. There is<lb/> clear case of violation of the guidelines present and also that<lb/> the land situated in village panchayat area has been<lb/> deliberately shown to be in the municipal area, for the<lb/> purpose of benefiting only two of the land oustees, which<lb/> clearly indicates commission of offences which are required<lb/> to be inquired and accordingly inquiry has been done and<lb/> acted upon. Hence, the award dated 12-02-2018 by the<lb/> competent authority and dated 11-07-2019 by the<lb/> Commissioner are non-est and void being vitiated by fraud<lb/> and criminal conspiracy. Reliance has been placed on the<lb/> judgments of Hon&apos;ble the Supreme Court in the cases of S.P.<lb/> Chengalvaraya Naidu Vs. Jagannath, (1994) 1 SCC 1,<lb/> Bhaurao Dagdu Paralkar Vs. State of Maharashtra,<lb/> (2005) 7 SCC 605, State of U.P. and others Vs. Ravindra<lb/> Kumar Sharma and others, (2016) 4 SCC 791 and<lb/> Rameshwar Vs. State of Haryana, (2018) 6 SCC 215.<lb/> It is also submitted that subsequent events can be<lb/> taken into consideration by a writ Court, regarding which<lb/> reliance has been placed on the judgment of Hon&apos;ble the<lb/> Supreme Court in the case of State of U.P. Vs. Mahindra &amp;<lb/> Mahindra Ltd., (2011) 13 SCC 77.<lb/> It is submitted that in the peculiar circumstances of the<lb/> case, the writ is maintainable even if there exists any<lb/> alternative remedy, as has been held in the case of<lb/> Whirlpool Corpn. Vs. Registrar of Trade Marks, (1998) 8<lb/> SCC 1.<lb/> It is submitted by learned Senior Counsel that the writ<lb/> appeals are not fit to be entertained, therefore, the same<lb/> may be dismissed and also the interim protection granted by<lb/> learned Single Judge may be quashed.<lb/></p>

			<p>22.<lb/> Shri Prashant Bhushan learned counsel for appellant Bali<lb/> Nagwanshi submits in rebuttal, that the notification dated 02-<lb/>07-2014 is not meant only for elections. The boundaries and<lb/> areas are very clearly defined with respect to ward No.37,<lb/> Lokmanya Tilak ward. It starts from Palli Naka via<lb/> Dharampura No.2 via Shankar Mandir upto Urwasshi<lb/> Pandey&apos;s house in the North and mentions starting from<lb/> Shankar Mandir Narmunda via Rajat Jainti Kangoli via B.M.<lb/> cold storage upto Palli Naka. Village Palli is situated well<lb/> within this area. The land belonging to appellant Bali<lb/> Nagwanshi is adjacent to the road leading from MGM school<lb/> to Palli Naka. It is on this basis the competent authority has<lb/> calculated the compensation and enhancement of 25% was<lb/> given according to the guidelines present. Therefore, on the<lb/> basis of the notification dated 02-07-2014, it can be<lb/> assumed that land belonging to appellant Bali Nagwanshi<lb/> was urban land and the assessment was to be done in<lb/> accordance with Section 20(G) of the Act, 1989 and Section<lb/> 26 of the Act, 2013, which has been done by the competent<lb/> authority and further enhancement has been granted by the<lb/> Commissioner. Therefore, the award of the compensation of<lb/> the competent authority and the Commissioner are<lb/> maintainable and lodging of the FIR against appellant Bali<lb/> Nagwanshi is baseless, which is liable to be quashed.<lb/></p>

			<p>23.<lb/> Shri Anurag Dayal Shrivastava, learned counsel for appellant<lb/> Neelima Belsaria submits in rebuttal, that the notification<lb/> under Section 29 of the Act, 1961 is not limited for the<lb/> purposes of elections only. The guidelines that has been<lb/> issued by the authorities is to be strictly applied and the<lb/> same has been applied accordingly, in determining the<lb/> compensation. The submission of the counsel for<lb/> respondents regarding conspiracy is totally baseless. In the<lb/> report given by the Collector, the planning regarding<lb/> construction of railway station has been assailed, which<lb/> could not have been assailed by the Collector. The<lb/> notification issued under Section 20(E) of the Act, 1989 has<lb/> resulted in the vesting of acquired lands with the Central<lb/> Government, which has not been challenged by the<lb/> respondent BRPL. The diversion and transfer of project in<lb/> the matter of construction of railway station at Palli has not<lb/> affected the original acquisition plan and the construction of<lb/> railway station only is not the reason for enhancement of the<lb/> compensation amount. As the lands acquired were in the<lb/> acquisition plan from the very beginning, therefore,<lb/> conspiracy theory as propounded by the respondent BRPL<lb/> finds no support. It is submitted that the lands that were<lb/> acquired from appellant Neelima Belsaria were diverted<lb/> plots regarding which the appellant has the confirmation<lb/> from the order of the High Court in WP227 No.238/2012.<lb/> Therefore, it was fit to be assessed for compensation at<lb/> market value per square meter. Respondent BRPL has not<lb/> challenged the guidelines of 2017-18.<lb/> It is submitted, that in the report of the Collector even<lb/> the grant of 12% interest has been considered as<lb/> conspiracy, whereas, the appellant has entitlement of such<lb/> interest on the compensation. Reliance has been placed on<lb/> the judgment in the matter of Union of India and another<lb/> Vs. Tarsem Singh and others, AIR 2019 SC 4689. It is<lb/> submitted that Section 20(F) (vi) and (vii) of the Act, 1989,<lb/> provide for remedy against the award passed, which shall be<lb/> by way of arbitration. Respondents BRPL has challenged<lb/> the award before the Court of District Judge. Relying on the<lb/> judgment of Hon&apos;ble the Supreme Court in matter of<lb/> Pradeep Singh Vs. State of U.P., 2010 (2) SCC 114, it is<lb/> submitted that in case of concealment of fact by a party the<lb/> relief claimed can be denied by the court. It is further<lb/> submitted that the Collector had constituted inquiry<lb/> committee of officers below the rank of the persons accused,<lb/> especially the Competent Authority who held the rank of<lb/> Addl. Collector. Further, the application under Section 34 of<lb/> the Act, 1996 has also been filed with delay, which is clearly<lb/> bared by limitation as held by Hon&apos;ble the Supreme Court in<lb/> the case of P. Radha Bai and others Vs. P. Ashok Kumar<lb/> and others, AIR (2018) SC 5013. Hence, there is no basis<lb/> or evidence of conspiracy present in the case. The prayer<lb/> made in the appeals filed by Neelima Belsaria are fit to be<lb/> allowed.<lb/></p>

			<p>24. Shri Siddharth Shukla, learned counsel for appellant in WA<lb/> No.115/2022 submits in rebuttal, that appellant Hira Lal<lb/> Nayak passed the initial award dated 12-02-2018 and then<lb/> he was transferred. Therefore, compensation amount was<lb/> neither deposited in his tenure nor was disbursed. The<lb/> calculation of the compensation was made on the basis of<lb/> the guidelines and also on the report submitted by the office<lb/> of the Sub-Registrar. This appellant has no part in<lb/> conspiracy as alleged. The lodging of the FIR against him is<lb/> unsustainable.<lb/></p>

			<p>25. Shri Arvind Shrivastava, learned counsel for appellants in<lb/> WA No.119/2022 submits in rebuttal, that railway station at<lb/> Palli was proposed by BRPL. The appellants in this appeal<lb/> had not played any part in the diversion of the railway<lb/> project. Therefore, the allegation regarding their participation<lb/> in the conspiracy is totally baseless.<lb/></p>

			<p>26. Shri Varun Sharma, learned counsel for appellant in WA<lb/> No.144/2022 submits in rebuttal, that the appellant in this<lb/> case was working as Registration Clerk and he had<lb/> proposed the calculations for making assessment of<lb/> compensation on the basis of the guidelines of 2017-18. The<lb/> spot inspection was conducted by Sub-Registrar, Jagdalpur<lb/> and it was reported by letter dated 03-01-2011 to the<lb/> appellant Neelima Belsaria, that her land is situated in<lb/> municipal area of Jagdalpur. Therefore, there is no<lb/> conspiracy at all and neither any offence has been<lb/> committed in this case. Therefore, the writ appeal filed by<lb/> this appellant is fit to be allowed.<lb/></p>

			<p>27. Mr. R.K. Mishra, learned Asst.S.G. for U.O.I. adopts the<lb/> arguments advanced by the learned counsel for respondent-<lb/>BRPL and learned State counsel and submits that all the<lb/> Writ Appeals are fit to be dismissed.<lb/></p>

			<p>28. Heard learned counsel for the parties and perused the<lb/> documents available on record of all the Writ Appeals.<lb/></p>

			<p>29. The appellants had challenged the report dated 30.07.2019<lb/> by the Collector, the lodging of F.I.R. dated 04.08.2019 by<lb/> Police Station, Kotwali, Jagdalpur and also the order of the<lb/> S.H.O. Police Station, Jagdalpur directing the respective<lb/> Banks to seize the bank accounts of the respective<lb/> appellants/petitioners. The learned Single Judge, framed<lb/> following questions for determination in paragraph 67 of the<lb/> impugned order / judgment:-<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot;67. In view of the above stated factual matrix,<lb/> following points required to be determined by this<lb/> Court are :-<lb/></item>

			<item>(1) Whether the Collector is competent to conduct<lb/> enquiry with regard to the project carried out by the<lb/> Central Government.<lb/></item>

			<item>(2) Whether the facts and grounds raised by the<lb/> petitioners can be examined by this Court at this<lb/> stage to quash the FIR.<lb/></item>

			<item>(3) If the charge-sheet and the suspension order<lb/> has already been revoked, then what is the effect<lb/> with regard to criminal proceedings initiated against<lb/> the petitioner in WPCR No.1096 of 2019.<lb/></item>

			<item>(4) Whether the State House Officer was justified in<lb/> issuing the notice dated 05.08.2019 for freezing the<lb/> bank account.&quot;<lb/></item>

			<p>30. The learned Single Judge has held in paragraph 75 of the<lb/> impugned judgment that the role, power and jurisdiction of<lb/> the Collector cannot be curtailed under any circumstances.<lb/> The Collector upon the receiving information from any<lb/> sources whatsoever about discrepancies in the land<lb/> acquisition proceedings, was well within his authority to<lb/> order for inquiry and direct lodging of F.I.R. with respect to<lb/> commission of cognizable offences. In view of the judgment<lb/> of Supreme Court in Lalita Kumari Vs. Government of<lb/> Uttar Pradesh &amp; Others reported in (2014) 2 SCC 1, held<lb/> that the report of Collector is the basis of the F.I.R. lodged<lb/> against the concerned and whatever ground taken by the<lb/> appellants/petitioners is their defence, which cannot be<lb/> adjudicated by the Writ Court.<lb/></p>

			<p>31. Relying on the judgment in the case of Kaptan singh Vs.<lb/> State of U.P. &amp; Others, reported in 2021 SCC OnLine SC<lb/> 580 and the judgment of Supreme Court in the case of State<lb/> of Odisha Vs. Pratima Mohanty, in Criminal Appeal<lb/> Nos.1455-1456/2021, decided on 11.12.2021, the learned<lb/> Single Bench has rejected the plea of the petitioners for<lb/> quashing the F.I.R. against them and held in paragraph<lb/> No.97 as follows:-<lb/></p>

			<p>&quot;97. In view of the above, Point No. 1 is decided<lb/> against the petitioner that the Collector is Competent<lb/> to conduct the enquiry with regard to the project<lb/> carried out by the Central Government and Point No.<lb/> 2 is also decided against the petitioners that the facts<lb/> and grounds raised by them cannot be examined by<lb/> this Court at this stage to quash the FIR.&quot;<lb/></p>

			<p>32. On the basis of the submissions of Kousal Kumar Thakur,<lb/> who is the petitioner in W.P.(Cr.) No.1096/2019 and<lb/> appellant in W.A. No.144/2022, the development in his<lb/> favour was examined and the point No.3 was decided in<lb/> paragraph No.100 of the impugned judgment which is as<lb/> follows:-<lb/></p>

			<p>&quot;100. From the above stated legal position and<lb/> considering the factual matrix of the case, this Court is<lb/> of the view that even though the departmental enquiry<lb/> has been closed, the FIR cannot be closed on this<lb/> count alone, as such, Point No.3 decided against the<lb/> petitioner.&quot;<lb/></p>

			<p>33. The Point No.4 regarding the authority of Station House<lb/> Officer to freeze the bank accounts was examined and by<lb/> placing reliance on the judgment of Supreme Court in the<lb/> case of Teesta Atul Setalvad Vs. State of Gujarat reported<lb/> in (2018) 2 SCC 372, it was held as follows in paragraph<lb/> 102:<lb/></p>

			<p>&quot;102. From the above stated facts and<lb/> circumstances of the case, it is crystal clear that in<lb/> such circumstances, the police officer can very well<lb/> seize the bank account which is a property as per<lb/> Section 102 of the Cr.P.C. Thus, the Point No.4<lb/> decides against the petitioner.&quot;<lb/></p>

			<p>34. W.P.C No.3355/2019 was separately considered and<lb/> allowed regarding which paragraph Nos.127, 128, 129 130<lb/> and 131 are relevant, which are as follows:-<lb/></p>

			<p>&quot;127.In view of the above stated legal position, it is<lb/> quite clear that the petitioner/BRPL is interested<lb/> person, as such, he should have been noticed by the<lb/> learned Arbitrator where the award was challenged by<lb/> respondent No. 7. Thus, the arbitration award passed<lb/> by the Commissioner is in violation of principle of<lb/> natural justice and is liable to be set aside by this<lb/> Court also.<lb/></p>

			<p>128. Accordingly, the award dated 12.02.2018 passed<lb/> by the Competent Authority and the award passed by<lb/> the Commissioner, Jagdalpur dated 11.07.2019 are<lb/> set aside. Resultantly WPC No. 3355 of 2019 is<lb/> allowed. In consequence, the learned Competent<lb/> Authority is directed to re-calculate the award after<lb/> considering the circular, guidelines and if required to<lb/> ascertain the factual matrix, he may direct for<lb/> recording of the evidence also while passing the<lb/> award. The exercise should be carried out within six<lb/> months from the date of receipt of copy of this order.<lb/> Considering the fact that this Court has granted<lb/> interim protection of no coercive steps in WPCR No.<lb/> 1031 of 2019 shall be continued till the award is<lb/> passed by the Competent Authority afresh subject to<lb/> condition that the petitioner/land losers whose lands<lb/> have been acquired or purported to be acquired shall<lb/> file an affidavit before the concerned Bank within a<lb/> period of one month from the date of receipt of copy<lb/> of this order for transfer of amount, which they have<lb/> received towards compensation within one month<lb/> from the date of receipt of copy of this order.<lb/> Thereafter, the Bank shall immediately transfer the<lb/> amount in account of the land acquisition officer, who<lb/> shall not disburse the amount till the award is finally<lb/> decided by the Competent Authority.<lb/></p>

			<p>129. The petitioners/land losers are also directed to<lb/> refund the amount of compensation, which has been<lb/> received by them in pursuance of award dated<lb/> 12.02.2018 passed by the Competent Authority. Their<lb/> entitlement of compensation and quantum will be<lb/> decided by the Competent Authority afresh, in<lb/> accordance with law giving opportunity of hearing to<lb/> Bastar Railway Private Limited and others.<lb/></p>

			<p>130. So far as the Government Officers are<lb/> concerned, they are also granted protection of no<lb/> coercive steps with a condition that they will mark<lb/> their presence before the Station House Officer,<lb/> Jagdalpur every month till the award is finally decided<lb/> by the Competent Authority and subsequent presence<lb/> will be dependable on final outcome of the award.<lb/></p>

			<p>131. With these observations and directions, WPCR<lb/> No. 674 of 2019, 979 of 2019, 1037 of 2019, 751 of<lb/> 2019, 828 of 2019, 1031 of 2019 &amp; 1096 of 2019 are<lb/> disposed of and WPC No. 3355 of 2019 is allowed.&quot;<lb/></p>

			<p>35. A point has been raised by the appellant side regarding the<lb/> maintainability of W.P.(C.) No.3355 of 2019. It was submitted<lb/> that the remedy was available under Section 34 of the Act,<lb/> 1996, therefore, the award of the Competent Authority and<lb/> that of the Commissioner was not subject to challenge in the<lb/> Writ Petition. During the arguments, it has been brought to<lb/> the notice of this Court, that at a later point of time, the<lb/> respondent BRPL has preferred an application under<lb/> Section 34 of the Act, 1996, but the same has not been<lb/> registered till date and further, the application has been filed<lb/> beyond the limitation period as provided under Section 34(3)<lb/> of the Act, 1996.<lb/></p>

			<p>36. The main contention of the respondent State, respondent-<lb/>BRPL and respondent-Union of India is this that the whole<lb/> process for determination of compensation was based on<lb/> fraud and criminal conspiracy, as out of numerous land<lb/> oustees, only two of them, namely, Bali Nagwanshi and<lb/> Neelima Belsariya have been benefited hugely and unjustly<lb/> in the matter of grant of compensation and enhancement in<lb/> compensation which is a windfall gain on their part. Whereas<lb/> rest of the land oustees, who were similarly situated, have<lb/> not been benefited in the similar fashion. Secondly, for the<lb/> purpose of determining compensation in favour of Bali<lb/> Nagwanshi and Neelima Belsariya, the land acquired from<lb/> them was considered as urban land, whereas those lands<lb/> are situated in rural area of village-Palli, which is a village<lb/> under the Gram Panchayat Kumravand. The determination<lb/> of compensation was further against the guidelines of 2017-<lb/>18. In the F.I.R. lodged, it is alleged that the Patwari-<lb/>Dharmnarayan Sahu, Revenue Inspector-Arjun Shrivastava<lb/> and Tehsildar Deen Dayal Mandavi had conspired and<lb/> manipulated the revenue records, by forging the entries for<lb/> the benefit of appellant Bali Nagwanshi and Neelima<lb/> Belsariya. There is allegation of involvement of Sub<lb/> Divisional Officer (Revenue) Siyaram Kurre, Clerk/In-charge<lb/> of Sub-registrar Office-Koushal Thakur, who provided the<lb/> calculation for compensation at the inflated rate, on which<lb/> basis the total 2.69 hectares belonging to Bali Nagwanshi<lb/> was compensated with the amount of Rs.70.6 crores,<lb/> whereas according to guidelines for rural area, the total<lb/> compensation should have been Rs.7.79 crores only and<lb/> similarly because of this conspiracy and on the basis<lb/> calculation at the inflated market rates, 1.04 hectare land<lb/> acquired from Neelima Belsariya was determined to be<lb/> compensated at Rs.25.19 crores, whereas according to the<lb/> guidelines for rural area, the compensation would have been<lb/> Rs.4.38 crores only. It is also alleged that the 25% additional<lb/> compensation has been granted showing the land belonging<lb/> to Bali Nagwanshi and Neelima Belsariya adjacent to the<lb/> road and also of commercial importance, whereas similarly<lb/> placed other land oustees have been compensated as per<lb/> the rural criteria. It is also alleged in the F.I.R. that the<lb/> calculation of the interest at the rate of 12% per annum is<lb/> illegal and against the provisions of the Act, 1989 and also<lb/> the Act, 2013.<lb/></p>

			<p>37. There are number of allegations present in the report of the<lb/> Collector, which is the basis of the lodging of the F.I.R.,<lb/> which are directed against the assessment of compensation<lb/> made in the land acquisition process. After passing of the<lb/> award by a Competent Authority and the enhancement of<lb/> award by the Commissioner and also deposit of the<lb/> compensation amount by the BRPL, inquiry was made by<lb/> the office of the Collector, the report was submitted and on<lb/> that basis, the F.I.R. has been lodged. Consequent to this<lb/> development, the petitioner-BRPL in W.P.C. No.3355/2019<lb/> has raised the ground, that the award passed by the<lb/> competent authority is null and void with respect to the<lb/> respondents Bali Nagwanshi and Neelima Belsariya and<lb/> others, as the award was illegally determined against the<lb/> provisions of law, against the guidelines for market price for<lb/> the year 2017-18 and that the determination of the<lb/> compensation in favour of the respective parties, who have<lb/> been illegally benefited is the result of commission of<lb/> offences regarding which, F.I.R. has been lodged.<lb/></p>

			<p>38. The petitioner in W.P.(C.) No.3355/2019 has challenged the<lb/> award by the competent authority dated 12.02.2018 on the<lb/> ground of illegality. Same ground of illegality has been raised<lb/> in challenging the award of the Commissioner dated<lb/> 11.07.2019. The main allegation being both the awards had<lb/> been the result of fraud committed by the concerned. In the<lb/> case of S.P. Chengalvaraya Naidu Vs. Jagannath (Supra),<lb/> it was held by the Supreme Court that the judgment and<lb/> decree obtained by playing fraud on the court was a nullity.<lb/> In the case of Bhaurao Dagdu Paralkar Vs. State of<lb/> Maharashtra and others (Supra), it was held that &quot;Fraud&quot;<lb/> as is well known vitiates every solemn act. Fraud and justice<lb/> never dwell together. It has been similarly held in the case of<lb/> State of U.P. and Others Vs. Ravindra Kumar Sharma<lb/> and Others (Supra) and Rameshwar Vs. State of Haryana<lb/> (Supra). Section 34 (2) of the Act, 1996 is relevant in this<lb/> case, which is as follows:-<lb/></p>

			<p>&quot;Section 34(2) in THE ARBITRATION AND<lb/> CONCILIATION ACT, 1996:-<lb/></p>

			<item>(2) An arbitral award may be set aside by the Court only if<lb/> -<lb/></item>

			<item>(a) the party making the application furnishes proof<lb/> that-<lb/></item>

			<item>(i) a party was under some incapacity, or<lb/></item>

			<item>(ii) the arbitration agreement is not valid under the law<lb/> to which the parties have subjected it or, failing any<lb/> indication thereon, under the law for the time being in<lb/> force; or<lb/></item>

			<item>(iii) the party making the application was not given<lb/> proper notice of the appointment of an arbitrator or of<lb/> the arbitral proceedings or was otherwise unable to<lb/> present his case; or<lb/></item>

			<p>(iv) the arbitral award deals with a dispute not<lb/> contemplated by or not falling within the terms of the<lb/> submission to arbitration, or it contains decisions on<lb/> matters beyond the scope of the submission to<lb/> arbitration:<lb/> Provided that, if the decisions on matters submitted to<lb/> arbitration can be separated from those not so<lb/> submitted, only that part of the arbitral award which<lb/> contains decisions on matters not submitted to<lb/> arbitration may be set aside; or<lb/></p>

			<item>(v) the composition of the arbitral tribunal or the arbitral<lb/> procedure was not in accordance with the agreement<lb/> of the parties, unless such agreement was in conflict<lb/> with a provision of this Part from which the parties<lb/> cannot derogate, or, failing such agreement, was not in<lb/> accordance with this Part; or<lb/></item>

			<item>(b) the Court finds that-<lb/></item>

			<item>(i) the subject-matter of the dispute is not capable of<lb/> settlement by arbitration under the law for the time<lb/> being in force, or<lb/></item>

			<p>(ii) the arbitral award is in conflict with the public policy<lb/> of India.<lb/></p>

			<p>39. On a plain reading of this provision under Section 34(2) of<lb/> the Act, 1996, it is revealed that fraud and conspiracy is not<lb/> one of the grounds present for challenging an arbitral award.<lb/> It was held in the case of Andi Mukta Sadguru Shree<lb/> Muktajee Vandas Swami Suvarna Jayanti Mahotsav<lb/> Smarak Trust Vs. V.R. Rudani (Supra) in paragraph No.17<lb/> and 19, which are as follows:-<lb/></p>

			<p>&quot;17.There, however, the prerogative writ of mandamus<lb/> is confined only to public authorities to compel<lb/> performance of public duty. The &apos;public authority&apos; for<lb/> them mean every body which is created by statute--<lb/>and whose powers and duties are defined by statue.<lb/> So Government departments, local authori-ties, police<lb/> authorities,<lb/> and<lb/> statutory<lb/> undertakings<lb/> and<lb/> corporations, are all &apos;public authorities&apos;. But there is no<lb/> such limitation for our High Courts to issue the writ &apos;in<lb/> the nature of mandamus&apos;. Article 226 confers wide<lb/> powers on the High Courts to issue writs in the nature<lb/> of prerogative writs. This is a striking departure from<lb/> the English law. Under Article 226, writs can be issued<lb/> to &quot;any person or authority&quot;. It can be issued &quot;for the<lb/> enforcement of any of the fundamental rights and for<lb/> any other purpose&quot;.<lb/></p>

			<p>40. In the case of State of U.P. Vs. M/s Mahindra &amp; Mahindra<lb/> Ltd. (Supra), it is held that the High Court can always take<lb/> notice of the subsequent events and developments that<lb/> have taken place after filing of the Writ Petition etc., which is<lb/> the case present here, that the application under Section 34<lb/> of Act, 1996 has been filed by the respondent BRPL before<lb/> the District Court, but the fact remains that the same<lb/> application is clearly time-barred, therefore, the said remedy<lb/> is no longer available to the respondent BRPL. On the other<lb/> hand, it has been amply discussed here-in-above that the<lb/> fact and scenario of the present case is totally different as<lb/> the respondent BRPL is claiming that the award dated<lb/> 12.02.2018 by the competent authority and the award dated<lb/> 11.07.2019 by the Commissioner are non-est and void being<lb/> vitiated by fraud and criminal conspiracy. Therefore, in such<lb/> a case, we are of the view that the Writ Petition Civil<lb/> No.3355 of 2019 was maintainable under Article 226 of<lb/> Constitution of India.<lb/> Reliance on the judgment in SBP &amp; Co. Vs. Patel<lb/> Engg. Ltd. (supra) and Haryana Urban Development<lb/> Authority, Karnal vs M/S. Mehta Construction Company<lb/> and another (supra) by the appellant side is distinguishable.<lb/> Similarly, the reliance of the appellant on the judgment on<lb/> the case of M/s Kelkar and Kelkar Vs. M/s Hotel Pride<lb/> Executive Pvt. Ltd in Civil Appeal No.3479/2022 decided on<lb/> 4.5.2022 by the Supreme Court and the judgment of<lb/> Supreme Court in Bhaven Construction vs Executive<lb/> Engineer Sardar Sarovar Narmada Nigam Ltd.&amp; another,<lb/> reported in AIR OnLine 2021 SC 6, are also distinguishable<lb/> on the basis of the discussions made hereinabove as the<lb/> alternative remedy, though available against the arbitration<lb/> award, here the challenge of the respondent side to the<lb/> same is based on the touch-stone of commission of offences<lb/> of fraud and conspiracy, therefore, the remedy under Article<lb/> 226 of Constitution of India can be availed in view of the<lb/> pronouncement of Supreme Court in Andi Mukta Sadguru<lb/> (supra). As per the submissions and the facts presented, the<lb/> filing of application under Section 34 of the Act, 1996 was<lb/> done subsequent to the filing of Writ Petition(Civil)<lb/> No.3355/2019. Therefore, it cannot be said that there had<lb/> been any concealment of fact. Reliance of the appellant side<lb/> on the judgment in the case of Pradeep Singh Vs. State of<lb/> U.P. (supra) does not give any guidance in such a case.<lb/> Similarly, the judgment in the case of Union of India and<lb/> another Vs. Tarsem Singh and others (supra) can also be<lb/> distinguished on the basis of the facts and circumstances<lb/> present in this case.<lb/></p>

			<p>41. Another ground raised by the appellant side is that the<lb/> application for amendment to incorporate additional relief for<lb/> setting aside the award dated 11.07.2019 was allowed at the<lb/> final hearing stage and as the application under Section 34<lb/> of the Act, 1996 was already filed, therefore, this amendment<lb/> for additional relief was not fit to be allowed. The objection<lb/> raised by the appellant/petitioner side was not decided by<lb/> the learned Single Judge.<lb/></p>

			<p>42. It has been discussed in detail here-in-above while<lb/> considering the question of maintainability of W.P.(C.)<lb/> No.3355/2019, that the circumstances are present permitting<lb/> the filing of the petition under Article 226 Constitution of<lb/> India. It is true that the application for amendment was filed<lb/> at a later stage and the same was decided on 29.10.2021.<lb/> The order of the Single Judge has mentioned about the<lb/> objections raised by the opposite counsel and the court has<lb/> after due consideration, allowed the application for<lb/> amendment. Subsequent to which, the arguments were<lb/> heard and the case was reserved for judgment on<lb/> 16.11.2021 and then the judgment has been delivered on<lb/> 10.01.2022. Therefore, there is no such case present that<lb/> the prayer for amendment was allowed immediately before<lb/> delivering the judgment in this case.<lb/></p>

			<p>43. As the question of maintainability of the W.P.C.<lb/> No.3355/2019 has been decided, therefore, the objection<lb/> that there was alternative remedy present under Section 34<lb/> of the Act, 1996, is without any basis. In the case of<lb/> Whirlpool Corpn. Vs. Registrar of Trade Marks (Supra), it<lb/> was held by the Supreme Court in paragraph 15 as follows:-<lb/></p>

			<p>&quot;15.Under Article 226 of the Constitution, the High<lb/> Court, having regard to the facts of the case, has a<lb/> discretion to entertain or not to entertain a writ<lb/> petition. But the High Court has imposed upon<lb/> itself certain restrictions on of which is that if an<lb/> effective and efficacious remedy is available, the<lb/> High Court would not normally exercise its<lb/> jurisdiction. But the alternative remedy has been<lb/> consistently held by this Court not to operate as a<lb/> bar in at least three contingencies, namely, where<lb/> the Writ Petition has been filed for the enforcement<lb/> of any of the Fundamental rights or where there<lb/> has been a violation of the principle of natural<lb/> justice or where the order or proceedings are<lb/> wholly without jurisdiction or the vires of an Act is<lb/> challenged. There is a plethora of case law on this<lb/> point but to cut down this circle of fornices<lb/> whirlpool we would rely or some old decisions of<lb/> the evolutionary era of the constitutional law as<lb/> they still hold the field.&quot;<lb/></p>

			<p>44. Section 34(2) of the Act, 1996 empowers the Court to set<lb/> aside the award passed by the arbitrator only and therefore,<lb/> this petition does not empower the Court to set aside the<lb/> initial award passed by the Acquisition Officer/Competent<lb/> Authority. Further, on the basis of the discussions made<lb/> here-in-above, we are of the view that the objection, which<lb/> was raised by the appellant side before the learned Single<lb/> Bench, has been considered and decided, therefore, this<lb/> objection raised again needs no further consideration.<lb/></p>

			<p>45. The contention of the learned counsel for the appellants that<lb/> the notification dated 21.08.2017 issued under Section 20A<lb/> of the Railway Act, 1989 (hereinafter referred to as &quot;the Act,<lb/> 1989&quot;) cannot be challenged in any Court nor it can be<lb/> examined by a Criminal Court. The report of the Collector<lb/> mentions about the diversion of the project in the matter of<lb/> construction of Railway Station. The matter is merely<lb/> focused on the commission of various offences under the<lb/> penal provisions of Indian Penal Code. In case, the F.I.R.<lb/> lodged is investigated and charge-sheet is filed, the Criminal<lb/> Court shall have jurisdiction to examine the facts regarding<lb/> the commission of offences for which the charge-sheet may<lb/> be filed, therefore, there shall be no reason present to<lb/> examine the veracity of the notification issued under Section<lb/> 20A of the Act, 1989. The allegations which are required to<lb/> be investigated in the case would be mainly on the method<lb/> of assessment of compensation as alleged that same was<lb/> done for the purpose benefiting specific beneficiaries only<lb/> who are the appellants. The bonafide or the lack of it shall<lb/> be found out in the investigation and, therefore, there is no<lb/> reason that the Criminal Court shall examine the notification<lb/> for acquisition of lands under Section 20A of the Act, 1996.<lb/></p>

			<p>46. The main contention of the appellants/ petitioners is that the<lb/> lands acquired from the appellants, namely, Bali Nagwanshi<lb/> and Neelima Belsariya, were situated in urban area. By the<lb/> notification dated 21.8.2017, notice under Section 20A of the<lb/> Act, 1989 was issued showing the intention of the railway<lb/> authorities to acquire lands. The details of the lands, which<lb/> were to be acquired situated in village -Palli, are as<lb/> follows :-<lb/>Name of District : Bastar<lb/> Name of District : Bastar<lb/> Taluka : Jagdalpur<lb/> Taluka : Jagdalpur<lb/> Serial<lb/> Number<lb/> Name<lb/> of<lb/> Village<lb/> Khasra/<lb/> Plot<lb/> Number<lb/> Area(in<lb/> Hect.)<lb/> Serial<lb/> Number<lb/> Name of<lb/> Village<lb/> Khasra/<lb/> Plot<lb/> Number<lb/> Area<lb/> (in<lb/> Hect.)<lb/></p>

			<p>(1)<lb/> (2)<lb/> (3)<lb/> (4)<lb/> (1)<lb/> (2)<lb/> (3)<lb/> (4)<lb/> 1<lb/> Palli<lb/> 123/1<lb/> 1.990<lb/> 2<lb/> Palli<lb/> 123/2<lb/> 0.700<lb/> 3<lb/> Palli<lb/> 123/3<lb/> 0.120<lb/> 4<lb/> Palli<lb/> 124<lb/> 0.249<lb/> 5<lb/> Palli<lb/> 125/1 to<lb/> 125/29,<lb/> 125/31,<lb/> 125/33 to<lb/> 125/37<lb/> 1.040<lb/></p>

			<p>6<lb/></p>

			<head>Palli<lb/> 125/30 0.010<lb/> 7<lb/> Palli<lb/> 125/32 0.020<lb/> 8<lb/> Palli<lb/> 27<lb/> 0.550<lb/> Total<lb/> 4.679<lb/></head>

			<p>47. The lands above mentioned in the table are shown as<lb/> situated in village -Palli and the area of the same is also<lb/> shown in the hectares. It has been vehemently argued by<lb/> the appellants side that by the notification dated 02.07.2014,<lb/> village -Palli was included in the municipal area, regarding<lb/> which, the attention of this Court has been drawn to the<lb/> description of Ward No.37 i.e. Lokmanya Tilak Ward. The<lb/> description of Lokmanya Tilak Ward in the schedule of<lb/> notification dated 02.07.2014 is relevant, which is as<lb/> follows :-<lb/></p>

			<p>&quot;Ward no.37 Lokmanya Tilak Ward<lb/> North<lb/> -<lb/>starting from Palli Naka via<lb/> Dharampura No.-2 via Sankar Mandir<lb/> upto Urwasshi Pandey&apos;s house.<lb/> East<lb/> -<lb/>starting from Devi Gudi L.I.C road<lb/> upto Champa Bai house.<lb/> South<lb/> -<lb/>starting from Champa&apos;s house upto<lb/> Sankar Mandir house.<lb/> West<lb/> -<lb/>starting from Sankar Mandir<lb/> Narmunda via Rajat Jainti Kangoli via<lb/> B.M cold storage upto Palli Naka.&quot;<lb/></p>

			<p>48. From the description as given in the notification dated<lb/> 21.08.2017, it is clearly mentioned that Palli is village area.<lb/> The emphasis of the appellants submission that the village -<lb/>Palli has been included in Lokmanya Tilak Ward is not<lb/> reflected from the description given in Notification dated<lb/> 2.7.2014 regarding Ward No.37 Lokmanya Tilak Ward. The<lb/> description given for the North mentions that the ward starts<lb/> from Palli Naka but does not mention Palli village. The<lb/> description regarding East and South does not mention Palli<lb/> village and the description regarding Western area of the<lb/> ward also mentions of Palli Naka only and it does not make<lb/> a mention of Palli village in any respect.<lb/></p>

			<p>49.<lb/> The contention of the respondents&apos; side is that the village-<lb/>Palli was never notified as a municipal area. Section 5A of<lb/> the Act, 1961, empowers the Governor to declare the<lb/> intention to include within or exclude from the limits of a<lb/> municipal area, any specific area by making publication of<lb/> notification. Attention of this Court was drawn to the<lb/> notification dated 03.09.2002 to submit that this notification<lb/> was the last notification for inclusion of specified area in the<lb/> municipal limits of Municipal Council Jagdalpur, which is as<lb/> under :-<lb/></p>

			<p>&quot;Raipur, the 3 rd September 2002<lb/> NOTIFICATION<lb/> No.4719/18/2002 -In exercise of the powers conferred<lb/> under clause (b) of Sub-section (1) of Section 5-A of<lb/> Chhattisgarh Municipalities Act, 1961), the State<lb/> Government, hereby, include following villages within the<lb/> limits of Municipal Council, Jagdalpur of Bastar District, from<lb/> the date of its notification in the Gazette as given in the<lb/> Schedule-I.<lb/> SCHEDULE -I<lb/> The details of the villages to be included within the<lb/> limits of Jagdalpur Municipal Council.<lb/></p>

			<p>(1)<lb/> Village Sargipal Tahsil<lb/> Survey Nos.5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10 and<lb/> Jagadalpur<lb/> part portion of 3/1 G, area<lb/> 33.600Hec.<lb/></p>

			<p>(2)<lb/> Village Kangoli Tahsil<lb/> Jagadalpur<lb/> Survey Nos.1 to 76, 80, 83 to 99,<lb/> 121/1, total area 616.85 Hec.<lb/></p>

			<p>(3)<lb/> Village Dharampura<lb/> Tahsil Jagdalpur<lb/> Survey Nos.1 to 117, 122, 124,<lb/> 141 and 142, total area 233.758<lb/> Hec.<lb/></p>

			<p>(4)<lb/> Village Adhanpur Tahsil<lb/> Jagdalpur<lb/> Survey Nos.1 to 139/1, 140 to<lb/> 147, 150 to 152 and part portion<lb/> of 149/1 total area 279.989 Hec.<lb/></p>

			<p>(5)<lb/> Village Pakhanguda<lb/> Tahsil Jagdalpur<lb/> All Survey Nos. form 1/1 to 97/3<lb/> total area 189.567 Hec.<lb/></p>

			<p>(6)<lb/> Village Frazerpur Tahsil<lb/> Jagdalpur<lb/> All Survey Nos. from 1/1 K to 27<lb/> total area 118.391 Hec.<lb/></p>

			<p>(7)<lb/> Village Hatkalchora<lb/> Tahsil Jagdalpur<lb/> All Survey Nos. from 1/1 K to 230<lb/> total area 270.725 Hec.<lb/></p>

			<p>(8)<lb/> Village Karakapal Tahsil<lb/> Jagdalpur<lb/> Survey Nos.from 1/1 to 26/1,<lb/> 133/1, 133/8, 135/1, 134/1 total<lb/> area 54.875 Hec.<lb/></p>

			<p>(9)<lb/> Village Kohakapal Tahsil<lb/> Jagdalpur<lb/> All Survey Nos. from 1/2 to 95<lb/> total area 75.015 Hec.<lb/></p>

			<p>(10)<lb/> Village Asna Tahsil<lb/> Jagdalpur<lb/> Survey Nos. from 266/330 to<lb/> 628/1 total area 260.468 Hec.<lb/></p>

			<p>(11)<lb/> Village Jagdalpur Khas<lb/> Tahsil Jagdalpur<lb/> All Survey Nos. from 1 to 146/35<lb/> total area 189.344 Hec.<lb/></p>

			<p>50. This notification certainly does not include village -Palli<lb/> within the municipal area. The appellants&apos; side have not<lb/> brought to the notice of this Court about any other<lb/> notification under Section 5-A of the Act, 1961, showing the<lb/> inclusion of village Palli in the municipal area. The<lb/> arguments of the appellants&apos; side, that the notification dated<lb/> 02.07.2014 issued under Section 29 of the Act, 1961 shows<lb/> village-Palli in municipal area is not borne out by the<lb/> description given with respect to Ward No.37 i.e. Lokmanya<lb/> Tilak Ward Jagdalpur. Submissions have been made by the<lb/> appellants&apos; side that the notification under Section 29 of the<lb/> Act, 1961 provides for extension of the ward constituted for<lb/> each municipality has the effect of including the specified<lb/> area mentioned in the municipal area.<lb/></p>

			<p>51. The municipal area has been defined under Section 3(18)<lb/></p>

			<p>(a) of the Act, 1961, which is as follows :-<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot;Section 3 (18-a) -<lb/></item>

			<item>&quot;Municipal area&quot; means<lb/> the smaller urban area or the transitional area,<lb/> as the Governor may, by public notification,<lb/> specify, in accordance with the provisions laid<lb/> down in Section 5 of this Act;&quot;<lb/></item>

			<p>52.<lb/> This provision makes reference to only Section 5 of the Act,<lb/> 1961 and further Section 5-A of the Act, 1961 has been<lb/> brought by amendment of 1994. The definition of municipal<lb/> area does not mention of Section 29 of the Act, 1961.<lb/> Section 29 of the Act, 1961 is as under :-<lb/>3<lb/> [29.Determination of number and extent of<lb/> wards and conduct of elections.-(1) The State<lb/> Government shall from time to time, by<lb/> notification in the Official Gazette, determine the<lb/> number and extent of wards to be constituted<lb/> for each Municipality :<lb/> Provided that the total number of wards<lb/> shall not be more than forty and not less than<lb/> fifteen.<lb/></p>

			<item>(2) Only one Councillor shall be elected from<lb/> each ward.<lb/></item>

			<item>(3) The formation of the wards shall be made<lb/> in such a way that the population of each of the<lb/> wards shall, so far as practicable be the same<lb/> throughout the Municipal area and the area<lb/> included in the ward is compact.<lb/></item>

			<item>(4)<lb/> As soon as the formation of wards of a<lb/> Municipallity is completed, the same shall be<lb/> reported by the State Government to the State<lb/> Election Commission.<lb/></item>

			<item>(5) 1 [* * *]<lb/></item>

			<item>(6) 1 [* * *].<lb/></item>

			<p>53. It is not relevant to discuss or interpret Section 29 of the Act,<lb/> 1961 as this Court has already come to a conclusion that<lb/> inclusion of village-Palli is not specifically mentioned in the<lb/> notification dated 02.07.2014, which was notified under<lb/> Section 29 of the Act, 1961 and further, it was not included in<lb/> the notification of 03.09.2002. No such other notification has<lb/> been brought to the notice of this Court. As has been<lb/> submitted by learned counsel for the respondents&apos; side that,<lb/> Palli Naka should not be identified as Palli village. It is<lb/> observed that Palli Naka is a particular point for crossing on<lb/> the road having a barrier and therefore, Palli Naka can not<lb/> be referred to as Palli village in any respect.<lb/></p>

			<p>54. Section 6 of the Act, 1961 provides for publication of<lb/> notification under Section 5 or Section 5-A of the Act, 1961.<lb/> Section 7 of the Act, 1961 provides that after the<lb/> establishment of municipal area and inclusion of a<lb/> panchayat area, such specified area shall cease to exist in<lb/> the panchayat area.<lb/></p>

			<p>55.<lb/> Respondents&apos; side has referred to notification dated<lb/> 02.07.2014, which is a notification regarding constitution of<lb/> gram panchayats. In Sr. No.23 there is mention of Gram<lb/> Panchayat-<lb/>Kumrawand,<lb/> which<lb/> includes<lb/> villages<lb/> Kumrawand and Palli. The relevant extract is as follows :-<lb/></p>

			<p>**dk;kZ y;] dys DVj] ftyk cLrj ¼NRrhlx&lt;½<lb/> cLrj] fnuka d 21 tq ykbZ 2014<lb/> vf/klw puk<lb/> dz eka d@482@ia pk;r@2014&amp;15&amp; NRRkhlx&lt; &apos;kklu] ia pk;r ,oa<lb/> xz keh.k fodkl foHkkx dh vf/klw puk dz eka d ,Q &amp;1&amp;11&amp; 95&amp;<lb/> 22&amp; ia &amp;02] fnuka d 23 Qjojh 1999 Onkjk iz nRRk &apos;kfDr;ks a dks<lb/> iz ;ks x es a ykrs gq ,]NRrhlx&lt; ia pk;r jkt vf/kfu;e 1993¼dz eka d<lb/> 1 lu~ 1994½ ¼ftls blds i&apos;pkr~ mDr vf/kfu;e dgk x;k gS ½<lb/> dh /kkjk 129 [k ¼ 1 ½ ds iz ko/kkuks a ds v/khu es a va fdr<lb/> vkua n]dys DVj] ftyk cLrj la yXu lkj.kh ¼ ftls ]blds i&apos;pkrS<lb/> lkj.kh S dgk x;k gS ½ ds Lrka Hk ¼ 4 ½ es a n&apos;kkZ ;s x;s xka o ;k xka oks a<lb/> ds leq g ds fy, ftldh tula [;k lkj.kh ds Lra Hk ¼ 5 ½ es a<lb/> n&apos;kkZ ;h xbZ gS ]lkj.kh ds Lra Hk¼ 3 ½ es a mYys f[kr uke ls mDr<lb/> vf/kfu;e ds iz ;s ktuks a ds fy, S xz ke Sds :i es fofufnZ &quot;V djrk<lb/> gW W w rFkk lkoZ tfud tkudkjh ds fy, ,rn~ Onkjk iz dkf&apos;kr fd;k<lb/> tkrk gS A<lb/> bl LFkkfir xz ke es a vf/kfu;e dh /kkjk 8 ¼ d ½ ds<lb/> vuq lkj xz ke ia pk;r dk xBu fd;k tk;s xk]bl iz dkj xfBr xz ke<lb/> ia pk;rks a dks vf/kfu;e dh /kkjk 11 ds va rxZ r of.kZ r vf/kfu;e ds<lb/> iz ;ks tu ds fy, vko&apos;;d vU; leLr &apos;kfDr;ka iz kIr gks a xh-<lb/></p>

			<p>56. Although this notification does not mention the lands<lb/> included in the panchayat area but inclusion of village -Palli<lb/> in the panchayat area is sufficient to reflect that the village-<lb/>Palli continues as a village in the gram panchayat<lb/> Kumrawand. It is the submission of the respondents&apos; side<lb/> that the respective lands that were purchased by the<lb/> appellants/petitioners are shown as agricultural lands in the<lb/> respective sale deeds and their areas were mentioned in<lb/> hectares, which had not been denied by the appellants&apos; side.<lb/></p>

			<p>57. In the guidelines issued by the Office of Inspector General of<lb/> Registrar and Superintendent (Stamp), Raipur for the year<lb/> 2017-18, market price is mentioned with respect to Ward<lb/> No.37, which is as follows :-<lb/>iz k:i &amp;,d<lb/> ¼fu;e&amp;7 ns f[k;s ½<lb/> uxjh; la ifRr;ks a ds cktkj ew Y; ekxZ nf&apos;kZ d fl)ka r o&quot;kZ 2017&amp;2018<lb/> uxj ikfyd fuxe&amp;txnyiq j<lb/> ¼nj iz froxZ ehVj :i;s es a ½<lb/> dz 0 okMZ dk<lb/> uke ,oa<lb/> dz eka d<lb/> eks gYyk@dkW yks uh@lks lk;Vh@ekxZ dk uke<lb/> Hkw [k.M dk ew Y;<lb/></p>

			<item>la ifRr eq [; ekxZ<lb/> la ifRr eq [; ekxZ<lb/> ij fLFkr gks us dh<lb/> ls va nj gks us ij<lb/> fLFkfr es a 20 ehVj nj ¼ftles a eq [;<lb/> rd nj<lb/> ekxZ ls 20 ehVj<lb/> i&apos;pkr dh nj<lb/> Hkh lfEefyr gS a<lb/> 37 yks d ekU;<lb/> fryd<lb/> okMZ dz eka d<lb/> 1-,e-th-,e-Ldw y tkus dk jkLrk ls iYyh ukdk rd<lb/> 2-iYyh ukdk ls fxVṼh [knku rd<lb/> 3-v&apos;kks dk ykbZ Q LVkbZ y@ukxoa &apos;kh js lhMs Ulh@fuyhek<lb/> 13800<lb/> 6000<lb/> ---<lb/>----<lb/>8500<lb/> 11300<lb/> Page No.56<lb/></item>

			<p>58. There is mention of &quot;Nagwanshi Residency&quot; and &quot;Neelima<lb/> Spandan&quot;, regarding which, the appellants have their claims.<lb/> However, these properties are shown to be present beyond<lb/> 20 meters from the road.<lb/></p>

			<p>59. Further in the same guidelines under Format -III, there is<lb/> mention of village-Palli in Revenue Inspector Circle<lb/> Jagadalpur. The relevant entry at Sr.No.2 is as follows :-<lb/>iz k:i &amp;rhu<lb/> ¼fu;e&amp;7 ns f[k;s ½<lb/> df&quot;k Hkw fe ds fy;s cktkj ew Y; ekxZ nf&apos;kZ d fl)ka r o&quot;kZ 2017&amp;2018<lb/> rglhy&amp;txnyiq j ftyk &amp; cLrj<lb/> ¼nj iz fr gs DVs ;j es a ½<lb/></p>

			<item>i-<lb/>g-<lb/>ua -<lb/>xz ke dk uke<lb/> lHkh fdLe<lb/> eq [; ekxZ ij<lb/> fLFkr<lb/> fla fpr<lb/> vfla fpr<lb/> df&quot;k Hkw fe ds Vq dMs +<lb/> 500 oxZ ehVj rd<lb/> lM+ d ls 20 lM+ d ls 20<lb/> ehVj rd<lb/> ehVj ckn<lb/> 1<lb/> --------------------<lb/>---------------<lb/>-----------<lb/>---------------------------<lb/>----------------<lb/></item>

			<item>2<lb/> ?kkVinew j<lb/> 4795500<lb/> 3294000<lb/> 3212<lb/> 2188<lb/> dq Egjkoa M<lb/> 5061000<lb/> 3294000<lb/> 2891<lb/> 2188<lb/> iYyh<lb/> 5061000<lb/> 3294000<lb/> 2891<lb/> 2188<lb/></item>

			<p>60. On a minute perusal of the order dated 12.02.2018, given by<lb/> the Competent Authority, there appears to be no mention<lb/> that land that was acquired from the appellants Bali<lb/> Nagwanshi and Neelima Belsaria were within that the Ward<lb/> No.37 of the Jagdalpur Municipal Corporation and that the<lb/> lands were not situated in the rural area of village -Palli.<lb/></p>

			<p>61. The notification under Section 20A of the Act, 1989 dated<lb/> 21.08.2017 mentions the description of lands, situated at<lb/> village-Palli, regarding which, the intention for acquisition<lb/> was notified. After the publication of this notification in the<lb/> local news paper, the persons concerned have the liberty to<lb/> raise objection as provided under Section 20D of the Act,<lb/> 1989, which was to be made within 30 days from the date of<lb/> publication under Section 20A of the Act, 1989. Sub-section<lb/> 2 of Section 20-D of the Act, 1989 provides that the<lb/> Competent Authority shall give an opportunity of hearing to<lb/> the objector and to make an inquiry as may be necessary<lb/> and either allow or disallow the objections. Thereafter,<lb/> notification under Section 20-E of the Act, 1989 is to be<lb/> issued. The notification under Section 20E of the Act, 1989<lb/> was issued on 21.12.2017. The relevant part of this<lb/> notification is reproduced as under :-<lb/>MINISTRY OF RAILWAYS<lb/> (Railway Board)<lb/> NOTIFICATION<lb/> Bilaspur, the 21 st December, 2017<lb/> Notification under Section 20E of the<lb/> Railways Act, 1989<lb/> S.O.3000(E.) -Whereas by the notification of<lb/> the Gov. of India, In the Ministry of Railways<lb/> (Railway Board) number S.O.2856 (E),<lb/> published in the Gazette of India (Extra-<lb/>Ordinary) on dt.31.08.2017 Part-II section 3,<lb/> sub section (ii), herein after referred to as the<lb/> said notification under subsection (1) of 20A of<lb/> the Railway Act,1989 (24 of 1989) (hereinafter<lb/> referred to as the said Act), the central<lb/> Government declared its intention to acquire<lb/> the land specified in the schedule annexed to<lb/> the said notification for execution of special<lb/> Railway Project, namely Rowghat-Jagdalpur<lb/> (140 km.) of Dallirajhara-Jagdalpur in the state<lb/> of Chhattisgarh.<lb/> And, whereas the substance of the said<lb/> notification was published in the daily<lb/> Newspapers, Nava Bharat (Hindi) Bastar<lb/> Edition on 23.09.2017, and Dandakaranya<lb/> Samachar<lb/> (Hindi)<lb/> dt.24.09.2017<lb/> under<lb/> subsection (4) of section 20A of the said act.<lb/> And whereas, there are four objections<lb/> received within the set time period &amp; all were<lb/> rejected by the Competent Authority.<lb/> And, whereas, in pursuance of subsection<lb/> (1) of section 20E of the said act, the<lb/> Competent Authority has submitted his report to<lb/> the central Government;Now,therefore,upon<lb/> receipt of the said report of the Competent<lb/> Authority, and in exercise of the powers<lb/> conferred by subsection (1) of the section 20E<lb/> of the said act 1989, the central Government<lb/> hereby declares that the lands specified in the<lb/> schedule annexed here to shall be acquired for<lb/> the aforesaid purpose;<lb/> And, further, in pursuance of subsection<lb/> (2) of section 20E of the said Act, the Central<lb/> Government<lb/> hereby<lb/> declares<lb/> that<lb/> on<lb/> publication of this notification in the official<lb/> Gazette, the land specified in the Schedule<lb/> annexed here to shall vest absolutely in the<lb/> Central<lb/> Government<lb/> free<lb/> from<lb/> all<lb/> encumbrances.<lb/> Relevant entries in Sr. No. 1, 2 and 5 of the notification<lb/> are as under :-<lb/>SCHEDULE<lb/> Name of District: Bastar<lb/> Taluka: Jagdalpur<lb/> Serial<lb/> No.<lb/> Name of<lb/> Village<lb/> Khasra<lb/> /Plot<lb/> Numbe<lb/> r<lb/> Area (in<lb/> Hect.)<lb/> Type<lb/> of<lb/> Land<lb/> Nature of<lb/> land<lb/> Name of Land Owner<lb/> 1.<lb/> Palli<lb/> 123/1<lb/> 1.990<lb/> Pvt.<lb/> Fallow<lb/> Land<lb/> Bali Nag Vanshi Father<lb/> Buter Nagvanshi Caste<lb/> Hulba<lb/></p>

			<item>2.<lb/> Palli<lb/> 123/2<lb/> 0.700<lb/> Pvt.<lb/> Fallow<lb/> Land<lb/> Bali Nag Vanshi Father<lb/> Buter Nagvanshi Caste<lb/> Hulba<lb/> -<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/></item>

			<item>5.<lb/> Palli<lb/> 125/1<lb/> to<lb/> 125/29,<lb/> 125/31,<lb/> 125/33<lb/> to<lb/> 125/37<lb/></item>

			<item>1.040<lb/> Pvt.<lb/> Fallow<lb/> Land<lb/> Shirmati Neelima Father<lb/> Pillu Ram, Bell Saria<lb/> Husband<lb/> T.K.<lb/> Ravi<lb/> Caste Hulba<lb/></item>

			<p>62. It goes to show, that after the notification of intention to<lb/> acquire the lands, the appellants/petitioners did not raise any<lb/> such objection that the lands proposed to be acquired from<lb/> them was not a land situated in the rural area and that the<lb/> same was situated in the urban area under the limits of the<lb/> municipal corporation/council. Therefore, the notification<lb/> under Section 20E of the Act, 1989 mentions about the lands<lb/> acquired from the appellants Bali Nagwanshi and Neelima<lb/> Belsaria as agricultural land with description that the lands<lb/> acquired were fallow lands.<lb/></p>

			<p>63.<lb/> Section 20F of the Act, 1989 provides for<lb/> determination of compensation amount, in which after<lb/> publication of notification, under sub-section (4) of 20F of the<lb/> Act, 1989, the interested party may appear and under sub-<lb/>section (5) of Section 20F of the Act, 1989, he may make a<lb/> statement regarding the nature of his respective interest in<lb/> such lands, and not regarding the market valuation of the<lb/> acquired property, as it is the duty of the competent authority<lb/> to determine the compensation in accordance with Section<lb/> 20F (8) of the Act, 1989 taking into consideration the market<lb/> value. Here the case is quite different. The respective<lb/> notifications and the documents show that village Palli were<lb/> never included in the municipal area under any notification<lb/> issued under Section 5A of the Act, 1989. The claim of the<lb/> appellant-Bali Nagwanshi and Neelima Belsaria is that the<lb/> land shown in the guidelines by 2017-18 i.e. &quot;Nagwanshi<lb/> Residency&quot; and &quot;Neelima Spandan&quot; were subject to<lb/> acquisition. On the contrary, the notification under Section<lb/> 20A of the Act, 1989 and then the notification under Section<lb/> 20E of the Act, 1989, make a clear mention of the lands<lb/> acquired from the village-Palli, which are shown to be fallow<lb/> lands, without there being presence of any construction on<lb/> the same. The report of the Collector dated 30.07.2019,<lb/> which is filed as Annexure P-10 (in W.P.(C) No. 3355 of<lb/> 2019), mentions that seven persons were the land oustees<lb/> from village -Palli and the total compensation determined<lb/> was Rs. 99.07 Crores, out of which only two of the lands<lb/> oustees, who are the appellants Bali Nagwanshi and<lb/> Neelima Belsaria, have received Rs.95.82 Crores out of the<lb/> total amount. There is allegation of serious irregularities<lb/> committed in determination of compensation with specific<lb/> mention, that the land acquired from the appellants Bali<lb/> Nagwanshi and Neelima Belsaria were lands situated in<lb/> village area. This enquiry was conducted by a committee of<lb/> three members, constituted by the Collector, Jagdalpur, who<lb/> also happen to be the members of the revenue department<lb/> and the report given by them has relevance alongwith other<lb/> facts, which support the conclusion/ ground in this report<lb/> which has been described herein above. Therefore, the<lb/> conclusion drawn by the learned Single Judge in the<lb/> impugned order in favour of the report submitted by the<lb/> Collector does not appear to suffer from any kind of infirmity.<lb/></p>

			<p>64. The grounds raised by the appellant -Hiralal Nayak in W.A.<lb/> No. 115 of 2022, by the appellant -Siyaram Kurre in W.A.<lb/> No. 129 of 2022, and by the appellant -Koushal Kumar<lb/> Thakur in W.A. No. 144 of 2022, are that they performed<lb/> their duties in exercise of power vested in them. The<lb/> compensation was determined by the competent authority in<lb/> accordance with the documents provided to him and the<lb/> calculation sheet was provided by the registration clerk -<lb/>Koushal Kumar Thakur in accordance with the guidelines of<lb/> 2017-2018. It has also been contended that the appellant -<lb/>Hiralal Nayak passed the award<lb/> dated 12.02.2018,<lb/> subsequent to which, he was transferred. No amount of<lb/> compensation was deposited during his tenure. Appellant -<lb/>Siyaram Kurre was the then S.D.O. (Revenue), the appellant<lb/> -Dindayal Mandavi was the then Tahsildar, appellant -<lb/>Arjun Shrivastava was the then Revenue Inspector and<lb/> appellant -Dharam Narayan Sahu was the then Halka<lb/> Patwari and their submission is that they have performed<lb/> their duties lawfully.<lb/></p>

			<p>65. Section 186 of the Act, 1989 provides for immunity to the<lb/> Railway Administration or Railway Servant or any other<lb/> person from any civil action or criminal action, provided, that<lb/> the action of such administration or public servant was done<lb/> in good faith. The point of good faith is required to be<lb/> investigated and it is only after that the conclusion can be<lb/> drawn whether the action of the public servant concerned<lb/> was done in good faith on a lawful exercise of the duty. As<lb/> there are several allegations present regarding the<lb/> conspiracy and fraud, therefore, these allegations are<lb/> required to be investigated before drawing any conclusion<lb/> whether the act done by the public servant was done in good<lb/> faith or not and whether the public servant has the immunity<lb/> under Section 186 of the Act, 1989 ?<lb/></p>

			<p>66. In the inquiry report submitted and the report of the Collector<lb/> dated 30.07.2019, there are specific details of irregularities<lb/> committed and responsibility fastened. Firstly, it is reported<lb/> that the Patwari -Dharam Narayan Sahu manipulated the<lb/> revenue records showing the land of Neelima Belsaria and<lb/> Bali Nagwanshi as separate khatas, whereas earlier the<lb/> revenue record was showing the lands in joint khata with<lb/> others. Incharge Sub-Registrar, Koushal Kumar Thakur had<lb/> first submitted a report on 30.01.2018 showing the lands of<lb/> the appellants Bali Nagwanshi and Neelima Belsaria in one<lb/> khata. Subsequent to which, the second report has been<lb/> submitted on 31.01.2018 showing the lands of these<lb/> appellants in separate khatas. It is alleged that the Revenue<lb/> Inspector -Arjun Shrivastava, Dindayal Mandavi and<lb/> Siyaram Kurre, connived in the submission of the report. The<lb/> calculation sheet was provided by the In-charge Sub-<lb/>Registrar Koushal Kumar Thakur, and based on the same<lb/> compensation has been assessed in favour of the appellants<lb/> Bali Nagwanshi and Neelima Belsaria. The responsibility of<lb/> appellant -Hiralal Nayak has been fixed on this point, that<lb/> he also connived with the submission of report by the other<lb/> officials and did not consider, that only two land oustees are<lb/> receiving huge compensation as compared to the other land<lb/> oustees and it is on this basis, criminal liability has been<lb/> imposed upon these appellants, regarding which, FIR has<lb/> been lodged. The grounds on which the appellants are<lb/> placing reliance needs to be investigated. The writ Court or<lb/> this appellate Court can not go into the details of the<lb/> accusation and grounds that are present or the grounds that<lb/> have been raised by the appellants in their defence. The<lb/> learned Single Bench has rightly held that the grounds and<lb/> the defence of these appellants can not be adjudicated by<lb/> this Court and further the FIR lodged requires to be<lb/> investigated and truth will be revealed during the<lb/> investigation. Hence for these reasons, we are of the view<lb/> that the grounds raised by these appellants are not fit to be<lb/> considered by the writ Court and similarly are not fit to be<lb/> considered in these writ appeals.<lb/></p>

			<p>67. The contentions of the appellant -Suresh B. Matali and A.V.<lb/> R. Murty, the appellants in W.A. No.119 of 2022 that they<lb/> have no involvement in the alleged commission of offence is<lb/> taken into consideration. It is true that these appellants had<lb/> not been involved in the process of acquisition in<lb/> determination of compensation. In the report of the Collector<lb/> dated 30.07.2019, it is reported, that the responsibility of<lb/> survey determination of rail track and construction was given<lb/> to the IRCON. IRCON is one of the partners in joint venture<lb/> with National Mineral Development Corporation (NMDC),<lb/> Steel Authority of India (SAIL) and Chhattisgarh Mineral<lb/> Development Corporation (CMDC). It is alleged in the report,<lb/> that IRCON made a survey for diversion of project proposing<lb/> construction of railway station at village -Palli, as a result of<lb/> which, excess land was acquired and such lands were<lb/> acquired because of which, the burden of payment of<lb/> compensation was enhanced and therefore, the lands of the<lb/> village-Palli were acquired, leading to the discrepancy in<lb/> determining huge compensation and also in determining<lb/> compensation in favour of the appellants Bali Nagwanshi<lb/> and Neelima Belsaria in different manner, compared to the<lb/> compensation determined for the other land oustees. In this<lb/> case, the land acquisition procedure has taken place only<lb/> once, for which, notification dated 21.08.2017 under Section<lb/> 20A of the Act, 1989 was published showing the intention of<lb/> the railway authorities to acquire the lands. This notification<lb/> included the lands belonging to the appellants -Bali<lb/> Nagwanshi and Neelima Belsaria. Subsequent to that, the<lb/> notification under Section 20E, which was published on<lb/> 21.12.2017 for making acquisition of the lands, in which, the<lb/> acquisition of the lands proposed in notification under<lb/> Section 20A, was finalized. Hence, it is not a case that any<lb/> additional acquisition of lands has taken place at any later<lb/> point of time. The lands in question were already there in<lb/> acquisition plan, since the very beginning.<lb/></p>

			<p>68. Now the question is whether diversion of project in the<lb/> matter of construction of railway station at village Palli is one<lb/> of the reasons for determining enhanced compensation in<lb/> favour of the land oustees. In our view, when the lands<lb/> acquired were already in the construction plan of the special<lb/> railway project, change in plan and construction of railway<lb/> station at village -Palli or any diversion without there being<lb/> any additional acquisition for the same, does not affect the<lb/> determination of compensation in any manner because the<lb/> compensation is to be determined in accordance with the<lb/> guidelines 2017-18 issued by the Inspector General and<lb/> Superintendent (Stamp), Raipur, which prescribes for grant<lb/> of compensation according to the market price of the land<lb/> only and not on the ground of any other importance, for<lb/> example, construction of railway station.<lb/></p>

			<p>69. On close scrutiny of the award dated 12.02.2018 passed by<lb/> the competent authority, there appears to be no mention<lb/> regarding the construction of railway station at village-Palli<lb/> and also regarding determination of compensation on this<lb/> basis, that railway station is to be constructed at village Palli.<lb/> Similarly, the order of Commissioner (Arbitrator) dated<lb/> 11.07.2019 also does not mention any such ground for<lb/> enhancement of compensation granted to the appellant Bali<lb/> Nagwanshi and the order has been similarly passed in the<lb/> arbitration matter referred by the appellant -Neelima<lb/> Belsaria on 11.07.2019. On the contrary, it appears that the<lb/> grounds for determination of compensation had been only<lb/> the market price of the lands, which has been classified as<lb/> agricultural land, land of commercial value, land adjacent to<lb/> the road, urban land and rural land, which are the only<lb/> criteria prescribed in the guideline of 2017-18. Therefore, we<lb/> are of the view, that in the report of the Collector, an<lb/> erroneous conclusion has been drawn regarding the<lb/> involvement of Suresh B. Matali and others, the appellants in<lb/> W.A. No. 119 of 2022 holding that their action in the matter<lb/> of survey of railway lands etc. has been the reason of<lb/> erroneous determination of compensation in favour of the<lb/> appellants -Bali Nagwanshi and Neelima Belsaria. The<lb/> diversion of railway project, if any, has taken place, in that<lb/> case also the structure of the compensation, which was to<lb/> be determined in accordance with the guidelines of 2017-18,<lb/> could not have changed. On the other hand, the main<lb/> contention in the report of the Collector dated 30.07.2019<lb/> and the FIR lodged dated 04.08.2019 is only to this extent<lb/> that the lands belonging to the appellants Bali Nagwanshi<lb/> and Neelima Belsaria were assessed for compensation on<lb/> the basis of their being urban land, being situated within the<lb/> municipal limits of Jagdalpur and also being situated<lb/> adjacent to the road, which is subject for investigation in the<lb/> FIR lodged. Hence, we are of the view that involvement of<lb/> these appellants in the FIR as accused persons is baseless.<lb/> Hence, their prayer for quashing of FIR against them is fit to<lb/> be allowed.<lb/></p>

			<p>70. It had been the submission of the appellants&apos; side that the<lb/> Collector had no authority to make an inquiry into the<lb/> acquisition process for the railway project as there is no<lb/> such provision present in the Act, 1989. In this matter, the<lb/> Collector has not enquired into the acquisition process. The<lb/> inquiry has been conducted with respect to the erroneous<lb/> determination of compensation, regarding which, the report<lb/> has been submitted and it was on the basis of this report,<lb/> the FIR has been lodged. Section 39 of the Code of Criminal<lb/> Procedure provides that every person aware of commission<lb/> of any offence punishable under the provisions of IPC<lb/> specified in the section is duty bound to give information to<lb/> the nearest Magistrate or Police Officer. The offence under<lb/> Section 409 is included in this provision.<lb/></p>

			<p>71. Section 154 of Cr.P.C. provides that information which<lb/> discloses commission of cognizable offence, can be given to<lb/> the police station in the manner provided therein. Hence, on<lb/> the basis of these provisions in Criminal Procedure Code<lb/> and also the Collector being the administrative head of<lb/> revenue district, has the responsibility to see that the rule of<lb/> law prevails and he is duty bound to take cognizance<lb/> whenever there is some information regarding commission<lb/> of offence. Although the cognizance was taken by the<lb/> Collector on the basis of the news publication, but the<lb/> Collector did not proceed to lodge FIR only on that basis. An<lb/> enquiry was conducted by a team constituted by the<lb/> Collector and on the submission of report of the inquiry by<lb/> the said Committee, the action has been taken for lodging of<lb/> FIR in this case. There is no such restriction under the<lb/> provisions of the Act, 1989 and further, the inquiry report can<lb/> not be said to be against the railway authorities or against<lb/> the railway project. The report mentions about the diversion<lb/> of railway project, regarding which, suspicion has been<lb/> raised, which has been dealt with here-in-above. Therefore,<lb/> we are of the view that the Collector has ordered for enquiry<lb/> well within his authority and hence, the enquiry report dated<lb/> 30.07.2019 does not suffer from any infirmity or illegality.<lb/></p>

			<p>72. In conclusion, we are of the view that W.A. No. 81 of 2022,<lb/> W.A. 64 of 2022, W.A.77 of 2022, W.A. 83 of 2022, W.A. 115<lb/> of 2022, W.A.129 of 2022 and W.A.144 of 2022 are not fit to<lb/> be allowed. Hence, they are dismissed.<lb/></p>

			<p>73. However, the W.A. No. 119 of 2022 is fit to be allowed, which<lb/> is allowed and the FIR dated 04.08.2019 under Crime No.<lb/> 409 of 2019 to the extent, lodged against the appellants<lb/> Suresh B. Matali and A.V.R. Murty are hereby quashed.<lb/> Sd/-<lb/>Sd/-<lb/>(Arup Kumar Goswami)<lb/> (R.C.S. Samant)<lb/> Chief Justice<lb/> Judge<lb/> Nisha/Aadil/Monika/<lb/> Nirmala/Balram</p>


	</text>
</tei>
