<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<head>
			ANUP JAIRAM BHAMBHANI, J.
			<lb />
		</head>
		<head>
			Introduction
			<lb />
		</head>
		<p>
			The appellant, Natasha Narwal has preferred the present appeal under
			<lb />
			section 21(4) of the National Investigation Agency Act 2008 (&apos;NIA Act&apos;, for
			<lb />
			short) impugning order dated 28.01.2021 made by the learned Special Court
			<lb />
			(&apos;impugned order&apos;, for short) rejecting the appellant&apos;s bail application in
			<lb />
			case FIR No. 59/2020 (&apos;subject FIR&apos;, for short) dated 06.03.2020 registered
			<lb />
			initially under sections 147 / 148 / 149 / 120B of the Indian Penal Code
			<lb />
			1860 (&apos;IPC&apos;, for short) at P.S.: Crime Branch, New Delhi, to which offences
			<lb />
			under sections 109 / 114 / 124A / 153A / 186 / 201 / 212 / 295 / 302 / 307 /
			<lb />
			341 /353 / 395 / 419 / 420 / 427 / 435 / 436 / 452 / 454 / 468 / 471 / 34 IPC,
			<lb />
			sections 3 / 4 of the Prevention of Damage to Public Property Act 1984
			<lb />
			(&apos;PDPP Act&apos;, for short), sections 25 / 26 of Arms Act 1959 and sections 13 /
			<lb />
			16 / 17 / 18 of the Unlawful Activities (Prevention) Act 1967 (&apos;UAPA&apos;, for
			<lb />
			short) were subsequently added. The appellant is stated to be in custody
			<lb />
			since 29.05.2020 in the subject FIR.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			2.
			<lb />
			Briefly, the appellant is a student pursuing MPhil-Ph.D. Programme
			<lb />
			in the Department Centre of Women&apos;s Historical Studies at the
			<lb />
			Jawaharlal Nehru University, New Delhi, having completed her
			<lb />
			Bachelor of Arts (Honours) and Master of Arts in History from Hindu
			<lb />
			College, Delhi University.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<head>
			Essence of allegations against Appellant
			<lb />
		</head>
		<p>
			3.
			<lb />
			In essence, the case cited by the prosecution against the appellant is
			<lb />
			that she was involved in instigating the local population in certain
			<lb />
			Muslim dominated areas in Delhi, particularly women, to protest
			<lb />
			against the Citizenship Amendment Act 2019 (&apos;CAA&apos;, for short)
			<lb />
			passed by the Parliament and the exercise undertaken by the Central
			<lb />
			Government for creating a National Register of Citizens (&apos;NRC&apos;, for
			<lb />
			short), by allegedly seeking to incite feelings of persecution. Other
			<lb />
			than this, the allegation is that as part of a women&apos;s rights group
			<lb />
			called &apos;Pinjra Tod&apos; (which may loosely be translated as &apos;break-free
			<lb />
			from the cage&apos;, namely from societal shackles) and other activistic
			<lb />
			groups called the Delhi Protests Support Group (&apos;DPSG&apos;, for short),
			<lb />
			the Jamia Coordination Committee (&apos;JCC&apos;, for short), Warriors and
			<lb />
			&apos;Auraton ka Inquilab&apos;, the appellant participated in a so-called larger
			<lb />
			conspiracy to commit certain offences that are subject matter of the
			<lb />
			subject FIR, which also led to riots that occurred in the North-East
			<lb />
			part of Delhi between 22.02.2020 and 26.02.2020.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			4.
			<lb />
			For sake of completeness, it is necessary to mention that the appellant
			<lb />
			was accused and was also arrested in two other FIRs, being FIR No.
			<lb />
			48/2020 dated 24.02.2020 registered under section 147 / 186 / 188 /
			<lb />
			109 / 283 / 353 / 341 / 34 IPC at P.S.: Jafrabad and FIR No. 50/2020
			<lb />
			dated 26.02.2020 registered under section 147 / 148 / 149 /186 / 283 /
			<lb />
			302 / 307 / 332 / 323 / 353 / 427 / 109 / 188 / 120B / 34 IPC read with
			<lb />
			section 25 / 27 Arms Act and section 3 / 4 PDPP Act at P.S.: Jafrabad.
			<lb />
			It is noteworthy that in FIR No. 48/2020 the appellant was arrested on
			<lb />
			23.05.2020 and was admitted to bail by the learned Duty Metropolitan
			<lb />
			Magistrate vidé order dated 24.05.2020 observing inter alia that the
			<lb />
			appellant was merely protesting the passing of the CAA and the
			<lb />
			exercise undertaken by the Central Government for creating the NRC
			<lb />
			and that she did not indulge in any violence. Insofar as FIR No.
			<lb />
			50/2020 is concerned, the appellant was arrested on 24.05.2020, that
			<lb />
			is, on the very day and from the very court which admitted her to bail
			<lb />
			in FIR No. 48/2020 on 24.05.2020; and was subsequently admitted to
			<lb />
			bail in FIR No. 50/2020 vidé order dated 17.09.2020 by the learned
			<lb />
			ASJ, Karkardooma Courts, Delhi.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			5.
			<lb />
			The appellant was arrested in the subject FIR i.e. FIR No. 59/2020 on
			<lb />
			29.05.2020 while she was in judicial custody in Tihar Jail in FIR No.
			<lb />
			50/2020. Even at the time of her formal arrest in the subject FIR on
			<lb />
			29.05.2020, the Investigating Officer did not seek her police custody;
			<lb />
			which was sought 04 days later, whereupon she suffered police
			<lb />
			custody for 05 days beginning 03.06.2020.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			6.
			<lb />
			It would appear therefore that 03 separate FIRs came to be registered
			<lb />
			against the appellant, albeit arising from or in connection with, the
			<lb />
			same event, namely her alleged involvement with the protests against
			<lb />
			the CAA and the NRC. It must also be noticed that though FIR No.
			<lb />
			59/2020 was registered on 06.03.2020, the appellant came to be
			<lb />
			arrested in the subject FIR some 3 months later on 29.05.2020.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			7.
			<lb />
			Upon completion of investigation in the subject FIR, the respondent/
			<lb />
			Delhi Police has filed charge-sheet dated 16.09.2020 naming several
			<lb />
			accused persons, including the appellant. Although supplementary
			<lb />
			charge-sheets dated 22.11.2020 and 01.03.2021 have also been filed
			<lb />
			arising from the subject FIR, it is common ground that the said other
			<lb />
			charge-sheets do not relate to the appellant and are therefore not
			<lb />
			relevant for purposes of the present proceedings. Vidé order dated
			<lb />
			17.09.2020 the learned Special Court is stated to have taken
			<lb />
			cognizance of the offences alleged in the subject charge-sheet, except
			<lb />
			offences under section 124A / 153A / 109 / 120B IPC, for which
			<lb />
			sanction for prosecution was still awaited from the State Government
			<lb />
			as of the date of the impugned order. However, charges have not yet
			<lb />
			been framed against the appellant or any of the other accused persons.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			8.
			<lb />
			It may further be recorded for completeness that in Crl. M. C. No.
			<lb />
			2119/2020, by which the State had challenged the learned trial court&apos;s
			<lb />
			direction to provide a hardcopy of the charge-sheet to all accused
			<lb />
			persons, further proceedings in the trial had been stayed by a learned
			<lb />
			Single Judge of this court vidé order dated 10.11.2020, which stay
			<lb />
			order has however since been vacated by order dated 23.03.2021
			<lb />
			made by the learned Single Judge.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<head>
			Appellant&apos;s Submissions
			<lb />
		</head>
		<p>
			9.
			<lb />
			Mr. Adit S. Pujari, learned counsel appearing on behalf of the
			<lb />
			appellant contends that on point of fact, the appellant was not
			<lb />
			involved with any of the acts or omissions alleged against her in the
			<lb />
			subject charge-sheet. More specifically, counsel submits as follows :
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			(a)
			<lb />
			It is argued that the appellant was not involved or concerned
			<lb />
			with any violent protests against the CAA, whether as part of
			<lb />
			Pinjra Tod or DPSG; and that in any case she was not even a
			<lb />
			member of the JCC, the Warriors nor of the Auraton ka
			<lb />
			Inquilab WhatsApp groups at all.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(b)
			<lb />
			While the appellant does not deny that she was part of the
			<lb />
			women-led 24x7 sit-in protest at the site near Madina Masjid,
			<lb />
			Seelampur and of the protest at the 66-foota Road at Jafrabad
			<lb />
			Metro Station, she was not at the said protest sites on the date
			<lb />
			when riots and communal violence are alleged to have broken-
			<lb />
			out there, i.e. between 22.02.2020 and 26.02.2020 as would be
			<lb />
			evident from her call detail records (&apos;CDRs&apos;) and video-
			<lb />
			footage of CCTV cameras installed at and around the sites.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(c)
			<lb />
			It is urged that the appellant&apos;s name is being falsely dragged
			<lb />
			into several allegations, including her having participated in
			<lb />
			various meetings, having been present at the protest sites
			<lb />
			where violence and rioting occurred, supported only on the
			<lb />
			basis of statements of witnesses, most of whom are now
			<lb />
			protected witnesses, recorded much after the dates of the
			<lb />
			alleged incidents, whereas the &apos;best evidence&apos; that ought to be
			<lb />
			produced to demonstrate the basis of these allegations, such as
			<lb />
			CDRs and relevant video-footage are intentionally not being
			<lb />
			produced.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(d)
			<lb />
			Counsel submits that the State has not cited even a single
			<lb />
			statement of any actual victim of the alleged violence, since
			<lb />
			such victim would disprove the appellant&apos;s presence during
			<lb />
			the riots and violence. Even copies of the CDRs and video-
			<lb />
			footage are not being provided to the appellant, to prevent her
			<lb />
			from showing that she was not present.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(e)
			<lb />
			It is pointed-out that there is no reference in the charge-sheet
			<lb />
			to any specifics, such as names, addresses and other
			<lb />
			particulars of actual victims who may have suffered injuries or
			<lb />
			may have died at the locations where the appellant is alleged
			<lb />
			to have been present, nor to any other evidence as to the
			<lb />
			nature of injuries sustained, nor to any MLCs to that effect, all
			<lb />
			of which would belie and show the utter falsity of the
			<lb />
			allegations levelled inter alia against the appellant. In this
			<lb />
			behalf, it is also pointed-out that applications moved by the
			<lb />
			appellant before the learned Special Court seeking copies of
			<lb />
			the contents/data of her seized cell-phone and for
			<lb />
			requisitioning her CDRs and video-footage of the sites, have
			<lb />
			all been rejected. The appellant contends that video-footage of
			<lb />
			the protests was in fact professionally recorded by a
			<lb />
			videographer engaged by the Delhi Police; but such video-
			<lb />
			footage has not been produced in an effort to block-out any
			<lb />
			exculpatory evidence which would show that the appellant
			<lb />
			was not even present at the place on the dates and time
			<lb />
			alleged.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(f)
			<lb />
			It is accordingly the appellant&apos;s submission that the effort of
			<lb />
			the State is to embroil the appellant in events with which she
			<lb />
			had nothing to do; and in which she did not either perpetrate
			<lb />
			or participate in, on the vague and untenable plea of a &apos;larger
			<lb />
			conspiracy&apos;.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(g)
			<lb />
			It is further argued on behalf of the appellant that there is no
			<lb />
			substantive factual allegation, founded on any concrete,
			<lb />
			verifiable evidence adduced against the appellant; and in any
			<lb />
			case, the ingredients of the offences alleged under sections 15,
			<lb />
			17 or 18 under Chapters IV or VI of the UAPA are not made-
			<lb />
			out, by reason of which section 43D(5) of the UAPA has no
			<lb />
			application to the bail application. It is accordingly contended,
			<lb />
			that the bail application must be decided only on the general
			<lb />
			principles of bail, namely the &apos;triple test&apos; of flight risk,
			<lb />
			tampering with evidence and influencing witnesses and
			<lb />
			nothing more.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(h)
			<lb />
			It is pointed-out that the appellant was arrested almost 03
			<lb />
			months after the date of registration of the FIR, without even a
			<lb />
			notice under section 41A of the Cr.P.C. having been issued to
			<lb />
			her; yet she remained available for investigation at her
			<lb />
			residence throughout; and there is no chance of her fleeing
			<lb />
			from justice. It is further submitted that all evidence that was
			<lb />
			required to be collected is already available with the
			<lb />
			investigating agency and no documentary or other evidence of
			<lb />
			any nature whatsoever is in the appellant&apos;s possession; nor has
			<lb />
			the appellant acted in a manner whereby it could be suspected
			<lb />
			that she would tamper with evidence. Furthermore, it is the
			<lb />
			appellant&apos;s submission, that considering her educational
			<lb />
			profile and situation in life, namely that she is a student
			<lb />
			pursuing her M.Phil-Ph.D. at JNU, she is in no position to
			<lb />
			influence any witnesses and accordingly there is no risk even
			<lb />
			on that count.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<head>
			Respondent&apos;s Submissions
			<lb />
		</head>
		<p>
			10. Referring to certain portions of the subject charge-sheet, Mr. Amit
			<lb />
			Mahajan, learned Special Public Prosecutor appearing for the Delhi
			<lb />
			Police/State, has sought to explain the alleged role of the appellant in
			<lb />
			what the prosecuting agency calls the &apos;larger conspiracy&apos;. The
			<lb />
			portions of the subject charge-sheet dated 16.09.2020, which charge-
			<lb />
			sheet is stated to run into some 19000 pages, that are stated to be
			<lb />
			relevant as against the appellant, are extracted in Annexure -A to this
			<lb />
			judgment for ease of reference. Broadly, the prosecuting agency&apos;s
			<lb />
			allegations against the appellant may be summarised as follows:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			(a)
			<lb />
			The principal allegation against the appellant is that as a
			<lb />
			member of the women&apos;s rights organisation called Pinjra Tod,
			<lb />
			and as part of the WhatsApp groups under the name Warriors,
			<lb />
			Auraton ka Inquilab, DPSG, and JCC, the appellant engaged
			<lb />
			in a conspiracy to plan riots and destabilise the Government in
			<lb />
			the guise of an anti-CAA and anti-NRC protest. To support
			<lb />
			this submission, the State draws attention to the portion of the
			<lb />
			subject charge-sheet extracted as Screenshot 1a-1b in
			<lb />
			Annexure -A attached to this judgment.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(b)
			<lb />
			Furthermore, it is alleged that on 23.01.2020, the appellant
			<lb />
			was present at the Pinjra Tod office at E-1/13 Seelampur,
			<lb />
			Delhi, where one of the principal accused in the matter
			<lb />
			advised the persons present to escalate their planned chakka
			<lb />
			jaam (which may loosely be translated as a form of protest in
			<lb />
			which protesters cause complete stoppage of vehicles and
			<lb />
			blockade of roads), saying further, that merely giving inciting
			<lb />
			speeches would not work. In this behalf, the State draws
			<lb />
			attention to the portion of the subject charge-sheet extracted as
			<lb />
			Screenshot 2, 3a-3c, 4 and 5 in Annexure-A attached to this
			<lb />
			judgment.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(c)
			<lb />
			On the intervening night of 16/17.02.2020, the appellant is
			<lb />
			also alleged to have attended a meeting in a locality called
			<lb />
			Chand Bagh, where, it is alleged, that the conspirators pledged
			<lb />
			to plan for executing a chakka jaam, including at the time that
			<lb />
			the US President was scheduled to visit New Delhi. In this
			<lb />
			regard, the State points to the portion of the subject charge-
			<lb />
			sheet extracted as Screenshot 6, 7 and 8a-8c in Annexure-A
			<lb />
			attached to this judgment.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(d)
			<lb />
			More specifically, it is the State&apos;s allegation that the appellant
			<lb />
			was amongst the leaders who organised protests at a site
			<lb />
			described as the Plot of Chaudhary Mateen in Jafrabad, Delhi
			<lb />
			and at another protest site described as Opposite Tent Wala
			<lb />
			School, Jafrabad, Delhi, as also at a site described as Fruit
			<lb />
			Market, Seelampur, Delhi. To support this submission, the
			<lb />
			State refers to the portion of the subject charge-sheet extracted
			<lb />
			as Screenshot 9, 10 and 11 in Annexure-A attached to this
			<lb />
			judgment.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(e)
			<lb />
			The State alleges that the appellant was inter alia one of the
			<lb />
			conspirators who organised and instigated the 24x7 sit-in
			<lb />
			protest led by some 300 women at the Madina Masjid,
			<lb />
			Seelampur; and that on 23.02.2020, a group of protesting
			<lb />
			women also occupied the 66-foota Road at Jafrabad Metro
			<lb />
			Station, thereby completely blocking traffic and creating a
			<lb />
			chakka jaam, where the appellant also engaged in
			<lb />
			sloganeering and instigating the public against the
			<lb />
			government, which is described as giving &apos;bhadkau bhashan&apos;,
			<lb />
			namely inciting speeches. To support this submission, the
			<lb />
			State references the portion of the subject charge-sheet
			<lb />
			extracted as Screenshot 12a-12b, 13a-13b, 14, 15a-15b, 16,
			<lb />
			17, 18a-18b, 19a-19d and 20 in Annexure-A attached to this
			<lb />
			judgment.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(f)
			<lb />
			It is also alleged that the appellant engaged in distributing
			<lb />
			packets of chilli-powder to women protesters, with the
			<lb />
			purpose of attacking police and military with it; and also
			<lb />
			asked women and youngsters to stockpile chilli-powder,
			<lb />
			dandas (sticks), empty bottles, acid, and stones to be used
			<lb />
			when the occasion arises. In this context, the State draws
			<lb />
			attention to the portion of the subject charge-sheet extracted as
			<lb />
			Screenshot 21, 22, 23, 24, 25, 26, 27 and 28 in Annexure-A
			<lb />
			attached to this judgment.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(g)
			<lb />
			The appellant is alleged to have also been part of the group of
			<lb />
			protesting women who proceeded from the Jafrabad protest
			<lb />
			site towards the Maujpur-Babarpur Metro Station, which
			<lb />
			brought them near the pro-CAA protest site, where again it is
			<lb />
			alleged, that the appellant inter alia distributed chilli-powder,
			<lb />
			bottles and stones to women protesters, which were thrown at
			<lb />
			the pro-CAA protesters sitting at that protest site. To show
			<lb />
			this, attention of the court is invited to the portion of the
			<lb />
			subject charge-sheet extracted as Screenshot 29a-29b, 30, 31,
			<lb />
			32, 33, 34 and 35a-35b in Annexure-A attached to this
			<lb />
			judgment.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(h)
			<lb />
			The appellant&apos;s name is also sought to be included in the
			<lb />
			commission of the actual riots that occurred in North-East
			<lb />
			Delhi, which allegedly broke-out in execution of a &apos;common
			<lb />
			conspiracy&apos;. The State further alleges that as part of the
			<lb />
			protests in question, the perpetrators used fire arms, petrol
			<lb />
			bombs, acid, iron rods, swords, knives, stones, sling shots, and
			<lb />
			chilli-powder etc., to terrorise people and the society at large.
			<lb />
			To support this submission, the State references the portion of
			<lb />
			the subject charge-sheet extracted as Screenshot 36, 37a-37c,
			<lb />
			38, 39 and 40 in Annexure-A attached to this judgment.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(i)
			<lb />
			The prosecution also alleges that the above-mentioned
			<lb />
			allegations are substantiated by statements of several
			<lb />
			witnesses, including many who have since been declared as
			<lb />
			protected witnesses considering their vulnerabilities. It is also
			<lb />
			the prosecution&apos;s contention that video-recordings relating to
			<lb />
			the incidents in which the appellant was involved have been
			<lb />
			seized, which show the appellant&apos;s presence.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<head>
			Basis &amp; Reasoning of the Impugned Order
			<lb />
		</head>
		<p>
			11. Considering the nature of the allegations levelled against the
			<lb />
			appellant, this court also closely examined the basis and the reasoning
			<lb />
			that informed the decision of the learned Special Court to deny bail to
			<lb />
			the appellant. We find that, apart from proceeding to accept the
			<lb />
			allegations contained in the subject charge-sheet without any analysis
			<lb />
			or appreciation of the gravamen of the offences alleged, the following
			<lb />
			main aspects appear to have weighed with the learned Special Court
			<lb />
			in rejecting the appellant&apos;s bail:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			(a)
			<lb />
			The learned Special Court records that since under the
			<lb />
			provisions of section 45 of the UAPA, previous sanction of the
			<lb />
			Central Government is required before a court takes
			<lb />
			cognizance of any offence under Chapters IV or VI; and that
			<lb />
			before the Central Government gives sanction for prosecution,
			<lb />
			the Central Government itself is required to consider the
			<lb />
			report of an authority to be appointed by it, which authority is
			<lb />
			required to make an independent review of the evidence
			<lb />
			gathered in the course of investigation and make its
			<lb />
			recommendation to the Central Government as regards grant
			<lb />
			of sanction. The learned Special Court says that &quot;In the
			<lb />
			present case, previous sanction was taken under UAPA and
			<lb />
			thus, an independent review of the evidence gathered during
			<lb />
			the investigation has been done by an independent authority
			<lb />
			after its satisfaction about the evidence&quot; (extract from para 10
			<lb />
			of the impugned order), whereby, it is evident that the learned
			<lb />
			Special Court is persuaded to think that the purported
			<lb />
			independent review by an independent authority of the
			<lb />
			evidence gathered, leading to the grant of sanction for
			<lb />
			prosecution by the Central Government, almost obviates the
			<lb />
			need for the court to apply its own mind and consider whether
			<lb />
			or not any offence is disclosed against an accused under
			<lb />
			Chapters IV or VI of the UAPA.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(b)
			<lb />
			Furthermore, we find that a common thread that runs through
			<lb />
			the reasoning adopted by the learned Special Court when
			<lb />
			appreciating the material against the appellant, is that the
			<lb />
			appellant was a member of Pinjra Tod, DPSG, Warriors and
			<lb />
			Auraton ka Inquilab and was &apos;part of a multi-layered
			<lb />
			conspiracy and in regular touch and reporting to the higher
			<lb />
			conspirators&apos;, which makes her actions culpable.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(c)
			<lb />
			We may say, without the slightest hesitation, that the learned
			<lb />
			Special Court&apos;s view that merely because an independent
			<lb />
			review of the evidence gathered may have been undertaken by
			<lb />
			an independent authority, which authority may have been
			<lb />
			satisfied that offences under the UAPA are made-out; and the
			<lb />
			Central Government may have accorded sanction for
			<lb />
			prosecution for offences under the UAPA based on such
			<lb />
			review, does not in any manner imply that the court need not
			<lb />
			apply its own mind to form its own judicial view as to whether
			<lb />
			any offence under the UAPA is disclosed in the charge-sheet
			<lb />
			and the material placed alongwith it. The purported
			<lb />
			independent review of evidence by the purported independent
			<lb />
			authority; or the purported satisfaction of such authority, must
			<lb />
			never enter the consideration of the court while making its
			<lb />
			own assessment as to whether the ingredients of any offence
			<lb />
			under the UAPA are disclosed in the charge-sheet, not least
			<lb />
			because the offences engrafted in the UAPA are extremely
			<lb />
			serious and invite severe punishment.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<head>
			Interpretation of &apos;terrorist act&apos; &amp; related provisions
			<lb />
			under UAPA
			<lb />
		</head>
		<p>
			12. In its contemporaneous judgment 15.06.2021 rendered in &quot;Asif Iqbal
			<lb />
			Tanha vs. State&quot; being Crl.A. No. 39 of 2021, this court has analysed
			<lb />
			in detail the provisions engrafting &apos;terrorist act&apos; and &apos;conspiracy&apos; or
			<lb />
			&apos;act preparatory&apos; to the commission of a terrorist act. Without
			<lb />
			repeating that exercise in the present judgement, it would be sufficient
			<lb />
			to recapitulate the position of law in that regard, as expatiated by this
			<lb />
			court in the said judgement.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			13. As detailed by this court in Asif Iqbal Tanha (supra), the position is
			<lb />
			that though the phrase &apos;terrorist act&apos; has been given a very wide and
			<lb />
			detailed definition in section 15, in our considered view, the court
			<lb />
			must be careful in employing the definitional words and phrases used
			<lb />
			in section 15 in their absolute, literal sense or use them lightly in a
			<lb />
			manner that would trivialise the extremely heinous offence of
			<lb />
			&apos;terrorist act&apos;, without understanding how terrorism is different even
			<lb />
			from conventional, heinous crime.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			14. In Hitendra Vishnu Thakur &amp; Ors vs. State of Maharashtra &amp; Ors ,
			<lb />
			1
			<lb />
			the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court says that the extent and reach of a
			<lb />
			terrorist activity must travel beyond the effect of an ordinary crime
			<lb />
			and must not arise merely by causing disturbance of law and order or
			<lb />
			even public order. The Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court says that the effect of
			<lb />
			terrorist activity must be such that it travels beyond the capacity of the
			<lb />
			ordinary law enforcement agencies to deal with it under the ordinary
			<lb />
			penal law. The following words in Hitendra Vishnu Thakur (supra)
			<lb />
			bear careful attention :
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;…&apos;terrorism&apos; is generally an attempt to acquire or maintain power
			<lb />
			or control by intimidation and causing fear and helplessness in the
			<lb />
			minds of the people at large or any section thereof and is a totally
			<lb />
			abnormal phenomenon …&quot;.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			15. Furthermore, in the same judgment that the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court
			<lb />
			says:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;...it is not the intention of the Legislature that every criminal
			<lb />
			should be tried under TADA, where the fall out of his activity does
			<lb />
			not extend beyond the normal frontiers of the ordinary criminal
			<lb />
			activity. Every &apos;terrorist&apos; may be a criminal but every criminal
			<lb />
			cannot be given the label of a &apos;terrorist&apos; only to set in motion the
			<lb />
			more stringent provisions of TADA …&quot;
			<lb />
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			16. The Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court has further explained the concept of
			<lb />
			terrorism in People&apos;s Union For Civil Liberties &amp; Anr. vs. Union of
			<lb />
			(1994) 4 SCC 602.
			<lb />
			India (&apos;PUCL&apos;, for short) in which decision, quoting Mohd. Iqbal M.
			<lb />
			2
			<lb />
			Shaikh &amp; Ors. vs. State of Maharashtra , the Hon&apos;ble Supreme
			<lb />
			3
			<lb />
			Court says:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;…it may be possible to describe it as use of violence when its most
			<lb />
			important result is not merely the physical and mental damage of
			<lb />
			the victim but the prolonged psychological effect it produces or
			<lb />
			has the potential of producing on the society as a whole …&quot;
			<lb />
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			17. In PUCL (supra), the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court also observes that:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;... Terrorist acts are meant to destabilise the nation by
			<lb />
			challenging its sovereignty and integrity, to raze the constitutional
			<lb />
			principles that we hold dear, to create a psyche of fear and
			<lb />
			anarchism among common people, to tear apart the secular fabric,
			<lb />
			to overthrow democratically elected government, to promote
			<lb />
			prejudice and bigotry, to demoralise the security forces, to thwart
			<lb />
			the economic progress and development and so on. This cannot be
			<lb />
			equated with a usual law and order problem within a State. On the
			<lb />
			other hand, it is inter-State, international or cross-border in
			<lb />
			character. Fight against the overt and covert acts of terrorism is not
			<lb />
			a regular criminal justice endeavour. Rather, it is defence of our
			<lb />
			nation and its citizens. It is a challenge to the whole nation and
			<lb />
			invisible force of Indianness that binds this great nation
			<lb />
			together ...&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			18. More recently, in Yakub Abdul Razak Memon vs State of
			<lb />
			Maharashtra through CBI, Bombay , the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court
			<lb />
			4
			<lb />
			refers to acts of terrorism in the following words:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;... Acts of terrorism can range from threats to actual
			<lb />
			assassinations, kidnappings, airline hijackings, bomb scares, car
			<lb />
			bombs, building explosions, mailing of dangerous materials,
			<lb />
			computer based attacks and the use of chemical, biological, and
			<lb />
			nuclear weapons-weapons of mass destruction (WMD)&quot;
			<lb />
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			19. As this court held in Asif Iqbal Tanha (supra) therefore, in our view,
			<lb />
			although the definition of &apos;terrorist act&apos; in section 15 UAPA is wide
			<lb />
			and even somewhat vague, the definition must partake of the essential
			<lb />
			character of terrorism and the phrase &apos;terrorist act&apos; cannot be
			<lb />
			permitted to be applied in a cavalier manner to criminal acts or
			<lb />
			omissions that fall squarely within the definition of conventional
			<lb />
			offences as defined inter alia under the IPC. We must not forget the
			<lb />
			principle laid down by the Constitution Bench of the Hon&apos;ble
			<lb />
			Supreme Court in A.K. Roy vs. Union of India and Ors. where it
			<lb />
			5
			<lb />
			says that the requirement that crimes must be defined with an
			<lb />
			appropriate definitiveness is a fundamental concept of criminal law
			<lb />
			and must be regarded as a pervading theme of our Constitution
			<lb />
			since the decision in Maneka Gandhi vs. Union of India ; and that
			<lb />
			6
			<lb />
			the underlying principle is that every person is entitled to be informed
			<lb />
			as to what the State commands or permits and the life and liberty of
			<lb />
			the person cannot be put on peril of an ambiguity. The Constitution
			<lb />
			Bench further says that to stand true to this principle, what is expected
			<lb />
			is that the language of the law must contain adequate warning of the
			<lb />
			conduct which may fall within the proscribed area &apos;when measured
			<lb />
			(1982) 1 SCC 271.
			<lb />
			by common understanding&apos;. Most importantly, the Constitution
			<lb />
			Bench says:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;... These expressions, though they are difficult to define, do not
			<lb />
			elude a just application to practical situations. The use of language
			<lb />
			carries with it the inconvenience of the imperfections of
			<lb />
			language...&quot;.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			&quot;...We must, however, utter a word of caution that since the concepts
			<lb />
			are not defined, undoubtedly because they are not capable of a
			<lb />
			precise definition, courts must strive to give to those concepts a
			<lb />
			narrower construction than what the literal words suggest ...&quot;.
			<lb />
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			20. We must also carefully note the words of another Constitution Bench
			<lb />
			of the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court in Sanjay Dutt vs. State through CBI
			<lb />
			(II) to the effect that when law visits a person with serious penal
			<lb />
			7
			<lb />
			consequences, courts must take extra care to ensure that those to
			<lb />
			whom the legislature did not intend to be covered by the express
			<lb />
			language of the statute &quot;are not roped in by stretching the law&quot;.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			21. Our jurisprudence therefore dictates that where a provision of law
			<lb />
			which contains serious penal consequences is vague or widely
			<lb />
			worded, such provision must be construed narrowly to bring it within
			<lb />
			the constitutional framework; and most importantly, must be applied
			<lb />
			in a just and fair way, lest it unjustly sucks within its ambit persons
			<lb />
			whom the Legislature never intended to punish. Where the court finds
			<lb />
			that an act or omission is adequately addressed and dealt with by the
			<lb />
			ordinary penal law of the land, the court must not countenance a State
			<lb />
			agency &apos;crying wolf&apos;.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			22. Upon a careful consideration of the aforesaid verdicts of the Hon&apos;ble
			<lb />
			Supreme Court, in our opinion, the intent and purpose of Parliament
			<lb />
			in enacting the UAPA and in amending it in 2004 and 2008 to bring
			<lb />
			terrorist activity within its scope, was and could only have been, to
			<lb />
			deal with matters of profound impact on the &apos;Defence of India&apos;,
			<lb />
			nothing more and nothing less. Had that not been the case, UAPA
			<lb />
			could not have been enacted by Parliament since the only entries in
			<lb />
			List-I of the Seventh Schedule to the Constitution that would bring the
			<lb />
			statute within the legislative competence of Parliament are Entry 1
			<lb />
			read with Entry 93 relating to the Defence of India and offences with
			<lb />
			respect to the Defence of India. It was not the intent, nor purpose of
			<lb />
			enacting UAPA that other offences of the usual and ordinary kind,
			<lb />
			however grave, egregious or heinous in their nature and extent,
			<lb />
			should also be covered by UAPA, since such conventional matters
			<lb />
			would have fallen within Entry 1 of List-II (State List) and/or Entry 1
			<lb />
			of List-III (Concurrent List) of the Seventh Schedule of our
			<lb />
			Constitution. This is the only possible view that can be taken if we are
			<lb />
			to lean in favour of constitutionality of the provisions of section 15,
			<lb />
			17 and 18 of the UAPA, as we must.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<head>
			Right to Protest
			<lb />
		</head>
		<p>
			23. As in Asif Iqbal Tanha (supra), since this matter also emanates from
			<lb />
			protests organised by certain persons against the CAA and the NRC;
			<lb />
			and since the State alleges that these were not ordinary protests but
			<lb />
			were of a kind that have shaken, or are &apos;likely&apos; to have shaken, the
			<lb />
			entire foundations of our Nation, we must discuss what the law
			<lb />
			considers as permissible contours of a protest that would not threaten
			<lb />
			our Nation.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			24. In this context, we are required to examine, as to when the
			<lb />
			constitutionally guaranteed right to protest flowing from the right
			<lb />
			under Article 19(1)(b) of the Constitution to &quot;assemble peaceably and
			<lb />
			without arms&quot;, turns into a cognizable offence under the ordinary
			<lb />
			penal law; and when the right to protest gets further vitiated and
			<lb />
			becomes a terrorist act, or a conspiracy or an act preparatory, to
			<lb />
			commission of a terrorist act under the UAPA.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			25. The observations of the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court in Mazdoor Kisan
			<lb />
			Shakti Sangathan vs Union of India and Anr give the most lucid
			<lb />
			8
			<lb />
			answer, explaining the contours of legitimate protest. In the said
			<lb />
			decision, the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court says that legitimate dissent is a
			<lb />
			distinguishable feature of any democracy and the question is not
			<lb />
			whether the issue raised by the protestors is right or wrong or
			<lb />
			whether it is justified or unjustified, since people have the right to
			<lb />
			express their views; and a particular cause, which in the first instance,
			<lb />
			may appear to be insignificant or irrelevant may gain momentum and
			<lb />
			acceptability when it is duly voiced and debated. The Hon&apos;ble
			<lb />
			Supreme Court further says that a demonstration may take various
			<lb />
			forms : it may be noisy, disorderly and even violent, in which case it
			<lb />
			would not fall within the permissible limits of Article 19(1)(a) or
			<lb />
			19(1)(b) and in such case the Government has the power to regulate,
			<lb />
			including prohibit, such protest or demonstration. The Government
			<lb />
			may even prohibit public meetings, demonstrations or protests on
			<lb />
			streets or highways to avoid nuisance or disturbance of traffic but the
			<lb />
			Government cannot close all streets or open areas for public meetings
			<lb />
			thereby defeating the fundamental right that flows from Article 19(1)
			<lb />
			(a) and 19(1)(b) of the Constitution.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			26. In the present case, we are not deciding if the protests, in organising
			<lb />
			which the appellant is alleged to have been involved, were within the
			<lb />
			constitutionally guaranteed right to assembly, or whether they crossed
			<lb />
			the limit of what is permissible under Article 19(1)(a) and 19(1)(b)
			<lb />
			and became non-peaceful protests. However, what we find is that, for
			<lb />
			one there is nothing to say that the Government had prohibited the
			<lb />
			protest in the first instance. What we know is that offences, if any, that
			<lb />
			are alleged to have been committed by reason of the protests having
			<lb />
			been turned non-peaceful, are subject matter of FIR Nos. 48/2020
			<lb />
			and 50/2020, in which the appellant is one of the accused and in
			<lb />
			which the appellant has been admitted to bail and will face trial in
			<lb />
			due course. There is absolutely nothing in the subject charge-sheet, by
			<lb />
			way of any specific or particularised allegation, that would show the
			<lb />
			possible commission of a &apos;terrorist act&apos; within the meaning of section
			<lb />
			15 UAPA; or an act of &apos;raising funds&apos; to commit a terrorist act under
			<lb />
			section 17; or an act of &apos;conspiracy&apos; to commit or an &apos;act preparatory&apos;
			<lb />
			to commit, a terrorist act within the meaning of section 18 UAPA.
			<lb />
			Accordingly, prima-facie we are unable to discern in the subject
			<lb />
			charge-sheet the elemental factual ingredients that are a must to
			<lb />
			found any of the offences defined under section 15, 17 or 18 UAPA.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			27. In our view, the subject charge-sheet and the material filed therewith
			<lb />
			does not contain any specific, particularised, factual allegations that
			<lb />
			would make-out the ingredients of the offences under sections 15, 17
			<lb />
			or 18 UAPA. As we have observed in Asif Iqbal Tanha (supra),
			<lb />
			alleging extremely grave and serious penal offences under sections
			<lb />
			15, 17 and 18 UAPA against people frivolously, would undermine the
			<lb />
			intent and purpose of the Parliament in enacting a law that is meant to
			<lb />
			address threats to the very existence of our Nation. Wanton use of
			<lb />
			serious penal provisions would only trivialise them. Whatever other
			<lb />
			offence(s) the appellant may or may not have committed, at least on a
			<lb />
			prima facie view, the State has been unable to persuade us that the
			<lb />
			accusations against the appellant show commission of offences under
			<lb />
			sections 15, 17 or 18 UAPA.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			28. Since, in our opinion, no offence under sections 15, 17 or 18 UAPA is
			<lb />
			made-out against the appellant on a prima facie appreciation of the
			<lb />
			subject charge-sheet and the material collected and cited by the
			<lb />
			prosecution, the additional conditions, limitations and restrictions on
			<lb />
			grant of bail under section 43D(5) UAPA do not apply; and the court
			<lb />
			must therefore apply the usual and ordinary considerations for bail
			<lb />
			under section 439 Cr.P.C.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<head>
			General Principles of Bail
			<lb />
		</head>
		<p>
			29. The general principles of grant or refusal of bail are well settled.
			<lb />
			Since a detailed discussion of such principles has recently been made
			<lb />
			by us in our judgment in Asif Iqbal Tanha (supra), only a brief
			<lb />
			reiteration of the principles would suffice in the present case, since
			<lb />
			both cases arise from the same subject FIR.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			30. Though grant of bail involves exercise of discretionary power by the
			<lb />
			court, as always, the exercise of discretion must be judicious and not
			<lb />
			perfunctory or as a matter of course. In granting bail the court must
			<lb />
			keep in mind not only the nature of accusations but also the severity
			<lb />
			of the punishment and the nature of evidence in support of the
			<lb />
			accusations. Apart from being prima facie satisfied as regards the
			<lb />
			charges levelled; the court must also reasonably assess the
			<lb />
			apprehension of flight risk, evidence tampering and witness
			<lb />
			intimidation; with careful regard to the genuineness of the
			<lb />
			prosecution. The court must also consider the character, behaviour,
			<lb />
			means, position and standing of the accused and the likelihood of the
			<lb />
			offence being repeated. 9
			<lb />
			31. Furthermore, we remind ourselves that the object of bail is neither
			<lb />
			punitive nor preventative but is principally to secure the presence of
			<lb />
			the accused at the trial; and that punishment begins only after
			<lb />
			conviction and that everyone is deemed to be innocent until duly tried
			<lb />
			and found guilty. It is well settled that detention in custody pending
			<lb />
			completion of trial can cause great hardship to an accused; that it is
			<lb />
			improper for any court to refuse bail as a mark of disapproval of the
			<lb />
			past conduct or to refuse bail to a person yet to be convicted only to
			<lb />
			give him a taste of imprisonment as a lesson. &quot;Necessity&quot; to secure
			<lb />
			the attendance of an accused at the trial, the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court
			<lb />
			has held, is the operative test. It also requires to be understood that
			<lb />
			10
			<lb />
			though the larger interest of the public or the State and other similar
			<lb />
			considerations are also relevant, there is no hard and fast rule and
			<lb />
			cf. Ash Mohammad vs Shiv Raj Singh &amp; Anr., (2012) 9 SCC 446 : para 8 and 11.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			9
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			cf. Sanjay Chandra vs CBI, (2012) 1 SCC 40 : para 21-23.
			<lb />
			each case has to be considered on its own facts, circumstances and
			<lb />
			merits. 11
			<lb />
			32. Since courts often tend to fall into this error, it is extremely important
			<lb />
			to bear in mind the words of the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court that grant of
			<lb />
			bail cannot be thwarted merely by asserting that an offence is grave,
			<lb />
			since the gravity of the offence can only beget the length of the
			<lb />
			sentence, which may be awarded upon conclusion of the trial. 12
			<lb />
			33. We must also never forget the profound insight of V.R. Krishna Iyer,
			<lb />
			J., when he said that the consequences of pre-trial detention are
			<lb />
			grave; that by being kept in custody, an undertrial accused, though
			<lb />
			presumed innocent, is subjected to psychological and physical
			<lb />
			deprivations of jail life; that the accused is also prevented from
			<lb />
			contributing to the preparation of the defence; and that the burden of
			<lb />
			pre-trial detention frequently falls heavily on the innocent members of
			<lb />
			the family. 13
			<lb />
			Discussion &amp; Conclusions
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			34. In the present case, a closer reading of the allegations made against
			<lb />
			the appellant shows that no specific, particularised or definite act is
			<lb />
			attributed to the appellant, apart from the admitted fact that she
			<lb />
			engaged herself in organising anti-CAA and anti-NRC protests around
			<lb />
			the time when violence and rioting broke-out in the certain parts of
			<lb />
			North-East Delhi. Infact, on a reading of the portions of the subject
			<lb />
			charge-sheet to which attention has been drawn by the State and
			<lb />
			cf. P. Chidambaram vs. CBI, 2019 SCC OnLine SC 1380 : para 22.
			<lb />
			which have been extracted in the screenshots in Annexure-A to this
			<lb />
			judgment, it is seen that invariably the appellant&apos;s name appears
			<lb />
			alongwith that of several other alleged co-conspirators and even the
			<lb />
			instructions and directions issued by the main accused persons are not
			<lb />
			directed towards the appellant. In our reading of the subject charge-
			<lb />
			sheet and the material included in it, therefore, the allegations made
			<lb />
			against the appellant are not even borne-out from the material on
			<lb />
			which they are based. The State cannot thwart grant of bail merely by
			<lb />
			confusing issues.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			35. Allegations relating to inflammatory speeches, organising of chakka
			<lb />
			jaam, instigating women to protest and to stock-pile various articles
			<lb />
			and other similar allegations, in our view, at worst, are evidence that
			<lb />
			the appellant participated in organising protests, but we can discern no
			<lb />
			specific or particularised allegation, much less any material to bear-
			<lb />
			out the allegation, that the appellant incited violence, what to talk of
			<lb />
			committing a terrorist act or a conspiracy or act preparatory to the
			<lb />
			commission of a terrorist act as understood in the UAPA.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			36. We are constrained to express, that it seems, that in its anxiety to
			<lb />
			suppress dissent, in the mind of the State, the line between the
			<lb />
			constitutionally guaranteed right to protest and terrorist activity seems
			<lb />
			to be getting somewhat blurred. If this mindset gains traction, it would
			<lb />
			be a sad day for democracy.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			37. In our view therefore, after carefully considering the allegations in
			<lb />
			charge-sheet dated 16.09.2020 alongwith the material adduced
			<lb />
			therewith, we are not persuaded to think that prima-facie the
			<lb />
			accusations made against the appellant make-out any offence under
			<lb />
			sections 15, 17 and /or 18 of the UAPA; and therefore the stringent
			<lb />
			conditionalities contained in section 43D(5) of the UAPA would not
			<lb />
			apply and the appellant&apos;s bail plea would need to be considered on the
			<lb />
			general principles of bail enunciated above.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			38. The subject charge-sheet has been filed before the learned Special
			<lb />
			Court; cognizance of some of the offences has been taken; but charges
			<lb />
			are yet to be framed. Some 740 prosecution witnesses, including
			<lb />
			public witnesses, protected witnesses and police witnesses are stated
			<lb />
			to have been cited in the subject charge-sheet but deposition of the
			<lb />
			witnesses is yet to commence. Considering the prevailing situation,
			<lb />
			namely the havoc created by the second wave of the COVID-19
			<lb />
			pandemic, it is hardly likely that trial will proceed, much less
			<lb />
			conclude anytime soon.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			39. Moreover, the appellant has already been granted regular bail by the
			<lb />
			learned ASJ vidé order dated 17.09.2020 in FIR No. 50/2020; and by
			<lb />
			the learned Duty Metropolitan Magistrate vidé order dated 24.05.2020
			<lb />
			in FIR No. 48/2020, in which (latter) order, the court has in fact
			<lb />
			recorded that the appellant was only protesting the passage of the
			<lb />
			CAA and the conducting of the NRC and had not indulged in any
			<lb />
			violence. There is bound to be some overlap between what the
			<lb />
			appellant is alleged to have done in the said two other FIRs and in the
			<lb />
			subject FIR from which this appeal arises, since the offences alleged
			<lb />
			against the appellant are in the context of the violence and rioting that
			<lb />
			occurred in the North-East part of Delhi within the span of a few days
			<lb />
			in February 2020.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			40. In our considered opinion, keeping in view the background, profile
			<lb />
			and position of the appellant, there is no reasonably discernible basis
			<lb />
			to suspect, nor do we entertain any reasonable apprehension, that the
			<lb />
			appellant will either flee from justice; or that she will tamper with
			<lb />
			evidence; or that she will intimidate witnesses or otherwise attempt to
			<lb />
			frustrate trial. Due notice is also taken of the fact that the appellant
			<lb />
			was not arrested in the subject FIR for nearly 3 months after the date
			<lb />
			of its registration.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			41. As a sequitur to the foregoing discussion, we are of the view that the
			<lb />
			appellant is entitled to be enlarged on regular bail. We accordingly
			<lb />
			set-aside impugned order dated 28.01.2021 made by the learned
			<lb />
			Special Court in case arising from FIR No. 59/2020 dated 06.03.2020
			<lb />
			registered at P.S.: Special Cell, Delhi; and admit the appellant to
			<lb />
			regular bail until conclusion of trial, subject to the following
			<lb />
			conditions:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			(a)
			<lb />
			The appellant shall furnish a personal bond in the sum of Rs.
			<lb />
			50,000/-(Rs. Fifty Thousand Only) with 02 local sureties in
			<lb />
			the like amount, to the satisfaction of the learned trial court;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(b)
			<lb />
			The appellant shall furnish to the Investigating Officer/SHO a
			<lb />
			cellphone number on which the appellant may be contacted at
			<lb />
			any time and shall ensure that the number is kept active and
			<lb />
			switched-on at all times;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(c)
			<lb />
			The appellant shall ordinarily reside at her place of residence
			<lb />
			as per trial court record and shall inform the Investigating
			<lb />
			Officer if she changes her usual place of residence;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(d)
			<lb />
			If the appellant has a passport, she shall surrender the same to
			<lb />
			the learned trial court and shall not travel out of the country
			<lb />
			without prior permission of the learned trial court;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(e)
			<lb />
			The appellant shall not contact, nor visit, nor offer any
			<lb />
			inducement, threat or promise to any of the prosecution
			<lb />
			witnesses or other persons acquainted with the facts of case.
			<lb />
			The appellant shall not tamper with evidence nor otherwise
			<lb />
			indulge in any act or omission that is unlawful or that would
			<lb />
			prejudice the proceedings in the pending trial.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			42. Nothing in this order shall be construed as an expression on the merits
			<lb />
			of the pending trial.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			43. A copy of this order be sent to the concerned Jail Superintendent.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			44. The appeal stands disposed of in the above terms.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			45. Pending applications, if any, are also disposed of.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			SIDDHARTH MRIDUL, J
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			ANUP JAIRAM BHAMBHANI, J
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			JUNE 15, 2021
			<lb />
		</p>
	</text>
</tei>
