<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc xml:id="0" />
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <head>
            Per Arvind Singh Chandel, J.
            <lb />
        </head>

        <p>
            1.
            <lb />
            This appeal is directed against the judgment dated 26.6.2004
            <lb />
            passed in Sessions Trial No.374 of 1999 by the 4 th Additional
            <lb />
            Sessions Judge, Ambikapur at Surguja convicting and sentencing
            <lb />
            the accused/Appellants as under:
        </p>
        <lb />
        <table>
            Conviction
            <lb />
            Sentence
            <lb />
            Under Section 302 of the
            <lb />
            Indian Penal Code
            <lb />
            Imprisonment for Life and fine of
            <lb />
            Rs.1,000/-each with default
            <lb />
            stipulation
            <lb />
            Under Section 307/34 of
            <lb />
            the Indian Penal Code
            <lb />
            Rigorous Imprisonment for 7
            <lb />
            years and fine of Rs.500/-each
            <lb />
            with default stipulation
            <lb />
            Under Section 452/34 of
            <lb />
            the Indian Penal Code
            <lb />
            Rigorous Imprisonment for 5
            <lb />
            years and fine of Rs.200/-each
            <lb />
            with default stipulation
            <lb />
            Under Section 323/34 of
            <lb />
            the Indian Penal Code
            <lb />
            Rigorous Imprisonment for 1 year
            <lb />
        </table>

        <p>
            2.
            <lb />
            Case of the prosecution, in brief, is that on 26.8.1999 at about 5:00
            <lb />
            p.m., Balkumari (PW11) was standing up before her house and her
            <lb />
            husband Jagarnath (PW10) was inside the house. At that time,
            <lb />
            Appellant No.4, Bhisam alias Bhima along with his friends teased
            <lb />
            her. Having heard noise, her husband came out of the house. He
            <lb />
            abused Bhisam and his friends on which they ran away. At about
            <lb />
            9:00 p.m., when Balkumari was taking meals along with her
            <lb />
            children, her cousin Ramkishun (PW14) was standing up near the
            <lb />
            door of her house. At that time, the accused/Appellants entered
            <lb />
            her house and started beating Ramkishun and Jagarnath. When
            <lb />
            she intervened, the accused/Appellants assaulted her also with
            <lb />
            danda. Having heard noise, her neighbour Suryapal (deceased)
            <lb />
            came there. He was also assaulted by the accused/Appellants
            <lb />
            with danda. As a result of the assault, he sustained injury on the
            <lb />
            head and face and fell down. Having seen the villagers coming
            <lb />
            toward the accused/Appellants, they fled from there. Jagarnath
            <lb />
            and Suryapal were taken to the hospital. Suryapal died during
            <lb />
            treatment. Dehati Nalishi (Ex.P10) was lodged by Balkumari
            <lb />
            (PW11). Inquest (Ex.P5) was prepared on 27.8.1999. Post
            <lb />
            mortem examination was conducted by Dr. M.K. Jain (PW18). His
            <lb />
            report is Ex.P34A in which he found following injuries:
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            1.
            <lb />
            Three lacerated wounds over the middle of jaw
            <lb />
            and left side, size 1½ cm x ½ cm to 1 cm x ½
            <lb />
            cm, bone deep with multiple depressed
            <lb />
            fracture of mandibles
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            2.
            <lb />
            Small incised wound, in both upper and lower
            <lb />
            lip of left side
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            3.
            <lb />
            Small lacerated wound over the left eyebrow
            <lb />
            with block eye, left side
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            4.
            <lb />
            One lacerated wound over the left side cheek,
            <lb />
            1 cm x ½ cm
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            5.
            <lb />
            One incised wound over the left occipital
            <lb />
            region, 3 cm x ½ cm
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            6.
            <lb />
            Three big contusions over the anterior aspect
            <lb />
            of chest, 11&quot; x 3&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            7.
            <lb />
            One lacerated wound over the right pinna of
            <lb />
            ear 2 cm x ½ cm
            <lb />

        </item>
        <p>
            On dissection of the dead body, he found following injuries:
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            1.
            <lb />
            There is multiple depressed fracture of
            <lb />
            mandible seen, 4 pieces seen in mickle and left
            <lb />
            side of mandible and one depressed fracture of
            <lb />
            right angle of mandible seen
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            2.
            <lb />
            Depressed fracture of maxilla with loss of
            <lb />
            upper teeth, upper right side of maxilla with
            <lb />
            teeth impacted in deep part of throat post part
            <lb />
            of pharynx
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            3.
            <lb />
            Depressed fracture of nose with depressed
            <lb />
            fracture of maxilla and left side of zygomatic
            <lb />
            bone
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            4.
            <lb />
            Fracture of sternum with fracture of ribs in
            <lb />
            left side -2 nd to 4 th ribs fracture
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            5.
            <lb />
            Both lungs are grossly congested with blood
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            6.
            <lb />
            Smell of alcohol in stomach
        </item>
        <lb />
        <p>
            Cause of death was opined by him to be asphyxia resulted by
            <lb />
            airway obstruction due to multiple grievous injuries and the nature
            <lb />
            of death was opined to be homicidal.
            <lb />
            On 27.8.1999, First Information Report (Ex.P33) was registered
            <lb />
            on the basis of Dehati Nalishi. During investigation, memorandum
            <lb />
            statement (Ex.P21) of Appellant No.1, Rustam and memorandum
            <lb />
            statement (Ex.P22) of Appellant No.4, Bhisam were recorded. One
            <lb />
            iron khukhari was seized from Appellant No.4, Bhisam vide
            <lb />
            Ex.P23. One knife was seized from Appellant No.1, Rustam vide
            <lb />
            Ex.P15. One terricot full-pant was also seized from Appellant No.1
            <lb />
            vide Ex.P16. Memorandum statement (Ex.P20) of Appellant No.2,
            <lb />
            Ganesh was recorded and a piece of bahinga made of wood was
            <lb />
            seized from him vide Ex.P17. One vest stained with blood was
            <lb />
            also seized from him vide Ex.P18. Plain and blood stained soil
            <lb />
            were seized from the place of occurrence vide Ex.P12. Jagarnath
            <lb />
            was medically examined by Dr. B.P. Chandra (PW15) vide Ex.P27.
            <lb />
            Balkumari was also examined by Dr. B.P. Chandra vide Ex.P28.
            <lb />
            Ramkishun (PW14) was medically examined by Dr. Habib (PW16)
            <lb />
            vide Ex.P30. On completion of the investigation, a charge-sheet
            <lb />
            was filed against the accused/Appellants for offences punishable
            <lb />
            under Sections 147, 148, 149, 302, 307, 452, 450, 325 of the
            <lb />
            Indian Penal Code and Section 25 of the Arms Act. Charges were
            <lb />
            framed against them under Sections 147, 148, 452/149, 323/149,
            <lb />
            302/149, 307/149 of the Indian Penal Code.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            3.
            <lb />
            To rope in the accused/Appellants, the prosecution examined as
            <lb />
            many as 22 witnesses. Statement of the accused/Appellants were
            <lb />
            also recorded under Section 313 of the Code of Criminal
            <lb />
            Procedure in which they denied the guilt. No witness has been
            <lb />
            examined in their defence.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            4.
            <lb />
            After trial, the Trial Court acquitted accused Manoj son of Laxman,
            <lb />
            accused Sera son of Soharnath and accused Santosh son of
            <lb />
            Awadhesh of the charges framed against them, but convicted and
            <lb />
            sentenced the accused/Appellants as mentioned in the first
            <lb />
            paragraph of this judgment. Hence, this appeal by the Appellants.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            5.
            <lb />
            Learned Counsel appearing for the accused/Appellants argued that
            <lb />
            Balkumari (PW11), Ramkishun (PW14) and Jagarnath (PW10) did
            <lb />
            not know Appellant No.1, Rustam, Appellant No.2, Ganesh and
            <lb />
            Appellant No.3, Samat from earlier. The FIR was lodged on the
            <lb />
            date of incident itself in which only the name of Appellant No.4,
            <lb />
            Bhisam is mentioned. Appellants No.1, 2 and 3 have been later on
            <lb />
            falsely implicated. No identification parade was conducted in
            <lb />
            respect of Appellants No.1, 2 and 3. None of the prosecution
            <lb />
            witnesses has stated about Appellant No.3 in their Court
            <lb />
            statements. The prosecution witnesses have taken names of
            <lb />
            Appellants No.1 and 2 in their Court statements, but their names
            <lb />
            are not mentioned in the FIR, therefore, the case of the
            <lb />
            prosecution against Appellants No.1 and 2 is suspicious. Since
            <lb />
            Appellant No.4, Bhisam had worked in the house of Balkumari and
            <lb />
            Jagarnath and some dues was to be paid by them to Appellant
            <lb />
            No.4, therefore, he has been falsely implicated on the ground of
            <lb />
            this dispute.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            6.
            <lb />
            Per contra, Learned Counsel appearing for the State supported the
            <lb />
            impugned judgment.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            7.
            <lb />
            We have heard Learned Counsel appearing for the parties and
            <lb />
            perused the material available on record including the impugned
            <lb />
            judgment with utmost circumspection.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            8.
            <lb />
            In this case, there are 3 eyewitnesses, namely, Jagarnath (PW10),
            <lb />
            Balkumari (PW11) and Ramkishun (PW14).
            <lb />
            First, we shall
            <lb />
            examine the Court statements of these three eyewitnesses.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            9.
            <lb />
            Balkumari (PW11) has stated that on 26.8.1999 at about 5:00 p.m.,
            <lb />
            she was standing up behind her house. At that time, Appellant
            <lb />
            No.1 Rustam, Appelllant No.2 Ganesh and Appellant No.4 Bhisam
            <lb />
            came there and started scuffling with her and they teased her. She
            <lb />
            began to scold them. Having heard the noise, her husband
            <lb />
            Jagarnath (PW10) and Nanhuram (PW6) came there and
            <lb />
            prevented them. On this, these three accused/Appellants caused
            <lb />
            Nanhuram to fall down. When her husband intervened, they fled
            <lb />
            from there. Appellant No.1, Rustam, while going away warned that
            <lb />
            they would see them. She has further stated that at about 9:00
            <lb />
            p.m., when she was taking dinner with her family members at her
            <lb />
            house, her cousin Ramkishun (PW14) was also present in the
            <lb />
            dinner. She has further stated that Ramkishun went out of her
            <lb />
            house and when he returned inside the house, he told that many
            <lb />
            persons were coming towards their house armed with lathi and
            <lb />
            danda. 7-8 persons entered their house. They started beating her
            <lb />
            and her husband. She came out of the house and shouted. Kabina
            <lb />
            Kujur (PW9), Suryapal (deceased) and many other persons
            <lb />
            reached there. She has further stated that since her husband had
            <lb />
            sustained many injuries and had become unconscious, she had
            <lb />
            gone inside her house. Therefore, she was unable to tell that who
            <lb />
            assaulted Suryapal. She has further stated that the assailants had
            <lb />
            also assaulted Ramkishun. She has categorically stated that
            <lb />
            during the assault, she had identified accused Rustam, Ganesh,
            <lb />
            Bhisam and Samat. As per the statement of this witness, Dehati
            <lb />
            Nalishi (Ex.P10) was recorded. In paragraph 21 of her cross-
            <lb />
            examination, she has admitted that in the Dehati Nalishi, she had
            <lb />
            not named accused Samat. She has further admitted that she had
            <lb />
            taken the name of accused Samat in the Court for the first time and
            <lb />
            she had come to know his name from other persons. Regarding
            <lb />
            accused Rustam and Ganesh, she has denied the suggestion that
            <lb />
            she had not named accused Rustam and Ganesh in the Dehati
            <lb />
            Nalishi. But, a perusal of the Dehati Nalishi shows that the names
            <lb />
            of accused Rustam and Ganesh are not mentioned therein. But, in
            <lb />
            her statement (Ex.D2) under Section 161 Cr.P.C. recorded on
            <lb />
            27.8.1999, i.e., just next day of the incident, she has mentioned the
            <lb />
            names of accused Rustam and Ganesh also. In paragraph 11 of
            <lb />
            her deposition, she has admitted that she had seen accused
            <lb />
            Rustam and Ganesh first time in her life at the time of incident
            <lb />
            itself. In paragraph 23, she has stated that no identification parade
            <lb />
            was conducted by the police.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            10.
            <lb />
            Jagarnath (PW10), husband of Balkumari has stated that he knew
            <lb />
            only accused Rustam, Ganesh and Bhisam. He has further
            <lb />
            deposed that at the time of incident at about 5:00 p.m., accused
            <lb />
            Rustam, Bhisam and Ganesh had abused her wife Balkumari
            <lb />
            (PW11). At that time, he and Nanhuram (PW6) had gone there.
            <lb />
            These three accused had caused Nanhuram to fall down and
            <lb />
            warning that they will come again, ran away from there. He has
            <lb />
            further stated that at about 9:00 p.m., when he was at home along
            <lb />
            with his family members, these three accused and other 8 persons
            <lb />
            came inside his house and started assaulting Ramkishun (PW14),
            <lb />
            him and his wife. He has further stated that his wife shouting went
            <lb />
            out of the house. On this, Suryapal came there. The assailants
            <lb />
            assaulted Suryapal also. He has further stated that due to the
            <lb />
            assault, he fell unconscious. Later on, he came to know that
            <lb />
            Suryapal had died. In paragraph 9, he has admitted that he had
            <lb />
            seen accused Rustam and Ganesh for the first time at the time of
            <lb />
            incident. He knew only accused Bhisam from earlier. In paragraph
            <lb />
            20 of his cross-examination, he has categorically stated that he did
            <lb />
            not know accused Samat nor did he tell his name to the police. In
            <lb />
            paragraph 18, he has admitted that there was no previous enmity
            <lb />
            with accused Rustam, Ganesh and Bhisam.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            11.
            <lb />
            Ramkishun (PW14), the other eyewitness of the incident has
            <lb />
            stated that at about 8:00 p.m., he had gone to the house of his
            <lb />
            brother-in-law Jagarnath (PW10) and after taking dinner he was
            <lb />
            sitting in the courtyard of the house. He saw that 7-8 persons were
            <lb />
            coming towards the house of Jagarnath. He told about this to
            <lb />
            Jagarnath. Jagarnath asked him to put a lamp outside. He taking a
            <lb />
            lamp outside began to peep in the light. At that time, the persons
            <lb />
            coming towards the house of Jagarnath reached there and began
            <lb />
            to assault him and Jagarnath. He has further stated that when he
            <lb />
            began to run away, 3 assailants chased him. On the way, Suryapal
            <lb />
            met him. He told him about the incident. He has further stated that
            <lb />
            Suryapal went to the house of Jagarnath. He saw that 3-4
            <lb />
            assailants were assaulting Jagarnath. Having seen this, he ran
            <lb />
            away from there. He has categorically stated that he did not
            <lb />
            identify any of the assailants except acquitted accused Santosh
            <lb />
            and Manoj. He is the witness of memorandum statements
            <lb />
            (Ex.P20, P21, P22) and seizure (Ex.P15, P16, P17 and P23), but
            <lb />
            he has not supported the above memorandum statements and
            <lb />
            seizure memo and has been declared hostile.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            12.
            <lb />
            Kotwar Nanhuram (PW6) is the witness of memorandum (Ex.P22)
            <lb />
            of accused Bhisam and seizure (Ex.P23), but he has not supported
            <lb />
            the said memorandum and seizure and has been declared hostile.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            13.
            <lb />
            Constable Mansingh (PW2) is the witness who had taken the dead
            <lb />
            body of Suryapal for post mortem examination.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            14.
            <lb />
            Sunil Sarkar (PW3) has stated that Balkumari (PW11), wife of
            <lb />
            Jagarnath, saying Bachao Bachao, was shouting for help. He saw
            <lb />
            Jagarnath (PW10) in injured condition. He had sustained injuries
            <lb />
            on the head and hands and had fallen unconscious. He was taken
            <lb />
            to the hospital. He has further stated that the wife of Jagarnath had
            <lb />
            told him that some persons had entered her house and assaulted
            <lb />
            them.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            15.
            <lb />
            Ajit Mandal (PW4) has stated that he was sleeping. At about 9:30
            <lb />
            p.m., having heard the noise, he came out of his house and saw
            <lb />
            that both Jagarnath and Suryapal were in injured condition. Both
            <lb />
            were taken to the hospital. He has further stated that later on in
            <lb />
            the night, Jagarnath told him that accused Bhisam and his friends
            <lb />
            had assaulted him. But, this fact is not mentioned in his case diary
            <lb />
            statement.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            16.
            <lb />
            Krishna Sarkar (PW5) has stated that having heard the noise, he
            <lb />
            went to the spot. He saw both Jagarnath and Suryapal in injured
            <lb />
            condition. Both were taken to the hospital. Later on, he came to
            <lb />
            know that Suryapal died.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            17.
            <lb />
            Nanhuram (PW6) has stated that Kabina Kujur (PW9) came to his
            <lb />
            house and told him that Jagarnath (PW10) and Suryapal were
            <lb />
            assaulted by some persons. He has further stated that he went to
            <lb />
            the spot, where he saw that Jagarnath and Suryapal were being
            <lb />
            taken to the hospital. Later on, he came to know that Suryapal
            <lb />
            died. He has further stated that next day, at about 4:00 a.m.,
            <lb />
            Jagarnath told him that accused Bhisam and his friends had
            <lb />
            assaulted him. But, this fact is also not mentioned in his case diary
            <lb />
            statement.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            18.
            <lb />
            Kabina Kujur (PW9), other eyewitness of the incident has not
            <lb />
            supported the case of the prosecution and has been declared
            <lb />
            hostile.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            19.
            <lb />
            Preetlal (PW12) is the witness of seizure (Ex.P11). He has stated
            <lb />
            that knife, sleeper, cap, piece of brick and danda were seized in his
            <lb />
            presence from the courtyard of the house of Jagarnath (PW10).
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            20.
            <lb />
            Pannalal (PW13) is the witness of seizure (Ex.P12 and P13). Vide
            <lb />
            Ex.P12, plain and blood stained soil were seized from the spot.
            <lb />
            Vide Ex.P13, one pair of sleeper was seized from the spot. Vide
            <lb />
            Ex.P14, one stool made of wood, one pair of sleeper made of
            <lb />
            rubber, one cap and one rope were seized from the spot. He has
            <lb />
            supported these seizures. He is the witness of seizure (Ex.P15 to
            <lb />
            P19) and memorandum (Ex.P21), but he has not supported the
            <lb />
            said seizure and memorandum and, therefore, has been declared
            <lb />
            hostile.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            21.
            <lb />
            Dr. B.P. Chandra (PW15) has deposed that Jagarnath (PW10),
            <lb />
            Suryapal (deceased) and Balkumari (PW11) were brought to the
            <lb />
            hospital on 26.8.1999 in injured condition. After their admission in
            <lb />
            the hospital, Suryapal died during treatment. He intimated the
            <lb />
            police about death of Suryapal vide Ex.P25 and also intimated the
            <lb />
            police about the admission of Jagarnath and his wife Balkumari in
            <lb />
            the hospital vide Ex.P24 and P26. He has further stated that on
            <lb />
            27.8.1999, he had examined and prepared medical examination
            <lb />
            report of Jagarnath vide Ex.P27 in which he opined that the injuries
            <lb />
            suffered by Jagarnath could be caused by a hard and blunt object.
            <lb />
            Injuries No.2, 3 and 5 were simple in nature and the nature of rest
            <lb />
            of the injuries suffered by him could be reported only after x-ray
            <lb />
            examination. He also examined Balkumari. His report is Ex.P28 in
            <lb />
            which he found single lacerated wound over left parietal region of
            <lb />
            scalp of size 3 cms x 0.5 cm, skin deep with clotted blood present
            <lb />
            and opined that the injury suffered by Balkumari could be caused
            <lb />
            by a hard and blunt object and the nature of the injury suffered was
            <lb />
            simple.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            22.
            <lb />
            Dr. Habib (PW16) examined Ramkishun (PW14) on 27.8.1999. His
            <lb />
            report is Ex.P30 in which he opined that the injuries suffered by
            <lb />
            Ramkishun could be caused by a hard and blunt object and the
            <lb />
            nature of injuries were simple.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            23.
            <lb />
            Dr. M.K. Jain (PW18) is the witness who took out x-ray of
            <lb />
            Jagarnath (PW10) and gave report (Ex.P32) in which he found no
            <lb />
            bony injury on the head. He found compound fracture in left hand
            <lb />
            over radius and ulna bones. On 27.8.1999, he conducted post
            <lb />
            mortem examination of Suryapal and gave report (Ex.P34A). In
            <lb />
            Ex.P34A, he has reported the injuries aforementioned in this
            <lb />
            judgment and cause of death was opined by him to be asphyxia
            <lb />
            resulted by airway obstruction due to multiple grievous injuries and
            <lb />
            the nature of death was opined to be homicidal.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            24.
            <lb />
            Patwari Sanjay Singh (PW17) prepared spot-map (Ex.P31). Sub-
            <lb />
            Inspector Indrapal Singh (PW20) is the witness who investigated
            <lb />
            the alleged offence. Ward Boy Pramod Kumar (PW21) is the
            <lb />
            witness who, on 26.8.1999, took memo of the doctor to the police
            <lb />
            station. Merg Intimation was recorded vide Ex.P44. Teslal (PW22)
            <lb />
            is the witness before whom inquest (Ex.P5) was prepared.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            25.
            <lb />
            On minute examination of the evidence adduced by the
            <lb />
            prosecution, it is clear that the prosecution story is mainly based on
            <lb />
            the evidence of Balkumari (PW11), Jagarnath (PW10), Ramkishun
            <lb />
            (PW14) and the medical evidence. From the said evidence, it is
            <lb />
            clear that accused Bhisam had already worked in the house of
            <lb />
            Jagarnath and Balkumari and both the witnesses were acquainted
            <lb />
            with accused Bhisam. Both these witnesses did not know accused
            <lb />
            Rustam, Ganesh and Samat from earlier. From the statements of
            <lb />
            Ramkishun, Jagarnath and Balkumari, it is clear that at about 5:00
            <lb />
            p.m., accused Bhisam and some of his friends had teased
            <lb />
            Balkumari on which a dispute had arisen. It is further clear from
            <lb />
            their evidence that accused Bhisam and his friends ran away at
            <lb />
            that time. Later on, at about 9:00 p.m., accused Bhisam along with
            <lb />
            7-8 persons came to the house of Balkumari and all of them
            <lb />
            assaulted Ramkishun, Jagarnath and Balkumari. When Suryapal
            <lb />
            tried to intervene, he was also assaulted by all the assailants and
            <lb />
            as a result of which Suryapal later on died. Jagarnath had
            <lb />
            sustained grievous injuries as mentioned in the medical and x-ray
            <lb />
            examinations reports (Ex.P27 and P32) and Balkumari and
            <lb />
            Ramkishun had sustained simple injuries as mentioned in their
            <lb />
            medical examinations reports (Ex.P28 and P30, respectively).
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            26.
            <lb />
            In his Court statement, Ramkishun (PW14) has stated that he did
            <lb />
            not identify any of the accused. Jagarnath (PW10), in his
            <lb />
            evidence, has taken the names of accused Rustam, Ganesh and
            <lb />
            Bhisam only. He has categorically stated that accused Samat was
            <lb />
            not present at the time of occurrence. Balkumari (PW11) has also
            <lb />
            admitted that she had taken the name of accused Samat for the
            <lb />
            first time during her Court statement and that too she took his
            <lb />
            name in the Court statement on his name being told to her by
            <lb />
            some other persons. Though in Dehati Nalishi (Ex.P10) only the
            <lb />
            name of accused Bhisam is mentioned yet in her statement
            <lb />
            (Ex.D2) under Section 161 Cr.P.C. recorded just next day of the
            <lb />
            incident, i.e., on 27.8.1999, Balkumari has named accused Rustam
            <lb />
            and Ganesh also. In her Court statement also, she has named
            <lb />
            both accused Rustam and Ganesh along with accused Bhisam.
            <lb />
            Jagarnath has also named accused Rustam, Ganesh and Bhisam
            <lb />
            in his Court statement. Balkumari and Jagarnath have admitted in
            <lb />
            their Court statements that there was no previous enmity between
            <lb />
            them and accused Rustam, Ganesh and Bhisam. Therefore, there
            <lb />
            is no reason to believe that accused Rustam and Ganesh are
            <lb />
            being falsely implicated with accused Bhisam by Balkumari and
            <lb />
            Jagarnath.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            27.
            <lb />
            As per the statement of Dr. B.P. Chandra (PW15) and the medical
            <lb />
            examination report (Ex.P28) of Balkumari (PW11) and the
            <lb />
            statement of Dr. Habib (PW16) and the medical examination report
            <lb />
            (Ex.P30) of Ramkishun (PW14), both Ramkishun and Balkumari
            <lb />
            had sustained injuries as mentioned in Ex.P28 and P30 and the
            <lb />
            injuries sustained by them were simple in nature. As per the
            <lb />
            medical examination report (Ex.P27) of Jagarnath (PW10), he had
            <lb />
            sustained total 7 injuries. Injuries No.3 and 4 were present on the
            <lb />
            forehead, injuries No.5, 6 and 7 were present on the head and
            <lb />
            injury No.1 was present on the left hand. As per the x-ray report
            <lb />
            (Ex.P32), compound fracture was found in radius and ulna bones
            <lb />
            of left hand. As per the post mortem report (Ex.P34A) of Suryapal,
            <lb />
            injuries No.1 and 5 were present on the vital parts of his body.
            <lb />
            Multiple depressed fractures of mandibles were found. Depressed
            <lb />
            fracture of maxilla with loss of upper teeth was found. Depressed
            <lb />
            fracture of nose with depressed fracture of maxilla was also found.
            <lb />
            2 nd to 4 th ribs were also found fractured.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            28.
            <lb />
            From the evidence adduced by the prosecution, it is clear that
            <lb />
            there was no quarrel between the accused/Appellants and
            <lb />
            Jagarnath (PW10) and Balkumari (PW11). The dispute which had
            <lb />
            arisen due to teasing of Balkumari was the reason of the incident in
            <lb />
            question. There was no dispute between the accused/Appellants
            <lb />
            and deceased Suryapal. Suryapal was assaulted only when he
            <lb />
            had tried to intervene in the incident. Therefore, it is not
            <lb />
            established that the assailants had any intention to kill Suryapal.
            <lb />
            Similarly, out of the injuries suffered by Jagarnath, only the injury
            <lb />
            present on the left hand was grievous in nature and rest of his
            <lb />
            injuries were simple in nature. The injuries sustained by him was
            <lb />
            the result of a sudden quarrel took place between the parties.
            <lb />
            Therefore, there appears no intention on the part of the assailants
            <lb />
            to commit murder of Jagarnath. From the evidence, it is also clear
            <lb />
            that there is no evidence against accused/Appellant Samat. He is
            <lb />
            entitled to get benefit of doubt. From the evidence, no offence is
            <lb />
            made out against accused/Appellant Samat, therefore, he is
            <lb />
            acquitted of all the charges framed against him.
            <lb />
            Against
            <lb />
            accused/Appellants Rustam, Ganesh and Bhisam, the offence
            <lb />
            alleged under Section 302/34 IPC is not made out and instead
            <lb />
            thereof their offence falls under Section 304 Part II IPC. Similarly,
            <lb />
            there appears no intention on the part of the assailants to commit
            <lb />
            murder of Jagarnath. Therefore, the offence under Section 307/34
            <lb />
            IPC of accused/Appellants Rustam, Ganesh and Bhisam is altered
            <lb />
            to Section 325/34 IPC. For inflicting simple injuries to Balkumari
            <lb />
            (PW11) and Ramkishun (PW14), conviction of accused/Appellants
            <lb />
            Rustam, Ganesh and Bhisam under Sections 323/34 and 452/34
            <lb />
            IPC is affirmed.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            29.
            <lb />
            Now, we shall examine the case of Appellant No.1, Rustam and
            <lb />
            Appellant No.2, Ganesh, who have claimed that at the time of
            <lb />
            incident they were juvenile.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            30.
            <lb />
            Question of Appellants No.1 and 2 being juvenile was neither
            <lb />
            raised before the Committal Court nor before the Trial Court. It has
            <lb />
            been raised for the first time at this appellate stage. Both the
            <lb />
            Appellants have claimed that they were below 18 years of age on
            <lb />
            the date of incident, i.e., 26.8.1999. This Court, after hearing both
            <lb />
            the parties on I.A. No.1, by order dated 7.11.2016 had directed the
            <lb />
            Trial Court, i.e., the 4 th Additional Sessions Judge, Ambikapur
            <lb />
            under the Juvenile Justice (Care and Protection of Children) Act,
            <lb />
            2015 (henceforth &apos;the Act of 2015&apos;) to hold an inquiry and record a
            <lb />
            finding regarding the age of Appellants No.1 and 2 on the date of
            <lb />
            incident, i.e., 26.8.1999. Under Section 9(2) of the Act of 2015 to
            <lb />
            determine their age on the date of incident, the Additional Sessions
            <lb />
            Judge, Ambikapur has conducted an inquiry and submitted a report
            <lb />
            dated 27.10.2017 stating that date of birth of Appellant No.1,
            <lb />
            Rustam is 19.11.1982 and on the date of incident he was aged
            <lb />
            about 16 years 9 months 7 days. Similarly, it is further stated in the
            <lb />
            said report that the date of birth of Appellant No.2, Ganesh is
            <lb />
            3.3.1983 and on the date of incident he was aged about 16 years 5
            <lb />
            months and 23 days. Thus, both the Appellants were juvenile on
            <lb />
            the date of incident. The said report is not opposed by the State
            <lb />
            Counsel.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            31.
            <lb />
            In view of the above unassailed finding of the Additional Sessions
            <lb />
            Judge, Ambikapur, on the date of incident, the age of Appellant
            <lb />
            No.1, Rustam was 16 years 9 months 7 days and the age of
            <lb />
            Appellant No.2, Ganesh was 16 years 5 months and 23 days. The
            <lb />
            parties have accepted the correctness of the age determined by
            <lb />
            the Court below. Thus, it is established that Appellants No.1 and 2
            <lb />
            were juvenile on the date of incident. Therefore, their case has to
            <lb />
            be dealt with taking into consideration their juvenility.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            32.
            <lb />
            In the judgment dated 30.10.2012 passed in Criminal Appeal
            <lb />
            No.805 of 1995 [Mohan alias Brij Mohan and another v. The State
            <lb />
            of Madhya Pradesh (now State of Chhattisgarh)] by a Division
            <lb />
            Bench of this Court, it was observed thus:
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;15. The Juvenile Justice Act, 1986 was subsequently
            <lb />
            repealed by the Juvenile Justice (Care and Protection of
            <lb />
            Children) Act, 2000. On 22.8.2006 Section 2(l) of the 2000
            <lb />
            Act was amended stating that &apos;juvenile in conflict with law&apos;
            <lb />
            means a juvenile who is alleged to have committed an
            <lb />
            offence and has not completed eighteenth year of age as on
            <lb />
            the date of commission of such offence. The Juvenile
            <lb />
            Justice (Care and Protection of Children) Rules, 2007 were
            <lb />
            brought into force on 26.10.2007. As per Rule 97(2) all the
            <lb />
            cases pending which have not received a finality has to be
            <lb />
            dealt with and disposed of in terms of the provisions of the
            <lb />
            2000 Act as amended on 22.8.2006 and the 2007 Rules.
            <lb />
            According to the above Rules, therefore, Hari Shankar (A-2)
            <lb />
            would be entitled to benefit under the provisions of the 2000
            <lb />
            Act. In such situation, appellant No.2 (A-2) ought to have
            <lb />
            been tried by the Competent Board, and not by a Regular
            <lb />
            Court, in terms of Section 14 of the Act, 2000.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            16.
            <lb />
            Section 15 of the Act provides about the order that
            <lb />
            may be passed regarding a juvenile. U/s 15(1)(g), it has
            <lb />
            been provided that the Board may make an order directing
            <lb />
            the juvenile to be sent to a special home for a period of three
            <lb />
            years. Under the proviso, the board has power, for the
            <lb />
            reasons to be recorded, to reduce the period of stay to such
            <lb />
            period as it thinks fit.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            17.
            <lb />
            Section 16(1) of the Act 2000 provides that
            <lb />
            notwithstanding anything to the contrary contained in any
            <lb />
            other law for the time being in force, no juvenile in conflict
            <lb />
            with law shall be sentenced to death or imprisonment for any
            <lb />
            term which may extend to imprisonment for life, or
            <lb />
            committed to prison in default of payment of fine or in default
            <lb />
            of furnishing security. According to the proviso, where a
            <lb />
            juvenile who has attained the age of sixteen years has
            <lb />
            committed an offence and the Board is satisfied that the
            <lb />
            offence committed is so serious in nature or that his conduct
            <lb />
            and behaviour have been such that it would not be in his
            <lb />
            interest or in the interest of other juvenile in a special home
            <lb />
            to send him to such special home and that none of the other
            <lb />
            measures provided under this Act is suitable or sufficient, the
            <lb />
            Board may order the juvenile in conflict with law to be kept in
            <lb />
            such place of safety and in such manner as it thinks fit and
            <lb />
            shall report the case for the order of the State Government.
            <lb />
            Sub-section (2) of Section 16 further provides that on receipt
            <lb />
            of a report from a Board under sub-section (1), the State
            <lb />
            Government may make such arrangement in respect of the
            <lb />
            juvenile as it deems proper and may order such juvenile to
            <lb />
            be kept under protective custody at such place and on such
            <lb />
            conditions as it thinks fit. Provided that the period of
            <lb />
            detention so ordered shall not exceed in any case the
            <lb />
            maximum period provided under section 15 of this Act.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            18.
            <lb />
            Section 19 of the Act 2000 provides for removal of
            <lb />
            disqualification attaching to conviction. It provides that
            <lb />
            notwithstanding anything contained in any other law, a
            <lb />
            juvenile who has committed an offence and has been dealt
            <lb />
            with under the provisions of this Act shall not suffer
            <lb />
            disqualification, if any, attaching to a conviction of an offence
            <lb />
            under such law.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            19.
            <lb />
            Therefore, it is clear that in no case a juvenile on
            <lb />
            holding him guilty for an offence can be sent for more than
            <lb />
            the period prescribed u/s 15 of the Act and the case of Hari
            <lb />
            Shankar (A-2) has to be dealt with in the above manner.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            33.
            <lb />
            In (2015) 15 SCC 637 (Abdul Razzaq v. State of Uttar Pradesh),
            <lb />
            it has been observed by the Supreme Court thus:
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            &quot;11. In Hari Ram v. State of Rajasthan, (2009) 13
            <lb />
            SCC 211, it was observed: (SCC pp. 22527, paras
            <lb />
            4959)
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            xxxxx
            <lb />
            xxxxx
            <lb />
            xxxxx
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            59.
            <lb />
            The law as now crystallised on a
            <lb />
            conjoint reading of Sections 2(k), 2(l), 7A, 20
            <lb />
            and 49 read with Rules 12 and 98, places
            <lb />
            beyond all doubt that all persons who were
            <lb />
            below the age of 18 years on the date of
            <lb />
            commission of the offence even prior to 14
            <lb />
            2001, would be treated as juveniles, even if
            <lb />
            the claim of juvenility was raised after they
            <lb />
            had attained the age of 18 years on or before
            <lb />
            the date of commencement of the Act and
            <lb />
            were undergoing sentence upon being
            <lb />
            convicted.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            34.
            <lb />
            Section 18(1)(g) of the Juvenile Justice (Care and Protection of
            <lb />
            Children) Act, 2015 provides as under:
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;18. Orders regarding child found to be in
            <lb />
            conflict with law.-(1) Where a Board is satisfied on
            <lb />
            inquiry that a child irrespective of age has committed a
            <lb />
            petty offence, or a serious offence, or a child below the
            <lb />
            age of sixteen years has committed a heinous offence,
            <lb />
            then, notwithstanding anything contrary contained in
            <lb />
            any other law for the time being in force, and based on
            <lb />
            the nature of offence, specific need for supervision or
            <lb />
            intervention, circumstances as brought out in the social
            <lb />
            investigation report and past conduct of the child, the
            <lb />
            Board may, if it so thinks fit, -
            <lb />
            xxxxx
            <lb />
            xxxxx
            <lb />
            xxxxx
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (g)
            <lb />
            direct the child to be sent to a special
            <lb />
            home, for such period, not exceeding three
            <lb />
            years, as it thinks fit, for providing
            <lb />
            reformative services including education,
            <lb />
            skill development, counselling, behaviour
            <lb />
            modification
            <lb />
            therapy,
            <lb />
            and
            <lb />
            psychiatric
            <lb />
            support during the period of stay in the
            <lb />
            special home:
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            Provided that if the conduct and behaviour of
            <lb />
            the child has been such that, it would not be
            <lb />
            in the child&apos;s interest, or in the interest of
            <lb />
            other children housed in a special home, the
            <lb />
            Board may send such child to the place of
            <lb />
            safety.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            From the above, it is clear that in no case, a juvenile, on holding
            <lb />
            him guilty for an offence, can be sent for more than a period
            <lb />
            prescribed under Section 18(1)(g) of the Act of 2015, that is, not
            <lb />
            exceeding three years.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            35.
            <lb />
            In the premises of aforestated, in the instant case, the conviction
            <lb />
            and sentence imposed upon Appellant No.1, Rustam and Appellant
            <lb />
            No.2, Ganesh by the impugned judgment are set aside and instead
            <lb />
            thereof both of them are convicted and sentenced as follows:
        </p>
        <lb />
        <table>
            Conviction
            <lb />
            Sentence
            <lb />
            Under Section 304 Part II of
            <lb />
            the Indian Penal Code
            <lb />
            Rigorous Imprisonment for 3
            <lb />
            years with fine of Rs.1,000/-,
            <lb />
            in default of payment of fine,
            <lb />
            they shall be liable to undergo
            <lb />
            rigorous imprisonment for 6
            <lb />
            months
            <lb />
            Under Section 325/34 of the
            <lb />
            Indian Penal Code
            <lb />
            Rigorous Imprisonment for 3
            <lb />
            years with fine of Rs.500/-, in
            <lb />
            default, to further undergo
            <lb />
            rigorous imprisonment for 3
            <lb />
            months
            <lb />
            Under Section 452/34 of the
            <lb />
            Indian Penal Code
            <lb />
            Rigorous Imprisonment for 3
            <lb />
            years with fine of Rs.500/-, in
            <lb />
            default, to further undergo
            <lb />
            rigorous imprisonment for 3
            <lb />
            months
            <lb />
            Under Section 323/34 of the
            <lb />
            Indian Penal Code
            <lb />
            Rigorous Imprisonment for 1
            <lb />
            year
            <lb />
            All the sentences to run
            <lb />
            concurrently.
        </table>
        <lb />
        <p>
            Since Appellants No.1 and 2 have already undergone a period
            <lb />
            of about 7 years, they are now not required to be sent back to jail.
            <lb />
            The conviction and sentence imposed upon Appellant No.4,
            <lb />
            Bhisam by the impugned judgment are also set aside and instead
            <lb />
            thereof he is convicted and sentenced as under:
        </p>
        <lb />
        <table>
            Conviction
            <lb />
            Sentence
            <lb />
            Under Section 304 Part II of
            <lb />
            the Indian Penal Code
            <lb />
            Rigorous Imprisonment for 10
            <lb />
            years with fine of Rs.1,000/-,
            <lb />
            in default of payment of fine,
            <lb />
            he shall be liable to undergo
            <lb />
            rigorous imprisonment for 6
            <lb />
            months
            <lb />
            Under Section 325/34 of the
            <lb />
            Indian Penal Code
            <lb />
            Rigorous Imprisonment for 5
            <lb />
            years and fine of Rs.500/-, in
            <lb />
            default, to further undergo
            <lb />
            rigorous imprisonment for 3
            <lb />
            months
            <lb />
            Under Section 452/34 of the
            <lb />
            Indian Penal Code
            <lb />
            Rigorous Imprisonment for 5
            <lb />
            years and fine of Rs.200/-, in
            <lb />
            default, to further undergo
            <lb />
            rigorous imprisonment for 1
            <lb />
            month
            <lb />
            Under Section 323/34 of the
            <lb />
            Indian Penal Code
            <lb />
            Rigorous Imprisonment for 1
            <lb />
            year
        </table>
        <lb />
        <p>
            Appellant No.4 is directed to surrender or he shall be taken into
            <lb />
            custody forthwith for undergoing remaining part of his sentence.
        </p>
        <lb />
        <p>
            All the sentences imposed above shall run concurrently. The
            <lb />
            period already undergone shall be adjusted against the period of
            <lb />
            sentence imposed today.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            36.
            <lb />
            Consequently, the appeal is allowed in part to the extent indicated
            <lb />
            above.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            37.
            <lb />
            It is reported that Appellant No.3, Samat is on bail. His bail bonds
            <lb />
            shall continue for a further period of six months from today in terms
            <lb />
            of Section 437A of the Code of Criminal Procedure.
        </p>
        <lb />
        <p>
            Sd/-
            <lb />
            Sd/-
            <lb />
            (Pritinker Diwaker)
            <lb />
            (Arvind Singh Chandel)
            <lb />
            JUDGE
            <lb />
            JUDGE
            <lb />
            Gopal
        </p>


    </text>
</tei>