<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<item>
			Con~oller that the suit premises were bona fide required by the landlord A
			<lb />
			for his own use and occupation.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			The respondent-tenant filed a revision petition in the High Court
			<lb />
			which held that (i) the landlord was not consistent with reference to tl1e
			<lb />
			location. of the Company which was the pawn-broking business of partner-
			<lb />
			ship; (ii) it was not clear as to what exactly was the area that was required B
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			by the respondent for the saitj. pawn broking business; and (iii) the
			<lb />
			appellate authority had failed to consider not only the totality of facts and
			<lb />
			circumstances of the case but also the bona fide on the part of the landlord
			<lb />
			on account of alleged requirement of the partnership business. According-
			<lb />
			ly the High Court by its order dated April 11, 1990 remanded the matter C
			<lb />
			to the appellate authority to dispose of the case afresh in accordance with
			<lb />
			law.
			<lb />
			After the order of remand, the appellate authority affirmed the order
			<lb />
			of eviction passed by the Rent Controller against the tenant under Section D
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			10(3) (a) (iii) of the Rent Act holding that (i) the eviction grounds founded
			<lb />
			in the proceedings were not identical with grounds indicated in the notice
			<lb />
			ror eviction inasmuch as the case of the bona fide requirement on account
			<lb />
			of expansion of partnership business had not been mentioned in the notice;
			<lb />
			(ii) but in view of the tenant&apos;s admission that the landlord was running a
			<lb />
			jewdlery shop and also a pawn broker&apos;s business run by his wire and E
			<lb />
			daughter-in-law, the landlord was entitled to claim eviction of the tenant
			<lb />
			bcna fide on account of the said two business concerns; (iii) the documents
			<lb />
			filed by the landlord clearly establish that partnership business had in fact
			<lb />
			been run even though it was not mentioned in the eviction notice; (iv)
			<lb />
			documents of accounts of the partnership filed after the first order of F
			<lb />
			remand clearly establish that the partnership business had been slowly
			<lb />
			progressing and it was assessed for income tax from the year 1985 onward;
			<lb />
			and (v) in view of the admitted position that the said two business
			<lb />
			establishment were being run, much importance was not required to be
			<lb />
			attached as to the location or the pawn broking business.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			G
			<lb />
			Thereafter, the respondent-tenan4 filed a Revision Petition and the
			<lb />
			High Court held that the appellate authority had not decided the appeal
			<lb />
			after remand in conformity with the order of remand dated Aprll 11, 1990.
			<lb />
			Accordingly the High Court by i!s order dated December 11, 1992
			<lb />
			remanded the appeal for the second time to the appellate authority with a H
			<lb />
			SUPREME COURT REPORTS
			<lb />
			[1994] 2 S.C.R.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			A direction that the appeal should be disposed of in accordance with the
			<lb />
			directions contained in the earlier order of remand dated April 11, 1990.
			<lb />
			The appellant-landlord flied an appeal in this Coiurt challenging the
			<lb />
			second order of remand dated December 11, 1992 contending that (i)
			<lb />
			omission in the Eviction Notice to mention about bona fide requirement
			<lb />
			B on account of partnership business was of little significance because in
			<lb />
			reality the said partnership business was in existence at the time of giving
			<lb />
			the notice for eviction and tht: said business was being run even at the time
			<lb />
			(
			<lb />
			of disposal of the proceedings for .eviction; (il) the High Court bas
			<lb />
			J
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			proceeded on bypertechnicallty and set aside the well-rtasooed order of
			<lb />
			C the appellate authority simply on the ground that the observation made in
			<lb />
			the first order of remand had not be followed properly; (iii) assuming that
			<lb />
			the appellate authority&apos;s findings were not strictly according to the obser-
			<lb />
			vatioios made in the order of remand, if the ultimate finding of the
			<lb />
			appellate authority was in conformity with the provisions of Section
			<lb />
			10(3)(a)iii) of the Rent Act, there was no occasion for the High Court to
			<lb />
			D set aside the said order and send the matter back for redetermloat!oo of
			<lb />
			the case; and (iv) in view 9f the appellate authority&apos;s finding that the
			<lb />
			business activities had been steadily increasing, it was not at all necessary
			<lb />
			to specifically refer in the d~ision which exhibit related to what document.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			E
			<lb />
			Dlsposing •the appeal, this Court
			<lb />
			HELD : 1. Non-mention of a reasonable ground for eviction in the
			<lb />
			notice for eviction on the basis of which a claim for eviction is later on
			<lb />
			founded usually raises a suspicion about the existence of such gouod but
			<lb />
			such non-mention by itself cannot disentitle a landlord to claim eviction
			<lb />
			F on such ground. If a claim for eviction founded on such ground in the
			<lb />
			petition for•eviction is proved to be wellfounded and the same is consistent
			<lb />
			with the grounds on which eviction is permissible in law, the landlord will
			<lb />
			be entitled to a decree for eviction notwithstanding the fact that such
			<lb />
			ground was not mentioned in the notice for eviction. [33-F-G]
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			G
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			2&quot;. The appellate authority had rightly indicated in the facts of this
			<lb />
			case that the partnership business was in existence even prior to giving
			<lb />
			notice for eviction by the landlord. Therefore, it cannot be reasonably held
			<lb />
			that the claim or bona fide requirement on account of the said partnership
			<lb />
			business is per se ma/a fide and should not be taken Into consideration
			<lb />
			been mentioned in the notice for eviction. [33-G-34A•B]
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			A
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			3. The High Court bas acted with hyper-technicality in discarding
			<lb />
			the finding of the appellate authority about the continuous expension of
			<lb />
			the said partnership business. The appellate authority has referred to the
			<lb />
			exhibits including the income-tax assessment orders for the purpose of
			<lb />
			coming to the finding that the said business had been gradually expanding. B
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			Such finding, therefore, appears to be justified. In the aforesaid facts, it
			<lb />
			was not proper to discard such finding of the appellate authority by
			<lb />
			indicating that the exhibits had not been elaborated in detail.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(34-H, 35-A-C]
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			4. The requirement of spact ~•&quot; t~ ,sqid partnership business con-C
			<lb />
			sistent with the nature rf ba.1s&apos;mt:ss and expanding activities had not been
			<lb />
			gone into by the app: tlate authority and the relevant materials are also
			<lb />
			not before this Court. Therefore, the order of remand is upheld to the
			<lb />
			limited extent, namely, that the appellate authority on the basis of
			<lb />
			materials already on record would consider the actual requirement of
			<lb />
			space for the saiu lJ(ht&apos;lership business consistent with the nature of D
			<lb />
			business keeping in view, tli~ expanding activities in such business. If on
			<lb />
			such consideration, the appellate authority comes to the finding that the
			<lb />
			landlord bona fide require11 me disputed premises for running the said
			<lb />
			business in a separate enclosure, the order of eviction under Section
			<lb />
			10(3)(a)(iii) of the Rent Act should be passed by the appellate authority. E
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			[35-D-G]
			<lb />
			Hameeda Hardware Stores v. B.Mohan Lal&apos;Sowcar, A.l.R. (1988) S.C.
			<lb />
			1060 and Krishnan Nair v. Ghouse Basha, A.l.R. (1987) S.C. 2199, referred
			<lb />
			to.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			5. There is no manner of doubt that the bona fide requirement is F
			<lb />
			required to be considered objectively with reference to the materials on
			<lb />
			record and it is necessary to determine the real intention of the landlord
			<lb />
			on the basis of evidences adduced in a case. If the materials on record
			<lb />
			clearly justify a case of bona fide requirement, there will be no occasion
			<lb />
			for the court to hold that the landlord did not require the premises bona G
			<lb />
			fide simply because on a previous occasion the actton of the landlord for
			<lb />
			bringing an eviction case was not bona fide. [34-B-C]
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			6. The cause for eviction is a recurring cause of action and even if
			<lb />
			the existence of such cause of action had not been found in a previous
			<lb />
			proceeding for eviction, the same cannot be discarded if such claim is H
			<lb />
			SUPREME COURT REPORTS
			<lb />
			[1994) 2 S.C.R.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			A ()s,tablished by cogent evidecnes adduced by the landlord in a subsequent
			<lb />
			proceeding. The landlord may bring an action for eviction of the tenant on
			<lb />
			subsequent cause of action justifying a case of bo11a fide requirement.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			[34-D-E]
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			7. To say that the Rent Act is a legislation for protecting a tenant
			<lb />
			will be over simplification of the legislative import of the Rent Act. It will
			<lb />
			B be more appropriate to .say that the Rent Act regulates the incidence of
			<lb />
			tenancy and inter se rights and obli~ations of the landlord and tenant.
			<lb />
			[34-GJ
			<lb />
			c
			<lb />
			D
			<lb />
			CIVIL APPELLATE JURISDICTION : Civil Appeal No. 878 of
			<lb />
			1994.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			From the Judgment and Order dated 11.12.92 of the Madras High
			<lb />
			Court in C.R.P. No. 436 of 1991.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			P. Chidambaram, V.K. Vijyaraghavan and S. Mur1idhar for the Ap-
			<lb />
			pellant.
			<lb />
			Siva Subramanian, V. Balachandran and G. Nagarajan for the
			<lb />
			Respondent.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			The Judgment of the Court was delivered by
			<lb />
			E
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			G.N. RAY, J. Leave granted. Pursuant to the notice issued on the
			<lb />
			special leave petition No. 1687 of 1993, the respondent has entered ap-
			<lb />
			pearance through counsel and the counter affidavit has also been filed.
			<lb />
			The appellant landlord is the owner of the suit premises being shop
			<lb />
			No. 142. Gandhiji Raod, Mayiladuthurai, Tamil Nadu. On June 15, 1971,
			<lb />
			F the appellant landlord leased out the premises in question to Sri G.
			<lb />
			Vasanthan on a monthly rental of Rs. 400 with effect from June 15, 1971
			<lb />
			and the appellant landlord sought eviction of the said tenant Vasanthan
			<lb />
			and filed a petition for eviction on April 22, 1975 under Section 14(1)( 4)
			<lb />
			of the Tamil Nadu Building (Lease and Rent Control) Act, 1960
			<lb />
			(hereinafter referred to as the Rent Act) before the Rent Controller
			<lb />
			G Mayiladutburai. By an order dated December 12, 1975, the learned Rent
			<lb />
			Contr.oller dismissed tl.te said eviction proceeding being R.C.O.P. No. 9 of
			<lb />
			1975. The appellant landlord preferred an appeal against the said order
			<lb />
			of the Rent Controller before the appellate authority. By order dated
			<lb />
			August 31, 1977. the appellate authority allowed the said appeal and
			<lb />
			H directed the eviction of the said tenant Vasanthun. Thereafter, the appel-
			<lb />
			lant landlord on August 29, 1978, let out the suit premises to the respon-A
			<lb />
			dent M.R. Ramachandra Naidu for a period of three years from August 1,
			<lb />
			1978 to August 31, 1981 on a rental of Rs. 750 per month. The period of
			<lb />
			lease was extended further for another term of three years with effect from
			<lb />
			September 1, 1981 to August 31, 1984. It is the case of the landlord that
			<lb />
			he required the suit premises for expansion of his own business and also B
			<lb />
			the pawn broking business under the partnership of his wife and daughter-
			<lb />
			in-law. The appellant landlord served a notice dated November 5, 1984
			<lb />
			upon the respondent tenant asking him to vacate the suit premises. The
			<lb />
			respondent tenant refused to vacate the suit premises and on April 17,
			<lb />
			1985, the appellant landlord filed an eviction petition under Section
			<lb />
			10(3)(a)(iii) of the Rent Act for eviction of !he tP.nant on the ground that C
			<lb />
			the appellant landlord required .1 1ore space for running the said pawn
			<lb />
			broking shop as well as the business of his own. The appellant landlord
			<lb />
			also urged that since the suit premises were old and in a dilapidated
			<lb />
			condition the same required urgent demolition and construction and ac-
			<lb />
			cordingly the tenant should also be evicted under Section 14(i)(b) of the D
			<lb />
			Rent Act. By an order c!ated L&apos;ctober 5, 1987, the learned Rent Controller
			<lb />
			allowed the said R.C.0 .P. No. 37 of 1985 on the ground that the appellant
			<lb />
			landlord had made out a case under Section 10(3)(a)(iii) of the R~nt Act
			<lb />
			and he required the suit premises Lvna fide for his own occupation. The
			<lb />
			Rent Controller, however, negatived the case of the appellant landlord that
			<lb />
			he required the premises fer demolition or construction under Section E
			<lb />
			14(i)(b) of the Rent Act. The respondent tenant thereafter filed R.CA.
			<lb />
			No. 4 of 1988 dated April 26, 1989. The appellant landlord also filed Cross
			<lb />
			Appeal being R.C.A. No. 9 of 1988 against the dismissal of the appellant
			<lb />
			landlord&apos;s case for eviction under Section 14(i)(b) of the Rent Act. By a
			<lb />
			judgment and order dated April 26, 1988, the appellate authority dismissed F
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			R.C.A. No. 4 of 1988 filed by the respondent tenant after endorsing the
			<lb />
			finding of the learned Rent Controller that the suit premises was bona fide
			<lb />
			required by the appellant landlord for his use and occupation. The learned
			<lb />
			appellate authority, however, dismissed the landlord&apos;s Cross Appeal being
			<lb />
			R.C.A. No. 9 of 1988 by the same judgment. The respondent tenant
			<lb />
			thereafter filed Civil Revision Petition No. 1448 of 1989 in the High Court G
			<lb />
			of Madras challenging the said eviction order under Section 10(3)(lli) of
			<lb />
			the Rent Act. By. an order dated April 11, 1990, the said Civil Revision
			<lb />
			Petition No. 1448 of 1989 was allowed by the High Court of Madras and
			<lb />
			the case was remanded to the appellate authority inter alia directing the
			<lb />
			H
			<lb />
			SUPREME COURT REPORTS
			<lb />
			(1994) 2 S.C.R.
			<lb />
			A appellate authority to dispose of the case afresh in accordance with law
			<lb />
			and in terms of the directions c.ontained in the said order, Thereafter,
			<lb />
			pursuant to the liberty granted by the Ri!!h Court to both the parties to
			<lb />
			adduce further evid•:ncc bcfo:e th, ... p ellate authority, fresh evidence~
			<lb />
			troth oral or docuDlentary were adduced before the appellate authori,ty.
			<lb />
			The appellate authority by a judgment and order dated December 14, 1990,
			<lb />
			B dismissed the said R.CA. No. 4 of 1988 filed by the respondent tenant and
			<lb />
			confirmed the order of eviction passed by the learned Rent Controller. The
			<lb />
			respondent tenant thereafter filed a Civil Revision Petition being Civil
			<lb />
			Revision Petition No. 436 of 1991 in February, 1991.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			C
			<lb />
			The said Civil Revision. Petition was allowed by the High Court by
			<lb />
			its order dated December 11, 1992 inter alia on the finding that the
			<lb />
			appellate authority had not decided the appeal after remand in conformity
			<lb />
			with the order of remand dated April 11, 1990 passed by the High Court.
			<lb />
			The appeal was remanded for the second time by the High Court before
			<lb />
			D the appellate authority by directing inter a/ia that the said appeal should
			<lb />
			be disposed of by following the directions contained in the order of remand
			<lb />
			dated April, 11, 1990. It is this second order of remand dated December
			<lb />
			;:....
			<lb />
			11, 1992 which has been challenged in the instant appeal by the appellant
			<lb />
			landlord.
			<lb />
			E
			<lb />
			Since the impugned second order of remand has been passed by the
			<lb />
			fligh Court inter alia on the finding that the appellate authority failed to
			<lb />
			dispose of the appeal in accordance with the directions contained in the
			<lb />
			earlier order of remand, it is necessary to advert to the observations made
			<lb />
			in the first order of remand in order to appreciate as to whether or not the
			<lb />
			F appellate authority has failed to dispose of the appeal properly ~ accord-
			<lb />
			ance with the directions contained in the order of remand.
			<lb />
			The High Court had noted in the first order of remand that in the
			<lb />
			notice for eviction the landlord stated about the reqwrement of the dis-
			<lb />
			puted premises on account of expanding his own business but in the
			<lb />
			G eviction petition, the case for bona fide requirement of the landlord was
			<lb />
			founded not only for the requirement for expansion of his own business
			<lb />
			but also for the expansion the pawn broking business &apos;6f the wife and
			<lb />
			daughter-in-law of the landlord, and also for demolition and construction
			<lb />
			of the suit premises. The High Court observed that the landlord was not
			<lb />
			H consistent with ,reference to the location of Govindammal and Company
			<lb />
			which was the paw:i broking business in partnership or&apos; the wife and A
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			daug.Jiter-in-law o( the Iaudlord. The High Court also observed that it was
			<lb />
			net clear as to what exactly was the area that was required by the respon-
			<lb />
			dent for the said pawn broking business in jewellery which was purely a
			<lb />
			business of advancing money on the security of jewels. The High Court also
			<lb />
			ob:;erved that the appellate authority came to the finding that the said B
			<lb />
			partnership business had e&gt;..&apos;J&apos;anded by looking at Exts. A-10, A•ll and A-12
			<lb />
			but the High Court was of the. view that in the absence of sufficient
			<lb />
			materials right from the date of the commencement of the business, it was
			<lb />
			not possible to make any finding about the improvP,ment of the said
			<lb />
			business. &apos;The High Court also observed that even if the business had
			<lb />
			improved, the very nature of the business that the pledged jewels had to C
			<lb />
			be secured either in the locker in the iron safe or in the bank, the
			<lb />
			requirement of a very large area for c;uch business might not be bona fide.
			<lb />
			It was, therefore, necessary to determine whether the landlord required the
			<lb />
			suit premises after keeping in mind the nature of the said partnership
			<lb />
			business and the area already under the possession of the landlord. The D
			<lb />
			High Court also observed that the triai court and the appellate authority
			<lb />
			..-....
			<lb />
			did not accept the case for eviction on the ground of demolition and
			<lb />
			reconstruction. But even for the purpose of deciding bona fide requirement
			<lb />
			of the landlord, the entire circumstances under which the landlord bad
			<lb />
			instituted the proceedings were required to be taken into account. Refer-
			<lb />
			-
			<lb />
			ring to a decision of this Court in Hameeda Hardware Stores v. B. Mohand E
			<lb />
			Lal Sowcar, AIR 1988 SC 1060, the High Court observed that it was clear
			<lb />
			from the said decision that when a landlord had sought eviction of a tenant
			<lb />
			from the non-residential premises under Section 10(3)(a)(iii) of the Act,
			<lb />
			the landlord was required to establish other ingredients, referred to in the
			<lb />
			said Judgment. It was he&apos;d by the High Comt that as the appellate authority F
			<lb />
			had failed to consider not only the totality and circumstances and the facts
			<lb />
			of the case but also the bona fide on the part of the landlord in seeking
			<lb />
			eviction from the demised premises on account of alleged requirement of
			<lb />
			the said partnership business, the impugned order of the appellate
			<lb />
			authority was vitiated. The High Court, therefore, held in the order of first
			<lb />
			remand that :
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			G
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;It is in these circumstances, the order of the appellate authority
			<lb />
			is set aside and the matter is remitted back to the appellate
			<lb />
			authority to consider the totality of the facts and circumstances of
			<lb />
			the case and the bona fide on the part of the respondent&apos;s require-H
			<lb />
			SUPREME COURT REPORTS
			<lb />
			[1994) 2 S.C.R.
			<lb />
			A
			<lb />
			ment of the demised premises for the purpose of carrying on the
			<lb />
			business of Govindammal and Company, by the members of the
			<lb />
			family.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			As aforesaid, the High Court directed that both the parties would be
			<lb />
			B at liberty to file fresh evidence both oral and documentary in support of
			<lb />
			their case.
			<lb />
			After the said first order of remand, the appellate authority held, on
			<lb />
			consideration of the materials on record including fresh evidences ad-
			<lb />
			duced, that the grounds on which the eviction of the tenant was founded
			<lb />
			C in the proceedings in question were not the identical grounds as indicated
			<lb />
			in the notice for eviction given by the landlord to the tenant because the
			<lb />
			c.ase of the bona fide ,tequirement on account of expansion of said partner-
			<lb />
			ship business had not been mentioned. The appellate authority, however,
			<lb />
			held that the tenan~, both in the counter as well as in his oral evidence,
			<lb />
			D had admitted that the landlord was running a jewellery shop in the name
			<lb />
			of Sunder Jewellery and also a pawn broker&apos;s business run by his wife and
			<lb />
			daughter-in-law at door No. 141 in the name and style of S. Govindammal
			<lb />
			and Company. The appellate authority held that in view of the aforesaid
			<lb />
			admitted position and in view of the documents filed by the landlord which
			<lb />
			clearly established that such partnership business had in fact been run in
			<lb />
			E door No. 141, even though the landlord had not rr.entioned in the notice
			<lb />
			that the landlord required the suit premises also for the said partnership
			<lb />
			business run by his wife and daughter-in-law, the landlord was entitled to
			<lb />
			seek eviction on account of requirement of the said premises for the said
			<lb />
			business. The appellate authority also held that it was not the case that the
			<lb />
			F said business in the name and style of Govindammal and Company h~d not
			<lb />
			been run at door No. 141 prior to the giving df notice for eviction and such
			<lb />
			business was introduced only for the purpose of making a case for eviction.
			<lb />
			Accordingly, it could not be contended that claim for eviction on account
			<lb />
			of the said partnership business was not made with any good intention. The
			<lb />
			G appellate authority also held that on perusal of E.&lt;t:. No. 13 filed by the
			<lb />
			landlord it could be noted that the partnership agreement had been
			<lb />
			entered or August 25, 1988 and from Ext. 7 it transpired that the licence
			<lb />
			for the said business had been issued on August 28, 1982 by the Tensildar
			<lb />
			at Myiladuthurai and from Ext. 8 and 9 it transpired that the said partner-
			<lb />
			ship firm had been registered on May 24, 1983 and from Ext. 10 it
			<lb />
			from Exts. 11 and 12 it appeared that the income tax had been assessed A
			<lb />
			from the year 1985 onward. The appellate authority, therefore, held that
			<lb />
			the running of the said partnership business in the said door No. 141 was
			<lb />
			amply proved. The appellate authority also found that the jeweliery shop
			<lb />
			of the landlord known as Sunder Jewellery was also being run in the said
			<lb />
			door No. 141. The appellate authority, therefore, held that the landlord was B
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			entitled to claim eviction of the tenant bona fide on account of the said two
			<lb />
			business concerns. The appellate authority also held that on perusal of the
			<lb />
			landlord&apos;s Ext: 30 to 37 and 43 to 50 pertaining to the accounts of the said
			<lb />
			Govindarnmal and Company which were filed after the said first order of
			<lb />
			remand, it was clearly established that the said parternship business namely
			<lb />
			Govindammal and Company had been slowly progressing from year 1983. C
			<lb />
			Coming to the question of the location of the said business in pawn broking
			<lb />
			and also the business of the landlord known as Sunder jewellary, the
			<lb />
			appellate authority held that much importance was not required to be
			<lb />
			attached as to the location of the pawn broking business in view of the fact
			<lb />
			the it was an admitted position that at door No. 141 both the said two D
			<lb />
			businesses est&amp;blishments were being run. The appellate authority then
			<lb />
			took into consideration as to whether the landlord had other premises in
			<lb />
			his occupation in which requirement for running the said business concerns
			<lb />
			could be carried out. The appellate authority came to the finding that the
			<lb />
			tenant in his evidence had admitted that the newly constructed building of
			<lb />
			the landlord had not been fully completed and no shop was being run in E
			<lb />
			the aforesaid building. The appellate authority, therefore, came to the
			<lb />
			finding that the landlord did not own any vacant building. Referring to a
			<lb />
			decision of this Court made in Krishanan Nair v. Ghouse Basna, AIR(1987)
			<lb />
			SC 2199, the appellate authority inter alia came to the finding that a petition
			<lb />
			under Section 10(3)(a)(iii) of the Rent Act on account of requirement of F
			<lb />
			a partnership business in which the members of the family of the landlord
			<lb />
			were partners with strangers, was admissible and. the landlord was entitled
			<lb />
			to claim eviction of the tenant for running such partnership business with
			<lb />
			strangers. The appellate authority also took into consideration the case of
			<lb />
			bona fide requirement of the landlord in the context of not mentioning the
			<lb />
			requirement of the landlord on account of the said pawn broking business G
			<lb />
			in the notice. The appellate authority, however, hr.Id that since admittedly
			<lb />
			both the said two businesses had been run in the said door No. 141 and
			<lb />
			the said partnership business had existed even prior to giving notice for
			<lb />
			eviction to the tenant, it was established that the landlord&apos;s claim of
			<lb />
			H
			<lb />
			SUPREME COURT REPORTS
			<lb />
			[1994] 2 S.C.R.
			<lb />
			A requirement of the suit premises for expanding the said partnership busi-
			<lb />
			ness was based on bona fide intention. The appellate authority, however,
			<lb />
			held that the case of requirement of the disputed premises on account of
			<lb />
			expansion of the landlord&apos;s said business in the name and style of Sunder
			<lb />
			Jewellery was not acceptable but it was necessary to separate the said
			<lb />
			B
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			business in pawn broking in the name and style of Govindammal and
			<lb />
			Company from the other business of the landloard known as Sunder
			<lb />
			Jewellery. The appellate authority.dismissed the claim of the landlord for
			<lb />
			eviction on the ground of re-building after considering the relevant
			<lb />
			evidence about the condition of the building. Accordingly, the appellate
			<lb />
			authority affirmed the order of eviction passed by the learned Rent Con-
			<lb />
			C troller against the tenant under Section 10(3)(a)(iii) of the Rent Act.
			<lb />
			As aforesaid, the said decision of :he appellate authority after
			<lb />
			remand has been set aside by the High Cotrt in revision inter alia on the
			<lb />
			finding that the appellale authority had not applied its mind about the exact
			<lb />
			D location where the pawn broker&apos;s shop was situated and the appellate
			<lb />
			authority had also not taken into consideration the question of bona fide
			<lb />
			requirement of the landlord for the purpose of carrying on the said
			<lb />
			business in pawn broking having regard to t.he area under occupation of
			<lb />
			the tenant and the actual requirement for the said business in pawn
			<lb />
			broking. The High Court was of t~e view that the appellate authority was
			<lb />
			E expected to go into the question whether the : ntire area under the occupa-
			<lb />
			tion of the tenant was required or not. The High Court also observed that
			<lb />
			although the appellate authority referred to Exts. 30 to 37 and 43 to 50 and
			<lb />
			came to the finding that the said partnership business had been steadily
			<lb />
			improving from 1983, the appellate authorit) failed to indicate what were
			<lb />
			F the documents under the said exhibits and bow the said doc11ments were
			<lb />
			relevant. The High Court set aside the order of the appellate authority on
			<lb />
			the finding that the decision of the appellate authority was not only
			<lb />
			unsatisfactory but the same was also not in conformity with the earlier
			<lb />
			order of remand-passed by the High Court. 1he High Court also held that
			<lb />
			the requirement of the building for demolitio.a and reconstruction had not
			<lb />
			G been seriously pressed before it and such question was, therefore, not
			<lb />
			required to be considered.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			Mr. Chidambaram, the learned senior counsel appearing for the
			<lb />
			landlord-appellant, has very strongly contended that the High Court passed
			<lb />
			H the impugned ordP.r of remand for the second time without properly
			<lb />
			(
			<lb />
			appreci;tting the facts and circumstances of the case and the materials on A
			<lb />
			record an&lt;l the import of the finding made by the appellate authority after
			<lb />
			first order of remand. He has submitted chat the High Court has proceeded
			<lb />
			on hyper-technicality and set aside the well-reasoned order of the appellate
			<lb />
			authority simply on the ground that the observation made in the first order
			<lb />
			of remand bad not been followed properly. He has submitted that even if B
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			it is asswned that the appellate authority had not made the finding strictly
			<lb />
			according to the observatioru made in the order of remand, if the ultimate
			<lb />
			finding of the appellate auth lrity on the basis of the materials on record
			<lb />
			and the evidence adduced after the first order of remand is in conformity
			<lb />
			with the provisions of Section 10 (3)(a)(iii) of the Rent Act, there was no
			<lb />
			occasion for the High Court to set aside the said order and send the matter C
			<lb />
			back for redetermination of the case. The anxiety of the Court should be
			<lb />
			not to prolong the course of litigation but to achieve its finality as early as
			<lb />
			possible. He has submitted that the appellate authority has rightly held that
			<lb />
			the exact location of the said partnership business was not required to be
			<lb />
			determined because of the admitted postion that both the said two business D
			<lb />
			concerns namely Sunder Jewellery and Govindammal and Company had
			<lb />
			been run in door No. 141. The real question required to be considered for
			<lb />
			the purpose of deciding the claim for eviction is whether there was neces-
			<lb />
			sity for expanding of the said two businesses and whether or not the
			<lb />
			landlord and any alternative suitable accommodation for carrying out the
			<lb />
			said two businesses consistent with the requirement of the same. Mr. E
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			Chidambaram has also contended that the appellate authority has referred
			<lb />
			to the assessment orders passed by the income tax authority from 1985
			<lb />
			onward in respect of the said partnership business and with reference to
			<lb />
			such assessment orders, the appellate authority came to the finding that
			<lb />
			the business activities had been steadily increasiog. It was, therefore, not F
			<lb />
			at all necessary to specifically refed in the decision which exhibit related
			<lb />
			to what document. In any event, the materials were before the High Court
			<lb />
			and the High Court could look into the same and could appreciate as to
			<lb />
			whether or not the finding of the appellate authority about the steady
			<lb />
			expansion of the said business was justified or not. Mr. Chidambaram bas
			<lb />
			also submitted that in the notice for eviction the bona fide requiremnt of G
			<lb />
			the suit premises also on account of the accommodation of the said
			<lb />
			partnership business was not mentioned. But such omission to mention the
			<lb />
			said fact was of little significance because in reality• the said partnership
			<lb />
			business was in existence at the time of giving the notice for eviction and
			<lb />
			H
			<lb />
			SUPREME COURT REPORTS
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			[1994) 2 S.C.R.
			<lb />
			A the said bus. iness was being run even at the time of disposal of the
			<lb />
			proceedings for eviction. He has, therefore, submitted that the appellate
			<lb />
			authority was justified in holding that there was no lack of bona fide on the
			<lb />
			part of the landlord in basing a claim for eviction also on account of said
			<lb />
			partnership business although such case was not mentioned in the notice
			<lb />
			B because the said business was not brought into existence after institution
			<lb />
			of the said eviction suit but the same was there from before. The landlord,
			<lb />
			according to Mr. Chidambaram, has led evidence to establish that for the
			<lb />
			said expanding business more space was necessary and as the landlord did
			<lb />
			not have any other suitable acommodation for the said business, he bona
			<lb />
			fide required the suit premises. He has, therefore, submitted that the
			<lb />
			C impugned order has resulted in gross failure of justice to the landlord
			<lb />
			appellant and the same should be set aside and the order of eviction on
			<lb />
			concurrent finding of bona fide requirement of the landlord by the learned
			<lb />
			Rent Controller and the appellate authority should be upheld by this Court
			<lb />
			and the order of eviction passed by the appellate authority should be
			<lb />
			D maintained.
			<lb />
			The learned counsel for the tenant respondent has, however, dis-
			<lb />
			puted the said submissions of Mr. Chidambararn. It has been contended
			<lb />
			by the learned counsel for the tenant respondent that for the purpose of
			<lb />
			coming to a finding as to whether or not the landlord has a bona fide
			<lb />
			E requirement in pasing a claim for eviction of the tenant under the Rent
			<lb />
			Act, the Court is required to look into all the facts and circumstances of
			<lb />
			the case. It has been contended by the learned counsel for the tenant that
			<lb />
			the previous tenant was evicted on the ground of building and reconstruc-
			<lb />
			tion of the suit premises but the landlord deliberately failed to reconstruct
			<lb />
			F the same and having obtained the possession, he inducted a new tenant. It
			<lb />
			is only for the purpose of evicting the tenant respondent for getting higher
			<lb />
			rer..t the claim for eviction on the ground of building and reconstruction
			<lb />
			has been made by the landlord but such claim bas not been upheld. The
			<lb />
			learned counsel for the tenant has also submitted that the landlord did not
			<lb />
			G bona fide require the suit premises is evident from the fact that there was
			<lb />
			no mention of requiremnt for the expansion of the said partnership busi-
			<lb />
			ness in the notice for eviction. Had there been any such requirement, the
			<lb />
			said fact should have been mentioned in the notice for evictiou. Although
			<lb />
			j,/&apos;
			<lb />
			the landlord really did not require the suit premises for the alleged purpose
			<lb />
			of expansion of the said business, the same was alleged ma/a fide in the
			<lb />
			H petition for eviction. The omission to mention the said ground should be
			<lb />
			considered for the purpose of determining whether there was a real need A
			<lb />
			for expansion of said business. It is precisely for the said reasons, all the
			<lb />
			antecedent facts and circumstances are required to be taken note of for
			<lb />
			the purpose of deciding the bona fide requirement of the landlord. The
			<lb />
			learned counsel has submitted that the Rent Act is essentially a beneficial
			<lb />
			legislation for protection of the tenant against the caprices and whims of B
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			the landloard. The avowed purpose of the legislation to give such protec-
			<lb />
			tion will be frustrated if propec consideration as to the bona fide require-
			<lb />
			ment of the landlord . .s not taken into consideration. The learned counsel
			<lb />
			for the tenant has also submitted that even if it is assumed that the said
			<lb />
			partnership business is expanding, it is necessary to determine the exact
			<lb />
			nature of business and the space required for carrying out such business C
			<lb />
			consistent with the expansion of such business. The necessity for such
			<lb />
			determination of the requirement of space had been indicated in the first
			<lb />
			order of remand by the High Court but despite the same, the appellate
			<lb />
			authority failed and neglected to determine the same and simply on a
			<lb />
			finding that the business was improving and it required expansion, the D
			<lb />
			decree for eviction had been passed against the tenant. ln the aforesaid
			<lb />
			facts, the High Court was justified in setting aside the decree for eviction
			<lb />
			and sending the appeal to the appellate authority on remand for redeter-
			<lb />
			mination in accordance with the observation made in the first order of
			<lb />
			remand. No interference is, therefore, called for in t1&apos;is appeal and the
			<lb />
			same should be dismissed with exemplary cost.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			E
			<lb />
			After giving our careful consideration to the facts and circumstances
			<lb />
			of the case, it appears to us that non-mention of a reasonable ground for
			<lb />
			eviction in the notice for eviction on the basis of which a claim for eviction
			<lb />
			is later on founded usually raises a suspicion about the existence of such F
			<lb />
			ground but such non-mention by itself cannot disentitle a landlord to claim
			<lb />
			eviction on such ground. If a claim for eviction founded on such ground in
			<lb />
			the petition for eviction is proved to be well-founded and the same is
			<lb />
			consistent with the grounds on which eviction is permissible in law, the
			<lb />
			landlord will be entitled to a decree for eviction notwithstanding the fact G
			<lb />
			that such ground was not mentioned in the notice for eviction, In our Yiew,
			<lb />
			the appellate authority has rightly indicated in the facts of this case: that
			<lb />
			the partnership business under the name and style of Govindammal and
			<lb />
			Company was in existence even prior to giving notice for eviction by the
			<lb />
			landlord. Such partnership business was registered and the licence for the
			<lb />
			business was obtained and the business had been subjected to assessments H
			<lb />
			SUPREME COURT REPORTS
			<lb />
			[1994] 2 S.C.R.
			<lb />
			A made by the income tax authorities. Hence, such business was not brought
			<lb />
			into existence only for the purpose of making a foundation for eviction of
			<lb />
			the tenant with maid fide intention. Hence, in the facts and circumstances
			<lb />
			of the case, it cannot be reasonably held that the claim of bona fide
			<lb />
			requirement on account of the said partnership business is per se mala fide
			<lb />
			B and should not be taken into consideration simply because the case for
			<lb />
			bona fide requirement on that account had not been mentioned in the
			<lb />
			notice for eviction. There is no manner of doubt .that the bona fide
			<lb />
			requirement is required to be considered objectively \vith reference to the
			<lb />
			materials on record and it is necessary to determine the real intention of
			<lb />
			the landlord on the basis of evidences adduced in a case. If the materials
			<lb />
			C on record clearly justify a ~se of bona fide requirement, there will be no
			<lb />
			occasion for the court to hold that the landlord did not require the
			<lb />
			premises bona fide simply because on a previous occasion the action of the
			<lb />
			landlord for bringing an eviction case was not bona fide. It should be borne
			<lb />
			in mind that cause for eviction is a recurring cause of action and even if
			<lb />
			D the existence of such cause of action had not been found in a previous
			<lb />
			proceeding for eviction, the same cannot be discarded if such claim is
			<lb />
			established by cogent evidences adduced by the landlord in a subsequent
			<lb />
			proceeding. It will not be correct to hold that only because after a tenant
			<lb />
			was evicted by the landlord on the ground of reasonable requirement for
			<lb />
			building and reconstruction, the landlord did not make the alleged
			<lb />
			E reconstruction but let out the premises to another tenant after obtaining
			<lb />
			possession, any subsequent eviction case for the said premises deserves to
			<lb />
			be dismissed in limine. The landlord, in our view, may bring an action for
			<lb />
			evictioci of the tenant on subsequent cause of action justifying a case of
			<lb />
			bona fide requirement. Similarly, rejection of a case for building and
			<lb />
			F reconstruction by itself will not disentitle the landlord to get an order of
			<lb />
			-r-
			<lb />
			eviction if the eviction on such ground can be founded in a chaqged
			<lb />
			circumstance. We may also indicate here that the contention that the Rent
			<lb />
			Act is a legislation for protecting a tenant will be over simplification of the
			<lb />
			~egislative import of the Rent Act. In our view, it will be more appropriate
			<lb />
			to hold that the Rent Act regulates the incidence of tenancy and inter se
			<lb />
			G rights and obligations of the landlord and tenant.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			In our view, Mr. Chidambaram is justified in his submission that the
			<lb />
			High Court has acted with byper-~ecbnicality in discarding the finding of
			<lb />
			the appellate authority about the continuous expansion of the said partner-
			<lb />
			H ship business. The appellate authority has ref erred to the exhibits including
			<lb />
			the i lcome-tax assessment orders for the purpose of coming to the finding A
			<lb />
			that the said business had been gradually expanding. In the aforesaid facts,
			<lb />
			it was not proper to discard such finding of the appellate authority by
			<lb />
			indicating that the exhibits had not been elaborated in detail. In any event,
			<lb />
			such exhibits were before the High Court for its consideration and in the
			<lb />
			anxiety to dispose of a !is as early as practicable, the High Court should B
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			have looked into the records and considered the justification of the finding
			<lb />
			made by the appellate authority. It appears to us that the appellate
			<lb />
			authority has referred to the assessment orders from 1985 and has come
			<lb />
			to the finding that the said assessment orders indicated that the business
			<lb />
			was expanding. le is nobody&apos;s case that the documents did not indicate such
			<lb />
			expansion in business activities. Such finding, therefore, appears to be C
			<lb />
			justified.
			<lb />
			Since the eviction proceeding is pending for long, it would have been
			<lb />
			only desirable if the same could have been concluded before this Court.
			<lb />
			But the requirement of space for the said partnership businesses consistent D
			<lb />
			with the nature of business and expanding activities had not been gone into
			<lb />
			by the appellate authority and the relevant materials are also not before
			<lb />
			us. We may also indicate here that the appellate authority has specifically
			<lb />
			held that for the expansion of the business of the landlord styled as Sunder
			<lb />
			Jewellery no further space was required but the partnership business in
			<lb />
			pawn broking was required to be separated. Such finding has not been E
			<lb />
			challenged before the High Court and also before us. It therefore appears
			<lb />
			to us that the said pawn broking business requires to be run separately.
			<lb />
			Hence, W1! upheld the order or remand to the limited extent, namely, that
			<lb />
			the appellate authority on the basis of materials already on record would
			<lb />
			consider the actual requirement of space for the said partnership business F
			<lb />
			consistent with the nature of business styled as Govindammal and Com-
			<lb />
			paay after keeping in view, the expanding activities in such business. If on
			<lb />
			such consideration, the appellate authority comes to the finding that the
			<lb />
			landlord bona fide requires the disputed premises for runing the said
			<lb />
			business in a separate enclosure, the order of eviction under Section 10
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(3)(a)(iii) of the Rent Act should be passed by the appellate authority. G
			<lb />
			Since parties have already led evidence pursuant to the liberty given by the
			<lb />
			High Court in the first order of remand, no further evidence should be
			<lb />
			allov.:ed to be led by either of the parties. This order will, however, not
			<lb />
			preclude the tenant respondent to give additional evi ence. If any, in
			<lb />
			support of the contention that there had been change in the circumstances H
			<lb />
			SUPREME COURT REPORTS
			<lb />
			(1994] 2 S.C.R.
			<lb />
			A after the impugned decision of the High Court under which the landlord
			<lb />
			has already got in his possession suitable alternative accommodation which
			<lb />
			will satisfy the requirement of the landlord for running the aforesaid busi-
			<lb />
			ness concerns. As the matter is pending for long, we direct the appellate
			<lb />
			authority to dispose of this matter within three months from the date of
			<lb />
			B the receipt of this order. In the facts and circumstances of the case, there
			<lb />
			will be no order as to costs.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			G.N.
			<lb />
			Appeals disposed of.
			<lb />
			&apos;
			<lb />
		</item>
	</text>
</tei>
