<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<item>
			COUNCILOFLEGALAIDANDADVICEv. BAR COUNCIL
			<lb />
			could not be expected to maintain the high stan~ard of professional A
			<lb />
			conduct. It was submitted that persons who retire from various govern-.
			<lb />
			ment, semi-government and other institutions when admitted to the legal
			<lb />
			profession use their earlier contacts to convass for cases and such be-
			<lb />
			haviour leaves a lingering effect on the profession. Such persons being not
			<lb />
			inspired by lofty ideals of the profession, their only motive being money-
			<lb />
			making for which they are prepared to stoop to any level.
			<lb />
			B
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			Allowing the petitions, this Court
			<lb />
			HELD: 1.1. Section 24 of the Advocates Act, prescribes the minimum
			<lb />
			age for enrolment as twenty one years complete. There is no provision in C
			<lb />
			the Act which can be said to prescribe the maximum age for entry into the
			<lb />
			profession. There is no provision empowering the Bar Council of India to
			<lb />
			fraine such a rule. [314-H, 316-B)
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			1.2. By rule 9 of the Bar Council of India Rules, the entry of those
			<lb />
			who have completed 45 years at the date of application for enrolment is D
			<lb />
			sought to be barred. The rule operates at the pre-enrolment stage and
			<lb />
			cannot, therefore, receive the shelter of clause (ah) of section 49(1) of the
			<lb />
			Act. Under the said clause conditions applicable to an advocate touching
			<lb />
			his right to practise can be laid down. But it does not permit laying down
			<lb />
			of conditions for entry into the profession. Therefore, clause (ah) of E
			<lb />
			Section 49(1) of the Act does not empower the Ba.r Council of India to
			<lb />
			frame a rule barring persons who have completed 45 years of age from
			<lb />
			enrolment as an advocate. The impugned rule is, therefore, ultra vires the
			<lb />
			said provision. [315-F-G]
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			1.3. It is within the exclusive domain of the State Bar Council to F
			<lb />
			admit persons as advocates on their rolJs or to remove their names from
			<lb />
			the rolls. There is no provision dealing with admission and enrolment of
			<lb />
			advocates which restricts the entry of those who ha. ve completed 45 years
			<lb />
			as advocates. Nor bas any State Bar Council made any such rule. [317-G)
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			1.4. There is no basis to accept the interpretation that all those above G
			<lb />
			the age group of 45 years constitute a class within the scope of clause (ag)
			<lb />
			of Section 49(1) of the Act to permit the Bar Council of India to debar
			<lb />
			their entry into the profession for all times. In the guise of making a rule
			<lb />
			the Bar Council of India is virtually introducing an a dditional clause in
			<lb />
			Section 24 of the Act prescribing an upper age ceiling of completed age of H
			<lb />
			SUPR EME CO URT REPORTS
			<lb />
			11995] 1 S.C.R.
			<lb />
			A 45 years or !s inserting an additional clause in Section 24A of the Act
			<lb />
			prescribing a disqualification. Therefore, the impugned rule is beyond the
			<lb />
			rule making power of the Rar Council of India and is, therefore, 1tltra vires
			<lb />
			the Act. [318-E-H]
			<lb />
			B
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			1.5. The rationale for the rule stated to be is to maintain the dignity
			<lb />
			and purity of the profession by keeping out those who retire from various
			<lb />
			government, quasi government and other institutions since they on being
			<lb />
			enrolled as advocates use their past contacts to canvass for cases and
			<lb />
			thereby bring the profession into disrepute and also pollute the minds of
			<lb />
			C young fresh entrants to the profession. Thus the object of the rule is clearly
			<lb />
			to shut the doors of the profession for those who seek entry into the
			<lb />
			profession after completing the age of 45 years. In the first place, there is
			<lb />
			no reliable statistical or other material placed on record in support of the
			<lb />
			inference that ex-government or quasi-government servants or the like
			<lb />
			indulge in undesirable activity of the type mentioned after entering the
			<lb />
			D profession. Secondly, the rule does not debar only such persons from entry
			<lb />
			into the profession but those who have completed 45 years of age on the
			<lb />
			date of seeking enrolment. Thirdly those who were enrolled as advocates
			<lb />
			while they were young and had later taken up some job in any government
			<lb />
			or quasi-government or similar institution and had kept the sanad in
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			E abeyance are not debarred from reviving their sanads even after they have
			<lb />
			completed 45 years of age. There may be a large number of persons who
			<lb />
			initially entered the profession but later took up jobs or entered any other
			<lb />
			gainful occupation who revert to practise at a later date eve after t hey
			<lb />
			have crossed the age of 45 years and under t he impugned ru~.: ~.Il!J are not
			<lb />
			debarred from practising. Therefore, in the first place there is no depend-
			<lb />
			F able material in support of the rationale on which the rule i foundu l and
			<lb />
			secondly the rule is discriminatory as it debars one group of persons who
			<lb />
			have crossed the age of 45 years from enrolment while allowing another .
			<lb />
			group to revive and continue practice even after crossing the age of 45
			<lb />
			years. The rule, therefore, is clearly discriminatory. Thirdly, it is un-
			<lb />
			G reasonable and arbitrary as the choice of the age of 45 years is ma rle
			<lb />
			keeping only a certain group in mind ignoring the vast majority of other
			<lb />
			persons who were in the service of government or quasi-government or
			<lb />
			similar institution at any point of time. Thus, the impugned rule violates
			<lb />
			the principle of equality enshrined in Article 14 of the Constitution.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			H
			<lb />
			[319-8-G]
			<lb />
			CIVIL APPELLATE JUR!S£?1CTION : Wril Petition (C) No. 786 A
			<lb />
			of 1993 etc. etc.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(Under Arlicle 32 of lhc Conslilution of India)
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			V.R. Reddy, Additional Solicilor General, Rajinder Sachar, Soli J.
			<lb />
			Sorabjee, G.V. Iyer, A.K. Ganguli, R.P. Bhalt, V.N. Ganpule, Sanjay B
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			Parikh, B:P. Singh, R.K. Karanjawala, Maoik Karanjawala, Darshana
			<lb />
			Bhogilal, Nandioi Gore, Ruby Ahuja, D.A. Dave, N. Seervai, C.N. Sree
			<lb />
			Kumar, C. Ravichandran Iyer, Rani Chhabra, Ms. Kirao Suri, P. Parmes-
			<lb />
			warao, R.P. Srivastava, H.A. Raichura, U.A. Rana, Rajiv Tyagi, Anand
			<lb />
			Prasad, Mohinder Rupal, for Gagrat &amp; Co., R. Mohan, R. Nedumaran, C
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			V.G. Pragasam, R.B. Misra, V.B. Joshi and B.P. Singh for the appearing
			<lb />
			parties.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			The Judgemnt of the Court was delivered by
			<lb />
			AHMADI, CJ. The Bar Council of India by Resolution No. 64/93 D
			<lb />
			dated 22nd August, 1993 added Rule 9 in Chapter III of Part VI of the
			<lb />
			Bar Council of India Rules which resolution was gazetted on 25th Septem-
			<lb />
			ber, 1993. The said newly added rule reads as under :
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;A person who has completed the age of 45 years on the date on E
			<lb />
			which he submits his application for his enrolment as an advocate
			<lb />
			to the State Bar Council shall not be enrolled as an advocate.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			All the State Bar Councils in the country were dufy informed about the
			<lb />
			insertion of the said rule. The legality and validity of the said rule is
			<lb />
			questioned in this batch of petitions as inconsistent with Articles 14, F
			<lb />
			19(1)(g) and 21 of the Constitution and Section 24 of the Advocates Act,
			<lb />
			1961, hereinafter called &apos;the Act&apos;.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			The Act came into fo rce with effect from 19th May, 1961. The
			<lb />
			dictionary of the Act is to be found in Section 2, clause (a) whereof defines
			<lb />
			an Advocate as a person entered in any roll under the provisions of the G
			<lb />
			Act as such and the term &apos;roll&apos; according to clause (k) means a roll of
			<lb />
			advocates prepared and maintained under the Act. Section 3 provides that
			<lb />
			there shall be a Bar Council for each of the States to be known as the Bar
			<lb />
			Council of that State. Section 4 next provides for a Bar Council for the
			<lb />
			territories to which the Act extends t.o be known as the Bar Council of H
			<lb />
			SUPRE ME COURT REPORTS
			<lb />
			f 1995J 1 S.C.R.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			A India. The functions of the State bar Council and the Bar Council of India
			<lb />
			have been set out in Sections 6 &amp; 7, respectively. The functions of the State
			<lb />
			Bar Council include admission of persons as advocates on its roll, prepara-
			<lb />
			tion and rnainten~ of such roll, safeguardi ng the rights, pr.ivileges and
			<lb />
			interests of advocates on its roll and to do all things necessary for discharg-
			<lb />
			B ing the above functions. The functions of the Bar Council of India include
			<lb />
			the laying down of standards of professional condnct and etiquette for
			<lb />
			advocates and for safeguarding their rights, privileges and interests. Chap-
			<lb />
			ter III which deals with &apos;Admission and Enrollment of Advocates&apos; com-
			<lb />
			prises of Sections 16 to 28. Section 16 provides that there shall be two
			<lb />
			classes of advocates, senior advocates and other advocates; Section 17 sets
			<lb />
			C out how every State Bar Councils shall prepare and maintain a roll of
			<lb />
			advocates; Section 18 deJls with the transfer of name of an advocate from
			<lb />
			one State roll to another; Section 19 enjoins upon every State Bar Council
			<lb />
			to send a copy of the roll of advocates to the Bar Council of India; Section
			<lb />
			20 makes special provision for enrolment of every advocate who was
			<lb />
			D entitled to practice in the Supreme Court immediately before the appoint-
			<lb />
			ment day in the roll of a State Bar Council; Section 21 relates to the fixation
			<lb />
			of seniority; Section 22 provides for issuance of certificate of enrolment
			<lb />
			and Section 23 confers the right of pre-audience on the Attorney General
			<lb />
			of India, the Solicitor General of India, the Additional Solicitor General
			<lb />
			of India, etc. Section 24 to the extent it is relevant for our purpose provides
			<lb />
			E •as under :
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;24. Persons who may be admitted as advocates on a State roll -
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(1) Subject to the provisions of this Act, and the rules made
			<lb />
			thereunder, a person shall be qualified to be admitted as an
			<lb />
			F
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			advocate on a State roll, if he fulfills the following conditions,
			<lb />
			namely:-
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			(a) he is a citizen of India;
			<lb />
			G
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(b) he has completed the age of twenty-one years; and
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			(c) he has obtained a degree in law.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			Section 24A provides that no person shall be admitted as an advocate on
			<lb />
			a State roll, for the period indicated in the proviso, if he is convicted of
			<lb />
			H an offence involving moral turpitude, or if he is convicted of an offence
			<lb />
			under the provisions of Untouchability (Offences) Act, 1955 or if he is A
			<lb />
			dismissed or removed from employment or oflice under the Stale on any
			<lb />
			charge involving moral tur pitude; Section 25 indicates the authority L o
			<lb />
			whom applications fo r enrolment may be made; Section 26 provides for the
			<lb />
			disposal of such applicati ons; Section 26A confers powers on the State Bar
			<lb />
			Council to remove any name from its roll; Sectio n 27 provides 1hat where B
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			a State Bar. Council has refused the application of any person fo r admission
			<lb />
			as an advocate, no other State Bar Council shall entertain his/her applica-
			<lb />
			tion for admission on its roll except with the previous consent of the fo rmer
			<lb />
			and of the Bar Council of India and Section 28 confers power on a State
			<lb />
			Bar Colincil to make rules to carry out the purposes of the Chapter which
			<lb />
			may in particular, incer alia, provide fo r the conditions subject to which a
			<lb />
			person may be admitted as an advocate on its roll Chapter IV deals with
			<lb />
			the &apos;Right to Practise&apos;. Section 29 says that subject to the provisions of the
			<lb />
			Act and any rule made thereunder there shall, as from the appointed day,
			<lb />
			c
			<lb />
			be only one class of persons entitled to practise the profession of law,
			<lb />
			namely, advocates. According to Section 30 every advocate whose name is D
			<lb />
			entered in the State roll shall be entitled as of right to practise throughout
			<lb />
			the territories to which the Act extends in all courts including the Supreme
			<lb />
			Court of India, before any Tribunal or person legally authorised to take
			<lb />
			evidence and before any authority or person before whom such advocate
			<lb />
			is, by or under any law for the time being in force, entitled to practise.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			Section 33 funher provides that no person shall, on or after the appointed E
			<lb />
			d ay, be entitled to practise in any court or before any authority or person
			<lb />
			unless he is enrolled as an advocate under the Act. Chapter V deals with
			<lb />
		</item>
		<item>
			&apos;Conduct of Advocates&apos;. Under Section 35 where on receipt of a complaint
			<lb />
			or otherwise a State Bar Council has reason to believe that any advocate
			<lb />
			on its roll has been guilty of professional or other misconduct it shall refer
			<lb />
			the case for disposal to its disciplinary committee. Section 37 provides for
			<lb />
			an appeal to the bar Council of India against an order made by the
			<lb />
			disciplinary committee of a State Bar Council. Section 36 provides that
			<lb />
			where on receipt of a complaint or otherwise, the Bar Council of India has
			<lb />
			reason to believe that any advocate whose name is not entered on any State
			<lb />
			F
			<lb />
			roll has been guilty of professional or other misconduct, it shall refer the G
			<lb />
			case to the disciplinary committee. Any person aggrieved by an order made
			<lb />
			by the disciplinary committee of the Bar Council of India under Section 36
			<lb />
			or 37 may prefer an appeal to the Supreme Court of India under Section
			<lb />
			38 of the Act. The powers of the disciplinary committee have been
			<lb />
			H
			<lb />
			SUPREME COURT REPORTS
			<lb />
			[1995] 1 S.C.R.
			<lb />
			A enumerated in Section 42. Chapter VI tlea!s with &apos;Miscellaneous&apos; matters.
			<lb />
			We are concerned with Section 49 which empowers the Bar Council of
			<lb />
			India to make rules for discharging its functions under the Act. Clauses
			<lb />
			(ag) anti (ah) of sub-section (1) of Section 49 inter alia, empower the Bar
			<lb />
			Council of India to make rules (i) prescribing the class or category of
			<lb />
			B persons entitled to be enrolled as advocates and (ii) laying down the
			<lb />
			conditions subject lo which an advocate shall have the right to practise and
			<lb />
			the circumstances under which a person shall be deemed lo practise as an
			<lb />
			advocate in •a court. These, in brief, are the relevant provisions of the Act
			<lb />
			which have a bearing on the question of legality and validity of the newly
			<lb />
			added rule 9 in Chapter lII of Part VI of the Rules.
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			c
			<lb />
			It will be seen from the above provision!&gt; that unless a person is
			<lb />
			enrolled as an advocate by a State Bar Council, he shall have no right to
			<lb />
			practise in a cour• t of law or before any other Tribunal or authority. Once
			<lb />
			a person fulfills the requirements of Section 24 for enrolment, he becomes
			<lb />
			D entitled to be enrolled as an advocate and on such enrolment he acquires
			<lb />
			a right to practise as stated above. Having thus acquired a right to practise
			<lb />
			he incurs certain obligations in regard to his conduct as a member of the
			<lb />
			noble profession. The Bar Councils are enjoined with the duty to act as
			<lb />
			sentinels of professional conduct and must ensure that the dignity and
			<lb />
			purity of the profession are in no way undermined. Its job is to uphold the
			<lb />
			E standards of professional conduct and etiquette. Thus every State Bar
			<lb />
			Council and the Bar Council of India has a public duty to perform, namely,
			<lb />
			to ensure that the monopoly of practice granted under the Act is not
			<lb />
			misused or abused by a person who is enrolled as an advocate. The Bar
			<lb />
			Councils have been created at the State level as well as the Central level
			<lb />
			F not only to protect the rights, interests and privileges of its members but
			<lb />
			also to protect the litigating public by ensuring that high and noble tradi-
			<lb />
			tions are maintained so that the purity and dignity of the profession are
			<lb />
			not jeopardized. It is generally believed that members of the legal profes-
			<lb />
			sion have certain social obligatiqns, e.g., to render &apos;pro bono publico&apos;
			<lb />
			service to the poor and the under-privileged. Since the duty of a lawyer is
			<lb />
			G to assist the court in the administration of justice, the practice of law has
			<lb />
			a public utility flavour and, therefore, he must strictly and scrupulously
			<lb />
			abide by the Code of Conduct behoving the noble profession and must not
			<lb />
			indulge in any activity which may tend to lower the image of the profession
			<lb />
			in society. That is why the functions of the Bar Council include the laying
			<lb />
			H down of standards of professional conduct and etiquette which advocates
			<lb />
			must follow to maintain the dignity and purity of the profession ..
			<lb />
			In the above background it was contended on behalf of the-Bar
			<lb />
			Council of India that the need to uphold standards of professional conduct
			<lb />
			A
			<lb />
			and etiquette cannot be over-emphasised. The Act, besides highlighting the
			<lb />
			essential functions of the Bar Council of India in this behalf, provides for B
			<lb />
			the enforcement of the same and sets up disciplinary authorities to chastise
			<lb />
			and, if necessary, punish members of the profession for misconduct. The
			<lb />
			punishment may include suspension from practice as well as removal of
			<lb />
			the name from the roll of advocates. Section 49(1) confers power on the
			<lb />
			Bar Council of lndia to make rules, inter alia, for discharging its functions
			<lb />
			under the Act. Section 49(1)(ag) when read with Section 24 of the Act C
			<lb />
			confers wide powers on the Bar Council of India to indicate the class or
			<lb />
			category of persons who may be enrolled as advocates which power would
			<lb />
			include the power to refuse enrolment in certain circumstances. The
			<lb />
			obligation to maintain the dignity and purity of the profession and to punish
			<lb />
			erring members carries with it the power to regulate entry into the prof es-D
			<lb />
			sion with a view to ensuring that only profession-oriented and service-
			<lb />
			oriented people join the Bar and those not so oriented are kept out.
			<lb />
			Counsel submitted that a person who has already spent the best years of
			<lb />
			his Life in pursuing some other profession or occupation cannot be said to
			<lb />
			have the correct attitude of a service-oriented professional and cannot be
			<lb />
			expected to maintain the high standards of professional conduct. Accord-E
			<lb />
			ing to the respondent-Bar Council of India persons wbo retire from various
			<lb />
			government, quasi-government and other institutions when admitted to the
			<lb />
			legal professi~n use their earlie~ contacts to convass for cases; a conduct
			<lb />
			which brings down the standard of professional ethics expected to be
			<lb />
			maintained by a member of the profession and that has a very adverse F
			<lb />
			influence on the minds of young fresh entrants to the profession. It is no
			<lb />
			answer to state that disciplinary action can be taken against those who
			<lb />
			deviate from the standard of cond&apos;:1cl expected of a member of the Bar
			<lb />
			because all cases of infraction of th• e Code of Conduct do not come to the
			<lb />
			notice of the Bar Council and behaviour• leaves a lingering effect on the
			<lb />
			profession. It is in order to uphold. the high standards of professional G
			<lb />
			morality and integrity that the Bar Council of India was compelled to enact
			<lb />
			a rule restricting the entry into the legal profession by prescribing the age
			<lb />
			limit of 45 years. The Bar Council of India contends that it has acted bona
			<lb />
			fide within the framework of the Act and the Constitution. According to it
			<lb />
			the right to practise as an advocate not being a fundamental right but only H
			<lb />
			SUPREME COURT REPORTS
			<lb />
			11995) 1 $.C.R.
			<lb />
			A &apos; a privilege conferred by the Act can always be withdrawn and in any case
			<lb />
			reasonable restrictions can be imposed even if it were a f un&lt;lamental righ!
			<lb />
			under Article 19(1)(g) of the Constitution. The restriction imposed by the
			<lb />
			newly added rule is to serve a public purpose and can never b~ termed as
			<lb />
			unreasonable, violative of Article 14 of the Constitution. Since the upper
			<lb />
			age limit has been fixed to save the legal profession from decay and
			<lb />
			B deterioration it is, contends the Bar Council, difficult to comprehend how
			<lb />
			it can be said to be inconsistent with Article 21 and for that matter Article
			<lb />
			14 of the Constitution. The prescription of the higher •age limit does not
			<lb />
			violate Section 24 of the Act and since Section 49 permits classification and
			<lb />
			categorization which even Article 14 pern:tits, the newly added rule is
			<lb />
			C clearly intra vi res the Act and the Constitution. That, in brief, is the defence
			<lb />
			set up by the Bar Council of India in support of the rule impugned before
			<lb />
			us.
			<lb />
			It is clear from the above averments found in the counter filed on
			<lb />
			D behalf of the Bar Council of India that the rationale is that the profession
			<lb />
			of law being a pious and honourable profession, its main object being
			<lb />
			service of mankind by serving the system of administration of justice, it is
			<lb />
			the pious duty of the Bar Council to protect its public image by restricting
			<lb />
			the inflow of a large number of retired personnel who seek to enter a legal
			<lb />
			profession solely for additional gains. Such persons are not inspired by
			<lb />
			E loftly ideals of the profession but their only motive is money-making for
			<lb />
			which they are prepared to stoop to any levels which has a very negdiive
			<lb />
			influence on young minds who join the profession after graduation. Can
			<lb />
			the restriction imposed on this rationale be sustained? That is the short
			<lb />
			question.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			F
			<lb />
			We have briefly noticed the relevant provisions of the Act in the
			<lb />
			earlier part of this judgment. We may now briefly indicate the scheme.
			<lb />
			Before we do so it may not be out of place to mention that the profession
			<lb />
			of law is one of the oldest professions and was practised in one form or
			<lb />
			G the other in the hoary past. After the advent of the British in India, certain
			<lb />
			rules in regard to the practise of law were introduced. Before inde-
			<lb />
			pendence there were Mukhtars and Vakils who were permitted to practise
			<lb />
			law in moffusil courts even though not all of them were Law graduates.
			<lb />
			However, slowly and gradually they were allowed to wither away and their
			<lb />
			H place was taken by Pleaders who were, after securing a degree in law,
			<lb />
			permiued to praclise at the district level. Thos~ who were enrolled as A
			<lb />
			advocates could praclice in any court •subordinate to the High Court
			<lb />
			including the High Court. The difference beLweeo a Pleader and an advo-
			<lb />
			cate was merely on account of th.e fee charged for enrolment After
			<lb />
			independence, came the Act which was enacted &apos; to amend and consolidate
			<lb />
			the law relating to legal practitioners and to provide for the constilulion of B
			<lb />
			Bar Councils and an all-India Bar&apos;. The Act creates an all-India Bar wilh
			<lb />
			only one class of legal practitioners, namely, advocates, who of course are
			<lb />
			classified as senior advocates and other advocates (Section 16). The
			<lb />
			general superintendence of ethics and etiquette of the profession is the
			<lb />
			responsibility of the Bar Councils created under the Act and they have C
			<lb />
			been charged with the duty to punish their members for misconduct. The
			<lb />
			Act envisages the existence of a Bar Council for every State. The funcion
			<lb />
			of admission of persons as advocates is entrusted to every State Bar
			<lb />
			Council which is required to prepare and maintain a roll for that purpose.
			<lb />
			While disciplinary jurisdiction is conferred on the Slate Bar Councils to D
			<lb />
			punish its members for misconduct, it is at the same time charged with the
			<lb />
			duty to safeguard their rights, privileges and interest. They must perform
			<lb />
			all the functions conferred on them by or under the Act and do everything
			<lb />
			that is necessary to discharge the functions set out in Section 6. So far as
			<lb />
			the Bar Council of India is concerned, its functions are of a more general E
			<lb />
			nature, e.g., to lay down standards of professional conduct and etiquette
			<lb />
			for advocates, to safeguard their rights, privileg~ and interests, to super-
			<lb />
			vise and control the working of the State Bar Council, to promote legal
			<lb />
			education, to recognise universities, to organise legal aid to the poor and
			<lb />
			F
			<lb />
			to perform all other functions conferred by or under the Act and do
			<lb />
			everything that may necessary to discharge the functions enumerated in
			<lb />
			Section 7. Besides the above it too is required to exercise discipline and
			<lb />
			control over the members of the profession. Thus the functions are divided
			<lb />
			between the State Bar Councils and the Bar Council of India, although for
			<lb />
			obvious reasons overlaps are unavoidable. The rule making power has been G
			<lb />
			conferred on the State Bar Councils under Sections 15 and 28 and on the
			<lb />
			Bar Council of India under Section 49 of the Act.
			<lb />
			The power conferred by Section 15 is to make rules providing for the
			<lb />
			elections of the members of the Bar Council, its Chairman and Vice-Chair-
			<lb />
			man and matters incidental thereto. These rules shall not have effect unless H •
			<lb />
			SUPREME CO URT REPORTS
			<lb />
			[1995] 1 S.C.R.
			<lb />
			A approved. by the Bar Council of India. We are not concerned wilh the rul~
			<lb />
			making power under this provision. Seclion 28 empowers the State Bar
			<lb />
			Council to make rules which may, i11cer alia, provide for lhe form in which
			<lb />
			an advocale must express his inlention for entry of his name in the roll of
			<lb />
			a State Bar Council, the form in which an application must be made for
			<lb />
			B admission as an advocate on its roll and the conditions subject to which a
			<lb />
			person may be admitted as an advocate on any such roll. These rules also
			<lb />
			must be approved by the Bar Council of India before they come into force.
			<lb />
			We have already indicated earlier the matters in regard to which the Bar
			<lb />
			Council of India may make rules for discharging its functions under the
			<lb />
			Act. Besides the State Bar Councils and the Bar Council of India Section
			<lb />
			C 34 confers power on the High Courts to make rules laying down the
			<lb />
			conditions subi~ct to which an advocate may be permitted to practise in
			<lb />
			the High Court and courts subordinate thereto. Power is also conferred on
			<lb />
			the Central Government by Section 49-A to make rules by notification in
			<lb />
			the Official Gazette for carrying out the purposes of the Act including rules
			<lb />
			D with respect to any matter for&apos; which the Bar Council of India or a State
			<lb />
			Bar Council has power to make rules. Thus the rule making power of the
			<lb />
			Central Government is wide enough to embrace matters for which the Bar
			<lb />
			Council of India or a State Bar Council has power to make rules. These
			<lb />
			rules may, inter alia, lay down the qualifications and disqualifications for
			<lb />
			membership of a Bar Council, the manner in which the Bar Council of
			<lb />
			E India must exercise supervision and control over State Bar Councils, the
			<lb />
			class or category of persons entitled to be enrolled as advocates under the
			<lb />
			• Act, the category of persons who may be exempted for undergoing a course
			<lb />
			of training and passing an examination prescribed under Section 24(1)(d),
			<lb />
			the manner in which seniority among advocates may be determined, the
			<lb />
			F procedure to be followed by the disciplinary committee of the Bar Council
			<lb />
			for hearing cases and any other matter which may be prescribed. These, in
			<lb />
			brief, are the rule making powers conferred on various agencies under the
			<lb />
			Act.
			<lb />
			The newly added rule seeks to bar the entry of persons who have
			<lb />
			G . completed the age of 45 years on the date of application for enrolment as
			<lb />
			an advocate from being enrolled as such by the concerned State Bar
			<lb />
			Council. While Section 24 of the Act prescribes the minimum age for
			<lb />
			enrolment as twenty-one years complete, there is no provision in the Act
			<lb />
			which can be said to prescribe the maximum age for entry into the
			<lb />
			H profession. Since the Act is silent on this point the Bar Council of India
			<lb />
			was requi red to resort to its rule ~aking power. The rules made by the Bar A
			<lb />
			Council of India under Section 49(1) of the Act are in seven pares, each •
			<lb />
			part having its own chapters. Part Vl is entitled &apos;Rules Governing
			<lb />
			Advocates&apos; and the said part bas three chapters. Chapter 1 sets out the
			<lb />
			restrictions on senior advocates and is relatable to Section 16(3) and
			<lb />
			49(l )(g) of the Act, Chapter IT lays down the standards• of professional B
			<lb />
			conduct and etiquette and is relatable to Section 49(1)( c) _ read with the
			<lb />
			proviso thereto and chapter Ill deals with &apos;Conditions for right to practice&apos;
			<lb />
			and is stated to be made in exercise of power under clause (ah) of
			<lb />
			sub-section (1) of Section 49 of the Act. That clause reads as under :
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;(ah) -the conditions subject to which an advocate shall have the C
			<lb />
			right to practise and the circumstances under which a person shall
			<lb />
			be deemed to practise as an advocate in a court;&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			On the plain language of the said clause it seems clear to us that under the
			<lb />
			said provision the Bar Council of lndia can lay down the &apos;conditions&apos; D
			<lb />
			subject to which &apos;an advocate&apos; shall have the righ~ to practise. These
			<lb />
			conditions which the Bar Council of lndia can lay down are applicable to
			<lb />
			an advocate, i.e., a person who has already been enrolled as an advocate
			<lb />
			by the concerned State Bar Council. The conditions which can be
			<lb />
			prescribed must apply at the post-enrolment stage since they are expected E
			<lb />
			to relate to the right to practise. They can, therefore, not operate at the
			<lb />
			pre-enrolment stage. By the impugned rule, the entry of those who have
			<lb />
			completed 45 years at the date of application for enrolment is •sought to be
			<lb />
			barred. The rule clearly operates at the pre-enrolment stage and cannot,
			<lb />
			therefo re, receive the shelter of clause (ah) of Section 49(1) of the Act.
			<lb />
			Under the said clause conditions applicable to an advocate touching his
			<lb />
			right to practise can be laid down, and if laid down he must exercise his
			<lb />
			right subject to those conditions. But the language of the said clause does
			<lb />
			F
			<lb />
			not permit laying down of conditions for entry into the profession. We have,
			<lb />
			therefore, no hesitation in coming to the conclusion tliat clause (ah) of
			<lb />
			Section 49(1) of the Act does not empower the Bar Council of India to G
			<lb />
			frame a rule barring persons who have completed 45 years of age from
			<lb />
			enrolment as an advocate. The impugned rule is, therefore, ultra vires the
			<lb />
			said provision.
			<lb />
			Can the rule be saved under any other provision of the Act? As H
			<lb />
			SUPREME COURT REPORTS
			<lb />
			11995] 1 S.C.R.
			<lb />
			A stated earlier the Act in Section 24(1)(b) provides that the person who
			<lb />
			seeks enrolment as an advocate must have completed th e age of twenty-one
			<lb />
			years. Nowhere does the Act provide the maximum age beyond which a
			<lb />
			person shall not be entitled to enrolment as an advocate nor does the Act
			<lb />
			make any specific provision empowering the Bar Council of India lo frame
			<lb />
			B such a rule. Reliance was, however placed on clause (ag) of Section 49(1)
			<lb />
			which reads as under :
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			&quot;(ag) the class or category of persons entitled to be enrolled as
			<lb />
			advocates.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			C Can persons who have completed 45 years of age be said to constitute a
			<lb />
			class or category to entitle the Bar Council of India to debar them from
			<lb />
			being enrolled as advocates? Rule 49(1) empowers the Bar Council of
			<lb />
			India to make rules for discharging its functions under the Act and in
			<lb />
			particular those enumerated in clauses (a) to G) thereof. None of the
			<lb />
			D functions under Section 7 specifically provides for laying down such a
			<lb />
			condition debarring persons of a certain age group from enrolment as
			<lb />
			advocates. The Clause relied upon is couched in positive terms, namely, it
			<lb />
			says the rules may prescribe the class or category of persons who may be
			<lb />
			admitted to the legal profession. Therefore, under this rule the class or
			<lb />
			category of persons &apos;entitled to be • enrolled&apos; as advocates may be
			<lb />
			E prescribed. The rule can, therefore, i:pecify the class or category of persons
			<lb />
			&apos;entitled&apos; to be enrolled as an advocates, but the rule gives no indication
			<lb />
			that it can debar persons belonging to a certain age group from being
			<lb />
			enrolled as advocates. Where a provision is couched in positive language
			<lb />
			and is in the nature of an enabling provision, there is no canon of construc-
			<lb />
			F tion which says that by necessary implication the rule making authority can
			<lb />
			make a provision disentitling admission or enrolment to the profession.
			<lb />
			Such a submission is difficult to countenance.
			<lb />
			But the larger question needs to be answered and that is whether the
			<lb />
			said clause applies to persons belonging to a certain age group. Section
			<lb />
			G 28(1)(d) of the Act authorises a State Bar Council to make rules prescrib-
			<lb />
			ing the conditions subject to which a person may be admitted as an
			<lb />
			advocate. The power to specify the class or category of persons entitled to
			<lb />
			be enrolled as advocates is conferred on the Bar Council of India under
			<lb />
			Section 49(1)(ag) and on the Central Government under Section 49A of
			<lb />
			H the Act. The role which a State Bar Council has to play under Section 28
			<lb />
			is distinct fro~ that the Bar Council of India has to play under Section A
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			49(1)(ag) of the Act, in that, after the class or category is identified, they •
			<lb />
			&lt;lo not automatically get admitted or enrolled they still have to abide by
			<lb />
			the requirements for admission to the State roll. Therefore, apart from a
			<lb />
			class or group being declared &apos;entitled to enrolment&apos;, the other conditions
			<lb />
			or norms evolved by the State Bar Council for entry of the individual on B
			<lb />
			its role would have to be satisfied.
			<lb />
			It seems Parliament while enacting the Act created agencies at the
			<lb />
			State level as well as at the Central level in the form of State Bar Councils
			<lb />
			and Bar Council of India and invested them with rule making powers on
			<lb />
			diverse matters touching the legal profession, presumably because it must C
			<lb />
			have realised that matter pertaining to the profes~ion are best left to
			<lb />
			informed bodies comprising of members of the said profession. However,
			<lb />
			while doing so it provided for basic substantive matters, e.g., eligibility fo~
			<lb />
			entry into the profession (Section 24), disqualification for enrolm~nt (Sec-
			<lb />
			tion 24A), authority entitled to grant admission (Sections 25 and 26), the D
			<lb />
			authority which can remove any name from the roll (Section 26A), etc.,
			<lb />
			and placed them within the domain of a State Bar Council. Thus it is the
			<lb />
			State Bar Council which alone must decide on the question of enrolment
			<lb />
			of an applicant on its roll. Under Section 24 a person who is a citizen of
			<lb />
			India and possesses a degree in law becomes qualified to be admitted as E
			<lb />
			an advocate if he has completed twenty one years of age, subject of course
			<lb />
			to the other provisions of the Act. No doubt he must fulfil the other
			<lb />
			conditions specified in the rules made by the State Bar Council (Section
			<lb />
			24(1)(e)). Every person whose name is entered in the list of advocates has
			<lb />
			a right to practise in all courts including the Supreme Court, before any
			<lb />
			tribunal or other authority. It is, therefore, within the exclusive domain of
			<lb />
			the State Bar Councils to admit persons as advocates on their rolls or to
			<lb />
			remove their names from the rolls. There is no provision in Chapter III
			<lb />
			dealing with admission and enrolment of advocates which restricts the
			<lb />
			entry of those who have completed 45 years as advocates. Nor has the State
			<lb />
			Bar Council made any such rule under its rule making power.
			<lb />
			There is no specific provision in Section 7 of the Act which
			<lb />
			enumerates the functions of the Bar Council of India empowering it to fix
			<lb />
			F
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			G
			<lb />
			the maximum age beyond which entry into the profession would be barred.
			<lb />
			That is why reliance is placed on the rule making power of the Bar Council H
			<lb />
			SU PREME COURT REPORTS
			<lb />
			I 1995] 1 S.C.R.
			<lb />
			A•• ol 1IQdia enshrined in Section 49. T~at Section empowers the making of
			<lb />
			rule by the Bar Council of India &apos;for discharging its functions&apos; under the
			<lb />
			Act, and, in particular, such rules may prescribe the class or category of
			<lb />
			persons entitled to be enrolled as advocates. The functions of the Bar
			<lb />
			Council of India enumerated in Section 7 do not envisage laying down a
			<lb />
			B stipulation disqualifying persons otherwise qualified from entering the legal
			<lb />
			profession merely because they have completed the age of 45 years. On the
			<lb />
			other hand Section 24A was introduced by Section 19 of Act 60 of 1973
			<lb />
			with effect from 31st January, 1974 to disqualify certain persons from
			<lb />
			entering the legal profession for a limited period. By the impugned rule
			<lb />
			C every person even if qualified but who has completed 45 years of age is
			<lb />
			debarred for all times from enrolment as an advocate. If it had been
			<lb />
			possible to restrict the entry of even those class or category of persons
			<lb />
			referred to in Section 24A by a mere rule made by the Bar Council of India,
			<lb />
			where was the need for a statutory amendment? That is presumably
			<lb />
			D because matters concerning disqualification even for a limited period was
			<lb />
			considered to be falling outside the ken of rule making power, being a
			<lb />
			matter of public policy. It is difficult to accept the interpretation that all
			<lb />
			those above the age group of 45 years constitute a class within the scope
			<lb />
			of clause (ag) of Section 49(1) of the Act to permit the Bar Council of
			<lb />
			India to debar their entry into the profession for all times. ln the guise of
			<lb />
			E making a rule the Bar Council of India is virtually introducing an additional
			<lb />
			clause in Section 24 of the Act prescribing an upper age ceiling of com-
			<lb />
			pleted age of 45 years beyond which no person shall be eligible for
			<lb />
			enrolment as an advocate or is inserting an additional clause in Section
			<lb />
			24A of the Act prescribing a disqualification. Viewed from either point of
			<lb />
			F view we are clearly of the opinion that the rule making power under clause
			<lb />
			(ag) of Section 49(1) of the Act does not confer any such power on the
			<lb />
			Bar Council of India. We are unable to subscribe to thP view that all those
			<lb />
			&apos; who have completed the age of 45 years and are otherwise eligible to be
			<lb />
			enrolled as advocates constitute a class or category which can be dis-
			<lb />
			G qualified as a single block from entering the profession. Besides, as stated
			<lb />
			above clause (ag) identification and specification of a class or category of
			<lb />
			persons &apos;entitled&apos; to be enrolled and not &apos;disentitled&apos; to be enrolled as
			<lb />
			advocates. We, therefore, are of the opinion that the impugned rule is
			<lb />
			beyond the rule making power of the Bar Council of India and is, therefore,
			<lb />
			H ultra vires the Act.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			-(
			<lb />
			COUNCIL OF LEGAL AID A D ADVICE 1•. BAR COUNCIL I AHMADI. CJ .I 319
			<lb />
			The next question i. , is the rule reasonblc or arbit~ary anc.l un-A
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			reasonable? The rationable for the rule, a~ . tatec.l earlier, is to maintain
			<lb />
			the c.lignity anc.l purity of the profession by keeping out tho. e who retire
			<lb />
			from various government, quasi-government anc.l other institutions since
			<lb />
			they on heing enrollee.I as ac.lvocatcs use their past contacts to canvass fo r
			<lb />
			cases anc.l thereby bring the profession into disrepute anc.l also pollute the B
			<lb />
			minds of young fresh entrants to the profession. Thus the object of the
			<lb />
			rule is clearly to shut the doors of the profession fo r those whc seek entry
			<lb />
			into the profession after completing the age of 45 years. In the first place,
			<lb />
			there is no reliable statistical or other material placed on record in
			<lb />
			support of the inference that ex-governrneuc or quasi-government servants C
			<lb />
			or the like indulge in undesirable activity of the type mentioned afte1
			<lb />
			entering the profession. Secondly, the rule does not debar only such
			<lb />
			persons from entry into the profession but those who have completed 45
			<lb />
			years of age on the date of seeking enrolmnent. Thirdly those who were
			<lb />
			enrolled as advocates while they were young and had later taken up some D
			<lb />
			job in any government or quasi-goverment or similar institution aud had
			<lb />
			kept the sanad in abeyance are not debarred from reviving their sanads
			<lb />
			even after they have completed 45 years of age. There may be a large
			<lb />
			number of persons who initially entered the profession but later took up
			<lb />
			jobs or entered any other gainful occupation who revert to practise at a
			<lb />
			later date even after they have crossed the age of 45 years and under the E
			<lb />
			impugned rule they are not debarred from practising. Therefore, in the
			<lb />
			first place there is no dependable material in support of the rationale on
			<lb />
			which the rule is founded and secondly the rule is discriminatory as it
			<lb />
			debars one group of persons who have crossed the age of 45 years from
			<lb />
			entrolment while allowing another group to revive and continue practise
			<lb />
			even after crossing the age of 45 years. The rule, in our view, therefore,
			<lb />
			is clearly discriminatory. Thirdly, it is t. .. reasonable and arbitrary as the
			<lb />
			choice of the age of 45 years is made keeping only a certain group in
			<lb />
			mind ignoring the vast majority of other persons who were in the service
			<lb />
			F
			<lb />
			of government or quasi-government or similar institutions at any point of G
			<lb />
		</item>
		<p>
			time. Thus, in our view the impugned rule violates the principle of
			<lb />
			equality enshrined in Article 14 of the Constitution.
			<lb />
			In tile view that we take on the aforesaid points we do not consider
			<lb />
			it necessary to examine the larger question whether or not the impugned H
			<lb />
			SUPREME COURT REPORTS
			<lb />
			(1995) 1 S.C.R.
			<lb />
			A rule violates Article 19(1)(g) of the Constitution. We, therefore, do not
			<lb />
			express any view on the said question.
			<lb />
			ln the result, these petitions succeed. The new rule 9 inserted in
			<lb />
			Chapter m ~xtracted in the opening paragraph of this judgment is struck
			<lb />
			down as ultra vires the Act and opposed to Article 14 of the Constitution.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			B The Bar Council of India and the State Bar Councils are directed not to
			<lb />
			implement the said rule. No order as to costs.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			A.G.
			<lb />
			Petitions allowed.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			.•
		</p>
	</text>
</tei>
