<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<p>
			1. All these I.As arise out of the directions issued by this
			<lb />
			Court vide order dated 10th  November 2021 in Civil Appeal
			<lb />
			Nos. 3661­3662 of 2020.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			2. The   State   of   Bihar   had   approached   this   Court
			<lb />
			challenging the order dated 14th October 2020, passed by the
			<lb />
			National   Green   Tribunal,   Principal   Bench,   New   Delhi
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(hereinafter referred to as &quot;the Tribunal&quot;) in O.A. No.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			40/2020/EZ with O.A. No. 57/2020/EZ, thereby issuing
			<lb />
			various directions. This Court after taking into consideration
			<lb />
			various aspects, including the necessity to curb illegal
			<lb />
			mining activities and the necessity to permit legal mining in
			<lb />
			the interregnum till the other directions issued by this Court
			<lb />
			are complied with, had issued the following directions dated
			<lb />
			10 th November 2021:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot;14. We therefore find it appropriate to substitute
				<lb />
				the directions issued by the Tribunal vide judgment
				<lb />
				and order dated 14 th October 2020, with the
				<lb />
				following directions:
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(i) The exercise of preparation of DSR for
				<lb />
				the purpose of mining in the State of Bihar
				<lb />
				in all the districts shall be undertaken
				<lb />
				afresh. The draft DSRs shall be prepared by
				<lb />
				the subdivisional committees consisting of
				<lb />
				the SubDivisional Magistrate, Officers from
				<lb />
				Irrigation Department, State Pollution
				<lb />
				Control Board or Committee, Forest
				<lb />
				Department, Geological or mining officer.
				<lb />
				The same shall be prepared by undertaking
				<lb />
				site visits and also by using modern
				<lb />
				technology. The said draft DSRs shall be
				<lb />
				prepared within a period of 6 weeks from
				<lb />
				the date of this order. After the draft DSRs
				<lb />
				are prepared, the District Magistrate of the
				<lb />
				concerned District shall forward the same
				<lb />
				for examination and evaluation by the
				<lb />
				SEAC. The same shall be examined by the
				<lb />
				SEAC within a period of 6 weeks and its
				<lb />
				report shall be forwarded to the SEIAA
				<lb />
				within the aforesaid period of 6 weeks from
				<lb />
				the receipt of it. The SEIAA will thereafter
				<lb />
				consider the grant of approval to such DSRs
				<lb />
				within a period of 6 weeks from the receipt
				<lb />
				thereon;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(ii) Needless to state that while preparing
				<lb />
				DSRs and the appraisal thereof by SEAC
				<lb />
				and SEIAA, it should be ensured that a
				<lb />
				strict adherence to the procedure and
				<lb />
				parameters laid down in the policy of
				<lb />
				January 2020 should be followed;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(iii) Until further orders, we permit the
				<lb />
				State Government to carry on mining
				<lb />
				activities through Bihar State Mining
				<lb />
				Corporation for which it may employ the
				<lb />
				services of the contractors. However, while
				<lb />
				doing so, the State Government shall ensure
				<lb />
				that all environmental concerns are taken
				<lb />
				care of and no damage is caused to the
				<lb />
				environment.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			The matter was directed to be listed after 20 weeks.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<head>
			I.A. Nos. 154740154741 of 2021
			<lb />
		</head>
		<p>
			3.
			<lb />
			The present I.As have been filed being aggrieved by the
			<lb />
			cancellation of Letter of Intent (hereinafter referred to as the
			<lb />
			&quot;LoI&quot;) dated 21 st January 2020, issued in favour of the
			<lb />
			applicant. The applicant also apprehended that in view of the
			<lb />
			order dated 10 th November 2021 passed by this Court with
			<lb />
			respect to Banka District, the State Government may also
			<lb />
			issue short Notice Inviting Tender (hereinafter referred to as
			<lb />
			the &quot;NIT&quot;) with respect to Kishanganj District. After the
			<lb />
			present I.As were filed, NIT has also been issued in respect of
			<lb />
			sand ghats in Kishanganj District on 2 nd December 2021.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			4.
			<lb />
			Shri Mukul Rohatgi, learned Senior Counsel appearing
			<lb />
			on behalf of the applicant submitted that the applicant was a
			<lb />
			successful bidder in the auction held for the Kishanganj
			<lb />
			District and as such, the action of the respondent in
			<lb />
			cancelling the LoI and issuing fresh NIT for Kishanganj
			<lb />
			District is not sustainable in law. It is submitted that the
			<lb />
			offer of the applicant was for a much higher amount as
			<lb />
			compared to the offer received by the respondentBihar State
			<lb />
			Mining Corporation (hereinafter referred to as the
			<lb />
			&quot;Corporation&quot;) for Kishanganj District.
			<lb />
			He therefore
			<lb />
			submitted that it is in the interest of justice that the
			<lb />
			applicant may be permitted to carry out the mining activities
			<lb />
			in the Kishanganj District.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<head>
			I.A. Nos. 153531153532 of 2021
			<lb />
		</head>
		<p>
			5.
			<lb />
			In the present I.As, the applicant claimed that it was a
			<lb />
			successful bidder for auction of sand ghats in respect of
			<lb />
			Banka District for the period from 2015 to 2019. It is the
			<lb />
			case of the applicant that it had been granted extension after
			<lb />
			the year 2019 from time to time and the last of such
			<lb />
			extensions was granted till 31 st March 2022. The applicant
			<lb />
			apprehended that in pursuance to the order dated 10 th
			<lb />
			November 2021 passed by this Court, NIT would also be
			<lb />
			issued in respect of Banka District. During the pendency of
			<lb />
			these I.As, NIT in respect of sand ghats in Banka District has
			<lb />
			been issued by the Corporation on 2 nd December 2021.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			6.
			<lb />
			We have heard Shri Narender Hooda, learned Senior
			<lb />
			Counsel appearing on behalf of the applicant in the said
			<lb />
			application.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			7.
			<lb />
			Shri Hooda submitted that since the applicant was the
			<lb />
			highest bidder in the auction conducted for the period from
			<lb />
			5
			<lb />
			2015 to 2019 and since thereafter, the applicant had been
			<lb />
			granted extensions, he is entitled to carry out the mining
			<lb />
			activities at least till 31 st March 2022. He further submitted
			<lb />
			that the amount which the respondentCorporation would
			<lb />
			receive for the sand ghats in pursuance to the NIT dated 2 nd
			<lb />
			December 2021, is much less than the one the applicant has
			<lb />
			offered and therefore, it is in the interest of justice that the
			<lb />
			applicant be permitted to continue with the mining activities
			<lb />
			at least till 31 st March 2022.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<head>
			I.A. No. 165173 of 2021
			<lb />
		</head>
		<p>
			8.
			<lb />
			The grievance of the present applicant is somewhat
			<lb />
			similar to the grievance of the applicant in I.A. Nos. 154740
			<lb />
			154741 of 2021. Here again, it is the contention of the
			<lb />
			applicant that it was a successful bidder in respect of the
			<lb />
			sand ghats in the Jamui District in the bids conducted in the
			<lb />
			year 2019. It is therefore submitted that the impugned NIT
			<lb />
			dated 15 th November 2021 issued by the Corporation
			<lb />
			prejudicially affects the interest of the applicant.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			9.
			<lb />
			We have heard Shri Prashant Bhushan, learned counsel
			<lb />
			in support of the said application. Shri Bhushan submitted
			<lb />
			that the applicant was a successful bidder in the bids
			<lb />
			conducted in the year 2019 and he is entitled to be appointed
			<lb />
			as a contractor or in the alternative at least he be granted a
			<lb />
			right to match the highest bidder along with the right of first
			<lb />
			refusal.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<head>
			I.A. Nos. 160138, 160139 and 160142 of 2021
			<lb />
		</head>
		<p>
			10. The grievance of the present applicant is similar to the
			<lb />
			grievance of the applicant in I.A. Nos. 153531153532 of
			<lb />
			2021. It is the case of the applicant that it was a successful
			<lb />
			bidder for the period from 2015 to 2019 at Nawada District.
			<lb />
			Thereafter, the applicant was granted extensions from time to
			<lb />
			time and the last of such extensions was granted till 31 st
			<lb />
			March 2022.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			11. Shri C.A. Sundaram, learned Senior Counsel appearing
			<lb />
			on behalf of the applicant submitted that as such, the
			<lb />
			applicant would be entitled to carry out the mining activities
			<lb />
			till 31 st March 2022.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<head>
			I.A. No. 163177 of 2021.
			<lb />
		</head>
		<p>
			12. In the present application, it has been submitted on
			<lb />
			behalf of the applicant that the mining activities which are
			<lb />
			being carried out by the Corporation are without the grant of
			<lb />
			Environmental Clearance. It is submitted that the very
			<lb />
			purpose for which the order was passed by the Tribunal and
			<lb />
			modified by this Court, was to ensure that the environment
			<lb />
			is not damaged on account of rampant mining activities
			<lb />
			without the grant of Environmental Clearance by the
			<lb />
			Competent Authority. It is therefore submitted that the NITs
			<lb />
			dated 15 th November 2021 and 2 nd December 2021 are silent
			<lb />
			about the environmental aspects and therefore, the action of
			<lb />
			the respondentCorporation in issuing NITs amounts to
			<lb />
			contempt of this Court.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			13. Shri Atmaram Nadkarni, learned Senior Counsel
			<lb />
			appearing on behalf of the appellantState of Bihar submitted
			<lb />
			that the NITs in question were issued for a limited period in
			<lb />
			view of the order passed by this Court dated 10 th November
			<lb />
			2021. He submitted that the rest of the directions as are
			<lb />
			issued by this Court with regard to preparation of draft
			<lb />
			District Survey Report (hereinafter referred to as &quot;DSR&quot;) and
			<lb />
			consideration of the same by State Expert Appraisal
			<lb />
			Committee (hereinafter referred to as &quot;SEAC&quot;) and State
			<lb />
			Environment Impact Assessment Authority (hereinafter
			<lb />
			referred to as &quot;SEIAA&quot;) are under process.
			<lb />
			He further
			<lb />
			submitted that in view of the permission granted by this
			<lb />
			Court vide order dated 10 th November 2021, the Corporation
			<lb />
			is employing the services of the contractor for the limited
			<lb />
			period. He submitted that after the directions issued by this
			<lb />
			Court are complied with, a fresh process for allotment of
			<lb />
			sand ghats in accordance with law would be initiated subject
			<lb />
			to the orders of this Court. He further submitted that while
			<lb />
			permitting the mining activities through the services of the
			<lb />
			contractor, the Corporation is ensuring that no damage is
			<lb />
			caused to environment by such activities.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			14. We had issued the directions vide order dated 10 th
			<lb />
			November 2021 in the peculiar facts and circumstances of
			<lb />
			the matter. We had noticed that unless the detailed DSRs
			<lb />
			are prepared by the SubDivisional Committees by
			<lb />
			undertaking site visits and using the modern technology and
			<lb />
			unless the same are examined by SEAC and SEIAA, it will
			<lb />
			9
			<lb />
			not be appropriate to carry out the mining activities.
			<lb />
			However, we had also noticed that if there is a ban on mining
			<lb />
			activities, apart from it leading to illegal sand mining,
			<lb />
			criminalization and clashes between the sand mafias, it
			<lb />
			would also cause huge loss to the public exchequer. We had
			<lb />
			noticed that sand is also required for construction of public
			<lb />
			infrastructural projects as well as public and private
			<lb />
			construction activities.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			15. Taking into consideration these aspects of the matter,
			<lb />
			we had issued directions so that the SubDivisional
			<lb />
			Committees, the SEAC and SEIAA act within the stipulated
			<lb />
			time periods. We had granted 6 weeks&apos; time at each level and
			<lb />
			had directed the matter to be kept after 20 weeks. However
			<lb />
			noticing, that during the said period, it was necessary to
			<lb />
			permit the mining activities so as to prevent illegal mining
			<lb />
			and also to prevent loss to the public exchequer, we had
			<lb />
			permitted the Corporation to carry out the mining activities,
			<lb />
			and further to employ the services of the contractor.
			<lb />
			However, while doing so, we had directed the State
			<lb />
			Government to ensure that all environmental concerns are
			<lb />
			10
			<lb />
			taken care of and no damage is caused to the environment. It
			<lb />
			could thus be seen that this was only a stop gap
			<lb />
			arrangement.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			16. A perusal of the NITs in question, issued by the
			<lb />
			Corporation would reveal that the Corporation has
			<lb />
			specifically referred to the order dated 10 th November 2021,
			<lb />
			passed by this Court and has also specified that the
			<lb />
			operation period of sand ghats will only be up to 31 st March
			<lb />
			2022, and subject to further orders passed by this Court in
			<lb />
			the present proceedings.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			17. Insofar as the applicants in I.A. Nos. 153531153532 of
			<lb />
			2021 and I.A. Nos.160138, 160139 and 160142 of 2021, who
			<lb />
			claim to have a vested right in view of the extensions granted
			<lb />
			in their favour are concerned, we see no merit in these
			<lb />
			applications. Though they were successful in the bidding
			<lb />
			process held in the year 2015, which was extended up to
			<lb />
			2019 and thereafter, they were only continuing under the
			<lb />
			extensions granted.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			18. Insofar as the other applicants in I.A. Nos.154740
			<lb />
			154741 of 2021 and I.A. No.165173 of 2021 are concerned,
			<lb />
			though they were successful bidders in the tender process
			<lb />
			conducted in the year 2019, in view of the order passed by
			<lb />
			the Tribunal dated 14 th October 2020, which was modified by
			<lb />
			this Court vide order dated 10 th November 2021, they also
			<lb />
			cannot claim a vested right to do the mining activities.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			19. Taking into consideration the peculiar facts and
			<lb />
			circumstances in which we had passed the order, we find
			<lb />
			that entertaining any of such applications would result in
			<lb />
			further complications. In any case after our directions
			<lb />
			issued on 10 th November 2021 are complied with, we will
			<lb />
			take a final look of the matter in the last week of March,
			<lb />
			2022. The NITs issued by the Corporation for mining, cover
			<lb />
			the period only up to 31 st March 2022. We are therefore not
			<lb />
			inclined to entertain the aforesaid four I.As.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			20. Insofar as the I.A. No. 163177 of 2021, filed by the
			<lb />
			applicant alleging contempt of this Court&apos;s order dated 10 th
			<lb />
			November 2021 is concerned, we have already directed the
			<lb />
			State of Bihar to ensure that while carrying out the mining
			<lb />
			activities, it shall ensure that all environmental concerns are
			<lb />
			taken care of and no damage is caused to the environment.
			<lb />
			We remind the State Government of the said directions and
			<lb />
			direct it to ensure that the said directions are complied with
			<lb />
			scrupulously.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			21. In that view of the matter, I.A. Nos. 154740154741 of
			<lb />
			2021, 153531153532 of 2021, 160138 of 2021, 160139 of
			<lb />
			2021, 160142 of 2021 and 165173 of 2021 are rejected.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			22. I.A. No. 163177 of 2021 is disposed of in terms of
			<lb />
			paragraph (20) of this order.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			……....….......................J.
			<lb />
			[L. NAGESWARA RAO]
			<lb />
			..…....….......................J.
			<lb />
			[B.R. GAVAI]
			<lb />
			NEW DELHI;
			<lb />
			JANUARY 18, 2022.
			<lb />
		</p>
	</text>
</tei>
