<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<p>
			1.
			<lb />
			The Petitioner has filed an application under Order VI
			<lb />
			Rule 17 read with section 151 of the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908
			<lb />
			(in short, &quot;CPC&quot;), seeking to insert amendments in the Writ Petition.
			<lb />
			The proposed amendments are as follows;
			<lb />
			Insertion of Paragraph 4.1 and 4.2 after the existing
			<lb />
			Paragraph 4:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot;4.1. The Petitioner is also challenging the
				<lb />
				proviso to Section 174(2)(c) of the
				<lb />
				Central Goods and Services Tax Act, 2017
				<lb />
				which provides that tax exemption
				<lb />
				granted as an incentive through a
				<lb />
				notification would not continue if such
				<lb />
				notification is rescinded.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				4.2
				<lb />
				Further, the Petitioner is also challenging
				<lb />
				the Notification No.21/2017-C.E. dated
				<lb />
				18.07.2017 vide which the exemption
				<lb />
				notifications issued under the erstwhile
				<lb />
				regime
				<lb />
				(including
				<lb />
				Notification
				<lb />
				No.20/2007-C.E. dated 25.04.2007) were
				<lb />
				rescinded.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				Replacing the contents of the existing Paragraph 32
				<lb />
				with the following:
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				&quot;32. Thus, aggrieved by the impugned proviso
				<lb />
				to Section 174(2)(c) of the CGST Act, the
				<lb />
				impugned Notification No.21/2017-C.E.
				<lb />
				dated 18.07.2017 and the Budgetary
				<lb />
				Support Scheme which have resulted in
				<lb />
				denial of vested right to the Petitioner to
				<lb />
				continue to enjoy the benefits promised to
				<lb />
				it, the Petitioner is filing the present
				<lb />
				petition based on the following grounds.
				<lb />
				Each ground is independent and without
				<lb />
				prejudice to one another.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				Incorporating Paragraph A18 after the existing
				<lb />
				paragraph A17:
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				&quot;A.18 It is submitted that the proviso to Section
				<lb />
				174(2)(c) of the CGST Act and the
				<lb />
				impugned Notification No.21/2017-C.E.
				<lb />
				dated 18.07.2017 are in effect taking
				<lb />
				away the vested rights of the Petitioner by
				<lb />
				reducing
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				exemptions/benefits
				<lb />
				promised to the Petitioner. Thus, the
				<lb />
				impugned proviso to Section 174(2)(c) of
				<lb />
				the CGST Act and the impugned
				<lb />
				Notification
				<lb />
				No.21/2017-C.E.
				<lb />
				dated
				<lb />
				18.07.2017
				<lb />
				are
				<lb />
				contrary
				<lb />
				to
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				established principles of promissory
				<lb />
				estoppel and legitimate expectation as
				<lb />
				submitted in foregoing Grounds. For this
				<lb />
				reason, the impugned proviso to Section
				<lb />
				174(2)(c) of the CGST Act and the
				<lb />
				impugned Notification No.21/2017-C.E.
				<lb />
				dated 18.07.2017 are liable to be struck
				<lb />
				down being violative of Article 14 of the
				<lb />
				Constitution of India and the vested rights
				<lb />
				of the Petitioner. It may be noted that
				<lb />
				this submission is without prejudice to
				<lb />
				Petitioner&apos;s
				<lb />
				contention
				<lb />
				that
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				exemptions promised to the Petitioner is
				<lb />
				a vested right.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				Incorporating the following clauses in place of
				<lb />
				existing clauses (c) to (e):
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				&quot;(c) strike down the proviso to Section
				<lb />
				174(2)(c) of the Central Goods and
				<lb />
				Services
				<lb />
				Tax
				<lb />
				Act,
				<lb />
				2017
				<lb />
				as
				<lb />
				unconstitutional being contrary to Article
				<lb />
				14 of the Constitution of India;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(d)
				<lb />
				strike down the Notification No.21/2017-
				<lb />
				C.E. dated 18.07.2017 issued by the
				<lb />
				Respondent No.1 as unconstitutional
				<lb />
				being contrary to Article 14 of the
				<lb />
				Constitution of India
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(e)
				<lb />
				Hold that proviso to Section 174(2)(c) of
				<lb />
				the Central Goods and Services Tax Act,
				<lb />
				2017; Notification No.21/2017-C.E. dated
				<lb />
				18.07.2017 and the Scheme of Budgetary
				<lb />
				support under Goods and Service Tax
				<lb />
				regime to the units located in the States
				<lb />
				of Jammu &amp; Kashmir, Uttarakhand,
				<lb />
				Himachal
				<lb />
				Pradesh
				<lb />
				and
				<lb />
				North-East
				<lb />
				including Sikkim to Article 14 and the
				<lb />
				vested rights of the Petitioner;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(f)
				<lb />
				Issue any other writ, order or direction as
				<lb />
				this Hon&apos;ble Court may deem just and fair
				<lb />
				and circumstances of the case;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(g)
				<lb />
				For such further and other reliefs as the
				<lb />
				nature and circumstances of the case may
				<lb />
				require.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			3.
			<lb />
			Learned Counsel for the Petitioner submits that the
			<lb />
			proposed amendments are necessary for an effective adjudication of
			<lb />
			the main Writ Petition and will under no circumstance cause any
			<lb />
			harm, loss or prejudice to the Respondents. The proposed
			<lb />
			amendments do not change the nature and character of the Writ
			<lb />
			Petition and are being sought bona fide in the interest of justice. The
			<lb />
			proposed amendments hence be considered and allowed.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			4.
			<lb />
			Per contra, the Learned Counsel for the Respondents
			<lb />
			No.1 and 2 filed his reply to the I.A. and in the averments thereof
			<lb />
			objected to the proposed amendments. Learned Counsel contended
			<lb />
			that post the Judgment of the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court in Civil Appeal
			<lb />
			Nos.2256-2263 of 2020 arising out of S.L.P.(C) Nos.28194-
			<lb />
			28201/2010 dated 22-04-2020 in the matter of the Union of India &amp;
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot;14.3 As observed hereinabove, the subsequent
				<lb />
				notifications/industrial policies do not take away any
				<lb />
				vested right conferred under the earlier notifications/
				<lb />
				industrial policies. Under the subsequent notifications/
				<lb />
				industrial policies, the persons who establish the new
				<lb />
				undertakings shall be continue to get the refund of the
				<lb />
				excise duty. However, it is clarified by the subsequent
				<lb />
				notifications that the refund of the excise duty shall be
				<lb />
				on the actual excise duty paid on actual value addition
				<lb />
				made
				<lb />
				by
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				manufacturers
				<lb />
				undertaking
				<lb />
				manufacturing activities. Therefore, it cannot be said
				<lb />
				that subsequent notifications/industrial policies are hit
				<lb />
				by the doctrine of promissory estoppel. The respective
				<lb />
				High Courts have committed grave error in holding that
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				subsequent
				<lb />
				notifications/industrial
				<lb />
				policies
				<lb />
				impugned before the respective High Courts were hit
				<lb />
				by the doctrine of promissory estoppel. As observed
				<lb />
				and held hereinabove, the subsequent notifications/
				<lb />
				industrial policies which were impugned before the
				<lb />
				respective High Court can be said to be clarificatory in
				<lb />
				nature and the same have been issued in the larger
				<lb />
				public interest and in the interest of the Revenue, the
				<lb />
				same can be made applicable retrospectively,
				<lb />
				otherwise the object and purpose and the intention of
				<lb />
				the Government to provide excise duty exemption only
				<lb />
				in respect of genuine manufacturing activities carried
				<lb />
				out in the concerned areas shall be frustrated. ………&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			5.
			<lb />
			That, the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court has thereby rejected
			<lb />
			the original Petition of the Petitioner wherein they had sought
			<lb />
			benefits on the ground of promissory estoppel and hence this
			<lb />
			Petition deserves no consideration. It was further contended that
			<lb />
			the I.A. has been brought at a belated stage when the original Writ
			<lb />
			Petition has been heard in its entirety and the Judgment in the
			<lb />
			matter was reserved, indicating the mala fides of the Petitioner. It
			<lb />
			was next pointed out that with the Goods and Services Tax being
			<lb />
			rolled out a new Scheme has been offered as a measure of goodwill,
			<lb />
			only to the units which were eligible for drawing benefits under the
			<lb />
			earlier excise duty exemption/refund scheme, but has no relation to
			<lb />
			the erstwhile schemes, thus the Petitioner has been compensated
			<lb />
			for the benefits that they were drawing in the earlier excise regime.
			<lb />
			That, instead of the 56% that was fixed earlier, the amount to be
			<lb />
			refunded is fixed at 58% giving the Petitioner the benefit of an
			<lb />
			additional 2%.
			<lb />
			Denying the statements of the Petitioner in
			<lb />
			Paragraphs 2 to 5 of the I.A. in totality it was contended that the
			<lb />
			proposed amendments change the entire nature and character of
			<lb />
			the suit besides the fact that nothing remains for adjudication in the
			<lb />
			Writ Petition in view of the above cited ratiocination of the Hon&apos;ble
			<lb />
			Supreme Court and the proposed amendments merit no
			<lb />
			consideration and the petition ought to be dismissed.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			6.
			<lb />
			We have heard Learned Counsel for the parties at
			<lb />
			length. We have also perused the Writ Petition and the amendments
			<lb />
			proposed as detailed in the I.A.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			7.
			<lb />
			The prayers in the Writ Petition inter alia read as follows;
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot;(a) Issue an appropriate Writ reading down Clause 5.1 &amp;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				5.2 of the Notification F.No.10(1)/2017-DBA-II/NER,
				<lb />
				notifying &apos;Scheme of Budgetary support under Goods
				<lb />
				and Service Tax regime to the units located in the
				<lb />
				States of Jammu &amp; Kashmir, Uttarakhand, Himachal
				<lb />
				Pradesh and North-East including Sikkim&apos; so as to
				<lb />
				enable the Petitioner to claim full refund of the CGST
				<lb />
				and 50% of IGST paid through the electronic cash
				<lb />
				ledger;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(b)
				<lb />
				Or, in the alternative, issue a writ of mandamus or any
				<lb />
				other writ/order/direction, to the Respondents No.1 to
				<lb />
				3, directing them to fix a special rate of refund eligible
				<lb />
				to the Petitioner so that under the Budgetary Support
				<lb />
				Scheme, the Petitioner is entitled to refund equivalent
				<lb />
				to that under the erstwhile regime;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(c)
				<lb />
				Hold that the Scheme of Budgetary support under
				<lb />
				Goods and Service Tax regime to the units located in
				<lb />
				the States of Jammu &amp; Kashmir, Uttarakhand,
				<lb />
				Himachal Pradesh and North-East including Sikkim is
				<lb />
				contrary to Article 14 and the vested rights of the
				<lb />
				Petitioner;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(d)
				<lb />
				Issue any other writ, order or direction as this Hon&apos;ble
				<lb />
				Court may deem just and fair and circumstances of the
				<lb />
				case;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(e)
				<lb />
				For such further and other reliefs as the nature and
				<lb />
				circumstances of the case may require.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			8.
			<lb />
			The prayers, therefore, are confined to granting the
			<lb />
			Petitioner refund of the Central Goods and Services Tax and 50% of
			<lb />
			the Integrated Goods and Services Tax paid through the electronic
			<lb />
			cash ledger. An alternative prayer ensues directing the Respondents
			<lb />
			to fix a special rate of refund eligible to the Petitioner to entitle them
			<lb />
			to refund equivalent to that available under the erstwhile regime
			<lb />
			which should also be granted under the budgetary support scheme.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			9.
			<lb />
			Order VI Rule 17 of the CPC clothes the Court with
			<lb />
			powers to allow either party to alter or amend their pleadings at any
			<lb />
			stage of the proceedings on such terms as may be just. It also
			<lb />
			requires that all such amendments shall be made as may be
			<lb />
			necessary for the purpose of determining the real question in
			<lb />
			controversy between the parties provided that no application for
			<lb />
			amendment should be allowed after the trial has commenced unless
			<lb />
			the Court comes to the conclusion that in spite of due diligence the
			<lb />
			party could not have raised the matter before the commencement
			<lb />
			of trial. Thus, the provisions in the first part is discretionary and in
			<lb />
			the second part is imperative inasmuch as amendments that are
			<lb />
			necessary for the purpose of determining the real question in
			<lb />
			controversy between the parties ought to be allowed.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			10.
			<lb />
			In the matter at hand, the Writ Petition was finally heard
			<lb />
			on 03-09-2019 and Judgment reserved.
			<lb />
			In the interim, the
			<lb />
			Petitioner filed an application being I.A. No.02 of 2019, wherein it
			<lb />
			was averred that the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court took up the entire batch
			<lb />
			of appeals filed by the Respondent against the Judgments passed by
			<lb />
			the Hon&apos;ble High Court of Gujarat, Jammu and Kashmir, Guwahati
			<lb />
			and Sikkim on the issue of curtailment of central excise duty
			<lb />
			exemption, on 04-09-2019 in the Miscellaneous List. The appeal filed
			<lb />
			by the Respondent against the Judgment of this High Court dated
			<lb />
			M/s. Sun Pharma Laboratories Limited vs. Union of India and Others
			<lb />
			21-11-2017 was heard on 05-09-2019 and Judgment reserved.
			<lb />
			This fresh development was brought to the notice of this Court.
			<lb />
			Evidently the Judgment then came to be pronounced by the Hon&apos;ble
			<lb />
			Supreme Court on 22-04-2020 in M/s. V.V.F. Ltd. (supra), the
			<lb />
			relevant Paragraph being 14.3 has already been extracted and
			<lb />
			reflected in the arguments of Learned Counsel for the Respondents
			<lb />
			No.1 and 2 hereinabove.
			<lb />
			Subsequent thereto, the amendment
			<lb />
			application being I.A. No.03 of 2020 was filed on 06-06-2020,
			<lb />
			seeking to incorporate amendments already extracted supra.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			11.
			<lb />
			By the proposed amendments the Petitioner seeks to
			<lb />
			challenge the vires of Section 174(2)(c) of the Central Goods and
			<lb />
			Services Tax Act, 2017 and Notification No.21/2017-C.E., dated 18-
			<lb />
			07-2017, on the ground that it takes away the vested rights of the
			<lb />
			Petitioner by reducing the exemption/benefits to the Petitioner. The
			<lb />
			prayers in the Writ Petition are confined to enabling the Petitioner to
			<lb />
			claim full refund of the CGST and 50% of the IGST paid through the
			<lb />
			electronic cash ledger. It cannot be said that the Petitioner was
			<lb />
			unaware of the provision of the statute the vires of which they now
			<lb />
			seek to assail, nor was it inserted at some point later in time to the
			<lb />
			filing of the Writ Petition. The question of the Petitioner&apos;s inability
			<lb />
			to raise the matter in spite of due diligence, before the matter was
			<lb />
			heard or was taken up for hearing, therefore, does not arise. In view
			<lb />
			of the questions involved in the instant Writ Petition it cannot be said
			<lb />
			that the amendments are necessary for determining the real
			<lb />
			question in controversy between the parties considering the prayers
			<lb />
			of the Petitioner referred above. The proposed amendments if
			<lb />
			permitted would in fact change the very nature and character of the
			<lb />
			Writ Petition and introduce an entirely different Cause of action,
			<lb />
			which is not permissible.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			12.
			<lb />
			Consequently, we are not inclined to exercise our
			<lb />
			discretion in favour of the Petitioner, hence the Petition stands
			<lb />
			rejected and dismissed.
		</p>
	</text>
</tei>
