<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<p>
			1.
			<lb />
			Learned Additional Advocate General for State-
			<lb />
			Respondents No.1 and 2 on advance Notice.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			2.
			<lb />
			Heard Learned Counsel for the Petitioner at length.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			3.(i)
			<lb />
			Briefly, the case of the Petitioner is that vide
			<lb />
			Agreement dated 04.05.2017, the Petitioner was awarded the
			<lb />
			Contract for the purpose of supply and maintenance of POS
			<lb />
			Devices, POS application, its installation, maintenance,
			<lb />
			integration with the TPDS Software and Automation of Fair Price
			<lb />
			Shops of the 1421 Fair Price Shops in Sikkim.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(ii)
			<lb />
			As per Clause 2 of the said Agreement, the
			<lb />
			Petitioner was to adhere to the Request for Proposal (RFP)
			<lb />
			Guidelines and the Service Level Agreement also formed a part
			<lb />
			of the Agreement.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(iii)
			<lb />
			Clauses 2 and 8 of the Agreement were to be read
			<lb />
			together to determine the rights and liabilities of the parties.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(iv)
			<lb />
			Clause 7.9 of the RFP contained the Arbitration
			<lb />
			Agreement as defined under Section 7 of the Arbitration and
			<lb />
			Conciliation Act, 1996. The relevant portion of Clause of 7.9 of
			<lb />
			the RFP inter alia reads as under;
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot;7.9. Resolution of Disputes.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				FCS&amp;CA Department and the successful bidders
				<lb />
				shall make every effort to resolve amicably by direct
				<lb />
				informal negotiation, any disagreement or dispute,
				<lb />
				arising between them under or in connection with the
				<lb />
				contract.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				Any dispute or difference whatsoever arising
				<lb />
				between the parties to this Contract out of or relating
				<lb />
				to the meaning, scope, operation or effect of this
				<lb />
				Contract or the validity of the breach thereof, which
				<lb />
				cannot be resolved, shall be referred to a sole
				<lb />
				Arbitrator to be appointed by mutual consent of both
				<lb />
				the parties herein. If the parties cannot agree on the
				<lb />
				appointment of the Arbitrator within a period of one
				<lb />
				month from the notification by one party to the other
				<lb />
				of existene of such dispute, then the Arbitrator shall
				<lb />
				be nominated by the Secretary, Law Department,
				<lb />
				Government of Sikkim (&quot;Law secretary&quot;). The
				<lb />
				provisions of the Arbitration and Conciliation Act, 1996
				<lb />
				will be applicable and the award made thereunder
				<lb />
				shall be final and binding upon the parties hereto,
				<lb />
				subject to legal remedies available under the law.
				<lb />
				Such differences shall be deemed to be a submission
				<lb />
				to arbitration under the Indian Arbitration and
				<lb />
				Conciliation Act, 1996, or of any modifications, rules
				<lb />
				or re-enactments thereof. The arbitration proceedings
				<lb />
				will be held at Gangtok, Sikkim, India.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			(v)
			<lb />
			The work was to be taken up by the Petitioner in a
			<lb />
			phased manner as per the terms and conditions specified in
			<lb />
			Order No.1804/FCS&amp;CA, dated 29.03.2017. The Petitioner
			<lb />
			commenced the works accordingly.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(vi)
			<lb />
			By a Letter, dated 25.05.2020 (Annexure-12),
			<lb />
			addressed to the State-Respondent No.2 by the Petitioner, the
			<lb />
			Petitioner raised a Bill of Rs.3,65,01,842.00 (Rupees three
			<lb />
			crores, sixty five lakhs, one thousand, eight hundred and forty
			<lb />
			two) only, and requested the State-Respondent No.2 to release
			<lb />
			the pending payment within seven days to enable them to run
			<lb />
			the project, besides informing them that the Petitioner may not
			<lb />
			be able to manage operations beyond 01.06.2020 unless the
			<lb />
			payments were made over to them for the Bills raised.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(vii)
			<lb />
			From the month of June, 2020, the Petitioner
			<lb />
			stopped all works granted to them vide the Contract mentioned
			<lb />
			supra.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(viii)
			<lb />
			That, the State-Respondent No.2 issued Show
			<lb />
			Cause (Annexure-10) bearing No.753/F&amp;CSD, dated 11.01.2021,
			<lb />
			reminding the Petitioner that the State-Respondent No.2 had
			<lb />
			released a sum of Rs.1,44,87,880.00 (Rupees one crore, forty
			<lb />
			four lakhs, eighty seven thousand, eight hundred and eighty)
			<lb />
			only, in March, 2017, in favour of the Petitioner as mobilization
			<lb />
			advance.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(ix)
			<lb />
			The Show Cause also stated that from the month
			<lb />
			of June, 2020, without informing the State-Respondents No.1
			<lb />
			and 2, the Petitioner stopped providing their services resulting in
			<lb />
			a complete halt in the Public Distribution System through EPOS
			<lb />
			Machine at Fair Price Shops. That, further the unilateral
			<lb />
			suspension of services is ultra vires the Service Level Agreement.
			<lb />
			That, the discontinuance of services by the Petitioner caused a
			<lb />
			set back to the State-Respondents No.1 and 2 for timely
			<lb />
			implementation of the One Nation One Ration Card Scheme,
			<lb />
			hence they were to explain as to why the Agreement entered on
			<lb />
			04.05.2017 should not be terminated.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(x)
			<lb />
			By a Letter also of the same date i.e. 11.01.2021
			<lb />
			(Annexure-11), the State-Respondent No.2 agreed to release
			<lb />
			payments which were due to the Petitioner in a phased manner.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(xi)
			<lb />
			It is the Petitioner&quot;s case that on 16.01.2021, the
			<lb />
			response to the Show Cause was given by them.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(xii)
			<lb />
			Despite the response to the Show Cause, the
			<lb />
			services of the Petitioner were terminated vide Letter bearing
			<lb />
			No.801/F&amp;CSD/2021, dated 22.01.2021.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(xiii)
			<lb />
			Having thus terminated the services of the
			<lb />
			Petitioner, the Respondent No.2 on 02.02.2021, issued &quot;Notice
			<lb />
			Inviting E-Tender&quot; from eligible Bidders for the same works that
			<lb />
			had earlier been awarded to the Petitioner i.e. Automation of Fair
			<lb />
			Price Shops in Sikkim.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(xiv)
			<lb />
			Pursuant to the E-Tender, the Respondent No.3
			<lb />
			was awarded the Contract and Work Order issued on
			<lb />
			09.03.2021.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(xv)
			<lb />
			On 24.04.2021, the Petitioner was before the
			<lb />
			Learned Commercial Court, East Sikkim at Gangtok, seeking
			<lb />
			reliefs under Section 9 of the Arbitration and Conciliation Act,
			<lb />
			1996, the prayers being;
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot;i. Kindly issue an ad interim ex-parte injunction order
				<lb />
				to restrain the Respondent from accepting any bid in
				<lb />
				relation to the Notice Inviting E-Tender dated
				<lb />
				02.02.2021.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				ii. Kindly issue an order of injunction to restrain the
				<lb />
				Respondent from accepting any bid in relation to the
				<lb />
				Notice Inviting E-Tender dated 02.02.2021 until the
				<lb />
				conclusion of the determination of the controversy
				<lb />
				between the parties by an Arbitrator.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				iii. Kindly pass an order quashing the Show Cause
				<lb />
				Notice bearing No.753/F&amp;CSD dated 11.01.2021.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				iv. Kindly pass an order quashing Notice of
				<lb />
				Termination of Service issued by the Secretary, Food
				<lb />
				and
				<lb />
				Civil
				<lb />
				Supplies
				<lb />
				Department
				<lb />
				bearing
				<lb />
				No.801/F&amp;CSD/2021 dated 22.01.2021.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				v. Any other order/orders that this Hon&apos;ble Court
				<lb />
				deems fit to pass in the interests of justice.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			The reliefs so claimed supra are similar to the prayers made
			<lb />
			before this Court.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(xvi)
			<lb />
			Vide an ex-parte ad interim Order, dated
			<lb />
			27.04.2021, the Learned Commercial Court restrained the State-
			<lb />
			Respondent No.2 herein, the Secretary, Food and Civil Supplies
			<lb />
			Department, who was the Respondent therein, from accepting
			<lb />
			any Bid in connection with the E-Tender floated by them on
			<lb />
			02.02.2021.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(xvii)
			<lb />
			Later, after hearing both parties, by a subsequent
			<lb />
			Order, dated 27.05.2021, the Learned Commercial Court vacated
			<lb />
			its earlier ex-parte ad interim Order, dated 27.04.2021.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(xviii)
			<lb />
			Learned Counsel for the Petitioner submits that
			<lb />
			subsequent to the Order dated 27.05.2021, the Petitioner
			<lb />
			invoked the Arbitration Clause of the Agreement, dated
			<lb />
			04.05.2017 and sought for appointment of an Arbitrator. The
			<lb />
			suggested Arbitrator was not agreeable to the State-Respondent
			<lb />
			No.2 and hence further steps in this context are being taken and
			<lb />
			the process is underway.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			4.(i)
			<lb />
			Having heard and considered the facts placed
			<lb />
			before this Court, admittedly the Petitioner did not impugn the
			<lb />
			Letter dated 22.01.2021 terminating the Contract. It is also
			<lb />
			admitted that the Petitioner, of their own accord, stopped the
			<lb />
			works awarded to them vide the Agreement dated 04.05.2017
			<lb />
			from the month of June, 2020. Pursuant to the Petitioner having
			<lb />
			stopped the works, the Show Cause Notice, dated 11.01.2021,
			<lb />
			was issued following which the Contract between the Petitioner
			<lb />
			and the State-Respondent No.2 stood terminated on 22.01.2021.
			<lb />
			Learned Counsel for the Petitioner canvassed the contention that
			<lb />
			the E-Tender, dated 02.02.2021, was not assailed as the
			<lb />
			Petitioner had already written a Letter dated 30.01.2021, to the
			<lb />
			State-Respondent No.2 expressing their willingness to restart the
			<lb />
			project by mobilizing funds from other projects and internal fund
			<lb />
			adjustments but sought an assurance from the State-Respondent
			<lb />
			No.2 that pending payments would be cleared.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(ii)
			<lb />
			In the interim, the Contract came to the awarded
			<lb />
			to a third party.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(iii)
			<lb />
			The Petitioner approached the Learned Commercial
			<lb />
			Court on 24.04.2021 and is before this Court by way of filing the
			<lb />
			instant Writ Petition on 31.05.2021 with prayers which are, in
			<lb />
			sum and substance, similar in both Courts.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			5.
			<lb />
			It may relevantly be stated here that this Court is
			<lb />
			aware that the existence of an Arbitration Clause would not
			<lb />
			divest the High Court of its jurisdiction under Article 226 of the
			<lb />
			Constitution, neither is the exercise of Writ jurisdiction under
			<lb />
			Article 226 in a contractual matter ruled out. However, this
			<lb />
			jurisdiction is invoked when there is no efficacious alternative
			<lb />
			remedy for the Petitioner.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			6.
			<lb />
			The Hon&quot;ble Supreme Court, recently in Bhaven
			<lb />
			Construction through Authorised Signatory Premjibhai K. Shah vs.
			<lb />
			Executive Engineer Sardar Sarovar Narmada Nigam Ltd. and Another 1
			<lb />
			referred to the ratio in Nivedita Sharma v. Cellular Operators
			<lb />
			Association of India 2 and inter alia observed as follows;
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot;17. In any case, the hierarchy in our legal
				<lb />
				framework, mandates that a legislative enactment
				<lb />
				cannot curtail a Constitutional right. In Nivedita
				<lb />
				Sharma v. Cellular Operators Association of India,
				<lb />
				(2011) 14 SCC 337, this Court referred to several
				<lb />
				judgments and held:
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				&quot;11.
				<lb />
				We
				<lb />
				have
				<lb />
				considered
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				respective
				<lb />
				arguments/submissions. There cannot be any dispute
				<lb />
				that the power of the High Courts to issue directions,
				<lb />
				orders or writs including writs in the nature of habeas
				<lb />
				corpus, certiorari, mandamus, quo warranto and
				<lb />
				prohibition under Article 226 of the Constitution is a
				<lb />
				basic feature of the Constitution and cannot be
				<lb />
				curtailed by parliamentary legislation -L. Chandra
				<lb />
				Kumar v. Union of India, (1997) 3 SCC 261.
				<lb />
				However, it is one thing to say that in exercise of
				<lb />
				the power vested in it under Article 226 of the
				<lb />
				Constitution, the High Court can entertain a writ
				<lb />
				petition against any order passed by or action
				<lb />
				taken
				<lb />
				by
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				State
				<lb />
				and/or
				<lb />
				its
				<lb />
				agency/instrumentality or any public authority
				<lb />
				or
				<lb />
				order
				<lb />
				passed
				<lb />
				by
				<lb />
				a
				<lb />
				quasi-judicial
				<lb />
				body/authority, and it is an altogether different
				<lb />
				thing to say that each and every petition filed
				<lb />
				under Article 226 of the Constitution must be
				<lb />
				entertained by the High Court as a matter of
				<lb />
				course ignoring the fact that the aggrieved
				<lb />
				person has an effective alternative remedy.
				<lb />
				Rather, it is settled law that when a statutory forum is
				<lb />
				created by law for redressal of grievances, a writ
				<lb />
				petition should not be entertained ignoring the
				<lb />
				statutory dispensation.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(emphasis supplied)
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				18. It is therefore, prudent for a Judge to not
				<lb />
				exercise discretion to allow judicial interference
				<lb />
				beyond the procedure established under the
				<lb />
				enactment. This power needs to be exercised in
				<lb />
				exceptional rarity, wherein one party is left remediless
				<lb />
				under the statute or a clear &quot;bad faith&quot; shown by one
				<lb />
				of the parties. This high standard set by this Court is
				<lb />
				in terms of the legislative intention to make the
				<lb />
				arbitration fair and efficient.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			7.
			<lb />
			In light of the detailed discussions that have
			<lb />
			emanated supra, and in view of the obtaining facts and
			<lb />
			circumstances in the instant matter as reflected hereinabove, I
			<lb />
			am of the considered opinion that the Petitioner has failed to put
			<lb />
			forth any exceptional circumstances for invoking the Writ
			<lb />
			jurisdiction of this Court under Article 226 of the Constitution.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			8.
			<lb />
			The Writ Petition is accordingly dismissed and
			<lb />
			disposed of.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			9.
			<lb />
			Applications filed along with the Writ Petition, if
			<lb />
			any, also stand disposed of.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			Judge
		</p>
	</text>
</tei>
