<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<p>
			1.
			<lb />
			Heard Mr. Hissey Gyaltsen, learned Assistant Government
			<lb />
			Advocate.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			2.
			<lb />
			The State of Sikkim has preferred this writ petition under
			<lb />
			Article 226 of the Constitution of India seeking a writ for setting aside
			<lb />
			the show cause notice dated 13.01.2021 and orders dated 9.6.2021
			<lb />
			and 14.9.2021, passed by the National Human Rights Commission
			<lb />
			(NHRC) in NHRC Case No. 1/21/3/2020-jcd relating to the suicide of
			<lb />
			an under trial prisoner (UTP) Roshan Chettri in District Jail, Namchi,
			<lb />
			as being arbitrary and illegal.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			3.
			<lb />
			On 13.01.2021, the NHRC issued a show cause notice to
			<lb />
			the Chief Secretary of the petitioner stating, inter alia, that the
			<lb />
			Commission had received intimation on 06.05.2020 from the Jailor,
			<lb />
			District Jail, Namchi, Sikkim, regarding suicide by the UTP Roshan
			<lb />
			Chettri (aged about 27 years), son of Shri Dilip Chettri in the prison on
			<lb />
			04.04.2020. The show cause notice also records that the Investigation
			<lb />
			Division of NHRC after collecting/analyzing relevant reports/records
			<lb />
			has submitted that the deceased UTP was a covid-19 positive patient
			<lb />
			and was in quarantine along with another UTP. On 04.04.2020, at 11
			<lb />
			a.m., the deceased made an attempt to commit suicide by hanging
			<lb />
			on the door of his cell with the help of cloth of the blanket
			<lb />
			provided to him but that act was noticed by his cell mate who
			<lb />
			caught hold his body and called out for help. Subsequently, jail
			<lb />
			authorities arrived and brought him down by cutting the blanket
			<lb />
			cloth. He was immediately shifted to hospital wherein he died
			<lb />
			during the treatment. The inquest and the Post Mortem
			<lb />
			Examination (PME) revealed no injury on the body of the
			<lb />
			deceased other than ligature marks, the cause of death was
			<lb />
			asphyxia due to hanging. The Magisterial Enquiry Report (MER)
			<lb />
			conducted by the learned Judicial Magistrate, South Sikkim,
			<lb />
			Namchi, concluded that no medical negligence and foul play was
			<lb />
			found in the death of the deceased and that he committed
			<lb />
			suicide by hanging.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			4.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			The show cause notice further recorded that vide
			<lb />
			direction dated 11.12.2020, the Commission after considering
			<lb />
			the relevant reports had considered and directed as under:-
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot;Prima facie, the deceased committed suicide in
				<lb />
				day time i.e. at 11:10 AM. Ensuring the safety and
				<lb />
				security of inmates who are under care and
				<lb />
				custody of the prison is one of the prime duties of
				<lb />
				the authorities concerned in which it failed. Had the
				<lb />
				prison authorities been vigilant enough, this
				<lb />
				incident could have been avoided and the precious
				<lb />
				life would have been saved. Hence, the State is
				<lb />
				vicariously liable to compensate the next of kin of
				<lb />
				the deceased under trial prisoner.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			5.
			<lb />
			The show cause notice thereafter required the
			<lb />
			petitioner to show cause as to why monetary compensation of
			<lb />
			Rs.3,75,000/-should not be recommended under section 18(a)(i)
			<lb />
			of the Protection of Human Rights Act, 1993, to be paid to the
			<lb />
			next of kin of the deceased Roshan Chettri.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			6.
			<lb />
			On 05.03.2021, the petitioner responded to the show
			<lb />
			cause notice stating that no case of negligence on the part of jail
			<lb />
			administration was found during the judicial enquiry by the
			<lb />
			learned Judicial Magistrate, South Sikkim at Namchi. The
			<lb />
			petitioner also forwarded the following documents to the NHRC:-
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot;(i)
				<lb />
				The detailed report of DIGP, State Central
				<lb />
				Prison, Rongyek received vide letter dated
				<lb />
				No.
				<lb />
				463/GOS/PRISON/2021
				<lb />
				dated
				<lb />
				25/02/2021;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(ii)
				<lb />
				Letter to the Ld. CJM, South District by the
				<lb />
				Jailer,
				<lb />
				Sub
				<lb />
				Jail,
				<lb />
				Namchi
				<lb />
				regarding
				<lb />
				commission of suicide by UTP Roshan
				<lb />
				Chhetri;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(iii)
				<lb />
				final enquiry report of Ld. JM, Namchi u/s
				<lb />
				176 of Cr.PC. 1973;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(iv)
				<lb />
				Warrant of Commitment to Judicial Custody;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(v)
				<lb />
				Report submitted to the Sikkim Human
				<lb />
				Rights Commission;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(vi)
				<lb />
				First Information Report;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(vii)
				<lb />
				Inquest Form u/s 174 of Cr.PC of Namchi
				<lb />
				Police Station;
				<lb />
				(viii) Inquest Report u/s 176 of Cr.PC of Judicial
				<lb />
				Magistrate, Namchi;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(ix)
				<lb />
				Post Mortem Report of the deceased Roshan
				<lb />
				Chettri;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(x)
				<lb />
				Statement of witnesses taken by the Police;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(xi)
				<lb />
				Final Report of a reported case of unnatural
				<lb />
				dead (sic &quot;death&quot;) u/s 174 of Cr.PC. 1973.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			7.
			<lb />
			In the meanwhile, Dilip Chettri, father of the deceased
			<lb />
			Roshan Chettri, filed a Writ Petition (Civil) No. 02 of 2021 (Dilip
			<lb />
			Chettri vs. State of Sikkim &amp; Others) under Article 226 of the
			<lb />
			Constitution of India. The writ petition prayed for a direction
			<lb />
			upon the state respondents to pay compensation to the tune of
			<lb />
			Rs.20,00,000/-as well as for an independent investigation of the
			<lb />
			incident of the alleged suicide by a retired judge or a government
			<lb />
			officer or any other person as deemed fit. The writ petition was
			<lb />
			taken up on 12.03.2021 by the learned Single Bench of this
			<lb />
			court and the following order was passed:-
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot;After hearing Learned Counsel for the Petitioner
				<lb />
				and duly considering the matter, this Writ Petition
				<lb />
				deserves to be and is dismissed in limine.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			8.
			<lb />
			Thereafter, the NHRC vide communication dated
			<lb />
			09.06.2021 addressed to the Chief Secretary of the petitioner,
			<lb />
			informed that the Commission on 09.06.2021 had directed as
			<lb />
			follows:-
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot;……………….. In the instant case, the Commission
				<lb />
				had received an intimation on 06.05.2020 from
				<lb />
				Jailor Dist. Jail Namchi, Sikkim regarding suicide
				<lb />
				by under trial prisoner Roshan Chhetari (aged
				<lb />
				about 27 year), S/o Dilip Chhetrari in the prison on
				<lb />
				04.04.2020.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				Vide proceeding dated 24.04.2021, the Commission
				<lb />
				observed and directed as under-
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				&quot;Pursuant to the directions of the Commission,
				<lb />
				letter dated 05.03.2021 has been submitted by the
				<lb />
				Joint Director (Confdl.), Home Department, Govt. of
				<lb />
				Sikkim who has submitted the detailed report,
				<lb />
				Letter to Ld. CJM, South District, final enquiry
				<lb />
				report, warrant of commitment to judicial custody,
				<lb />
				report submitted to Sikkim Human Rights
				<lb />
				Commission, First Information Report, Inquest form
				<lb />
				and report, post mortem report of the deceased,
				<lb />
				statement of witnesses, final report of a reported
				<lb />
				case of unnatural death U/sec. 174 Cr.P.C. As per
				<lb />
				the attached detailed report of the DIGP, State
				<lb />
				Central Prison dated 25.02.2021, the authority has
				<lb />
				relied upon the judicial enquiry and the final report
				<lb />
				filed by the P.S. Namchi, which does not establish
				<lb />
				any negligence on the part of the jail
				<lb />
				administration, district prison, Namchi.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				The Commission has taken note of the contents of
				<lb />
				the reports/reply to the show cause notice
				<lb />
				submitted by the authorities and has also
				<lb />
				considered the facts and circumstances of the case.
				<lb />
				Admittedly the prisoner was in the care and
				<lb />
				custody of the State and it was the bounden duty
				<lb />
				of the State to ensure his safety. It is also an
				<lb />
				admitted fact that he had committed suicide in day
				<lb />
				time i.e. at 11:10 AM so had the prison authorities
				<lb />
				been vigilant enough, this incident could have been
				<lb />
				avoided and a precious life would have been
				<lb />
				saved. Hence, the Commission is not inclined to
				<lb />
				review its order of payment of monetary
				<lb />
				compensation of Rs.3,75,000/-(Rs. Three Lakhs
				<lb />
				Seventy Five Thousand only) to the NoK of the
				<lb />
				aforesaid deceased UTP and hence confirms its
				<lb />
				recommendation.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				The Chief Secretary, Govt. of Sikkim is directed to
				<lb />
				submit the proof of payment of monetary
				<lb />
				compensation of Rs.3,75,000/-(Rupees Three
				<lb />
				Lakhs Seventy-Five Thousand only) to the NoK of
				<lb />
				the deceased UTP within six weeks failing which
				<lb />
				the Commission will be constrained to invoke its
				<lb />
				coercive power u/s 13 of the PHR Act, 1993 calling
				<lb />
				for the personal appearance of the authority
				<lb />
				concerned before the Commission.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				The Commission observes that the requisite reports
				<lb />
				from aforesaid authority is still awaited.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				In normal circumstances, such non responsive
				<lb />
				attitude towards direction of the Commission would
				<lb />
				have invited issuance of summons u/s 13 of the
				<lb />
				PHR Act, 1993 calling for his personal appearance
				<lb />
				before the Commission, but in view of the pandemic
				<lb />
				situation in the country, last opportunity is being
				<lb />
				given to the Chief Secretary, Govt. of Sikkim for
				<lb />
				submission of requisite compliance report along
				<lb />
				with proof of payment within four weeks failing
				<lb />
				which the Commission would be constrained to
				<lb />
				invoke its coercive power u/s 13 of the PHR Act,
				<lb />
				1993 calling for the personal appearance of the
				<lb />
				authority
				<lb />
				concerned
				<lb />
				before
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				Commission.………………………..&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			9.
			<lb />
			On 16.07.2021, the petitioner wrote to the NHRC
			<lb />
			informing them, inter alia, that a Writ Petition (Civil) No. 02 of
			<lb />
			2021 (supra) was filed by the father of the deceased before this
			<lb />
			court on 09.03.2021 praying for compensation which came up
			<lb />
			for hearing on 12.03.2021 and this court after hearing the
			<lb />
			learned counsel for the petitioner dismissed it in limine &quot;on merit
			<lb />
			of the case and duly considering the matter&quot;. The petitioner thus
			<lb />
			urged the NHRC that the petitioner may be exempted from
			<lb />
			payment of compensation as the proceeding before the NHRC
			<lb />
			was barred by the principle of res judicata.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			10.
			<lb />
			On
			<lb />
			14.09.2021,
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			NHRC
			<lb />
			made
			<lb />
			another
			<lb />
			communication to the Chief Secretary of the petitioner stating
			<lb />
			that on that day the Commission directed as follows:-
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot;The present matter pertains to intimation
				<lb />
				regarding death of UTP Roshan of District Jail
				<lb />
				Namchi, Sikkim.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				In continuation of earlier proceedings vide
				<lb />
				proceedings dated 26.07.2021 this Commission
				<lb />
				has observed/directed as under:-
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				&quot;In the instant case, the Commission had received
				<lb />
				an intimation on 06.05.2020 from Jailor Dist. Jail
				<lb />
				Namchi, Sikkim regarding suicide by under trial
				<lb />
				prisoner Roshan Chhetari (aged about 27 year),
				<lb />
				S/o Sh. Dilip Chhetari in the prison on 04.04.2020.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				The Commission observes that the matter is
				<lb />
				pending for want of compliance report along with
				<lb />
				proof of payment of monetary compensation of
				<lb />
				Rs.3,75,000/-(Rupees Three Lakhs Seventy-Five
				<lb />
				Thousand only) to be paid to the NOK of the
				<lb />
				deceased UTP Roshan Chhetari (aged about 27
				<lb />
				year), S/o Sh. Dilip Chhetari who committed suicide
				<lb />
				in the prison on 04.04.2020.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				Registry is directed to issue final reminder to the
				<lb />
				Chief Secretary, Govt. of Sikkim for submission of
				<lb />
				compliance report along with the proof of payment
				<lb />
				within four weeks failing which the Commission
				<lb />
				shall be constrained to invoke its coercive power
				<lb />
				u/s 13 of the PHR Act, 1993 calling for the personal
				<lb />
				appearance of the authority concerned before the
				<lb />
				Commission.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				Thus this Commission has sought the compliance
				<lb />
				report regarding the payment of monetary
				<lb />
				compensation of Rs.3,75,000/-to the NOK of
				<lb />
				deceased UTP. Pursuant to same a report dated
				<lb />
				16.07.2021 is received from Joint Director (Home
				<lb />
				Department), Sikkim vide which he has submitted
				<lb />
				that since the writ petition of the victim&quot;s father has
				<lb />
				already been dismissed by Hon&quot;ble Sikkim High
				<lb />
				Court, the Commission shall review its order and
				<lb />
				State Govt. be exempted from the payment of
				<lb />
				compensation as directed by the NHRC. It is
				<lb />
				pertinent to observe here that vide proceedings
				<lb />
				dated
				<lb />
				09.06.2021
				<lb />
				this
				<lb />
				Commission
				<lb />
				has
				<lb />
				categorically declined the request of review of
				<lb />
				concerned State Government. This Commission has
				<lb />
				observed that:-
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				&quot;The Commission has taken note of the contents of
				<lb />
				the reports/reply to the sow cause notice submitted
				<lb />
				by the authorities and has also considered the
				<lb />
				facts and circumstances of the case. Admittedly,
				<lb />
				the prisoner was in the care and custody of the
				<lb />
				State and it was the bounden duty of the State to
				<lb />
				ensure his safety. It is also an admitted fact that he
				<lb />
				had committed suicide in day time i.e. at 11.10 AM
				<lb />
				so had the prison authorities been vigilant enough,
				<lb />
				this incident could have been avoided and a
				<lb />
				precious life would have been saved. Hence, the
				<lb />
				Commission is not inclined to review its order of
				<lb />
				payment
				<lb />
				of
				<lb />
				monetary
				<lb />
				compensation
				<lb />
				of
				<lb />
				Rs.3,75,000/-(Rs. Three Lakhs Seventy Five
				<lb />
				Thousand only) to the NOK of the aforesaid
				<lb />
				deceased
				<lb />
				UTP
				<lb />
				and
				<lb />
				hence
				<lb />
				confirms
				<lb />
				its
				<lb />
				recommendation.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				Thus this plea of the concerned authority has
				<lb />
				already been declined. In view of same the Chief
				<lb />
				Secretary, Govt. of Sikkim is recommended to pay
				<lb />
				the compensation to the NOK of deceased of
				<lb />
				Rs.3,75,000/-and submit a report in this regard
				<lb />
				within eight weeks.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			11.
			<lb />
			The NHRC vide the above communication requested
			<lb />
			that the additional/compete report as directed by the
			<lb />
			Commission in the matter be sent latest by 19.11.2021 for
			<lb />
			further consideration by the Commission.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			12.
			<lb />
			The petitioner aggrieved by the issuance of the show
			<lb />
			cause notice and the impugned orders dated 09.06.2021 and
			<lb />
			14.09.2021 has approached this court on eleven grounds.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			13.
			<lb />
			On perusal of the grounds and hearing the learned
			<lb />
			counsel, it is clear that the petitioner is primarily aggrieved on
			<lb />
			five counts. The petitioner is aggrieved that inspite of the
			<lb />
			dismissal of W.P.(C) No. 02 of 2021 (supra) by this court, the
			<lb />
			NHRC has passed the impugned orders which was barred by the
			<lb />
			principle of res judicata; that the show cause notice and the
			<lb />
			impugned orders did not disclose the commission of violation of
			<lb />
			human rights by the police authorities or the negligence of the
			<lb />
			police authorities in prevention of violation of human rights; that
			<lb />
			the NHRC could not have entertained the complaint under
			<lb />
			Regulation 9(xi) and 9(xii) of the National Human Rights
			<lb />
			Commission (Procedure) Regulations, 1994; and that the NHRC
			<lb />
			did not consider the final inquiry report dated 20.05.2021 of the
			<lb />
			learned Judicial Magistrate and the final report of the Namchi
			<lb />
			Police Station. It is further argued that merely because suicide
			<lb />
			took place during the day, it does not in any manner corroborate
			<lb />
			or substantiate that there was any negligence on the part of the
			<lb />
			police authorities. Each of these grounds shall be considered
			<lb />
			separately.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			14.
			<lb />
			The admitted facts are that show cause notice was
			<lb />
			issued on 13.1.2021; the father of the deceased UTP Roshan
			<lb />
			Chettri filed W.P.(C) No. 02 of 2021 (supra) on 09.03.2021 which
			<lb />
			was dismissed in limine on 12.03.2021. The impugned orders
			<lb />
			were thereafter passed by the NHRC.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			15.
			<lb />
			In Dario and others vs. State of Uttar Pradesh 1 , the
			<lb />
			Supreme Court held as under:-
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot;19. We must now proceed to state our conclusion
				<lb />
				on the preliminary objection raised by the
				<lb />
				respondents. We hold that if a writ petition filed by
				<lb />
				a party under Art. 226 is considered on the merits
				<lb />
				as a contested matter and is dismissed the
				<lb />
				decision thus pronounced would continue to bind
				<lb />
				the parties unless it is otherwise modified or
				<lb />
				reversed by appeal or other appropriate
				<lb />
				proceedings permissible under the Constitution. It
				<lb />
				would not be open to a party to ignore the said
				<lb />
				judgment and move this Court under Art. 32 by an
				<lb />
				original petition made on the same facts and for
				<lb />
				obtaining the same or similar orders or writs. If the
				<lb />
				petition filed in the High Court under Art. 226 is
				<lb />
				dismissed not on the merits but because of the
				<lb />
				laches of the party applying for the writ or because
				<lb />
				it is held that the party had an alternative remedy
				<lb />
				available to it, then the dismissal of the writ
				<lb />
				petition would not constitute a bar to a subsequent
				<lb />
				petition under Art. 32 except in cases where and if
				<lb />
				the facts thus found by the High Court may
				<lb />
				themselves be relevant even under Art. 32. If a writ
				<lb />
				petition is dismissed in limine and an order is
				<lb />
				pronounced in that behalf, whether or not the
				<lb />
				dismissal would constitute a bar would depend
				<lb />
				upon the nature of the order. If the order is on the
				<lb />
				merits it would be a bar; if the order shows that the
				<lb />
				dismissal was for the reason that the petitioner
				<lb />
				was guilty of laches or that he had an alternative
				<lb />
				remedy it would not be a bar, except in cases
				<lb />
				which we have already indicated. If the petition is
				<lb />
				dismissed in limine without passing a speaking
				<lb />
				order then such dismissal cannot be treated as
				<lb />
				creating a bar of res judicata. It is true that, prima
				<lb />
				facie, dismissal in limine even without passing a
				<lb />
				speaking order in that behalf may strongly suggest
				<lb />
				that the Court took the view that there was no
				<lb />
				substance in the petition at all; but in the absence
				<lb />
				of a speaking order it would not be easy to decide
				<lb />
				what factors weighed in the mind of the Court and
				<lb />
				that makes it difficult and unsafe to hold that such
				<lb />
				a summary dismissal is a dismissal on merits and
				<lb />
				as such constitutes a bar of res judicata against a
				<lb />
				similar petition filed under Art. 32. If the petition is
				<lb />
				dismissed as withdrawn it cannot be a bar to a
				<lb />
				subsequent petition under Art. 32, because in such
				<lb />
				a case there has been no decision on the merits by
				<lb />
				the Court. We wish to make it clear that the
				<lb />
				conclusions thus reached by us are confined only to
				<lb />
				the point of res judicata which has been argued as
				<lb />
				a preliminary issue in these writ petitions and no
				<lb />
				other. ..................................................................&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			16.
			<lb />
			Thus, it is clear that if the petition is dismissed in
			<lb />
			limine without passing a speaking order then such dismissal
			<lb />
			cannot be treated as creating a bar of res judicata and although,
			<lb />
			prima facie, dismissal in limine even without passing a speaking
			<lb />
			order in that behalf may strongly suggest that the court took the
			<lb />
			view that there was no substance in the petition at all, but in the
			<lb />
			absence of the speaking order it would not be easy to decide what
			<lb />
			factors weighed in the mind of the court and that makes it
			<lb />
			difficult and unsafe to hold that such a summary dismissal is a
			<lb />
			dismissal on merits and as such constitutes a bar of res judicata.
			<lb />
			the present case, this court is of the opinion that there is no
			<lb />
			such issue. The order passed by the learned Single Bench on
			<lb />
			12/03/2021 clearly records that it was dismissed, in fact, in
			<lb />
			limine. The pronouncement of the learned Single Bench was
			<lb />
			absolutely clear. It was a dismissal in limine. In view of the clear
			<lb />
			pronouncement of the Supreme Court, the dismissal of the writ
			<lb />
			petition in limine does not act as res judicata against the
			<lb />
			proceedings before the NHRC.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			17.
			<lb />
			The next point urged by the learned counsel is the show
			<lb />
			cause notice as well as the impugned orders not disclosing the
			<lb />
			commission of violation of human rights by the police authorities or
			<lb />
			the negligence of the police authorities in prevention of violation
			<lb />
			of human rights. It is quite evident that the Commission was of the
			<lb />
			firm view on both facts and law. The fact that the UTP committed
			<lb />
			suicide during the day at 11:10 a.m. in the jail is not disputed by the
			<lb />
			petitioner. The NHRC records that &quot;ensuring the safety and security of
			<lb />
			the inmates who are under care and custody of the prison is one of the
			<lb />
			prime duties of the authorities concerned&quot;. This cannot be disputed. It
			<lb />
			is quite obvious that had the jail authorities been vigilant enough, as
			<lb />
			observed by the NHRC, this incident could have been avoided and the
			<lb />
			precious life would have been saved. The State is vicariously liable to
			<lb />
			compensate the next of kin of the deceased UTP. It is not the case of
			<lb />
			the petitioner that the jail was not under its control when the incident
			<lb />
			happened in the manner described and admittedly inside the jail.
			<lb />
			There cannot be any doubt that the responsibility of ensuring the
			<lb />
			safety of the inmates during the day or in the night as long as they are
			<lb />
			in the prison is upon the said authorities. It may not have been at the
			<lb />
			instance of any of the jail officers that the suicide was committed but
			<lb />
			the fact that the incident has happened inside the jail makes the
			<lb />
			petitioner vicariously liable.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			18.
			<lb />
			The National Human Rights Commission (Procedure)
			<lb />
			Regulations, 1994 as amended, provides in Regulation 9 that in
			<lb />
			certain cases complaints are not ordinarily entertainable. It provides
			<lb />
			that the Commission may dismiss in limini complaints of various
			<lb />
			nature as enumerated below:-
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot;(i) illegible;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(ii) vague, anonymous or pseudonymous;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(iii) trivial or frivolous;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(iv) barred under section 36(1) of the Act;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(v) barred under section 36(2) of the Act;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(vi) allegation is not against any public servant;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(vii) the issue raised relates to civil dispute, such as
				<lb />
				property rights, contractual obligations and the like;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(viii) the issue raised relates to service matters;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(ix) the issue raised relates to labour/industrial
				<lb />
				disputes;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(x) allegations do not make out any specific
				<lb />
				violation of human rights;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(xi) matter is sub judice before a Court/Tribunal;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(xii) matter is covered by a judicial verdict/decision
				<lb />
				of the Commission;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(xiii) where it is only a copy of the complaint
				<lb />
				addressed to some other authority;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(xiv) the matter is outside the purview of the
				<lb />
				Commission on any other ground.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			19.
			<lb />
			Regulation 9(xi) relates to matter which are sub judice
			<lb />
			before the court or tribunal. The admitted facts as pleaded do not
			<lb />
			reflect that the NHRC entertained the complaint when the matter
			<lb />
			was sub judice before this court. Regulation 9(xii) relates to
			<lb />
			matter which is covered by the judicial verdict or decision of the
			<lb />
			Commission. The arguments made by the learned counsel for the
			<lb />
			petitioner relates to the dismissal of the writ petition in limine
			<lb />
			which has already been discussed in detail above. Therefore,
			<lb />
			even this ground does not help the petitioner&apos;s case.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			20.
			<lb />
			The final inquiry report passed by the learned
			<lb />
			Judicial Magistrate, South Sikkim, Namchi, relates to the
			<lb />
			procedure under section 176 of the Cr.P.C. and the final report of
			<lb />
			the Namchi Police Station relates to the procedure under section
			<lb />
			174 Cr.P.C. Both did not deal with the issue before the NHRC.
			<lb />
			Consequently, this ground is also devoid of merits.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			21.
			<lb />
			Having examined each of the grounds raised by the
			<lb />
			petitioner, this court is of the considered view that the present
			<lb />
			writ petition is misconceived and is liable to be dismissed.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			22.
			<lb />
			It is accordingly ordered.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			23.
			<lb />
			Pending interlocutory application also stands
			<lb />
			disposed of.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			( Bhaskar Raj Pradhan )
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			Judge
			<lb />
		</p>
	</text>
</tei>
