<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<p>
			This common order will govern the captioned main writ petition and
			<lb />
			captioned WMP thereat. A public Wakf, which goes by the name
			<lb />
			&apos;Sunnathval Jamath Pallivasal, Kanni Beevi Dharka and Mamana Radha
			<lb />
			Dharka&apos; [hereinafter &apos;said Wakf&apos; for the sake of convenience and clarity] is
			<lb />
			the nucleus of the captioned writ petition and removal of committee of
			<lb />
			administration qua said Wakf is the central theme of the captioned writ
			<lb />
			petition.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			2. Captioned writ petition was filed in 2017, to be precise on
			<lb />
			15.02.2017 and the prayer is to remove the fifth respondent from the
			<lb />
			management of said Wakf.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			2/7
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			3. The case of the writ petitioner is that he is a member of the Jamath
			<lb />
			with voting rights qua said Wakf but it is not necessary to delve into these
			<lb />
			aspects of the matter and it is not necessary to dilate further on these aspects
			<lb />
			of the case on hand as the trajectory the captioned writ petition has taken
			<lb />
			and the central theme in the captioned writ petition make it unnecessary.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			4. This court is informed without any disputation or disagreement that
			<lb />
			pending writ petition, Tamil Nadu Wakf Board held elections for the
			<lb />
			committee of administration qua said Wakf on 21.07.2019 and 9 individuals
			<lb />
			were elected.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			5. Mr. Nihar Ali, learned counsel representing the counsel on record
			<lb />
			for the writ petitioner, Mr. S.A. Ajmal Khan, learned Standing Counsel for
			<lb />
			Tamil Nadu Wakf Board on behalf of respondents 1 to 3 and Mr.
			<lb />
			Hemakarthikeyan, learned counsel on record for respondents 4 and 5 are
			<lb />
			before me.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			6. All the aforementioned counsel submit in one voice that there is no
			<lb />
			disputation or disagreement about elections having been held on 21.07.2019
			<lb />
			qua said wakf. All the counsel also submit that of the nine individuals
			<lb />
			elected to the committee of administration 5 th respondent did not get elected
			<lb />
			but the writ petitioner got elected. This court is also informed that the
			<lb />
			tenure of the elected committee of administration is three years i.e, from
			<lb />
			21.07.2019 to 20.07.2022 and the committee is now in office.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			7. Learned Standing counsel for Tamil Nadu Wakf Board has placed
			<lb />
			before me proceedings regarding the elected 9 Member Committee of
			<lb />
			administration being put in place and a scanned reproduction of the same is
			<lb />
			as follows:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			8. All the aforementioned counsel further submit without any
			<lb />
			disputation that the above draws the curtains on the captioned main writ
			<lb />
			petition. Captioned main writ petition is disposed of as closed. Though
			<lb />
			obvious it is made clear that I have not expressed any view or opinion on
			<lb />
			the merits of the matter. Consequently, captioned MP is also disposed of as
			<lb />
			closed. There shall be no order as to costs.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			06.12.2021
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			mnr
		</p>
		<p>
			M.SUNDAR, J.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			mnr
			<lb />
		</p>
	</text>
</tei>
