<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<p>
			1. Oriental Insurance Co. Ltd. (hereinafter „OICL‟) has filed the
			<lb />
			present petition under Section 34 of the Arbitration and Conciliation
			<lb />
			Act, 1966 (hereinafter the „A&amp;C Act‟), inter alia, impugning an
			<lb />
			Arbitral Award dated 28.08.2020 (hereafter the „impugned award‟)
			<lb />
			passed by the Arbitral Tribunal constituted of Justice (Retd.) Kurian
			<lb />
			Joseph, a former judge of the Supreme Court of India as the sole
			<lb />
			arbitrator. The impugned award was rendered in the context of
			<lb />
			disputes relating to the insurance claims made by the respondent
			<lb />
			(hereinafter &quot;AFPL&quot;) under the insurance policy issued by OICL.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			2.
			<lb />
			AFPL is a company engaged in the business of manufacture of
			<lb />
			footwear. AFPL had a valid &quot;Standard Fire and Special Perils Policy
			<lb />
			(bearing policy number 510000/11/2018/483 with period of insurance
			<lb />
			commencing from 00:00 on 25.10.2017 to the midnight of 24.10.2018
			<lb />
			-hereafter the &quot;Policy&quot;). In terms of the Policy, AIPL was insured
			<lb />
			against the specified risks for a sum of ₹9,70,00,000.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			3.
			<lb />
			On 09.12.2017, a fire broke out in AFPL&quot;s manufacturing plant
			<lb />
			(bearing Plot No. 213, HSIIDC, Footwear Park, Sector-17,
			<lb />
			Bahadurgarh, Jhajjar, Haryana) which resulted in AFPL suffering
			<lb />
			substantial loss. On 11.12.2017, OICL appointed a surveyor (M/s
			<lb />
			Timeline Insurance Surveyors and Loss Assessors Private Limited -
			<lb />
			hereafter the &quot;Surveyor&quot;) to survey and assess the loss caused to the
			<lb />
			stock, building, plant and machinery due to the aforesaid incident.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			4.
			<lb />
			On 10.01.2018, AFPL lodged a claim amounting to
			<lb />
			₹10,98,28,543.70/-. The Final Survey Report was filed on 12.06.2018
			<lb />
			and the same quantified the loss suffered by AFPL at
			<lb />
			₹4,70,15,504.79/-excluding the Goods and Services Tax (GST)
			<lb />
			thereon. On 12.11.2018, OICL made an on-account payment of
			<lb />
			₹2,00,00,000/-. On 13.12.2018, OICL informed AFPL that its claim
			<lb />
			had been approved for a sum of ₹4,70,15,505/-, subject to adjustment
			<lb />
			of the on-account payment made by it on 12.11.2018. It further
			<lb />
			directed AFPL to provide a discharge voucher in the given format
			<lb />
			duly filled, stamped and counter-signed by the bank. On 15.12.2018,
			<lb />
			AFPL submitted the discharge voucher (hereinafter &quot;the Discharge
			<lb />
			Voucher&quot;) as required by OICL.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			5.
			<lb />
			On 20.12.2018, OICL released the balance sum of
			<lb />
			₹2,70,15,505/-to AFPL. On 26.12.2018, AFPL sent a protest letter
			<lb />
			stating that the Discharge Voucher was executed by it under protest
			<lb />
			and requested for a copy of the Final Survey Report. By way of a
			<lb />
			notice dated 29.01.2019, AFPL invoked the agreement to refer the
			<lb />
			disputes to arbitration as contained in the Policy. OICL responded to
			<lb />
			the said notice on 28.02.2019. It denied the averments made by AFPL
			<lb />
			but suggested the name of Mr. R.K. Kaul to be appointed as the
			<lb />
			arbitrator to adjudicate the disputes between the parties. AFPL did not
			<lb />
			agree with the proposed name and suggested that a retired High Court
			<lb />
			Judge be appointed as an Arbitrator.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			6.
			<lb />
			Eventually, on 22.05.2019, OICL appointed Justice Kurian
			<lb />
			Jospeh, a former Judge of the Supreme Court of India as the Sole
			<lb />
			Arbitrator and he entered reference on 27.05.2019.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			7.
			<lb />
			On 13.07.2019, AFPL filed its Statement of Claim before the
			<lb />
			Arbitral Tribunal, raising the following claims:-
			<lb />
		</p>
		<figure type="table">
			Table 1
			<lb />
			Claim No
			<lb />
			Claim Details
			<lb />
			Relief Claimed
			<lb />
			Claim No 1 Claim on account of loss to
			<lb />
			Plant and Machinery
			<lb />
			₹ 75,95,759/-
			<lb />
			Claim No 2 Claim on account of loss to ₹2,11,99,350/-
			<lb />
			Building
			<lb />
			Claim No 3 Claim on account of loss to
			<lb />
			Stock
			<lb />
			₹25,00,000/-
			<lb />
			Claim No 4 Claim on account of interest
			<lb />
			as per IRDA Regulations,
			<lb />
			2017
			<lb />
			₹54,70,826/-
			<lb />
			Claim No 5 Claim on account of excess
			<lb />
			deducted by the Insurance
			<lb />
			Company
			<lb />
			₹24,74,669/-
			<lb />
			Claim No 6 Claim on account of loss to
			<lb />
			Fire Fighting Equipment
			<lb />
			₹7,96,500/-
			<lb />
			Claim No 7 Claim on account of Removal
			<lb />
			of Debris
			<lb />
			₹4,00,371/-
			<lb />
			TOTAL
			<lb />
			₹4,04,37,475/-
			<lb />
		</figure>
		<p>
			8.
			<lb />
			In addition to the total claim of ₹4,04,37,475/-, AFPL also
			<lb />
			claimed interest thereon. On 30.08.2019, OICL filed its Statement of
			<lb />
			Defence along with an application under Section 16 of the A&amp;C Act,
			<lb />
			contending that AFPL&quot;s claims were not arbitrable. OICL also
			<lb />
			contended that the claims were liable to be rejected on the ground that
			<lb />
			the contract stood discharged by accord and satisfaction as AFPL had
			<lb />
			signed the Discharge Voucher in full and final settlement of all its
			<lb />
			claims. By way of a procedural order, the Arbitral Tribunal noted that
			<lb />
			the controversy raised in the application under Section 16 of the A&amp;C
			<lb />
			Act involved disputed questions of fact that required consideration of
			<lb />
			evidence and decided to frame an issue to be considered along with
			<lb />
			the reliefs claimed in the Statement of Claims.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			9.
			<lb />
			The dispute whether the contract of insurance stood discharged
			<lb />
			by accord and satisfaction was considered as issue no.1. The Arbitral
			<lb />
			Tribunal decided the same against the petitioner. It reasoned that
			<lb />
			AFPL was compelled to execute the Discharge Voucher for release of
			<lb />
			admitted payments. The Arbitral Tribunal found that AFPL was under
			<lb />
			compulsion, duress and coercion to execute the Discharge Voucher.
			<lb />
			Further, considering that AFPL had not been provided a copy of the
			<lb />
			Final Survey Report, which formed the basis of the calculations
			<lb />
			regarding the claims, the Arbitral Tribunal held that AFPL was
			<lb />
			entitled to dispute the arbitrary deductions made from the claims made
			<lb />
			by it. The Arbitral Tribunal rejected OICL&quot;s contention regarding non-
			<lb />
			production of the Arbitration Agreement on the ground that the
			<lb />
			wordings of the Standard Fire and Special Perils Policy are standard
			<lb />
			form and are approved by the Insurance Regulatory and Development
			<lb />
			Authority (IRDA) and thus, OICL could not raise a contention
			<lb />
			regarding the non-existence of an agreement to refer the disputes to
			<lb />
			arbitration.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			10. Insofar as the merits of the disputes are concerned, the Arbitral
			<lb />
			Tribunal noted that the following items were insured:-
			<lb />
		</p>
		<figure type="table">
			Table 2
			<lb />
			S. No.
			<lb />
			Description of Property
			<lb />
			Sum Insured (₹)
			<lb />
			1.
			<lb />
			Building (with Plinth and
			<lb />
			6,00,00,000
			<lb />
			Foundation)
			<lb />
			2.
			<lb />
			Plant and Machinery
			<lb />
			1,20,00,000
			<lb />
			3.
			<lb />
			Stocks of all types of Raw
			<lb />
			Material, goods in progress,
			<lb />
			semi-finished and finished goods
			<lb />
			2,50,00,000
			<lb />
			4.
			<lb />
			Total
			<lb />
			9,70,00,000/-
			<lb />
		</figure>
		<p>
			11. Regarding AFPL&quot;s claim on account of erroneous disallowance
			<lb />
			of the insurance claim pertaining to the plant and machinery, the
			<lb />
			Arbitral Tribunal awarded AFPL a sum of ₹90,71,367.25/-, including
			<lb />
			GST against AFPL&quot;s quantification of the said loss amounting to
			<lb />
			₹1,32,00,392/-. Since AFPL could not produce any independent
			<lb />
			witness for substantiating its claim, the Arbitral Tribunal based its
			<lb />
			calculation on the Final Survey Report. The Arbitral Tribunal noted
			<lb />
			that according to the Surveyor, the loss suffered by AFPL, without
			<lb />
			depreciation, stood at ₹88,87,287.25/-. If depreciation was to be
			<lb />
			added, the value would be below the amount of loss, assessed by the
			<lb />
			Surveyor. The learned Arbitrator held that there was no evidence on
			<lb />
			the part of AFPL to establish the loss claimed in its Statement of
			<lb />
			Claims in respect of the plant and machinery. Thus, the Arbitral
			<lb />
			Tribunal affirmed the quantification as made by the Surveyor in its
			<lb />
			Final Survey Report. However, the Arbitral Tribunal awarded AFPL
			<lb />
			the cost of two Roughing and Grinding Machines, quantified at
			<lb />
			₹1,84,080/-(₹92,040/-each). The Arbitral Tribunal also held that
			<lb />
			OICL was not justified in deducting 5% of the Plant and Machinery as
			<lb />
			salvage, since the same was based on the theoretical value of salvage
			<lb />
			and not its actual value.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			12. Next, the Arbitral Tribunal examined AFPL&quot;s claim for
			<lb />
			disallowing the insurance claim pertaining to the building (Claim No 2
			<lb />
			in Table 1 hereinabove). Against this claim, the Arbitral Tribunal
			<lb />
			awarded AFPL a total sum of ₹4,40,77,108.94/-, including GST. This
			<lb />
			claim was divided into three parts, namely, (a) Finishing based on
			<lb />
			DSR-2016 rates; (b) Retrofitting based on Water Resources
			<lb />
			Department, Government of Karnataka, Schedule of Rates 2016-2017;
			<lb />
			and (c) (Electrical, Plumbing and Sanitary, Fire Fighting System)
			<lb />
			based on CPWD Plinth Area Rates 2012 with Cost Index. Regarding
			<lb />
			Part (a), the Arbitral Tribunal noted that the amount claimed as per
			<lb />
			DSR-2016 rates was ₹90,39,143.49/-while the amount allowed stood
			<lb />
			at ₹84,00,019.71. The Arbitral Tribunal accepted AFPL&quot;s contention
			<lb />
			that the 5% contingency had been incorrectly disallowed by the
			<lb />
			Surveyor. It held that the Surveyor should not have disallowed
			<lb />
			AFPL&quot;s claim in the absence of a provision for contingent expenses.
			<lb />
			Regarding Part (b), the Arbitral Tribunal found that the Surveyor, in
			<lb />
			its Final Report, had noted that the staircase was broken and damaged
			<lb />
			due to the fire. However, AFPL&quot;s claim in this regard had not been
			<lb />
			allowed. The Arbitral Tribunal awarded a sum of ₹2,54,190/-for
			<lb />
			retrofitting with respect to the staircase. With regard to Part (c), the
			<lb />
			Arbitral Tribunal awarded the loss incurred by AFPL in respect of
			<lb />
			&quot;extra items&quot; to the tune of 7.25%, since it found that the Surveyor had
			<lb />
			incorrectly interpreted the CPWD Plinth Area Rates 2012. Further, the
			<lb />
			Arbitral Tribunal held that AFPL was entitled to 23.75% of the total
			<lb />
			cost of Building (totaling to ₹4,40,77,108.94/-).
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			13. Next, the Arbitral Tribunal considered AFPL&quot;s claim regarding
			<lb />
			the disallowance of its insurance claim pertaining to stocks. The
			<lb />
			Arbitral Tribunal found that the Surveyor&quot;s calculation was erroneous,
			<lb />
			since it had limited the allowable loss to the sum insured and then
			<lb />
			deducted 10% on account of speculative dead stock. The only
			<lb />
			deduction the Surveyor could have made was undisputed salvage
			<lb />
			value, which was admitted by AFPL to be ₹65,000/-. Thus, AFPL was
			<lb />
			held to be entitled to a sum of ₹2,49,35,000/-, in this regard.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			14. AFPL&quot;s claim regarding interest of 2% above the bank rate, in
			<lb />
			view of Clause 15 of the IRDA (Protection of Policyholders&quot; Interests)
			<lb />
			Regulations, 2017 was accepted by the Arbitral Tribunal and it
			<lb />
			awarded interest at the rate of 8.25% per annum from 11.04.2018 till
			<lb />
			the date of payment. The Arbitral Tribunal arrived at this figure by
			<lb />
			adding the Bank Rate fixed by the Reserve Bank of India (at the
			<lb />
			beginning of FY 2018-19), that is, 6.25% and 2% in terms of Clause
			<lb />
			15 of the IRDA Regulations.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			15. The Arbitral Tribunal found that the Surveyor was responsible
			<lb />
			for the delay in submitting its Final Report beyond the statutory period
			<lb />
			of ninety days from the date of its appointment and held that AFPL
			<lb />
			was entitled to interest for the delayed period (120 days).
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			16. The next aspect considered by the Arbitral Tribunal was
			<lb />
			regarding the deduction of 5% from the assessed amount towards
			<lb />
			excess waiver. The Arbitral Tribunal held the stipulation of exclusion
			<lb />
			of 5% of each and every claim was applicable only to Act of God
			<lb />
			(AOG) perils and in respect of all other perils, the sum was fixed at
			<lb />
			₹10,000/-. Therefore, the deduction under this head was restricted to
			<lb />
			₹60,000/-. With regard to the claim on account of erroneous
			<lb />
			disallowance of insurance claim pertaining to firefighting equipment,
			<lb />
			the Arbitral Tribunal awarded AFPL a sum of ₹7,96,500/-along with
			<lb />
			a sum of ₹1,93,796/-, which had already been given to AFPL by
			<lb />
			OICL. The Arbitral Tribunal observed that the Surveyor ought to have
			<lb />
			awarded the aforesaid amount, keeping in view that the Surveyor had
			<lb />
			verified the &quot;No Objection Certificate&quot; dated 04.10.2017 issued by the
			<lb />
			Haryana Fire and Emergency Services and the fact that most of the
			<lb />
			fire-fighting equipment had been destroyed in the fire. The claim
			<lb />
			made by AFPL, for the cost incurred by it for the removal of debris on
			<lb />
			actuals basis was rejected by the Arbitral Tribunal and it affirmed that
			<lb />
			only 1% of the claim amount could be paid to AFPL in terms of the
			<lb />
			Policy.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			17. Finally, the Arbitral Tribunal considered AFPL&quot;s claim for
			<lb />
			GST, which as per its contention before the Arbitral Tribunal, was an
			<lb />
			actual expense incurred to avail services and on purchase of
			<lb />
			machinery. In this regard, the Arbitral Tribunal held that AFPL would
			<lb />
			be entitled to the payment of GST for retrofitting, since the same is to
			<lb />
			be treated as an expense and AFPL would be ineligible for Input Tax
			<lb />
			Credit (ITC). On the question of GST in respect of plant and
			<lb />
			machinery, the Arbitral Tribunal held that AFPL would be entitled to
			<lb />
			reimbursement of the GST component under the head of Plant and
			<lb />
			Machinery only after the repairs to the plant and machinery were
			<lb />
			carried out and the GST Commissioner has scrutinized the return
			<lb />
			thereon,
		</p>
		<p>
			18. Thus, the Arbitral Tribunal awarded the following relief to
			<lb />
			AFPL:-
			<lb />
		</p>
		<figure type="table">
			Table 3
			<lb />
			Claim No.
			<lb />
			Particulars
			<lb />
			Amount (in ₹)
			<lb />
			Claim No. 1 Plant &amp; Machinery -Total claim
			<lb />
			allowed (excluding GST)
			<lb />
			74,47,189.95/-
			<lb />
			Claim No. 2 Building -Total Allowed Claim
			<lb />
			(with GST)
			<lb />
			4,40,77,108.94/-
			<lb />
			Claim No. 3 Stock -Total Allowed Claim
			<lb />
			2,49,35,000/-
			<lb />
			Claim No. 4 Interest -Total Allowed Claim as on
			<lb />
			28.08.2020 at the rate of 8.25%
			<lb />
			51,15,789.05
			<lb />
			Claim No. 5 Policy Excess -Total Allowed
			<lb />
			Deduction/Adjustment
			<lb />
			-60,000/-
			<lb />
			Claim No. 6 Fire Fighting -Total Allowed Claim
			<lb />
			9,90,296/-
			<lb />
			Claim No. 7 Removal of Debris -Total Allowed
			<lb />
			Claim
			<lb />
			2,88,640/-
			<lb />
			GST
			<lb />
			Total GST (subject to submission of
			<lb />
			GST certificate)
			<lb />
			16,24,177.31/-
			<lb />
			Total Award Amount with interest
			<lb />
			till 28.08.2020 (date of award)
			<lb />
			4,08,94,307.99/-
			<lb />
			Total Entitlement along with GST
			<lb />
			with interest till 28.08.2020 (subject
			<lb />
			to GST certificate)
			<lb />
			4,25,18,485.29/-
			<lb />
		</figure>
		<p>
			19. Aggrieved by the Arbitral Award dated 28.08.2020, OICL has
			<lb />
			filed the present petition.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<head>
			Submissions
			<lb />
		</head>
		<p>
			20. Mr. Joy Basu, the learned Senior Counsel appearing for OICL,
			<lb />
			has assailed the impugned award on, essentially, three grounds. First,
			<lb />
			he contended that there was a full and final settlement of the insurance
			<lb />
			claim by AFPL by executing the Discharge Voucher. Second, that the
			<lb />
			denial of deduction on account of underinsurance is patently illegal
			<lb />
			and contrary to the agreement between the parties. And third, that the
			<lb />
			Arbitral Tribunal&quot;s deduction of 5% under the Excess Clause is
			<lb />
			contrary to the terms of the Policy.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			21. At the outset Mr Basu submitted that the Discharge Voucher
			<lb />
			was signed by AFPL free from undue influence, coercion and
			<lb />
			pressure. AFPL did not protest the same either. The Arbitral Tribunal
			<lb />
			has provided no reasons for its conclusion that AFPL&quot;s execution of
			<lb />
			the Discharge Voucher was not out of its free will. He relied on the
			<lb />
			decision of the Supreme Court in Dyna Technologies Private Limited
			<lb />
			v. Crompton Greaves Limited.: (2019) 20 SCC 1, and contended that
			<lb />
			the impugned award was liable to be set aside as OICL&quot;s contention
			<lb />
			regarding discharge by accord and satisfaction, was rejected without
			<lb />
			providing any reasons. He further contended that the practice of
			<lb />
			execution of Discharge Vouchers and No-Objection Certificates as a
			<lb />
			precondition to release of amounts is an accepted practice in
			<lb />
			government departments and Public Sector Undertakings. He also
			<lb />
			contended that the Arbitral Tribunal should have dealt with and
			<lb />
			disposed the challenge to its jurisdiction, filed by OICL under Section
			<lb />
			16 of the A&amp;C Act, at the first instance and not along with the final
			<lb />
			Award.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			22. Next, Mr. Basu contended that the Arbitral Tribunal&quot;s rejection
			<lb />
			of deduction on account of underinsurance is patently illegal and runs
			<lb />
			contrary to the agreement between the parties. He submitted that the
			<lb />
			sum insured is always proposed by the insured and the insurer has no
			<lb />
			say in it. Since AFPL itself had insured the machinery for a value of
			<lb />
			₹1,20,00,000/-, it could not now state that there was an agreement on
			<lb />
			the value at the time of inception of the Policy. He contended that it is
			<lb />
			well established that the value of an item is always declared by the
			<lb />
			insured at the time of inception of a policy and the value of
			<lb />
			underinsurance is calculated by the insurer at the time of assessment
			<lb />
			of loss.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			23. Lastly, Mr Basu contended that the Arbitral Tribunal&quot;s rejection
			<lb />
			of the deduction of 5% under the Excess Waiver Clause was contrary
			<lb />
			to the terms of the contract. It amounted to foisting a new contractual
			<lb />
			term on the parties and therefore the impugned award was liable to be
			<lb />
			set aside.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			24. Mr. Sachin Dutta, learned Senior Counsel appearing for AFPL,
			<lb />
			countered the aforesaid submissions. He submitted that the petition
			<lb />
			ought to be dismissed, since the grounds for interfering with an
			<lb />
			Arbitral Award are limited under Section 34 of the A&amp;C Act and in
			<lb />
			this case, this narrow threshold is not met. He relied on the decision of
			<lb />
			the Supreme Court in Steel Authority of India Limited v. Gupta
			<lb />
			Brother Steel Tubes Limited: (2009) 10 SCC 63, and submitted that
			<lb />
			even if there is an error in the interpretation of a contract by an
			<lb />
			Arbitrator, the same is within his jurisdiction and such error is not
			<lb />
			amenable to correction by the courts as the same is not an error on the
			<lb />
			face of the record.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			25. In regard to the application filed by OICL under Section 16 of
			<lb />
			the A&amp;C Act, he submitted that the Arbitral Tribunal had come to its
			<lb />
			conclusion only after appreciating the evidence on record. He
			<lb />
			submitted that courts have held in various decisions that insurance
			<lb />
			companies cannot insist on the insured signing a Discharge Voucher
			<lb />
			as a pre-condition for releasing the amount. He referred to the
			<lb />
			decisions in National Insurance Co. Ltd. v. Boghara Polyfab (P)
			<lb />
			Ltd.: (2009) 1 SCC 267; Oriental Insurance Company Ltd. v.
			<lb />
			Mercury Rubber Mills: (2012) 127 DRJ 650(Del); and Worldfa
			<lb />
			Exports Pvt. Ltd. v. United India Insurance Co. Ltd.: Arb. P.
			<lb />
			459/2015, decided on 11.12.2015, in support of his contention. Next,
			<lb />
			he submitted that the Arbitral Tribunal had rightly denied deduction
			<lb />
			on account of underinsurance as there was no underinsurance and the
			<lb />
			such deduction could not be made without reference to the value of the
			<lb />
			asset at the time of insurance.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			26. With regard to the contention that the Arbitral Tribunal&quot;s
			<lb />
			deduction on account of 5% Excess being illegal, Mr. Dutta contended
			<lb />
			that contractual interpretations are within the domain of the Arbitrator
			<lb />
			and the learned Arbitrator had arrived at its decision after duly
			<lb />
			recording the submissions of the parties and considering the relevant
			<lb />
			contractual principles.
			<lb />
			Reasons and Conclusion
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			27. The first and foremost issue to be examined is whether the
			<lb />
			impugned award is unreasoned insofar as it rejects OICL&quot;s contention
			<lb />
			that the contract of insurance between the parties was discharged by
			<lb />
			accord and satisfaction. It was contended on behalf of OICL that the
			<lb />
			Arbitral Tribunal had not specifically returned any finding that AFPL
			<lb />
			was in financial distress and its financial condition was so dismal that
			<lb />
			it had no option but to accept the amounts as offered by OICL.
			<lb />
			Therefore, the impugned award is liable to be set aside as being
			<lb />
			unreasoned.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			28. This Court finds the aforesaid contention without any merit. A
			<lb />
			plain reading of the impugned award indicates that the Arbitral
			<lb />
			Tribunal had noted the submissions made on behalf of AFPL that the
			<lb />
			Discharge Voucher was executed in compelling circumstances and
			<lb />
			therefore, did not discharge the contract by accord and satisfaction.
			<lb />
			The Arbitral Tribunal specifically noted the contention that &quot;the
			<lb />
			compelling circumstances of desperate need for money have been
			<lb />
			stated in the SOC and have been brought out in evidence also&quot;.
			<lb />
			Having noted the aforesaid contention, the Arbitral Tribunal
			<lb />
			proceeded to hold that it was &quot;of the view that there is more force in
			<lb />
			the contentions of the Claimant, in the background of the Arbitration
			<lb />
			and the evidence on record, despite the persuasive arguments of Shri.
			<lb />
			Mohit Arora, learned Counsel for the Respondent Insurance
			<lb />
			Company&quot;.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			29. There is no ambiguity in the impugned award and it is clear that
			<lb />
			the Arbitral Tribunal had accepted the contention that the compelling
			<lb />
			circumstances, with regard to need of money, had been stated in the
			<lb />
			Statement of Claims and also been brought in evidence. It is also
			<lb />
			material to note that Mr. Akash Kapoor, Executive Director of AFPL
			<lb />
			had led evidence by way of an affidavit. In his affidavit, he had, inter
			<lb />
			alia, affirmed as under:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot;Pertinently, the Respondent [petitioner herein] insisted
				<lb />
				that the Claimant sign on a pre-printed format/document
				<lb />
				as a pre-condition for receiving money. The Claimant
				<lb />
				[the petitioner] succumbed to such practices of the
				<lb />
				Respondent in view of extreme duress to which the
				<lb />
				Claimant was subjected. Any delay in receipt of the
				<lb />
				money would have meant financial annihilation of the
				<lb />
				Claimant. The Claimant was forced to give their
				<lb />
				concurrence to the assessment of the claim at an amount
				<lb />
				less than the claimed amount. The Respondent made it
				<lb />
				clear that without providing this concurrence no amount
				<lb />
				would be released to the Claimant and therefore, the
				<lb />
				Claimant would continue to languish. Therefore, left with
				<lb />
				no other option, the helpless Claimant had to forcibly
				<lb />
				accept the assessment under duress and coercion.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				[underlined for emphasis]
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			30. Thus, CW-1 had affirmed that any delay in receipt of the money
			<lb />
			would have resulted in a financial collapse of AFPL. It is relevant to
			<lb />
			note that although CW-1 was cross-examined at length in regard to the
			<lb />
			assertion that AFPL had submitted a Discharge Voucher involuntarily
			<lb />
			and under undue influence, he was not cross examined on the aspect
			<lb />
			that delay in the receipt of funds would have led to AFPL&quot;s &quot;financial
			<lb />
			annihilation&quot;.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			31. The Arbitral Tribunal had also reproduced the response of CW-
			<lb />
			1 to certain questions posed to him in his cross-examination. The same
			<lb />
			are reproduced below:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot;Q. 12: Were you forced for signing any of the discharge
				<lb />
				vouchers?
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				Ans.: I received a phone call from Ms. Guneet Kaur,
				<lb />
				CBRO office, that may payment of Rs.2 Crore is being
				<lb />
				released as an interim relief and for that I have to sign a
				<lb />
				pre-printed discharge voucher. I objected to this and
				<lb />
				requested them to get the payment first and to kindly settle
				<lb />
				my claim since it has been languishing for a year. She told
				<lb />
				me it is obligatory and a pre-condition to sign the
				<lb />
				discharge voucher first and then only any payment will be
				<lb />
				released&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				&quot;Q.15 Is there any document / statement in the Statement
				<lb />
				of Claim, from the Respondent saying either you take it or
				<lb />
				leave it?
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				Ans.: it was told to me verbally.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			32. The Chief Regional Manager, CBRO of OICL was also cross-
			<lb />
			examined. The relevant questions and his responses, as noted by the
			<lb />
			Arbitral Tribunal, are reproduced below:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot;Q.22: I suggest to you that no payment would have been
				<lb />
				made to the Claimant unless he had given the discharge
				<lb />
				voucher which was a precondition as per prevalent
				<lb />
				practices of the Insurance Company. What do you say?
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				Ans.: Yes. The discharge voucher is a necessary
				<lb />
				requirement for all the claims whether minor or major.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				Q.23: Is it correct that the discharge voucher is a standard
				<lb />
				form printed by the Insurance Company?
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				Ans.: Yes. It is correct. Witness volunteers: However, the
				<lb />
				Insured while signing the discharge voucher can always
				<lb />
				qualify the same by putting his comments and the hand
				<lb />
				written comment will supersede the printed matter.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				Q.24: As per prevalent practice, is it permissible for the
				<lb />
				Insurance Company to release any amount to the Insured
				<lb />
				if any objection is raised to furnishing of discharge
				<lb />
				voucher by putting hand written comments on the same?
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				Ans.: It is not permissible. However, if the discharge
				<lb />
				voucher is qualified by the Insured, the matter would have
				<lb />
				been escalated to the Head Office for their observations
				<lb />
				and further guidance in the matter.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				Q.33: I suggest to you that the so-called discharge
				<lb />
				voucher mentions acceptance of amount by the Claimant
				<lb />
				even prior to payment having been made by the
				<lb />
				Respondent Insurance Company to the Claimant. What do
				<lb />
				you say?
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				Ans.: Yes. It is correct.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				Q.35: Would it be correct to say that the so-called
				<lb />
				discharge voucher was printed by the office of the
				<lb />
				Respondent Company?
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				Ans.: Yes.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			33. In view of the above, there is ample evidence on record that
			<lb />
			AFPL had been compelled to sign on a Discharge Voucher in the
			<lb />
			given format. This Court finds no infirmity with the aforesaid
			<lb />
			conclusion.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			34. In view of the unambiguous decision of the Arbitral Tribunal
			<lb />
			that it had accepted the contention advanced on behalf of AFPL, Mr.
			<lb />
			Basu&quot;s contention that the impugned award is unreasoned, is
			<lb />
			erroneous.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			35. The decision in the case of Dyna Technologies Private Limited
			<lb />
			v. Crompton Greaves Limited (supra) is of little assistance to OICL.
			<lb />
			In that case, the Supreme Court had observed that even if the court
			<lb />
			comes to the conclusion that there are certain gaps in the reasoning for
			<lb />
			the conclusions reached by the Tribunal, courts need to have regard to
			<lb />
			the documents submitted by the parties and the contentions raised
			<lb />
			before the Tribunal. This is to ensure that even awards with inadequate
			<lb />
			reasons are not set aside in a casual manner. The Supreme Court
			<lb />
			further clarified that only unintelligible awards, where there are no
			<lb />
			reasons at all, are required to be interfered with on the ground that the
			<lb />
			same falls foul of Section 31(3) of the A&amp;C Act. The relevant extract
			<lb />
			of the said decision is set out below:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot;36. When we consider the requirement of a reasoned
				<lb />
				order three characteristics of a reasoned order can be
				<lb />
				fathomed. They are: proper, intelligible and adequate. If
				<lb />
				the reasoning in the order are improper, they reveal a
				<lb />
				flaw in the decision making process. If the challenge to
				<lb />
				an award is based on impropriety or perversity in the
				<lb />
				reasoning, then it can be challenged strictly on the
				<lb />
				grounds provided under Section 34 of the Arbitration
				<lb />
				Act. If the challenge to an award is based on the ground
				<lb />
				that the same is unintelligible, the same would be
				<lb />
				equivalent of providing no reasons at all. Coming to the
				<lb />
				last aspect concerning the challenge on adequacy of
				<lb />
				reasons, the Court while exercising jurisdiction
				<lb />
				under Section has to adjudicate the validity of such an
				<lb />
				award based on the degree of particularity of reasoning
				<lb />
				required having regard to the nature of issues falling for
				<lb />
				consideration. The degree of particularity cannot be
				<lb />
				stated in a precise manner as the same would depend on
				<lb />
				the complexity of the issue. Even if the Court comes to a
				<lb />
				conclusion that there were gaps in the reasoning for the
				<lb />
				conclusions reached by the Tribunal, the Court needs to
				<lb />
				have regard to the documents submitted by the parties
				<lb />
				and the contentions raised before the Tribunal so that
				<lb />
				awards with inadequate reasons are not set aside in casual
				<lb />
				and cavalier manner. On the other hand, ordinarily
				<lb />
				unintelligible awards are to be set aside, subject to party
				<lb />
				autonomy to do away with the reasoned award.
				<lb />
				Therefore, the courts are required to be careful while
				<lb />
				distinguishing between inadequacy of reasons in an
				<lb />
				award and unintelligible awards.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			36. In the present case, the reasons that persuaded the Arbitral
			<lb />
			Tribunal to accept AFPL&quot;s claim are apparent, and this Court concurs
			<lb />
			with the same.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			37. The next question to be examined is whether the impugned
			<lb />
			award is liable to be set aside insofar as the Arbitral Tribunal has
			<lb />
			rejected the deduction made by the Surveyors from the amount due to
			<lb />
			AFPL, on account of underinsurance. The entire plant and machinery
			<lb />
			were insured for ₹1,20,00,000/-(Rupees One Crore and Twenty
			<lb />
			Lacs). The Surveyors had determined the market value of the said
			<lb />
			machinery at ₹1,54,36,246.90/-and had accordingly, proceeded on the
			<lb />
			basis that the plant and machinery in question had been underinsured
			<lb />
			to the extent of 22.26 %. The Surveyor had accordingly reduced the
			<lb />
			assessed claims in the aforesaid proportion.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			38. The Policy is dated 25.10.2017 and the date of loss was
			<lb />
			09.12.2017. The Arbitral Tribunal noted that the entire plant and
			<lb />
			machinery was insured for a sum of ₹1,20,00,000/-, as agreed to by
			<lb />
			the parties. Indisputably, OICL had accepted the said value.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			39. The Arbitral Tribunal also noted that the plant and machinery
			<lb />
			was purchased on various dates from 2012 to 2016 and its insurance
			<lb />
			value of ₹1,20,00,000/-was determined by applying depreciation on
			<lb />
			the purchase cost of plant and machinery. OICL&quot;s witness (RW-1) had
			<lb />
			affirmed that &quot;PRV is Present Replacement Value which would mean
			<lb />
			the replacement cost of a machine or an asset as on date of loss&quot;. The
			<lb />
			Surveyor had determined the replacement value on the depreciated
			<lb />
			value of new plant and machinery as on the date of loss. The Tribunal
			<lb />
			noted that it had obviously ignored the inflation factor amongst others
			<lb />
			involved in appreciation of the cost. The Arbitral Tribunal further
			<lb />
			observed that it was nobody&quot;s case that there was any
			<lb />
			misrepresentation of fraud on the part of AFPL in the matter regarding
			<lb />
			valuation of plant and machinery at the time of entering into the
			<lb />
			contract of insurance.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			40. A plain reading of the impugned award indicates that the
			<lb />
			Arbitral Tribunal did not accept that there was any underinsurance
			<lb />
			primarily for the reason that the Surveyor had calculated the value of
			<lb />
			the plant and machinery, as on date of the loss, while the machinery
			<lb />
			had been purchased on various dates between 2012 to 2016.
			<lb />
			Accordingly, the said plant and machinery had been valued at its
			<lb />
			depreciated cost as on the date of the Policy, which was agreed at
			<lb />
			₹1,20,00,000/-. This Court is not required to re-appreciate the
			<lb />
			evidence and cannot supplant its view in place of that of the Arbitral
			<lb />
			Tribunal. The grounds on which the arbitral award can be interfered
			<lb />
			with are limited. In Dyna Technologies Pvt. Ltd. v. Crompton
			<lb />
			Greaves Ltd. (supra) -the decision relied upon on behalf of OICL -
			<lb />
			the Supreme Court had held that the courts would not interfere
			<lb />
			&quot;unless the Court comes to a conclusion that the perversity of the
			<lb />
			award goes to the root of the matter without there being a possibility
			<lb />
			of alternative interpretation which may sustain the arbitral award&quot;.
			<lb />
			The Court also held that &quot;The mandate under Section 34 is to respect
			<lb />
			the finality of the arbitral award and the party autonomy to get their
			<lb />
			dispute adjudicated by an alternative forum as provided under the
			<lb />
			law.&quot;. The Court further observed as under:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot;25. Moreover, umpteen number of judgments of this
				<lb />
				Court have categorically held that the Courts should not
				<lb />
				interfere with an award merely because an alternative view
				<lb />
				on facts and interpretation of contract exists. The Courts
				<lb />
				need to be cautious and should defer to the view taken by
				<lb />
				the Arbitral Tribunal even if the reasoning provided in the
				<lb />
				award is implied unless such award portrays perversity
				<lb />
				unpardonable under Section 34 of the Arbitration Act.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			41. The view that there was no underinsurance is a plausible one.
			<lb />
			Thus, this Court finds no reason to interfere with the impugned award
			<lb />
			insofar as the conclusion of the Arbitral Tribunal that there is no
			<lb />
			underinsurance. The last aspect is to be examined is whether the
			<lb />
			Arbitral Tribunal had erred in restricting the Excess/Deductible under
			<lb />
			the Policy to ₹60,000/-(Claim No. 5). OICL had deducted an amount
			<lb />
			of ₹24,84,669/-from the assessed amount towards the excess to be
			<lb />
			borne by the insured. AFPL had contested the same and contended
			<lb />
			that the Standard Fire and Special Perils Insurance Policy had limited
			<lb />
			the waiver to ₹10,000/-in respect of all perils other than those
			<lb />
			resulting from lightening and certain other &quot;AOG Perils&quot; (Acts of
			<lb />
			God). In its Statement of Claims, it claimed that it was not open for
			<lb />
			OICL to unilaterally deduct a larger sum contrary to the Standard Fire
			<lb />
			and Special Perils Insurance Policy. The claim as articulated by AFPL
			<lb />
			in its Statement of Claims is reproduced below:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot;50. That the terms and conditions of the Insurance
				<lb />
				Policy clearly state the following:
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				&quot;SIGNIFICANT EXCLUSIONS
				<lb />
				Losses/Expenses not covered:
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				5% of each and every claim subject to minimum of
				<lb />
				Rs.10,000 resulting from Lightning, STFI and
				<lb />
				Subsidence and Landslide including Rockslide
				<lb />
				(AOG Perils) Rs. 10,000 in respect of all other
				<lb />
				perils.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				Expenses incurred on Architects, Surveyors&apos;
				<lb />
				Consultant Engineers fees and Debris Removal in
				<lb />
				excess of 3% and 1% of the claim amount
				<lb />
				respectively.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				Loss of earnings, loss by delay, loss of market or
				<lb />
				other consequential or indirect loss or damage of
				<lb />
				any kind.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				51. That a bare perusal of the Excess Clause clearly
				<lb />
				reveals that for a loss arising out of perils other than Act
				<lb />
				of God Perils, the applicable excess is Rs. 10,000/-
				<lb />
				therefore, by virtue of the said clause, the Respondent is
				<lb />
				entitled to deduct only Rs. 10,000/-as the cause of fire in
				<lb />
				the instant claim is admittedly a fire caused accidentally
				<lb />
				and not Act of God.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				52. It is further submitted that the terms and conditions
				<lb />
				of a Standard Fire and Special Perils Policy issued by
				<lb />
				Insurance Companies, have been formulated and
				<lb />
				espoused by the Insurance Regulatory and Development
				<lb />
				Authority of India and cannot be altered by the
				<lb />
				Respondent unilaterally. In this regard, the said terms and
				<lb />
				conditions mandate that in the event of a loss arising out
				<lb />
				of a peril other than an &quot;Act of god Peril&quot;, the applicable
				<lb />
				excess would be Rs.10,000/-. However, in the instant
				<lb />
				case, the Respondent has unlawfully deducted flat 5%
				<lb />
				from the Assessed Amount.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			42. AFPL had, accordingly, claimed that OICL was liable to pay
			<lb />
			₹24,74,669/-along with interest to AFPL (Claim no. 5).
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			43. OICL had disputed the above. In its Statement of Defence, it
			<lb />
			stated that the deduction was made in accordance with the terms and
			<lb />
			conditions of the insurance policy. It stated that the insurance policy
			<lb />
			itself provided for Excess to be computed at 5% subject to minimum
			<lb />
			of ₹10,000/-. The Clause of the Policy, as referred to by OICL, is
			<lb />
			reproduced below:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot;Total Sum Insured in Words : Indian Rupees Nineteen
				<lb />
				Crores Eighty Lakhs Only
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				Total Premium In Words : Indian Rupees Two Lakhs
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				Twenty-Nine Thousand Two Hundred Only
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<figure type="table">
			Excess / Deductible :
			<lb />
			The following minimum deductibles are applicable based on
			<lb />
			per Location Sum Insured of the policy.
			<lb />
			Sum Insured Brand per Location
			<lb />
			(including endorsements, If any)
			<lb />
			Material Damage
			<lb />
			% Of
			<lb />
			Claim
			<lb />
			Subject
			<lb />
			to
			<lb />
			Minimum
			<lb />
			Deductible in
			<lb />
			INR.
			<lb />
			Upto 10 Cr
			<lb />
			5
			<lb />
			10,000.00
			<lb />
			Above 10 Cr and upto 100 Cr
			<lb />
			5
			<lb />
			25,000.00
			<lb />
			Above 100 Cr and upto 1500 Cr
			<lb />
			5
			<lb />
			500,000.00
			<lb />
			Above 1500 Cr and upto 2500 Cr
			<lb />
			5
			<lb />
			2,500,000.00
			<lb />
			Above 2500 Cr
			<lb />
			5
			<lb />
			5,000,000.00
			<lb />
			&quot;
			<lb />
		</figure>
		<p>
			44. A reading of the impugned award indicates that the Arbitral
			<lb />
			Tribunal did not refer to the Clause as relied upon by OICL and as
			<lb />
			quoted above. Instead, the Arbitral Tribunal referred to the Clause
			<lb />
			regarding exclusions under a Standard Fire and Special Perils
			<lb />
			Insurance Policy and held that the maximum deduction under that
			<lb />
			head could be taken as ₹60,000/-towards the six claims as noted to by
			<lb />
			the Surveyor and accordingly, held that the total adjustment under the
			<lb />
			head -Policy Excess was ₹60,000/-.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			45. It is at once clear that the Arbitral Tribunal has not addressed
			<lb />
			the issue in dispute. There is no dispute that the Insurance Policy in
			<lb />
			question included the Clause, setting out a tabular statement,
			<lb />
			indicating the amounts to be deductible on account of Excess. AFPL
			<lb />
			had contended that it was not open for OICL to unilaterally include
			<lb />
			the said Clause, which according to it, was contrary to the Standard
			<lb />
			Fire and Special Perils Insurance Policy that was also accepted by
			<lb />
			IRDA (Insurance Regulatory and Development Authority). The
			<lb />
			Arbitral Tribunal has completely ignored the Clause in the Policy and
			<lb />
			has proceeded to determine the claim on the basis of a Standard Fire
			<lb />
			and Special Perils Insurance Policy.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			46. It did not address the dispute whether it was open for AFPL to
			<lb />
			question the Clause on the Policy and secondly, whether the Clause as
			<lb />
			included in the Policy issued by OICL was liable to be ignored. It is
			<lb />
			apparent that the Arbitral Tribunal has not considered the dispute and
			<lb />
			has accepted AFPL&quot;s claim without any reference to the Excess
			<lb />
			Clause under the Policy issued by OICL.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			47. In the circumstances, the impugned award to the extent that it
			<lb />
			allows AFPL&quot;s regarding the Excess/Deductible, cannot be sustained
			<lb />
			(Claim No. 5). The impugned award is set aside to the aforesaid
			<lb />
			extent. The amount awarded to AFPL is required to be recomputed.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			48. The petition is, accordingly, disposed of. The pending
			<lb />
			application is also disposed of.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			VIBHU BAKHRU, J
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			MAY 18, 2021
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			RK
		</p>
	</text>
</tei>
