<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc xml:id="0" />
    </teiHeader>
    <table xml:lang="en">

        <p>
            1.
            <lb />
            By order dated 11 th October, 2019 in OMP (I) (Comm)
            <lb />
            336/2019, OMP (I) (Comm) 337/2019 and order dated 14 th October,
            <lb />
            2019 in OMP (I) (Comm) 343/2019, a learned Single Judge of this
            <lb />
            Court referred the disputes, arising between the appellant and the
            <lb />
            respondent, to arbitration by an eminent retired Chief Justice of the
            <lb />
            High Court of Jammu and Kashmir. The appellant is the claimant in
            <lb />
            the said arbitral proceedings, and the respondent before me is also the
            <lb />
            respondent therein. These appeals, under Section 37(2)(a) of the
            <lb />
            Arbitration and Conciliation Act, 1996 (&quot;the 1996 Act&quot;) impugn the
            <lb />
            order, dated 5 th March, 2021, passed by the learned Arbitrator on
            <lb />
            applications, preferred before him by the respondent under Section 16
            <lb />
            of the 1996 Act.
            <lb />
        </p>
        <head>
            Factual Conspectus
            <lb />
        </head>
        <p>
            2.
            <lb />
            The offer of the appellant, in response to the notice, dated 24 th
            <lb />
            March, 2019, of the respondent, inviting tenders for certain civil
            <lb />
            works, was accepted by the respondent vide Letter of Acceptance
            <lb />
            dated 11 th May, 2017. As required by the conditions stipulated in the
            <lb />
            notice inviting tender and the Letter of Acceptance, Performance
            <lb />
            Bank Guarantees No 17793BG00038, 17793BG00040 and
            <lb />
            17793BG00041, dated 17 th July, 2017, 31 st August, 2017 and 31 st
            <lb />
            August, 2017 respectively (collectively referred to, hereinafter, as &quot;the
            <lb />
            BGs&quot;) and extended subsequently, were furnished by the appellant.
            <lb />
            Formal contracts, between the appellant and the respondent were
            <lb />
            executed on 26 th September, 2017. Clauses 8.4, 50 and 50.2 of the
            <lb />
            General Conditions of Contract (GCC) are relevant, and the relevant
            <lb />
            parts thereof may be reproduced thus:
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;8.4 Release of Performance Security:
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (a)
            <lb />
            Performance Security shall be returned to the
            <lb />
            Contractor, subject to the issue of Completion
            <lb />
            Certificate by the Engineer in accordance with clause
            <lb />
            65 of these conditions. This shall not relieve the
            <lb />
            Contractor from his obligations and liabilities, to make
            <lb />
            good any failures, defects, imperfections, shrinkages,
            <lb />
            or faults that may be detected during the defect
            <lb />
            liability period specified in the Contract.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (b)
            <lb />
            Wherever the contract is rescind(sic), the
            <lb />
            security deposit shall be forfeited and the Performance
            <lb />
            Security shall [be encashed] and the balance work
            <lb />
            shall be got done independently without risk and cost
            <lb />
            of the failed contractor. The failed contractor shall be
            <lb />
            debarred from participating in the tender for executing
            <lb />
            the balance work.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            If the failed contractor is a JV or a partnership firm,
            <lb />
            then every member/partner of such a firm shall be
            <lb />
            debarred from participating in the tender for the
            <lb />
            balance work either in his/her individual capacity or as
            <lb />
            a partner of any other JV/partnership firm.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (c)
            <lb />
            The Engineer shall not make a claim under the
            <lb />
            Performance Guarantee (PG) except for amounts to
            <lb />
            which Ircon International Limited is entitled under the
            <lb />
            contract (not withstanding and/or without prejudice to
            <lb />
            any other provisions in the contract agreement) in the
            <lb />
            event of :-
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            1.
            <lb />
            Failure by the contractor to extend the
            <lb />
            validity of the PG as described herein above, in
            <lb />
            which event the Engineer may claim the full
            <lb />
            amount of the PG.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            2.
            <lb />
            Failure by the contractor to pay Ircon
            <lb />
            International Limited any amount due, either as
            <lb />
            agreed by the contractor or determined under
            <lb />
            any of the Clauses/Conditions of the agreement,
            <lb />
            within 30 days of the service of notice to this
            <lb />
            effect by Engineer.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            3.
            <lb />
            The contract being determined or
            <lb />
            rescinded under the provision of the GCC the
            <lb />
            PG shall be forfeited in full and shall be
            <lb />
            absolutely at the disposal of the Engineer.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            &quot;50.0 DETERMINATION OF CONTRACT DUE TO
            <lb />
            CONTRACTOR&apos;S DEFAULT
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            50.1 Conditions leading to determination of contract
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            1.1.1 If the Contractor
            <lb />
            *****
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            h.
            <lb />
            fails to adhere to the agreed programme
            <lb />
            of work or fails to complete the works or parts
            <lb />
            of the works within the stipulated or extended
            <lb />
            period of completion, or is unlikely to complete
            <lb />
            the whole work or part thereof within time
            <lb />
            because of poor record of progress; or
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            *****
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            In any such case the Engineer on behalf of the
            <lb />
            Employer may serve the Contractor with a notice in
            <lb />
            writing to the effect and if the Contractor does not,
            <lb />
            within 7 days after delivery to him of such notice,
            <lb />
            proceed to make good his default in so far as the same
            <lb />
            is capable of being made good, and carry on the work
            <lb />
            or comply with such instructions as aforesaid to the
            <lb />
            entire satisfaction of the Engineer, the Employer shall
            <lb />
            be entitled after giving 48 hours notice in writing to
            <lb />
            terminate the contract, as a whole in terms of sub-
            <lb />
            clause no. 8.4(b) and 8.4(c).
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            ii.
            <lb />
            In such a case of termination, the
            <lb />
            Employer/Engineer may adopt the following courses
            <lb />
            a)
            <lb />
            Take possession of the site and any
            <lb />
            materials, construction plants, equipment,
            <lb />
            stores, etc.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            b)
            <lb />
            Measure up the balance work from
            <lb />
            which the Contractor has been removed, and get
            <lb />
            it completed by another Contractor.
            <lb />
            The
            <lb />
            manner and method, in which such work is to
            <lb />
            be completed, shall be entirely at the discretion
            <lb />
            of the Engineer whose decision shall be final
            <lb />
            and binding.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            c)
            <lb />
            Carry out the balance work from which
            <lb />
            the Contractor has been removed, by the
            <lb />
            employment of the required labour, materials,
            <lb />
            plants and equipment and other resources.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            50.2 Entitlement of Employer/Engineer:
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            In cases described in sub-clause 50.1(ii) above, the
            <lb />
            Employer/Engineer shall be entitled to forfeit the
            <lb />
            security deposit and encash the Performance Security
            <lb />
            amount as a whole in terms of sub-clause no. 8.4.&quot;
            <lb />
            (Emphasis supplied throughout)
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            3.
            <lb />
            In respect of packages SS3-A, SS3-B and SS2-C, of the work
            <lb />
            allotted to the appellant under the aforesaid contracts, the respondent
            <lb />
            issued, in the first instance, 7-day notices of default and, in the
            <lb />
            second, 48 hour notices of default, after which the contract was
            <lb />
            terminated. The dates of the 7-day notices, 48 hour notices and
            <lb />
            notices of termination, in respect of these three packages, may be
            <lb />
            depicted, in a tabular form, thus:
            <lb />
        </p>

        <table>
            Package No.
            <lb />
            Date of 7-day
            <lb />
            notice
            <lb />
            Date of 48-hour
            <lb />
            notice
            <lb />
            Date of notice
            <lb />
            terminating the
            <lb />
            contract
            <lb />
            SS3-A
            <lb />
            5 th
            <lb />
            October,
            <lb />
            2019
            <lb />
            16 th /17 th
            <lb />
            October, 2019
            <lb />
            22 nd
            <lb />
            October,
            <lb />
            2019
            <lb />
            SS3-B
            <lb />
            13 th September,
            <lb />
            2019
            <lb />
            30 th September,
            <lb />
            2019
            <lb />
            11 th
            <lb />
            October,
            <lb />
            2019
            <lb />
            SS2-C
            <lb />
            23 rd September,
            <lb />
            2019
            <lb />
            5 th
            <lb />
            October,
            <lb />
            2019
            <lb />
            11 th
            <lb />
            October,
            <lb />
            2019
            <lb />
        </table>

        <p>
            For ease of reference, I would allude to the communications in Arb A
            <lb />
            (Comm) 16/2021 -essentially because arguments were addressed
            <lb />
            with reference to the record of that appeal.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            4.
            <lb />
            The controversy, from which the present litigations emanate,
            <lb />
            owes its origin, in Arb A (Comm) 16/2021, to the aforementioned two
            <lb />
            communications, from the respondent to the appellant, dated 13 th
            <lb />
            September, 2019 and 30 th September, 2019, both purportedly issued
            <lb />
            under Clause 50.1 of the GCC. The letter dated 13 th September, 2019
            <lb />
            alleged that several critical components of the work allotted to the
            <lb />
            appellant were still outstanding, and, therefore, granted 7 days&apos; notice
            <lb />
            to the appellant to complete the outstanding work. Inter alia, the
            <lb />
            letter stated thus:
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;As you have:
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (i)
            <lb />
            Persistently disregarded instructions of IRCON
            <lb />
            and contravened provisions of the contract,
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (ii)
            <lb />
            Continuously failed to adhere to the agreed
            <lb />
            programme of work completion plan and
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (iii) Abandoned the contract by the de-mobilising all
            <lb />
            manpower from the site without intimating IRCON,
        </item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            In terms of clause 50.1 of General Conditions of Contract,
            <lb />
            you are hereby issued with a notice to proceed to make good
            <lb />
            your default and comply with the instructions to the entire
            <lb />
            satisfaction of IRCON within 7 days from the date of issue of
            <lb />
            this letter.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            *****
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            You shall note that if we are not observing sufficient progress
            <lb />
            in making your defaults good during the notice period, further
            <lb />
            contractual action as per clause 50 of GCC shall be initiated.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            5.
            <lb />
            The appellant replied, to the aforesaid notice dated 13 th
            <lb />
            September, 2019, on 21 st September, 2019. The reply did not find
            <lb />
            favour with the respondent which issued, on 30 th September, 2019, the
            <lb />
            second, 48-hours&apos; notice under Clause 50.1 of the GCC. After setting
            <lb />
            out the fact that the appellant had, earlier, been given a 7-day notice,
            <lb />
            <lb />
            requiring the appellant to comply with the stipulations mentioned
            <lb />
            therein, the notice dated 30 th September, 2019 went on to allege that
            <lb />
            &quot;no significant improvement has been noticed within the said period&quot;
            <lb />
            and that, &quot;in spite of (the respondent&apos;s) repeated requests, (the
            <lb />
            appellant&apos;s) response remained lukewarm&quot;. The notice concluded
            <lb />
            thus:
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;The above inaction, persistent disregard to IRCON&apos;s
            <lb />
            instructions and overall poor progress of works at site are
            <lb />
            considered tantamount to violation of the contract conditions.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            Due to your persistent failure, you are hereby issued &apos;48
            <lb />
            hours&apos; notice under clause 50 of GCC. You are advised
            <lb />
            immediately to comply the points raised in Seven days&apos; notice
            <lb />
            with submission of revised program commensurate with
            <lb />
            augmented resources and mobilise all necessary resources to
            <lb />
            ensure compliance during this notice period under intimation
            <lb />
            in writing to this office.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            In case of failing in above actions during the notice period,
            <lb />
            IRCON will be constrained to initiate action for termination
            <lb />
            of contract as per clause 50 of GCC.&quot;
            <lb />
            (Emphasis supplied)
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            6.
            <lb />
            The issuance of the aforesaid 48-hour notices by the
            <lb />
            respondent, threatening initiation of action for termination of the
            <lb />
            contract, provoked the appellant to move this Court by way of OMP
            <lb />
            (I) (Comm) 336/2019, OMP (I) (Comm) 337/2019 and OMP (I)
            <lb />
            (Comm) 343/2019, under Section 9 of the 1996 Act. The only prayer,
            <lb />
            in each of these OMPs, was for stay against execution/encashment of
            <lb />
            the aforesaid three Bank Guarantees furnished by the appellant to the
            <lb />
            respondent. The averments in the OMPs asserted that there was no
            <lb />
            default, on the part of the appellant, in complying with the conditions
            <lb />
            in the contract and that, therefore, the allegations in the notices dated
            <lb />
            13 th September, 2019 and 30 th September, 2019, were incorrect.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            7.
            <lb />
            During the pendency of the OMPs, the Bank Guarantees
            <lb />
            provided by the appellant were encashed by the bank, on the request
            <lb />
            of the respondent, and Demand Drafts, covering the amounts
            <lb />
            guaranteed, were provided to the respondent.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            8.
            <lb />
            OMP (I) (Comm) 336/2019 and OMP (I) (Comm) 337/2019
            <lb />
            were disposed of, by a coordinate Single Bench of this Court, vide
            <lb />
            order dated 11 th October, 2019. As this order is pivotal to resolution of
            <lb />
            the controversy before me, it is necessary to extract, in full, paras 3 to
            <lb />
            8 thereof, thus:
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;3.
            <lb />
            These are petitions under Section 9 of the Arbitration
            <lb />
            and Conciliation Act, 1996 (&apos;Act&apos;) seeking a stay against
            <lb />
            encashment of Bank Guarantees issued by Karnataka Bank
            <lb />
            Limited, Vadodara Branch.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            4.
            <lb />
            OMP (I) (Comm) 336/2019 relates to Bank Guarantee
            <lb />
            No.
            <lb />
            17793BG00038 dated 17.07.2017, extended on
            <lb />
            14.12.2018 and further extended on 26.06.2019, furnished by
            <lb />
            the petitioner to the respondent and OMP (I) (Comm)
            <lb />
            337/2019 relates to Bank Guarantee No. 17793BG00041
            <lb />
            dated 31.8.2017 extended on 27.11.2018.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            5.
            <lb />
            The parties had entered into a contract dated
            <lb />
            26.09.2017. Disputes have arisen between the parties with
            <lb />
            respect to the said contract. The respondent had given a
            <lb />
            seven days&apos; notice dated 13.09.2019 to the petitioner under
            <lb />
            clause 50.1 of the GCC requiring him to secure the alleged
            <lb />
            defaults. On 30.09.2019, 48 hours&apos; notice was given asking
            <lb />
            the petitioner to complete the work in accordance with the
            <lb />
            contract failing which the respondent was to initiate action
            <lb />
            towards termination of the contract.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            6.
            <lb />
            After some hearing, the parties have agreed to appoint
            <lb />
            a Sole Arbitrator to adjudicate upon the disputes arising
            <lb />
            between the parties. Settlement has also been arrived at with
            <lb />
            respect to the invocation/encashment of the Bank Guarantees
            <lb />
            in question till the Arbitrator considers the application under
            <lb />
            Section 17 of the Act.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            7.
            <lb />
            With the consent of the parties, the petitions are being
            <lb />
            disposed of as follows:
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (i)
            <lb />
            Hon&apos;ble Mr. Justice Badar Durrez Ahmad,
            <lb />
            former Chief Justice of Jammu &amp; Kashmir High Court
            <lb />
            (Retired) is appointed as Sole Arbitrator to adjudicate
            <lb />
            the disputes between the parties.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (ii)
            <lb />
            The learned Arbitrator will give disclosure
            <lb />
            under Section 12 of the Act.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (iii) The fee of the Sole Arbitrator will be as per the
            <lb />
            Fourth Schedule of the Act.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (iv) Bank Guarantees issued by Karnataka Bank
            <lb />
            Limited Branch, Vadodra bearing no. 17793BG00038
            <lb />
            dated 17.07.2017 and 17793BG00041 dated
            <lb />
            31.8.2017, have been encashed and the Demand Drafts
            <lb />
            are stated to be in possession of the respondent. The
            <lb />
            said Demand Drafts will not be encashed and will be
            <lb />
            deposited with the office of the Learned Arbitrator.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (v)
            <lb />
            Within 15 days of commencement of the
            <lb />
            arbitration proceedings, the petitioner will move an
            <lb />
            application under Section 17 of the Act for appropriate
            <lb />
            interim order. Needless to say that the Arbitrator
            <lb />
            would be free to continue/modify/vacate the order
            <lb />
            passed by this Court today.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            8.
            <lb />
            The demand draft lying with the respondent will not be
            <lb />
            encashed until further orders by the Arbitral Tribunal.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            9.
            <lb />
            On 14 th October, 2019, this Court also disposed of OMP (I)
            <lb />
            (Comm) 343/2019, by referring the dispute in the said case also to the
            <lb />
            same learned Arbitrator, i.e. Hon&apos;ble Mr. Justice Badar Durrez
            <lb />
            Ahmad (retired).
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            10. The contracts were rescinded, by the respondent, on 11 th
            <lb />
            October, 2019 and 22 nd October, 2019, as already stated in para 3
            <lb />
            supra.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            11. Joint proceedings are being conducted by the learned
            <lb />
            Arbitrator, in all these three matters.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            12. The appellant filed applications, before the learned Arbitrator,
            <lb />
            under Section 17 of the 1996 Act, as permitted by this Court in its
            <lb />
            orders dated 11 th October, 2019 and 14 th October, 2019 supra. These
            <lb />
            applications were disposed of, on 28 th November, 2019, by the learned
            <lb />
            Arbitrator, by consent, directing that the demand drafts be returned by
            <lb />
            the respondent to the appellant, in exchange for Bank Guarantees, for
            <lb />
            equivalent amounts, to be furnished by the appellant in favour of the
            <lb />
            respondent, which were to be kept alive during the arbitral
            <lb />
            proceedings, with a restraint on the respondent from encashing the
            <lb />
            Bank Guarantees.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            13. In the meanwhile, the appellant filed its Statements of Claims,
            <lb />
            in the three arbitral proceedings before the learned Arbitrator. For the
            <lb />
            purposes of the present appeal, I am not concerned with the
            <lb />
            contentions, on merits, contained in the Statement of Claim, or the
            <lb />
            grounds on which the appellant sought to deny the allegation, of the
            <lb />
            respondent, that it was in breach of the contract. I deem it
            <lb />
            appropriate, however, to reproduce paras 93 to 95 of the Statements of
            <lb />
            Claim, thus:
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;93. The Claimant submits that, the Respondent
            <lb />
            immediately after 48 hours notice without terminating the
            <lb />
            contract under the terms of the contract approached the
            <lb />
            Claimant&apos;s Branch Manager of Karnataka Bank, Vadodara
            <lb />
            Branch for the encashment of the above said performance
            <lb />
            guarantee on 04/10/2019. Thus, the contract in question has
            <lb />
            been put to an end by the Respondent is illegal and bad in
            <lb />
            law.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            94.
            <lb />
            The claimant submits that, Clause-8 of General
            <lb />
            Conditions of contract of which the relevant provisions of
            <lb />
            clause 8.4 (b) and (c) are reproduced as under:
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            8.4 (b) where the contract is rescind, the security
            <lb />
            deposit shall be forfeited and the Performance Security
            <lb />
            shall (be encashed) and the balance work shall be got
            <lb />
            done independently without risk and cost of the failed
            <lb />
            contractor. The failed contractor shall be debarred
            <lb />
            from participating in the tender for executing the
            <lb />
            balance work.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            8.4 (c) The Engineer shall not make a claim under the
            <lb />
            Performance Guarantee (PG) except for amounts to
            <lb />
            which IRCON International Limited is entitled under
            <lb />
            the contract (notwithstanding and/or without prejudice
            <lb />
            to any other provisions in the contract agreement) in
            <lb />
            the event of :-
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            1.
            <lb />
            Failure by the contractor to extend the
            <lb />
            validity of the PG as described hereinabove, in
            <lb />
            which event the Engineer may claim the full
            <lb />
            amount of the PG.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            2.
            <lb />
            Failure by the contract to pay Ircon
            <lb />
            International Limited any amount due, either as
            <lb />
            agreed by the contractor or determined under
            <lb />
            any of the Clauses/Conditions of the agreement,
            <lb />
            within 30 days of the service of notice to this
            <lb />
            effect by Engineer.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            3.
            <lb />
            The contract being determined or
            <lb />
            rescinded under provision of the GCC the PG
            <lb />
            shall be forfeited in full and shall be absolutely
            <lb />
            at the disposal of the Engineer.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            95.
            <lb />
            The claimant submits that, Clause 8.4 (b) provides for
            <lb />
            encashment of the performance Security only after the
            <lb />
            contract is rescinded, whereas in the present case the
            <lb />
            Respondent initiated action for invocation/encashment of the
            <lb />
            Bank Guarantee prior to termination/rescission of the
            <lb />
            contract. The contract was terminated/rescinded by the
            <lb />
            Respondent vide letter No. IRCON/3018/DFCCIL-CTP-
            <lb />
            12/SS3-SC/1086/1272 dtd. 11/10/2019.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            The invocation and encashment, by the respondent, of the Bank
            <lb />
            Guarantees furnished by the appellant was, therefore, assailed on the
            <lb />
            ground that the contractual provisions permitted such
            <lb />
            encashment/invocation only consequent on termination/rescission of
            <lb />
            the contract, and not prior thereto. This, as the discussion hereinafter
            <lb />
            would reveal, is an important circumstance.
            <lb />
            Thereafter, the
            <lb />
            Statements of Claim filed by the appellant also went on to assail the
            <lb />
            termination, by the respondent, of the contract, on various grounds.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            14. The respondent filed applications, before the learned Arbitrator,
            <lb />
            under Section 16 of the 1996 Act, essentially objecting to the
            <lb />
            inclusion, by the appellant, of the challenge to the termination, by the
            <lb />
            respondent, of the contract, in its Statements of Claim. The prayer
            <lb />
            clause in the applications, therefore, prayed that the learned Arbitral
            <lb />
            Tribunal &quot;be pleased to hold that it has jurisdiction to only adjudicate
            <lb />
            the disputes pertaining to the invocation of the BG and does not have
            <lb />
            jurisdiction to adjudicate any other disputes or claims raised by the
            <lb />
            Claimant in the present proceedings&quot;. A supplementary application
            <lb />
            was also preferred, by the respondent, before the learned Arbitrator,
            <lb />
            under Section 16 of the 1996 Act, praying that the learned Arbitral
            <lb />
            Tribunal acknowledge that it did not have the jurisdiction to arbitrate
            <lb />
            on claims, issues and disputes within the ambit of &apos;excepted matters&apos;
            <lb />
            under Clause 73 of the GCC. Clause 73.0 of the GCC read thus:
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;73.0 SETTLEMENT OF DISPUTES
            <lb />
            All disputes and differences of any kind whatsoever
            <lb />
            arising out of or in connection with the contract,
            <lb />
            whether during the progress of the work or after its
            <lb />
            completion and whether before or after the
            <lb />
            determination of the contract, shall be settled as under,
            <lb />
            provided that matters for which provision has been
            <lb />
            made in clauses 20.3, 36.5, 40.1, 40.2, 49.7, 50.0, 51.0,
            <lb />
            59.0, 61.2 and 72.2 of General Conditions of Contract
            <lb />
            or in any clause of the Special Conditions of Contract
            <lb />
            shall be deemed as &apos;excepted matters&apos; (matters not
            <lb />
            arbitrable) and decision of the Employer there are,
            <lb />
            shall be final and binding on the contractor; provided
            <lb />
            further that &apos;excepted matters&apos; shall stand specifically
            <lb />
            excluded from the purview of this clause.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            15. The appellant filed replies before the learned Arbitrator,
            <lb />
            opposing the aforesaid applications under Section 16, preferred by the
            <lb />
            respondent.
        </p>

        <p>
            16. The applications of the respondent, under Section 16, were
            <lb />
            disposed of, by the learned Arbitrator, vide a common Order dated 5 th
            <lb />
            March, 2021, which forms the subject matter of challenge in these
            <lb />
            appeals. Essentially, the learned Arbitrator reasoned/held thus:
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            (i)
            <lb />
            It was true that the prayer, in the OMPs filed under
            <lb />
            Section 9, by the appellant, was for stay of encashment of the
            <lb />
            Bank Guarantees provided by it. However, it was also true that
            <lb />
            the prayer was predicated on the circumstances leading to the
            <lb />
            issue of the 48 hour notices by the respondent and the
            <lb />
            impending termination of the contract.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            (ii) The use of the words &quot;disputes have arisen between the
            <lb />
            parties with respect to the said contract&quot;, as contained in para 5
            <lb />
            of the order dated 11 th October, 2019 supra, passed by this
            <lb />
            Court in the OMPs obviously referred &quot;to all the disputes which
            <lb />
            (had) been pointed out and brought to the notice of the court
            <lb />
            through the said section 9 petition&quot;, and could not &quot;be limited
            <lb />
            to only the question of invocation of the PBG&quot;. In fact, the
            <lb />
            issuance of the 7 day and 48 hour notices by the respondent was
            <lb />
            because disputes had arisen between the appellant and the
            <lb />
            respondent, pertaining to the contract. The mere fact that
            <lb />
            limited interim measures had been sought by the appellant, in
            <lb />
            its Section 9 petitions, did not &quot;circumscribe the arena of
            <lb />
            disputes between the parties&quot;.
        </p>

        <p>
            (iii) The words &quot;after some hearing, the parties have agreed to
            <lb />
            appoint a Sole Arbitrator to adjudicate upon the disputes arising
            <lb />
            between the parties&quot; and &quot;settlement has also been arrived at
            <lb />
            with respect to the invocation/encashment of the Bank
            <lb />
            Guarantees in question till the Arbitrator considers the
            <lb />
            application under Section 17 of the Act&quot;, as employed in para 6
            <lb />
            of the order of this Court, plainly read, indicated &quot;that there
            <lb />
            (had) been agreement/settlement on two aspects: (1) to appoint
            <lb />
            a Sole arbitrator to adjudicate upon the disputes arising between
            <lb />
            the parties; and (2) with regard to the invocation/encashment of
            <lb />
            the PBG which (had) been further elaborated in para 7(iv), 7(v)
            <lb />
            and 8 of the said order&quot;.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            (iv) Para-7 (i) of the order clearly indicated that the &quot;disputes
            <lb />
            between the parties&quot; were to be adjudicated by the learned
            <lb />
            Arbitrator.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            (v) Evidently, therefore, &quot;the disputes between the parties,
            <lb />
            not limited to the issue of invocation of the PBG were, by
            <lb />
            consent of the parties, referred to (the) Tribunal for
            <lb />
            adjudication&quot;. As such, &quot;the contention of the Respondent that
            <lb />
            the consent for arbitration given by the parties before the
            <lb />
            Hon&apos;ble High Court of Delhi was only limited to the issue of
            <lb />
            legality of invocation of the PBG (was) untenable and (was) not
            <lb />
            borne out of the said order passed by the Hon&apos;ble High Court&quot;.
            <lb />
            (vi) At the same time it was also evident that only those
            <lb />
            disputes which existed at the time of the passing of the order
            <lb />
            dated 11 th October, 2019 by this Court were referred to the
            <lb />
            Arbitrator for adjudication.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            (vii) Consequently, disputes pertaining strictly to the
            <lb />
            termination, which happened subsequently, and claims arising
            <lb />
            solely out of the termination, were not, as they could not have
            <lb />
            been, referred to the learned Arbitrator for adjudication.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            (viii) The respondent contended, before the Arbitrator, that he
            <lb />
            had no jurisdiction to arbitrate on the disputes as the conditions
            <lb />
            to arbitration, as set out in Clause 73 of the GCC had not been
            <lb />
            complied with. Relying, for the purpose, on Section 4 of the
            <lb />
            1996 Act 1 in this context, the respondent sought to contend that,
            <lb />
            as consent to arbitration had been given, by it, before this
            <lb />
            Court, limited to the legality of invocation of the Bank
            <lb />
            Guarantee, the respondent had not waived its right to object to
            <lb />
            any other dispute, within the meaning of Section 4. This
            <lb />
            contention was not tenable, as the consent to arbitration was
            <lb />
            given, before this Court, not limited to the issue of invocation
            <lb />
            of the Bank Guarantees, &quot;but covered all disputes which had
            <lb />
            reference in the claimant&apos;s petition under Section 9&quot;. As such,
            <lb />
            1 &quot;4.
            <lb />
        </p>
        <p>
            <lb />
            qua all such disputes, the respondents right to object to the
            <lb />
            jurisdiction of the learned Arbitrator, on the ground of non-
            <lb />
            fulfilment of preconditions for arbitration as contained in the
            <lb />
            GCC, stood waived.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            (ix) Specifically on the contention of the respondent that
            <lb />
            disputes and claims arising out of the termination of the
            <lb />
            contract could not be subject matter of arbitration in the
            <lb />
            proceedings before the learned Arbitrator, following on the
            <lb />
            order dated 11 th October, 2019 of this Court, as they were not in
            <lb />
            existence when the order was passed, the learned Arbitrator
            <lb />
            held thus, in para 15 of the impugned order:
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;The fourth contention of the learned counsel for the
            <lb />
            respondent was that disputes and claims arising out of
            <lb />
            termination of the contract were not in existence when
            <lb />
            the Hon&apos;ble High Court of Delhi passed its order dated
            <lb />
            11.10.2019 and as such they cannot be the subject
            <lb />
            matter of arbitration in the present proceedings. As
            <lb />
            already pointed out above, there is substance in this
            <lb />
            contention. However, a detailed examination of the
            <lb />
            claims raised by the Claimant would have to be
            <lb />
            undergone so as to separate those claims or part of
            <lb />
            those claims which arises solely out of the termination
            <lb />
            of the contract. The exercise, in my view, would have
            <lb />
            to be done at the final stage after evidence has been
            <lb />
            laid. The principle is clear that those claims which
            <lb />
            solely arise out of termination are not covered under
            <lb />
            the present reference by the Hon&apos;ble High Court by
            <lb />
            virtue of its order dated 11.10.2019. The actual
            <lb />
            separation and severance of such claims can only be
            <lb />
            done at a later stage as mentioned above.&quot;
            <lb />
            (Emphasis supplied)
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            (x) The contention, of the respondent, that &quot;excepted
            <lb />
            matters&quot; were outside the scope of arbitration, was
            <lb />
            unexceptionable, in view of Clause 73.0 of the GCC. This
            <lb />
            contention was accepted on principle, with the observation that
            <lb />
            the extent to which the claims of the appellant were &quot;excepted
            <lb />
            matters&quot;, if at all, could be assessed only after detailed scrutiny,
            <lb />
            once evidence in the case was complete. A specific issue to this
            <lb />
            effect had been framed.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            17. The impugned order, therefore, ends with the following
            <lb />
            conclusions:
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;20.1 The contention of the respondent that the consent for
            <lb />
            arbitration given by the parties before the Hon&apos;ble High Court
            <lb />
            of Delhi was only limited to the issue of legality of invocation
            <lb />
            of the PBG is untenable. At the same time, it is also evident
            <lb />
            that only those disputes which existed at the time of passing
            <lb />
            of the order dated 11.10.2019 by the Hon&apos;ble High Court of
            <lb />
            Delhi were referred to this Tribunal for adjudication.
            <lb />
            Consequently, disputes pertaining strictly to the termination,
            <lb />
            which happened subsequently, and claims arising solely out
            <lb />
            of the termination, in my view, were not, as they could not
            <lb />
            have been, referred to this Tribunal for adjudication in the
            <lb />
            present proceedings.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            20.2 The principle is clear that those claims which solely
            <lb />
            arise out of termination are not covered under the present
            <lb />
            reference by the Hon&apos;ble High Court by virtue of its order
            <lb />
            dated 11.10.2019. However, the actual separation and
            <lb />
            severance of such claims can only be done as a later stage as
            <lb />
            mentioned above.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            20.3 The waiver with regard to the pre-arbitration procedure
            <lb />
            specified in clause 73 of the GCC was not limited to the issue
            <lb />
            of invocation of the PBG but it also covered all the disputes
            <lb />
            which were opened before the Hon&apos;ble High Court.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            20.4 The reference to arbitration was by consent of the
            <lb />
            parties. This is specifically recorded in the said order dated
            <lb />
            11.10.2019 passed by the Hon&apos;ble High Court of Delhi.
            <lb />
            Therefore, the Respondent cannot contend that the pre-
            <lb />
            arbitration conditions spelt out in clause 73 of the GCC ought
            <lb />
            to have been complied with in respect of the disputes which
            <lb />
            were placed before the Hon&apos;ble High Court.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            20.5 It is correct that excepted matters are not arbitrable.
            <lb />
            The principle for deciding which matters can be regarded as
            <lb />
            &quot;excepted matters&quot; has also been explained above. However,
            <lb />
            to what extent the claims raised by the Claimant fall within
            <lb />
            the &quot;excepted matters&quot;, if at all, could not be decided without
            <lb />
            a detailed scrutiny which would be possible only after
            <lb />
            considering all the documents and evidence on record. This
            <lb />
            enquiry has to be postponed till the stage and will be decided
            <lb />
            under issue no. 2.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            20.6 The section 16 application as also the supplementary
            <lb />
            application under section 16 filed by the Respondent are
            <lb />
            disposed of in the aforesaid terms. This order shall govern
            <lb />
            not only these applications but also the parallel and virtually
            <lb />
            identical application in the matters arising out of OMP Nos.
            <lb />
            337/2019 and 343/2019.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            18. The appellant is essentially aggrieved by the finding, reflected
            <lb />
            in paras 20.1 and 20.2 of the impugned order, that disputes pertaining
            <lb />
            strictly to termination of the contract between the appellant and
            <lb />
            respondent, and claims arising solely out of such termination, were
            <lb />
            not amenable to adjudication in the arbitral proceedings before the
            <lb />
            learned Arbitrator. Additionally, Ms Meenakshi Arora, learned Senior
            <lb />
            Counsel for the appellant also assails the finding, in para 18 of the
            <lb />
            impugned Order, that claims prohibited by any clause in the SCC
            <lb />
            would, ipso facto, stand excluded from the ambit of the arbitration, as
            <lb />
            they would be &quot;excepted matters&quot;. This finding, she submits, is in the
            <lb />
            teeth of the law laid down by the Supreme Court in B.S.N.L. v
            <lb />
            Motorola India Pvt Ltd 2 .
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            Submissions of the appellant
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            19. I have heard Ms Meenakshi Arora, learned Senior Counsel for
            <lb />
            the appellant at length.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            20. Ms Arora assailed the decision of the learned Arbitrator to
            <lb />
            exclude, from the scope of the arbitral proceedings, the termination of
            <lb />
            the contract between the appellant and the respondent and all claims
            <lb />
            solely arising from such termination. She contended that a holistic
            <lb />
            reading of the order, dated 11 th October, 2019, of this Court, revealed
            <lb />
            that all &quot;disputes&quot;, between the appellant and the respondent stood
            <lb />
            referred to arbitration, by consent of the parties. The fact that the
            <lb />
            respondent had issued, to the appellant, notices, proposing to
            <lb />
            terminate the contract, was also noticed in the said order. The order,
            <lb />
            therefore, encompassed, within the scope of the &quot;disputes&quot; referred to
            <lb />
            arbitration, the termination proposed by the 7-day and, thereafter, the
            <lb />
            48-hour notices issued by the respondent to the appellant, even if no
            <lb />
            formal order of termination had been passed by then. Ms Arora
            <lb />
            pointed out that, having acted on the basis of the decision to terminate
            <lb />
            the appellant&apos;s contract by invoking the Bank Guarantees furnished by
            <lb />
            the appellant, issuance of a separate order of termination was a mere
            <lb />
            formality, and the respondent could not justifiably seek to exclude,
            <lb />
            2 (2009) 2 SCC 337
            <lb />
            from the ambit of the arbitral proceedings, the legality of the
            <lb />
            termination of the appellant&apos;s contract. She also contended that, in
            <lb />
            fact, the act of invocation of the Bank Guarantees, by the respondent,
            <lb />
            ipso facto resulted in termination of the contract between the appellant
            <lb />
            and the respondent. For this purpose, she sought to read, in
            <lb />
            conjunction, Clauses 50 and Clause 8.4(c)(3) of the GCC. These
            <lb />
            clauses, pointed out Ms Arora, permitted invocation of the Bank
            <lb />
            Guarantee only in the event of rescinding or termination of the
            <lb />
            contract between the appellant and the respondent. By invoking the
            <lb />
            Bank Guarantees, therefore, she submits, the respondent had exercised
            <lb />
            its authority under Clause 8.4(c)(3), which was available only in the
            <lb />
            event of termination. To that extent, submits Ms Arora, the contracts
            <lb />
            stood terminated by the invocation of the Bank Guarantees. At any
            <lb />
            rate, she submits, the letter dated 30 th September, 2019 concluded
            <lb />
            with the recital that the respondent would &quot;be constrained to initiate
            <lb />
            action for termination of contract as per Clause 50 of GCC&quot;. Issuance
            <lb />
            of a formal termination order was, therefore, she submits, a mere
            <lb />
            formality, which was inevitable in the circumstances. She invited my
            <lb />
            attention to the specific ground, urged before the learned Arbitrator
            <lb />
            and recorded in para 7 of the impugned Order, to the effect that &quot;the
            <lb />
            PBG could only be invoked post termination and since it had been
            <lb />
            invoked there was deemed termination prior to the passing of the
            <lb />
            order dated 11.10.2019 and therefore all disputes including the issue
            <lb />
            of termination was within the jurisdiction of this Tribunal&quot;.
        </p>

        <p>
            21. I posed, to Ms Arora, a hypothetical query. If, I suggested, no
            <lb />
            formal order of termination would have been issued by the
            <lb />
            respondent, after invoking the Bank Guarantees, would that not have
            <lb />
            constituted an independent ground for the appellant&apos;s to challenge the
            <lb />
            invocation as being violative of Clause 50 read with Clause 8.4(c)(3)
            <lb />
            of the GCC, which contemplated invocation, or forfeiture, of the
            <lb />
            security furnished by the appellant in the form of the Bank Guarantees
            <lb />
            only consequent upon determination/rescinding of the contract? Ms
            <lb />
            Arora, even while acknowledging that, in such a circumstance, the
            <lb />
            invocation of the Bank Guarantees could be assailed on the said
            <lb />
            ground, submits that the issue for consideration was different, viz. the
            <lb />
            scope and nature of the disputes which were referred, by this Court, to
            <lb />
            arbitration on 11 th October, 2019.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            22. Ms Arora also relied on sub-sections (2A), (3) and (4) of
            <lb />
            Section 23 3 of the 1996 Act. She submits that the very intent of
            <lb />
            inserting, in Section 23, sub-sections (2A) and (4) [the former by
            <lb />
            Section 11 of the Arbitration and Conciliation (Amendment) Act,
            <lb />
            2016 and the latter by Section 5 of the Arbitration and Conciliation
            <lb />
            (Amendment) Act, 2019] was to avoid multiplicity of litigation.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            3 &quot;23.
            <lb />
            Statement of claim and defence. -
            <lb />
            *****
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (2A)
            <lb />
            The respondent, in support of his case, may also submit a counter claim or plead a set off,
            <lb />
            which shall be adjudicated upon by the arbitral tribunal, if such counter claim or set off falls within
            <lb />
            the scope of the arbitration agreement.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (3)
            <lb />
            Unless otherwise agreed by the parties, either party may amend or supplement his claim
            <lb />
            or defence during the course of the arbitral proceedings, unless the arbitral Tribunal considers it
            <lb />
            inappropriate to allow the amendment or supplement having regard to the delay in making it.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (4)
            <lb />
            The statement of claim and defence under the section shall be completed within a period
            <lb />
            of six months from the date the arbitrator or all the arbitrators, as the case may be, received notice,
            <lb />
            in writing, of the appointment.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            <lb />
            Section 23(3) permitted rejection, of the prayer to amend the
            <lb />
            statement of claim, only on the ground of delay. Ms Arora also
            <lb />
            referred me to Section 2(9) 4 .
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            23. Ms. Arora further emphasised the comprehensive wording of
            <lb />
            the arbitration agreement between the appellant and the respondent,
            <lb />
            which covered &quot;all disputes and differences of any kind whatsoever
            <lb />
            arising out of or in connection with the contract, whether during the
            <lb />
            progress of the work or after its completion and whether before or
            <lb />
            after the determination of the contract&quot;. The termination of the
            <lb />
            contract was also, therefore, she submitted, a dispute referable to
            <lb />
            arbitration. Ms Arora exhorts this Court to interpret the order, dated
            <lb />
            11 th October, 2019, referring the parties to arbitration, as
            <lb />
            encompassing the legality of the termination of the contract, which
            <lb />
            was a foregone conclusion, as well. She points out that this Court did
            <lb />
            not limit or circumscribe the issues, or disputes, while referring the
            <lb />
            parties to arbitration.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            24. Ms Arora further submits that, if the legality of the termination,
            <lb />
            by the respondent, of the contract with the appellant, was not to be
            <lb />
            decided in the present arbitral proceedings, it would result in an
            <lb />
            incongruous situation, for various reasons. She submits that many of
            <lb />
            the claims of the appellant were predicated on the legality of the
            <lb />
            termination, and the appellant would stand foreclosed from having all
            <lb />
        </p>

        <head>
            4 &quot;2.
            <lb />
            Definitions
        </head>

        <item>
            . -
            <lb />
            *****
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (9)
            <lb />
            Where this Part, other than clause (a) of section 25 or clause (a) of sub-section (2) of
            <lb />
            section 32, refers to a claim, it shall also apply to a counter-claim, and where it refers to a defence,
            <lb />
            it shall also apply to a defence to that counter-claim.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            <lb />
            such claims arbitrated. Similarly, she submits, a piquant situation
            <lb />
            would arise, in which the legality of the invocation of the Bank
            <lb />
            Guarantees would be decided by one arbitral tribunal, and the legality
            <lb />
            of the termination, which is a contractual precondition for invoking
            <lb />
            the Bank Guarantees, would be decided by another. This would result
            <lb />
            in overlap of issues and multiplicity of proceedings which is required,
            <lb />
            at all costs, to be avoided. Ms Arora presses into service the
            <lb />
            judgement of the Supreme Court in State of Goa v. Praveen
            <lb />
            Enterprises 5 , which was also cited before the learned Arbitrator.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            25. Ms Arora also invoked Section 4 of the 1996 Act, to contend
            <lb />
            that, having failed to question the jurisdiction of the learned Arbitrator
            <lb />
            to entertain the challenge, of the appellant in its Statement of Claim,
            <lb />
            to the legality of the termination of the contract, the respondent was
            <lb />
            statutorily estopped from challenging said jurisdiction at a later stage.
            <lb />
            She points out that the first traversal, to the jurisdiction of the learned
            <lb />
            Arbitrator to entertain the challenge, of the appellant, to the
            <lb />
            termination of the agreement, was in the application under Section 16,
            <lb />
            filed as late as on 6 th May, 2020. This, she submits, indicates that the
            <lb />
            plea was by way of an afterthought, squarely barred by Section 4. She
            <lb />
            points out that this contention was specifically raised before the
            <lb />
            learned Arbitrator. Reliance has been placed, in this context, on para
            <lb />
            39 of the judgement of the Supreme Court in B.S.N.L. 2 . Ms Arora has
            <lb />
            also placed reliance on the judgement of a coordinate bench of this
            <lb />
            Court in A.K.M. Enterprises Pvt Ltd v. Ahluwalia Contract (India)
            <lb />
            Ltd 6 and invited my specific attention to para 2, 3, 5, 6, 10, 12 and 13
            <lb />
            of the said decision.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            26. Insofar as the findings of the learned Arbitrator regarding the
            <lb />
            &quot;excepted matters&quot; were concerned, Ms Arora is aggrieved by the
            <lb />
            finding that, where the claim is prohibited by any clause of the SCC, it
            <lb />
            would ipso facto fall within the definition of &quot;excepted matters&quot;.
            <lb />
            This, she submits, is contrary to the law laid down in B.S.N.L. 2 Ms
            <lb />
            Arora submits, however, that she would be satisfied if this finding, of
            <lb />
            the learned Arbitrator, is treated as prima facie in nature, reserving
            <lb />
            liberty to the appellant to establish, before the learned Arbitrator that,
            <lb />
            despite the said finding, any particular claim was amenable to
            <lb />
            arbitration.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            27. Finally, Ms Arora emphasises the distinction between appeals
            <lb />
            under Section 37(2), vis--vis challenges under Section 34 to final
            <lb />
            awards. She submits that the constraints on the Court, while
            <lb />
            exercising jurisdiction under Section 34, would not necessarily apply
            <lb />
            under Section 37. Impliedly, therefore, Ms Arora seeks to contend
            <lb />
            that the jurisdiction of the Court under Section 37 is wider than that
            <lb />
            under Section 34. However, she has not drawn my attention to any
            <lb />
            judicial authority, supporting the submission.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <head>
            Analysis
            <lb />
        </head>

        <p>
            28. Scope of Section 37(2) 7
        </p>

        <p>
            28.1 I may first address the last submission of Ms Arora that the
            <lb />
            jurisdiction of the Court under Section 37(2)(a) is wider than that
            <lb />
            under Section 34.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            28.2 Unquestionably, Section 37 purports to confer appellate power.
            <lb />
            Sub-section (1) thereof provides for appeals against orders passed by
            <lb />
            the Court under Section 34; in other words, it is in the nature of a
            <lb />
            second rung of challenge. As against this, Section 37(2) is in the
            <lb />
            nature of a first appeal, and is provided against orders passed by the
            <lb />
            arbitral tribunal under Section 16(2) or 16(3), or under Section 17.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            28.3 It is obvious that the legislature does not contemplate any
            <lb />
            difference in the extent of jurisdiction of the Court exercising
            <lb />
            appellate power under the two clauses of Section 37(2). In other
            <lb />
            words, the extent of appellate jurisdiction under Section 37(2)(a) and
            <lb />
            Section 37(2)(b) has to be regarded as equal, there being no statutory
            <lb />
            indication to the contrary.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            28.4 Whether under clause (a) or (b), the order of the Arbitral
            <lb />
            Tribunal, which is amenable to challenge before the Court, is
            <lb />
            indisputably interlocutory in nature. Indeed, if the order is not
            <lb />
            interlocutory, and finally decides any issue, the present appeal would
            <lb />
            7 &quot;37.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <head>Appealable</head>

        <item>
            orders. -
            <lb />
            *****
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (2)
            <lb />
            An appeal shall also like to a court from an order of the arbitral Tribunal -
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (a)
            <lb />
            accepting the plea referred to in sub-section (2) or sub-section (3) of section 16;
            <lb />
            or
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (b)
            <lb />
            granting or refusing to grant an interim measure under section 17.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            <lb />
            not be maintainable under Section 37(2), and the appellant would
            <lb />
            necessarily had to invoke the jurisdiction of the Court under Section
            <lb />
            34, in view of the position of law enunciated in Indian Farmers
            <lb />
            Fertiliser Cooperative Ltd v. Bhadra Products 8 .
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            28.5 If the submission of Ms Arora were to be accepted, it would
            <lb />
            imply that the jurisdiction of the Court to interfere, against an
            <lb />
            interlocutory order of the Arbitrator, would be more expansive than
            <lb />
            the jurisdiction available against the final award. To my mind, such
            <lb />
            an interpretation, of Section 37(2), would be incongruous and
            <lb />
            anomalous in equal measure. The scope of interference against
            <lb />
            interlocutory orders, classically, is far more circumscribed than the
            <lb />
            scope of interference against the final decision of the authority below.
            <lb />
            Section 37(2) cannot, in my view, be so read -in the absence of any
            <lb />
            statutory indication to that effect -as to turn this principle on its head.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            28.6 Besides, Section 37 falls, like Section 34, in Part I of the 1996
            <lb />
            Act and is, therefore, subject to the discipline of Section 5, which
            <lb />
            proscribes judicial intervention, in matters covered by Part I, except
            <lb />
            where also provided. The Supreme Court clearly held, in Bharat
            <lb />
            Sewa Sansthan v. Uttar Pradesh Electronics Corporation Ltd 9 , that
            <lb />
            &quot;main objective of the Act is to make provision for an arbitral
            <lb />
            procedure which is fair, efficient and capable of meeting the needs of
            <lb />
            the specific arbitration and to minimise the supervisory role of courts
            <lb />
            in the arbitral process and to permit an arbitral Tribunal to use
            <lb />
            mediation, conciliation or other procedures during the arbitral
            <lb />
            proceedings in settlement of disputes, etc.&quot;. Minimising of the
            <lb />
            supervisory role of courts in the arbitral process is, therefore, one of
            <lb />
            the sanctified aspirations of the Legislature, while enacting the 1996
            <lb />
            Act.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            28.7 In my considered opinion, this objective has to drive the
            <lb />
            approach of the Court, while exercising jurisdiction under any of the
            <lb />
            provisions contained in Part I of the 1996 Act. It must be borne in
            <lb />
            mind that the 1996 Act is an Act to foster and provide impetus to the
            <lb />
            arbitral process, and the sanctity thereof, and not an Act to clothe civil
            <lb />
            courts with jurisdiction. Exercise of jurisdiction by civil courts, under
            <lb />
            the 1996 Act has, therefore, necessarily to be extremely circumspect,
            <lb />
            keeping this guiding principle in mind.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            28.8 This Court has, in its recent decision in Dinesh Gupta v Anand
            <lb />
            Gupta 10 , held, on this aspect, as under (albeit in the context of
            <lb />
            Section 37(2)(b)):
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;40. Oftentimes, the question arises as to whether the
            <lb />
            jurisdiction of the High Court, under Section 37, is subject to
            <lb />
            the same circumscriptions as formed by its jurisdiction under
            <lb />
            Section 34. Mr. Nayar had submitted, before me, that it would
            <lb />
            be folly to restrict the jurisdiction of the High Court, under
            <lb />
            Section 37, by the principles which apply to Section 34. He
            <lb />
            had sought to emphasise that the jurisdiction vested in the
            <lb />
            Court by Section 37 was appellate, unlike Section 34.
            <lb />
            Appellate jurisdiction, by its very nature, Mr. Nayar had
            <lb />
            sought to submit, is wider than the jurisdiction which applies
            <lb />
            to consideration of objections against an arbitral award.
            <lb />
            Appellate jurisdiction encompasses, within its fold, the power
            <lb />
            10 MANU/DE/1727/2020
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            to review findings of fact and, in fact, the appellate court is,
            <lb />
            jurisprudentially, an extension of the original court, the
            <lb />
            appeal being a continuation of the original proceedings. As
            <lb />
            such, Mr. Nayar had sought to submit, the High Court,
            <lb />
            exercising appellate jurisdiction under Section 37, should not
            <lb />
            feel restricted by the constraints which govern its jurisdiction
            <lb />
            under Section 34.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            41.
            <lb />
            Empirically viewed, Mr. Nayar&apos;s submissions appear
            <lb />
            attractive. There is, undoubtedly, qualitatively, a distinction
            <lb />
            between appellate jurisdiction and &quot;judicial review
            <lb />
            jurisdiction&quot;. Appellate jurisdiction, equally, is classically
            <lb />
            regarded as an extension of original jurisdiction, the appellate
            <lb />
            proceedings being an extension of the original proceedings.
            <lb />
            The appellate court is, therefore, ordinarily, empowered to re-
            <lb />
            appreciate findings of fact entered by the original court. That
            <lb />
            the jurisdiction of the appellate court is much wider than the
            <lb />
            jurisdiction of a Court exercising judicial review, of any other
            <lb />
            kind, is also, classically, well settled.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            42.
            <lb />
            Legal principles are, however, in every instance,
            <lb />
            required to be applied to the factual scenario, in which their
            <lb />
            application is invited. While, therefore, appreciating the
            <lb />
            jurisdiction of the High Court, under Section 37 of the 1996
            <lb />
            Act, we are required to be aware of the fact that the order,
            <lb />
            interference with which is being invited, was passed by an
            <lb />
            arbitrator, or arbitral tribunal. The sanctity attached to arbitral
            <lb />
            awards, especially in the context of the 1996 Act-which is
            <lb />
            based on the UNCITRAL model-has, therefore, necessarily to
            <lb />
            be borne in mind, while exercising jurisdiction over the
            <lb />
            decision of the arbitrator, whether in the form of a final
            <lb />
            award, or an interim award under Section 17.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            43.
            <lb />
            In the opinion of this Court, another important, and
            <lb />
            peculiar, feature of the 1996 Act, which must necessarily
            <lb />
            inform the approach of the High Court, is that the 1996 Act
            <lb />
            provides for an appeal against interlocutory orders, whereas
            <lb />
            the final award is not amenable to any appeal, but only to
            <lb />
            objections under Section 34. If the submission of Mr. Nayar,
            <lb />
            as advanced, were to be accepted, it would imply that the
            <lb />
            jurisdiction of the Court, over the interlocutory decision of
            <lb />
            the arbitrator, would be much wider than the jurisdiction
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            against the final award. Though, jurisprudentially, perhaps,
            <lb />
            such a position may not be objectionable, it does appear
            <lb />
            incongruous, and opposed to the well settled principle that the
            <lb />
            scope of interference with interim orders, is, ordinarily, much
            <lb />
            more restricted than the scope of interference with the final
            <lb />
            judgment.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            44.
            <lb />
            Here, yet another peculiar dispensation, in the 1996
            <lb />
            Act, apropos the scope of interference with the decision of the
            <lb />
            arbitrator, manifests itself. The proviso to Section 36 (3)
            <lb />
            ordains that the Court, while considering an application for
            <lb />
            grant of stay of a final arbitral award for payment of money,
            <lb />
            shall &quot;have due regard to the provisions for grant of stay of a
            <lb />
            decree under the provisions of the Code of Civil Procedure,
            <lb />
            1908&quot;. By reference, therefore, Order 41 Rule 5 of the CPC,
            <lb />
            which deals with stay, by the appellate court, of original
            <lb />
            decrees, stands incorporated into Section 36(3) of the 1996
            <lb />
            Act. Though, therefore, the final arbitral award is not made
            <lb />
            amenable to appeal, by the 1996 Act, any prayer for stay of
            <lb />
            the arbitral award, that accompanies objections under Section
            <lb />
            34, is required to be examined in the light of the provisions,
            <lb />
            in the CPC, governing stay of original decrees, in exercise of
            <lb />
            appellate jurisdiction. Though, for the purposes of this
            <lb />
            judgment, it is not necessary to psychoanalyse the legislative
            <lb />
            intent in providing for such a peculiar dispensation, the fact
            <lb />
            that applications for stay of final arbitral awards, are required
            <lb />
            to be considered on the basis of the principles governing stay,
            <lb />
            by appellate courts, under Order 41 Rule 5 of the CPC,
            <lb />
            indicate, to an extent, that the principles of Order 41 are also
            <lb />
            required to be borne in mind, while exercising appellate
            <lb />
            jurisdiction, under Section 37.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            45.
            <lb />
            The 1996 Act is, preambularly, a fallout of the United
            <lb />
            Nation&apos;s Commission on International Trade Law
            <lb />
            (UNCITRAL), adopted in 1995 as the Model Law on
            <lb />
            International Commercial Arbitration. The Statement of
            <lb />
            Objects and Reasons, preceding the 1996 Act, stipulates, in
            <lb />
            paras 2 to 5 thereof, as under, in this respect:
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;2.
            <lb />
            The United Nations Commission on
            <lb />
            International Trade Law (UNCITRAL) adopted in
            <lb />
            1985 the Model Law on International Commercial
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            Arbitration. The General Assembly of the United
            <lb />
            Nations has recommended that all countries give due
            <lb />
            consideration to the said Model Law, in view of the
            <lb />
            desirability of uniformity of the law of arbitral
            <lb />
            procedures and the specific needs of international
            <lb />
            commercial arbitration practise. The UNCITRAL also
            <lb />
            adopted in 1980 a set of Conciliation Rules. The
            <lb />
            General Assembly of the United Nations has
            <lb />
            recommended the use of these Rules in cases where
            <lb />
            the disputes arise in the context of international
            <lb />
            commercial relations and the parties seek amicable
            <lb />
            settlement of the disputes by recourse to conciliation.
            <lb />
            An important feature of the UNCITRAL Model Law
            <lb />
            and Rules is that they have harmonized concepts on
            <lb />
            arbitration and conciliation of different legal systems
            <lb />
            of the world and thus contains provisions which are
            <lb />
            designed for universal applications.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            3.
            <lb />
            Though the said UNCITRAL Model Law and
            <lb />
            Rules are intended to deal with International
            <lb />
            Commercial Arbitration and Conciliation, they could,
            <lb />
            with appropriate modifications, serve as a model for
            <lb />
            legislation on domestic arbitration and conciliation.
            <lb />
            The present Bill seeks to consolidate and amend the
            <lb />
            law relating to domestic arbitration, international
            <lb />
            commercial arbitration, enforcement of foreign arbitral
            <lb />
            awards and to define the law relating to conciliation,
            <lb />
            taking into account the said UNCITRAL Model Law
            <lb />
            and Rules.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            4.
            <lb />
            The main objectives of the Bill are as under:-
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            a.
            <lb />
            to comprehensively cover international
            <lb />
            and commercial arbitration and conciliation as
            <lb />
            also domestic arbitration and conciliation;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            b.
            <lb />
            to make provision for an arbitral
            <lb />
            procedure which is fair, efficient and capable of
            <lb />
            meeting the needs of the specific arbitration;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            c.
            <lb />
            to provide that the arbitral tribunal gives
            <lb />
            reasons for its arbitral award;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            d.
            <lb />
            to ensure that the arbitral tribunal
            <lb />
            remains within the limits of its jurisdiction;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            e.
            <lb />
            to minimize the supervisory role of the
            <lb />
            courts in the arbitral process;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            f.
            <lb />
            to permit an arbitral tribunal to use
            <lb />
            mediation, conciliation or other procedure
            <lb />
            during the arbitral proceedings to encourage
            <lb />
            settlement of disputes;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            g.
            <lb />
            to provide that every final arbitral award
            <lb />
            is enforced in the same manner as if it were a
            <lb />
            decree of the court;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            h.
            <lb />
            to provide a settlement agreement
            <lb />
            reached by the parties as a result of conciliation
            <lb />
            proceedings will have the same status and effect
            <lb />
            as an arbitral award on agreed terms on the
            <lb />
            substance of the dispute rendered by an arbitral
            <lb />
            tribunal; and
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            i.
            <lb />
            to provide that, for purposes of
            <lb />
            enforcement of foreign awards, every arbitral
            <lb />
            award made in a country to which one of the
            <lb />
            two international Conventions relating to
            <lb />
            foreign arbitral awards to which India is a party
            <lb />
            applies, will be treated as a foreign awards.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            5.
            <lb />
            The Bill seeks to achieve the above objects.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            46.
            <lb />
            The Supreme Court has, in Chloro Controls (I) Ltd. v.
            <lb />
            Severn Trent Water Purification Inc. 11 , held that the
            <lb />
            legislative intent and essence of the 1996 Act &quot;is to bring
            <lb />
            domestic as well as international commercial arbitration in
            <lb />
            consonance with the UNCITRAL Model Rules, the New
            <lb />
            York Convention and Geneva Convention&quot;. The afore-
            <lb />
            extracted passages, from the Statements of Object and
            <lb />
            Reasons of the 1996 Act has, necessarily, to guide the Court,
            <lb />
            while interpreting the provisions thereof. While on the point,
            <lb />
            it may be noted that, in Bharat Sewa Sansthan v. U.P.
            <lb />
            Electronics Corporation Ltd. 9 , the Supreme Court has clearly
            <lb />
            held the &quot;main objective of the (1996) Act&quot; as being &quot;to make
            <lb />
            provision for an arbitral procedure which is fair, efficient and
            <lb />
            capable of meeting the needs of the specific arbitration and to
            <lb />
            minimise the supervisory role of courts in the arbitral process
            <lb />
            and to permit an arbitral Tribunal to use mediation, the
            <lb />
            conciliation or other procedures during the arbitral
            <lb />
            proceedings in settlement of disputes, etc.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            47.
            <lb />
            There can be no gainsaying the proposition, therefore,
            <lb />
            that, while exercising any kind of jurisdiction, over arbitral
            <lb />
            orders, or arbitral awards, whether interim or final, or with
            <lb />
            the arbitral process itself, the Court is required to maintain
            <lb />
            an extremely circumspect approach. It is always required to
            <lb />
            be borne, in mind, that arbitration is intended to be an avenue
            <lb />
            for &quot;alternative dispute resolution&quot;, and not a means to
            <lb />
            multiply, or foster, further disputes. Where, therefore, the
            <lb />
            arbitrator resolves the dispute, that resolution is entitled to
            <lb />
            due respect and, save and except for the reasons explicitly set
            <lb />
            out in the body of the 1996 Act, is, ordinarily, immune from
            <lb />
            judicial interference.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            48.
            <lb />
            Interestingly, while examining, in Snehadeep
            <lb />
            Structures (P) Ltd. v. Maharashtra Small Scale Industries
            <lb />
            Development Corporation Ltd. 12 , the scope of the expression
            <lb />
            &quot;appeal&quot; as employed in Section 7 of the Interest on Delayed
            <lb />
            Payments to Small Scale and Ancillary Undertakings Act,
            <lb />
            1993, the Supreme Court held that, &quot;if the meaning of
            <lb />
            &quot;appeal&quot; is ambiguous, the interpretation that advances the
            <lb />
            object and purpose of the legislation, shall be accepted.&quot;
            <lb />
            Purposive interpretation, as has been noticed in Shailesh
            <lb />
            Dhairyawan v. Mohan Balkrishna Lulla 13 and Richa
            <lb />
            Mishra v. State of Chhattisgarh 14 , has, over time, replaced
            <lb />
            the principle of &quot;plain reading&quot; as the golden rule, for
            <lb />
            interpreting statutory instruments.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            49.
            <lb />
            In my opinion, this principle has to guide, strongly, the
            <lb />
            approach of this Court, while dealing with a challenge such as
            <lb />
            the present, which is directed against an order which, at an
            <lb />
            interlocutory stage, merely directing furnishing of security, by
            <lb />
            one of the parties to the dispute. The power, of the learned
            <lb />
            Sole Arbitrator, to direct furnishing of security, is not under
            <lb />
            question; indeed, in view of sub-clause (b) of Section 17 (1)
            <lb />
            (ii) of the 1996 Act, it cannot. The arbitrator is, under the said
            <lb />
            sub-clause, entirely within his jurisdiction in securing the
            <lb />
            amount in dispute in the arbitration. Whether, in exercising
            <lb />
            such jurisdiction, the arbitrator has acted in accordance with
            <lb />
            law, or not, can, of course, always be questioned. While
            <lb />
            examining such a challenge, however, the Court has to be
            <lb />
            mindful of its limitations, in interfering with the decision of
            <lb />
            the arbitrator, especially a decision taken at the discretionary
            <lb />
            level, and at an interlocutory stage.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            50.
            <lb />
            One may also refer, in this context, to Section 5 of the
            <lb />
            1996 Act, which reads as under:
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            &quot;5. Extent of judicial intervention.-Notwithstanding
            <lb />
            anything contained in any other law for the time being
            <lb />
            in force, in matters covered by this Part, no judicial
            <lb />
            authority shall intervene except where so provided in
            <lb />
            this Part.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            It is, no doubt, possible to argue that the intent, of Section 5,
            <lb />
            is to restrict judicial intervention, with arbitral proceedings,
            <lb />
            and orders passed therein, to the avenues for such
            <lb />
            interference, as provided by Part I of the 1996 Act, and not to
            <lb />
            restrict the scope of the Sections and the provisions contained
            <lb />
            in Part I. Perhaps. Section 5 remains, however, a clear pointer
            <lb />
            to the legislative intent, permeating the 1996 Act, that judicial
            <lb />
            interference, with arbitral proceedings, is to be kept at a
            <lb />
            minimum. Significantly, in Venture Global Engineering v.
            <lb />
            Satyam Computer Services Ltd. 15 , it was opined that the
            <lb />
            scheme of the 1996 Act was &quot;such that the general provisions
            <lb />
            of Part I, including Section 5, will apply to all Chapters or
            <lb />
            Parts of the Act&quot;. In State of Kerala v. Somdatt Builders
            <lb />
            Ltd. 16 , a Division Bench of the Kerala High Court held that
            <lb />
            the jurisdiction of the Court, under Section 37 of the 1996
            <lb />
            Act, was also required to be interpreted in the light of the
            <lb />
            legislative policy contained in Section 5. I entirely agree.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            51.
            <lb />
            The principle of least intervention by courts was held,
            <lb />
            in Enercon (India) Ltd. v. Enercon Gmbh 17 , to be well-
            <lb />
            recognised in arbitration jurisprudence, in almost all
            <lb />
            jurisdictions. In a similar vein, earlier in point of time, the
            <lb />
            Supreme Court held, in P. Anand Gajapathi Raju v. P. V. G.
            <lb />
            Raju 18 , that Section 5 &quot;brings out clearly the object of the
            <lb />
            new Act, namely, that of encouraging resolution of disputes
            <lb />
            expeditiously and less expensively and when there is an
            <lb />
            arbitration agreement, the court&apos;s intervention should be
            <lb />
            minimal.&quot; Likewise, albeit in the context of Section 34, it was
            <lb />
            held, in McDermott International Inc. v. Burn Standard Co.
            <lb />
            Ltd. 19 , thus:
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            &quot;The 1996 Act makes provision for the supervisory
            <lb />
            role of courts, for the review of the arbitral award only
            <lb />
            to ensure fairness. Intervention of the court is
            <lb />
            envisaged in few circumstances only, like, in case of
            <lb />
            fraud or bias by the arbitrators, violation of natural
            <lb />
            justice, etc. the court cannot correct errors of the
            <lb />
            arbitrators. It can only quash the award leaving the
            <lb />
            parties free to begin the arbitration again if it is
            <lb />
            desired. So, the scheme of the provision aims at
            <lb />
            keeping the supervisory role of the court at minimum
            <lb />
            level and this can be justified as the parties to the
            <lb />
            agreement make a conscious decision to exclude the
            <lb />
            court&apos;s jurisdiction by opting for arbitration as they
            <lb />
            prefer the expediency and finality offered by it.&quot;
            <lb />
            (Emphasis supplied)
            <lb />
            Though the above exposition of the law is in the context of
            <lb />
            Section 34, the principles enunciated therein embody the
            <lb />
            general philosophy underlying the 1996 Act. The italicised
            <lb />
            words, towards the conclusion of the paragraph, especially,
            <lb />
            would apply, with equal force, to challenges to interlocutory
            <lb />
            orders of arbitral tribunals, under Section 37, as they would,
            <lb />
            to challenges to the final award, under Section 34.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            52.
            <lb />
            Section 37 is, in a sense, a somewhat peculiar
            <lb />
            provision as, against the decision of the arbitrator, it provides
            <lb />
            for a first appeal, as well as a second appeal, to the High
            <lb />
            Court. Sub-section (1) provides for an appeal, to the High
            <lb />
            Court, from the decision of the Section 34 Court, before
            <lb />
            which the final award has, in the first instance, been tested.
            <lb />
            Sub-section (2), on the other hand, provides for a first appeal,
            <lb />
            against interlocutory orders of the arbitral tribunal under
            <lb />
            Section 16 or Section 17. There is, necessarily, a qualitative
            <lb />
            difference between these two challenges, though both would
            <lb />
            lie to the High Court. The challenge under Section 37(1),
            <lb />
            which is directed against a final award of the
            <lb />
            arbitrator/arbitral tribunal, is akin to a second appeal, as was
            <lb />
            observed by this Court in M.T.N.L. v. Fujitshu India Pvt.
            <lb />
            Ltd. 20 . The challenge under Section 37(2), on the other hand,
            <lb />
            is directed against the decision of the arbitral tribunal and has
            <lb />
            therefore, in my opinion, necessarily to conform to the
            <lb />
            discipline enforced by Section 5. It would, therefore, be
            <lb />
            improper for a Court to treat an appeal, under Section 37 (2)
            <lb />
            of the 1996 Act, as akin to an appeal under the CPC, or as
            <lb />
            understood in ordinary-or extraordinary-civil law. An appeal
            <lb />
            against an order by an arbitrator, or by an arbitral tribunal, is
            <lb />
            an appeal sui generis, and interference, by the Court, in such
            <lb />
            appeals, has to be necessarily cautious and circumspect.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            28.9 Ms Arora has not cited any authority which would
            <lb />
            contradistinguish the principles to be applied while exercising
            <lb />
            jurisdiction under Section 37(2), with those applicable to exercise of
            <lb />
            jurisdiction under Section 34. Given the overarching objectives of the
            <lb />
            1996 Act, I am of the opinion that there is really no substantial
            <lb />
            difference between the two.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            28.10 Consequently, this Court, while exercising jurisdiction under
            <lb />
            Section 37(2)(a) over the impugned order of the letter Arbitrator,
            <lb />
            20 2015 (2) Arb LR 332 (Delhi)
            <lb />
            would only examine whether the order suffers from any patent
            <lb />
            illegality or perversity, or is otherwise unconscionable in law on facts.
            <lb />
            The Court does not, therefore, &quot;re-arbitrate&quot; the application decided
            <lb />
            by the learned Arbitrator. If the interpretation of the learned
            <lb />
            Arbitrator is plausible, I would be extremely loath to interfere
            <lb />
            therewith, especially at an interlocutory stage of the arbitral
            <lb />
            proceedings.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            29. Pared down to its essentials, I do not really see that the
            <lb />
            impugned Order, or the view expressed by the learned Arbitrator
            <lb />
            therein, merits interference by the Court. The learned Arbitrator has
            <lb />
            held that the order of termination of the contract, as well as claims
            <lb />
            depended solely on the said order, could not constitute part of the
            <lb />
            arbitral proceedings, as the contract was terminated after the passing
            <lb />
            of the order, dated 11 th October, 2019, by this Court. I am unable to
            <lb />
            understand how this interpretation could be said to be patently illegal,
            <lb />
            perverse, or would otherwise merit interference at the hands of the
            <lb />
            Court.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            30. The jurisdiction of the learned Arbitrator would,
            <lb />
            unquestionably, be governed by the terms of the order dated 11 th
            <lb />
            October, 2019, of this Court. Para 7 of the order, constituting the
            <lb />
            operative portion thereof, appointed the learned Arbitrator &quot;to
            <lb />
            adjudicate the disputes between the parties&quot;. The expression &quot;the
            <lb />
            disputes&quot;, etymologically, would have to refer to the disputes to which
            <lb />
            the earlier paras of the order allude. Para 5 of the order states thus:
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            &quot;Disputes have arisen between the parties with respect to the
            <lb />
            said contract&quot;.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            The phrase &quot;have arisen&quot; is in the present perfect tense. It refers,
            <lb />
            therefore, to disputes which existed, in praesenti, on the date when the
            <lb />
            order was passed. In Dolphin Drilling v O.N.G.C. 21 , the Supreme
            <lb />
            Court held that the word &quot;all disputes&quot;, as employed in the arbitration
            <lb />
            agreement in that case, &quot;can only mean &quot;all disputes&quot; that might be in
            <lb />
            existence when the arbitration clause is invoked and one of the parties
            <lb />
            to the agreement gives the arbitration notice to the other&quot;. The notices
            <lb />
            terminating the contract, in the present appeals, were all issued after
            <lb />
            the passing of the concerned referral orders by this Court and were
            <lb />
            not, therefore, in existence on the date when the disputes were
            <lb />
            referred to arbitration. On those dates, the contract between the
            <lb />
            parties was, as yet, not terminated qua the concerned packages.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            31. Apparently cognizant of this factual position, Ms Arora made a
            <lb />
            valiant effort to submit that, by invocation of the Bank Guarantees,
            <lb />
            the contract, ipso facto, stood terminated, even if no &quot;formal&quot; order of
            <lb />
            termination had yet been issued. The contention, quite obviously, has
            <lb />
            been merely to be stated to be rejected. As advanced, the contention
            <lb />
            is contrary both to Clause 50 as well as Clause 8.4 (b) and 8.4 (c)(3)
            <lb />
            of the GCC. A bare reading of these clauses makes it apparent that
            <lb />
            invocation of the Bank Guarantee is a consequence of termination.
            <lb />
            Clause 8.4 (b) states that &quot;whenever the contract is rescind (sic
            <lb />
            rescinded?), the security deposit shall be forfeited and the
            <lb />
            Performance Security shall be encashed. Parallelly, Clause 8.4(c)(3)
            <lb />
            permits the Engineer to make a claim under the Bank Guarantees &quot;in
            <lb />
            the event of the contract being determined or rescinded under the
            <lb />
            provisions of the GCC&quot;, in which case &quot;the PG shall be forfeited in
            <lb />
            full and shall be absolutely at the disposal of the Engineer&quot;.
            <lb />
            Invocation of the Bank Guarantees could not, therefore, in any event,
            <lb />
            terminate, proprio vigore, the contract between the appellant and the
            <lb />
            respondent. The submission of Ms Arora, if accepted, would amount
            <lb />
            to placing the cart before the horse.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            32. As I have already noted hereinbefore, a pointed query was put,
            <lb />
            to Ms Arora, as to whether, if no order of termination had been issued
            <lb />
            after the Bank Guarantees were encashed, that, by itself, would not
            <lb />
            constitute a ground to challenge the encashment of the Bank
            <lb />
            Guarantees. Ms Arora answered in the affirmative. Significantly,
            <lb />
            even in the Statement of Claim filed before the learned Arbitrator, the
            <lb />
            appellant has challenged the invocation of the Bank Guarantees on the
            <lb />
            ground that, prior to termination of the contract, such invocation was
            <lb />
            not permissible. Having thus taken a stand, both in its pleadings
            <lb />
            before the learned Arbitrator as well as in response to the query posed
            <lb />
            by the Court, that the respondents were not entitled to invoke the
            <lb />
            Bank Guarantees before the contract was terminated, the appellant
            <lb />
            cannot, quite obviously, be urged to contend that, by invocation of the
            <lb />
            Bank Guarantees, the contract stood terminated. That would amount
            <lb />
            to canvassing a stand directly contrary to the pleadings before the
            <lb />
            learned Arbitrator which, quite obviously, is not permissible. While it
            <lb />
            is open to a party to take alternative, contrary, pleas, a party cannot
            <lb />
            advance a contention before a court which is directly opposed to the
            <lb />
            stand taken in the pleadings. In any event, Clause 8.4(b) and 8.4(c)(3)
            <lb />
            of the GCC completely eviscerate the contention of Ms Arora that the
            <lb />
            invocation of the Bank Guarantees itself amounted to termination of
            <lb />
            the contract.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            33. I am, in fact, unaware of any contract in which it is open to a
            <lb />
            contracting party to terminate the contract by invoking the
            <lb />
            Performance Security or encashing the Bank Guarantee furnished in
            <lb />
            respect thereof. It is, in fact, difficult to conceive that any
            <lb />
            commercially sensitive contracting party would, willy-nilly, put his
            <lb />
            signature to a contract which permitted invocation of the Bank
            <lb />
            Guarantee even before the contract was terminated. Termination of
            <lb />
            the contract, axiomatically, requires a formal declaration to that effect,
            <lb />
            in writing by the party terminating the contract to the other
            <lb />
            contracting party. The contention of Ms Arora that, by invoking the
            <lb />
            Bank Guarantees furnished by the appellant, the respondent had
            <lb />
            effectively terminated the contract is, therefore, also contrary to the
            <lb />
            basic &quot;common sense&quot; of commercial contracts. It is, accordingly,
            <lb />
            rejected.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            34. The fallout is, therefore, that, as correctly held by the learned
            <lb />
            Arbitrator, the contract was not terminated on the date of passing, by
            <lb />
            this Court, of its order of reference, i.e. on 11 th October, 2019.
            <lb />
            Termination of the contract may have appeared imminent but, on
            <lb />
            facts, could not be treated as inevitable. This Court referred, to
            <lb />
            arbitration, the disputes which &quot;have arisen&quot; between the parties as on
            <lb />
            that date. To that extent, the contention, of Ms Arora, that this Court
            <lb />
            had not limited or circumscribed the ambit of the disputes referred to
            <lb />
            arbitration, cannot be accepted. Clearly, the intent of the Court was to
            <lb />
            refer, to arbitration, only the disputes which had arisen, till that date
            <lb />
            and which existed, as on that date, and not disputes relating to events
            <lb />
            which were to take place in the future. No order terminating the
            <lb />
            contract having been issued by the respondent till the date of the
            <lb />
            order, the view, of the learned Arbitrator, that disputes relating to the
            <lb />
            legality of validity of the termination, or claims arising from such
            <lb />
            termination, were not arbitrable before him in the present arbitral
            <lb />
            proceedings, could not be regarded as suffering from patent illegality,
            <lb />
            or a view which was unconscionable either in fact or in law. At the
            <lb />
            very least, it is a plausible view, which is sufficient to dispel any
            <lb />
            attempt, by the Court, to interfere therewith.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            35. No attempt was made by the appellant, even after the filing of
            <lb />
            the application under Section 16 by the respondent, to seek a
            <lb />
            clarification, from this Court, as to whether the &quot;disputes&quot; covered by
            <lb />
            the order dated 11 th October, 2019, would encompass the termination
            <lb />
            of the contract which took place thereafter. In the absence of any such
            <lb />
            clarification, the learned Arbitrator cannot be faulted for the view
            <lb />
            expressed by him in the impugned Order.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            36. The reliance, by Ms Arora, on Section 23(3) of the 1996 Act is,
            <lb />
            in my opinion, misplaced. Section 23(3) deals with the right of a
            <lb />
            party to amend or supplement the Statement of Claim or Statement of
            <lb />
            Defence during the course of the arbitral proceedings. No such
            <lb />
            application was filed by the appellant. Section 23(3) does not,
            <lb />
            consequently, even fall for consideration in the present case.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            37. Similarly, Section 4 of the 1996 Act is also of no application
            <lb />
            whatsoever. A bare reading of the said provision makes it apparent
            <lb />
            that it caters to objections by one or the other party to the arbitration
            <lb />
            to raise objections regarding non-compliance with any requirement
            <lb />
            under the arbitration agreement. Quite obviously, this clause does not
            <lb />
            deal with objections regarding jurisdiction, or to the maintainability,
            <lb />
            or arbitrability, of claims. Moreover, Section 16 has not, statutorily,
            <lb />
            been made subject to Section 4 or to any other provision of the 1996
            <lb />
            Act.
            <lb />
            No authority, for the proposition that an objection to
            <lb />
            maintainability of the claim, as being beyond the scope of arbitration,
            <lb />
            could be rejected merely because it was not taken immediately upon
            <lb />
            filing of the Statement of Claim, has been brought to my notice. The
            <lb />
            contention of Ms Arora that the plea of non-arbitrability, in the
            <lb />
            presently pending proceedings before the learned Arbitrator, of the
            <lb />
            legality of the termination by the respondent of the agreement with the
            <lb />
            appellant, was an &quot;afterthought&quot; and had, therefore, to be rejected as
            <lb />
            belated, cannot, therefore, be accepted. Equally, I am unable to
            <lb />
            subscribe to the contention of Ms Arora that, by operation of Section
            <lb />
            4, the respondent was estopped from raising the said plea, or that the
            <lb />
            respondent has waived its right to do so.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            38. Praveen Enterprises 5 , too, in my view, cannot help the
            <lb />
            appellant; rather, it may, properly read, militate against the stand
            <lb />
            canvassed by Ms Arora. Para 11 of the said decision, on Ms
            <lb />
            Arora placed especial reliance, reads thus:
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;11. Reference to arbitration can be in respect of all
            <lb />
            disputes between the parties or all disputes regarding a
            <lb />
            contract or in respect of specific enumerated disputes. Where
            <lb />
            &quot;all disputes&quot; are referred, the arbitrator has the jurisdiction to
            <lb />
            decide all disputes raised in the pleadings (both claims and
            <lb />
            counterclaims) subject to any limitations placed by the
            <lb />
            arbitration agreement. Where the arbitration agreement
            <lb />
            provides that all disputes shall be settled by arbitration but
            <lb />
            excludes certain matters from arbitration, then, the arbitrator
            <lb />
            will exclude the excepted matter and decide only those
            <lb />
            disputes which are arbitrable. But where the reference to the
            <lb />
            arbitrator is to decide specific disputes enumerated by the
            <lb />
            parties/court/appointing
            <lb />
            authority,
            <lb />
            the
            <lb />
            arbitrator&apos;s
            <lb />
            jurisdiction is circumscribed by the specific reference and the
            <lb />
            arbitrator can decide only those specific disputes.&quot;
            <lb />
            (Emphasis supplied)
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            Para 11 of the decision in Praveen Enterprises 5 would be better
            <lb />
            appreciated if read in conjunction with para 12, which may be
            <lb />
            reproduced, therefore, thus:
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;12. Though an arbitration agreement generally provides
            <lb />
            for settlement of future disputes by reference to arbitration,
            <lb />
            there can be &quot;ad hoc&quot; arbitrations relating to existing
            <lb />
            disputes. In such cases, there is no prior arbitration agreement
            <lb />
            to refer future disputes to arbitration. After a dispute arises
            <lb />
            between the parties, they enter into an arbitration agreement
            <lb />
            to refer that specific dispute to arbitration. In such an
            <lb />
            arbitration, the arbitrator cannot enlarge the scope of
            <lb />
            arbitration by permitting either the claimant to modify or add
            <lb />
            to the claim or the respondent to make a counterclaim. The
            <lb />
            arbitrator can only decide the dispute referred to him, unless
            <lb />
            the parties again agree to refer the additional
            <lb />
            disputes/counterclaims to arbitration and authorise the
            <lb />
            arbitrator to decide them.&quot;
            <lb />
            (Emphasis supplied)
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            Though rendered in the context of ad hoc arbitrations, the concluding
            <lb />
            sentence in the afore extracted para 12 of the judgement in Praveen
            <lb />
            Enterprises 5 applies, mutatis mutandis, to the present case, and also
            <lb />
            aids in appreciating the extent to which para 11 would apply.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            39. The learned Arbitrator has taken the view that the order, dated
            <lb />
            11 th October, 2019, referred, to him, only disputes which were in
            <lb />
            existence on that date and did not, therefore, cover the legality of the
            <lb />
            termination order which was yet to be issued. The view is, in my
            <lb />
            view, undoubtedly plausible.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            40. The sequitur would be that the disputes referred to the learned
            <lb />
            Arbitrator would only be those disputes which were existing, in
            <lb />
            praesenti, on 11 th October, 2019, when the order was passed by the
            <lb />
            Court. Packages SS3-B and SS2-C were terminated on 11 th October,
            <lb />
            2019, but a reading of the order passed by this Court, on the said date,
            <lb />
            indicates that, at the time of passing the order, the order of termination
            <lb />
            had yet to be served on the appellant. I may note, here, that it is
            <lb />
            nobody&apos;s case -and, indeed, Ms Arora, too, does not advance the
            <lb />
            initial submission -that this Court was seized with the fact that the
            <lb />
            contract already stood terminated, qua these packages. Indeed, a
            <lb />
            reading of the order dated 11 th October, 2019, makes it apparent that,
            <lb />
            till the passing of the said order, at least, no termination of the
            <lb />
            contract had taken place or, at the very least, that this Court was never
            <lb />
            made aware of any such order of termination. Qua Package SS2-C,
            <lb />
            the contract was terminated on 22 nd October, 2019, after the passing of
            <lb />
            the order, by this Court, on 14 th October, 2019. In any event, Ms
            <lb />
            Arora does not dispute the factual position that, at the time of passing
            <lb />
            of the concerned referral orders by this Court, the contract, qua the
            <lb />
            package(s) forming subject matter thereof, was yet to be terminated.
            <lb />
            The learned Arbitrator was, therefore, prima facie justified in taking
            <lb />
            the view that this Court did not refer, or intend to refer, for arbitration,
            <lb />
            the legality of the actual order of termination which came to be passed
            <lb />
            on 11 th October, 2019 or 22 nd October, 2019, or any claims arising as
            <lb />
            a result thereof.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            41. Whether any other view was possible, or not, is not for this
            <lb />
            Court to deliberate upon. Any such exercise would transgress the
            <lb />
            authority vested in it by law. Once the Court finds that the view taken
            <lb />
            by the learned Arbitrator was a plausible view, then, given the
            <lb />
            pervading philosophy of the 1996 Act, which is to minimise
            <lb />
            interference, by Courts, with the arbitral process, the Court must
            <lb />
            necessarily step back and decline to interfere.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            42. The expansive contours of the arbitration agreement, as
            <lb />
            contained in the GCC, too, cannot help the appellant. Undoubtedly,
            <lb />
            the arbitration agreement covers &quot;all disputes and differences of any
            <lb />
            kind whatsoever arising out of or in connection with the contract
            <lb />
            whether before or after the determination of the contract&quot;. Ms Arora
            <lb />
            maybe right in her contention that the termination of the contract was
            <lb />
            also a dispute referrable to arbitration. The question is, however, not
            <lb />
            whether the dispute was referrable to arbitration, but whether it had
            <lb />
            been referred to arbitration by this Court on 11 th October, 2019 and
            <lb />
            14 th October, 2019. As the Supreme Court observed in Praveen
            <lb />
            Enterprises 5 , once there was a specific reference to arbitration, the
            <lb />
            arbitration would have to abide by the terms of such reference, and
            <lb />
            only those disputes, which were referred to arbitration, could be
            <lb />
            arbitrated. The order, dated 11 th October, 2019, specifically referred,
            <lb />
            to arbitration, disputes which &quot;have arisen between the parties&quot;. To
            <lb />
            the same effect is the order dated 14 th October, 2019. Plainly, the
            <lb />
            order of termination not having been passed till then, the legality, or
            <lb />
            otherwise, thereof, or any claims consequent thereto, could not be
            <lb />
            regarded as disputes which &quot;had arisen&quot;, till then, between the parties.
            <lb />
            The jurisdiction of the learned Arbitrator having been circumscribed
            <lb />
            by the order of reference of this Court, no fault can be found with the
            <lb />
            interpretation, by the learned Arbitrator, that the reference did not
            <lb />
            encompass the legality, or otherwise, of the order of termination,
            <lb />
            which came to be passed later.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            43. The challenge, by the appellant, to the impugned Order dated
            <lb />
            5 th March, 2021, insofar as it excludes, from the scope of the arbitral
            <lb />
            proceedings, disputes regarding the legality of the order of termination
            <lb />
            of the contract between the appellant and the respondent, as well as
            <lb />
            claims based on such termination, therefore, fails.
        </p>

        <p>
            44. Insofar as the challenge to the finding, of the learned Arbitrator,
            <lb />
            regarding non-arbitrability of &quot;excepted&quot; matters, is concerned, while
            <lb />
            no patent error may be found even in that regard, Ms Arora restricts
            <lb />
            the prayer to an observation, by this Court, that the finding of the
            <lb />
            learned Arbitrator may be treated as prima facie in nature. To the
            <lb />
            limited extent, I see no objection to accede to the submission of Ms.
            <lb />
            Arora. While, therefore, not interfering with the finding, of the
            <lb />
            learned Arbitrator, that excepted matters were not amenable to
            <lb />
            arbitration, it is clarified that the finding would be treated as prima
            <lb />
            facie in nature. The appellant would, therefore, be at liberty, at the
            <lb />
            stage of final hearing before the learned Arbitrator, to argue against
            <lb />
            such prima facie finding. I am inclined to grant this much latitude to
            <lb />
            the appellant only as the impugned order has been passed at the
            <lb />
            interlocutory stage, and keeping in mind the interests of an
            <lb />
            expeditious resolution of the arbitral exercise.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <head>
            Conclusion
            <lb />
        </head>

        <p>
            45. Subject to the limited caveat in para 44 supra, the appeals are,
            <lb />
            consequently, dismissed in limine, with no orders as to costs.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            C. HARI SHANKAR, J.
            <lb />
            MAY 18, 2021
        </p>


    </table>
</tei>