<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<p>
			1.
			<lb />
			The hearing was conducted through video conferencing.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			2.
			<lb />
			Petitioner impugns order dated 16.12.2020 passed by the
			<lb />
			Institute of Chartered Accountants of India dismissing the complaint
			<lb />
			filed by the petitioner against respondent No. 3.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			3.
			<lb />
			The case set up by the petitioner is that respondent No. 3 has
			<lb />
			committed professional misconduct and submitted incorrect reports
			<lb />
			after scrutiny of the books and papers of the certain companies.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			4.
			<lb />
			A petition for merger was filed by M/s Napean Trading and
			<lb />
			Investment Company Private Limited, M/s Regal Trading and
			<lb />
			Investment Company Private Limited, M/s Vidhya Trading and
			<lb />
			Investment Company Private Limited and M/s Harsham Investment
			<lb />
			and Trading Company Private Limited. The first three mentioned
			<lb />
			companies were to be amalgamated into the fourth company.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			5.
			<lb />
			The scheme of arrangement of amalgamation was filed before
			<lb />
			the High Court of Karnataka. The High Court of Karnataka appointed
			<lb />
			respondent No. 3 for the purposes of verification of the books and
			<lb />
			papers of the three transferor companies and to submit his report.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			6.
			<lb />
			Respondent No.3 submitted his reports on 25.11.2014 to the
			<lb />
			Karnataka High Court. By order dated 26.03.2015, the scheme of
			<lb />
			merger was sanctioned by the Karnataka High Court.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			7.
			<lb />
			Petitioner is neither a shareholder in any of the companies nor
			<lb />
			was respondent No.3 ever associated with the petitioner in any
			<lb />
			manner.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			8.
			<lb />
			The contention of the learned counsel for the petitioner is that
			<lb />
			petitioner is a public spirited citizen and has noticed that the reports
			<lb />
			that were submitted to the Karnataka High Court were not correct and
			<lb />
			accordingly filed a complaint before the Institute of Chartered
			<lb />
			Accountants of India for taking disciplinary action against respondent
			<lb />
			No. 3.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			9.
			<lb />
			By the impugned order, the Disciplinary Committee of the
			<lb />
			Institute of Chartered Accountants has dismissed the complaint inter
			<lb />
			alia holding as under:-
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot;5. The Committee further noted that the Respondent
				<lb />
				conducted the audit on behalf of the Respondent firm whereby
				<lb />
				he, on verification of records, gave his opinion in the reports to
				<lb />
				the official liquidator. Thus, the Committee viewed that the
				<lb />
				appointment of the Respondent was made under the Orders of
				<lb />
				the Hon&apos;ble High Court of Karnataka and that the reports
				<lb />
				prepared by him were placed before and considered by the
				<lb />
				Hon&apos;ble High Court of Karnataka. Accordingly, the Committee
				<lb />
				was of the view that the said report of the auditor was the
				<lb />
				property of the Hon&apos;ble High Court of Karnataka which alone
				<lb />
				could pass any order on the same. It also noticed that the
				<lb />
				matter was sub judice and the Committee had no jurisdiction to
				<lb />
				take cognizance of the same. It is only the Hon&apos;ble High Court
				<lb />
				of Karnataka which can take a view on the Report of the
				<lb />
				Respondent. The Committee can take any action in the matter
				<lb />
				only if an order to this effect is passed by the Hon&apos;ble High
				<lb />
				Court of Karnataka and its continuing with an inquiry in the
				<lb />
				present complaint would not be appropriate. Accordingly, the
				<lb />
				extant complaint was dismissed by the Committee.
			</item>
			<lb />
			<item>
				Conclusion:
			</item>
			<lb />
			<item>
				6.
				<lb />
				Thus, the Committee dismissed the extant Complaint.
				<lb />
				However, the Complainant has right to file case before the
				<lb />
				Disciplinary mechanism of the Institute with the copy of Order
				<lb />
				of the Hon&apos;ble High Court of Karnataka. &quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			10. Petitioner aggrieved by order of dismissal of his complaint has
			<lb />
			filed the subject petition.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			11. On 08.02.2021, Petitioner was directed to file an affidavit,
			<lb />
			within 2 weeks, indicating his connection with respect to the
			<lb />
			companies in respect of which subject audit was conducted by
			<lb />
			respondent No.3. Said order also records the contention of learned
			<lb />
			counsel of the petitioner that petitioner is not a creditor of the said
			<lb />
			company.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			12. Petitioner impugned order dated 08.02.2021 of this Court by
			<lb />
			filing a Letters Patent Appeal. Said Letters Patent Appeal was
			<lb />
			dismissed on 01.03.2021 on the ground that no conclusive
			<lb />
			determination of rights and liabilities of the parties had been done by
			<lb />
			the said order.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			13. The Division Bench while dismissing the LPA imposed costs of
			<lb />
			Rs. 10,000/-on the petitioner to be deposited with the Delhi State
			<lb />
			Legal Services Authority within four weeks.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			14. The Division Bench by its order dated 01.03.2021 also directed
			<lb />
			the learned counsel for the petitioner to take instructions with regard
			<lb />
			to the deposit of costs imposed in respect of the several orders passed
			<lb />
			in various petitions filed by the Petitioner before the Delhi High
			<lb />
			Court. In Paragraph 5 the Division Bench extracted the list of such
			<lb />
			cases. Said list is as under:-
			<lb />
		</p>
		<figure type="table">
			SI.
			<lb />
			No.
			<lb />
			Case Details
			<lb />
			Date of
			<lb />
			Or der
			<lb />
			Bench
			<lb />
			Costs
			<lb />
			1.
			<lb />
			Wholesale Trading
			<lb />
			Services Pvt. Ltd. v.
			<lb />
			UOI;
			<lb />
			WP(C) 5602/2017
			<lb />
			07.07.2017 Division
			<lb />
			bench of the
			<lb />
			Hon&apos;ble
			<lb />
			Delhi High
			<lb />
			Court
			<lb />
			Imposed
			<lb />
			as
			<lb />
			costs on the
			<lb />
			Appellant
			<lb />
			Rs.10,000/-
			<lb />
			2.
			<lb />
			Wholesale Trading
			<lb />
			Services Pvt. Ltd. v.
			<lb />
			UOI;
			<lb />
			WP(C) 10536/2017
			<lb />
			04.12.2017 Hon&apos;ble
			<lb />
			Delhi High
			<lb />
			Court
			<lb />
			Payable
			<lb />
			to
			<lb />
			Delhi
			<lb />
			High
			<lb />
			Court
			<lb />
			Legal
			<lb />
			Services
			<lb />
			Committee
			<lb />
			within a period
			<lb />
			of three weeks,
			<lb />
			imposed on the
			<lb />
			Appellant.
			<lb />
			Rs.10,000/-
			<lb />
			3.
			<lb />
			Wholesale Trading
			<lb />
			Services Pvt. Ltd. v.
			<lb />
			ICAI &amp; Ors;
			<lb />
			WP(C) 8071/2019
			<lb />
			04.12.2017 Hon&apos;ble
			<lb />
			Delhi High
			<lb />
			Court
			<lb />
			Payable
			<lb />
			to
			<lb />
			Delhi
			<lb />
			High
			<lb />
			Court
			<lb />
			Legal
			<lb />
			Services
			<lb />
			Committee
			<lb />
			within a period
			<lb />
			of two weeks,
			<lb />
			imposed on the
			<lb />
			Appellant.
			<lb />
			Rs.10,000/-
			<lb />
			4.
			<lb />
			Wholesale Trading
			<lb />
			Services Pvt. Ltd. v.
			<lb />
			ICAI &amp; Ors;
			<lb />
			WP(C) 8081/2019
			<lb />
			01.08.2019 Hon&apos;ble
			<lb />
			Delhi High
			<lb />
			Court
			<lb />
			Rs.1,00,000/-
			<lb />
			payable
			<lb />
			to
			<lb />
			Delhi
			<lb />
			High
			<lb />
			Court
			<lb />
			Legal
			<lb />
			Services
			<lb />
			Committee
			<lb />
			within a period
			<lb />
			of two weeks,
			<lb />
			imposed on the
			<lb />
			Appellant. This
			<lb />
			order has been
			<lb />
			sustained by the
			<lb />
			Hon&apos;ble
			<lb />
			Division Bench
			<lb />
			of this Hon&apos;ble
			<lb />
			Court in
			<lb />
		</figure>
		<p>
			15. Learned counsel for the petitioner concedes that the costs as
			<lb />
			imposed by the Division Bench by its order dated 01.03.2021 as also
			<lb />
			the costs imposed by various orders noticed in Paragraph 5 of the
			<lb />
			Division Bench order, extracted hereinabove, have not been
			<lb />
			deposited.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			16. Learned counsel for the petitioner further submits that affidavit
			<lb />
			in terms of order dated 08.02.2021 directing the petitioner to indicate
			<lb />
			his connection with the companies in respect of which subject audit
			<lb />
			was conducted by respondent No. 3 has not been filed. He submits
			<lb />
			that Petitioner has no connection either with the companies or with
			<lb />
			Respondent No. 3 -the chartered accountant.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			17. It is submitted by learned senior counsel appearing for the
			<lb />
			respondent No.3 that petitioner and his counsel Mr. R. Subramanian
			<lb />
			have been instrumental in fomenting litigation and harassing
			<lb />
			respondent No.3.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			18. It is submitted that the scheme of merger was sanctioned by the
			<lb />
			Karnataka High Court on 26.03.2015 and thereafter, an application
			<lb />
			was filed in the said company petition before the High Court of
			<lb />
			Karnataka by an entity called &quot; India Awake for Transparency&quot;
			<lb />
			seeking recall of the sanction.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			19. It is submitted that one of the grounds taken in the said
			<lb />
			application seeking recall of the order of merger was the same as
			<lb />
			taken in the complaint against respondent No.3 i.e., challenge to the
			<lb />
			reports submitted by respondent No. 3 before the Karnataka High
			<lb />
			Court.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			20. The recall application has been dismissed by the Karnataka
			<lb />
			High Court by its order dated 17.03.2021 holding that applicant was
			<lb />
			not a party to the main petition and did not has the locus standi to file
			<lb />
			the application.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			21. Said order records that applicant was not an aggrieved party as
			<lb />
			was neither a shareholder nor a director or any other person who is
			<lb />
			connected to or has a nexus with the parties to the proceedings or the
			<lb />
			impugned order. The order also records that the applicant was guilty
			<lb />
			of abuse of process of law, as the claim of the applicant had been
			<lb />
			rejected not only by Ministry of Corporate Affairs but also by the
			<lb />
			Reserve Bank of India.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			22. It is pointed out by learned senior counsel appearing for
			<lb />
			respondent No. 3 that an appeal filed by the said applicant against the
			<lb />
			order dated 17.03.2021 being OSA 1/2021 was also dismissed on
			<lb />
			24.02.2021 by the Division Bench of Karnataka High Court.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			23. One very peculiar fact emerges from a perusal of order dated
			<lb />
			17.03.2021 of the Karnataka High Court and that is that the said
			<lb />
			application filed by India Awake for Transparency shows that its
			<lb />
			authorised signatory is Mr. R. Subramanian, the counsel appearing for
			<lb />
			the petitioner herein.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			24. Further, it may be seen that respondent No. 3 was appointed,
			<lb />
			the Karnataka High Court, to scrutinise the accounts and the books of
			<lb />
			the three companies, which were sought to be merged in the fourth
			<lb />
			company. After scrutiny, the reports were submitted before the
			<lb />
			Karnataka High Court. After perusal of the reports, the Karnataka
			<lb />
			High Court had sanctioned the merger on 26.03.2015.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			25. Karnataka High Court has dismissed the application for recall
			<lb />
			of the merger, in which one of the grounds was that the reports
			<lb />
			submitted by respondent No. 3 were not correct, on the ground that
			<lb />
			the applicant has no locus to challenge the same.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			26. The Disciplinary Committee of the Institute of Chartered
			<lb />
			Accountants has also passed the impugned order holding that since
			<lb />
			respondent No.3 was appointed by the Karnataka High Court and
			<lb />
			reports were submitted to it for the purposes of sanction of merger, it
			<lb />
			is only the Karnataka High Court which could comment upon the
			<lb />
			reports and only if any order to the said effect was passed by the High
			<lb />
			Court of Karnataka, any inquiry could be conducted by the
			<lb />
			Disciplinary Committee.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			27. What the petitioner and his advocate, Mr. R. Subramanian are
			<lb />
			seeking to do is to start parallel proceedings to challenge the sanction
			<lb />
			of merger by Karnataka High Court. As noticed by the Karnataka
			<lb />
			High Court as also admitted by the petitioner and Mr. R. Subramanian
			<lb />
			that the petitioner or Mr. R. Subramanian are neither shareholders, nor
			<lb />
			directors or any person connected or having a nexus to the parties to
			<lb />
			the scheme of merger.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			28. Since the petitioner has no connection or locus and in fact
			<lb />
			counsel for the petitioner has himself sought to challenge the scheme
			<lb />
			of merger which was rejected by the Karnataka High Court by its
			<lb />
			order dated 17.03.2021, I find no ground to permit petitioner to start
			<lb />
			parallel proceedings to challenge a scheme of merger which has been
			<lb />
			sanctioned by the Karnataka High Court, before this Court or
			<lb />
			indirectly challenge the same by way of asking the Institute of
			<lb />
			Chartered Accountants to return a finding on the reports submitted by
			<lb />
			respondent No.3 before the Karnataka High Court and acted upon by
			<lb />
			it.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			29. I find no infirmity in the view taken by the Disciplinary
			<lb />
			Committee of the Institute of Chartered Accountants that as
			<lb />
			respondent No.3 was appointed by Karnataka High Court and reports
			<lb />
			were submitted to the Karnataka High Court, it is only the High Court
			<lb />
			of Karnataka, which could take a view on the reports submitted by
			<lb />
			respondent No.3.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			30. Accordingly, I find no merit in this petition. The Petition is
			<lb />
			dismissed with costs, which is quantified at Rs.50,000/-.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			31. In view of the admission of learned counsel for the petitioner
			<lb />
			that petitioner has not deposited the costs imposed by the Division
			<lb />
			Bench by its order dated 01.03.2021 and also by various orders of this
			<lb />
			Court as noticed by the Division Bench in its order dated 01.03.2021,
			<lb />
			the Registry is directed not to register and list any petition or
			<lb />
			proceedings filed by the petitioner till petitioner encloses therewith
			<lb />
			the receipts of deposit of costs in the said cases mentioned
			<lb />
			hereinabove.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			32. Copy of the Order be uploaded on the High Court website and
			<lb />
			be also forwarded to learned counsels through email by the Court
			<lb />
			Master.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			SANJEEV SACHDEVA, J.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			MAY 13, 2021
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			NA
			<lb />
		</p>
	</text>
</tei>
