<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc xml:id="0" />
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <p>
            1.
            <lb />
            The petitioner has filed the present petition under Section 34 of
            <lb />
            the Arbitration and Conciliation Act, 1996 (hereinafter the ‗A&amp;C
            <lb />
            Act&apos;) impugning an arbitral award dated 02.12.2020 to the extent that
            <lb />
            the Arbitral Tribunal has not awarded pre-reference interest in respect
            <lb />
            of petitioner&apos;s Claim Nos. 1 to 4.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            2.
            <lb />
            The respondent (hereinafter ‗the DDA&apos;) had issued a notice
            <lb />
            inviting tenders for the work of -Construction of 1600 SFS houses
            <lb />
            category II &amp; III at Trilok Puri, Pocket &apos;B&apos; SH: Construction of 160
            <lb />
            SFS houses category II &amp; III 80 Nos. Two bedroom category II, 80
            <lb />
            nos. three bedroom category III &amp; 120 scooter garages under SFS
            <lb />
            pocket &apos;E&apos; including internal development Group V‖.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            3.
            <lb />
            Subsequently, by a letter dated 10.03.1986, the DDA awarded
            <lb />
            the said work to the petitioner. The works were to be completed within
            <lb />
            a period of twelve months from the 10 th day of issuance of the letter of
            <lb />
            award, that is, by 20.03.1987. The petitioner states that it completed
            <lb />
            the contracted works on 29.08.1989 and there appears to be no dispute
            <lb />
            that the works were taken over by the DDA. However, the petitioner
            <lb />
            states that the completion of the works was not recorded and the
            <lb />
            petitioner&apos;s final bill was not made. The petitioner claims that it was
            <lb />
            informed that the Quality Control Cell of the DDA had inspected the
            <lb />
            works and therefore, the final bill could not be finalised until the
            <lb />
            Quality Control observations were closed. The petitioner claims that it
            <lb />
            continued to pursue with the DDA for processing its final bill.
            <lb />
            However, the DDA did not do so. The petitioner further claims that it
            <lb />
            was informed by the DDA that the original agreement executed
            <lb />
            between the parties was not traceable. The petitioner states that
            <lb />
            thereafter, the DDA directed the petitioner to handover surplus store
            <lb />
            material so that the final bill could be prepared by the department. The
            <lb />
            petitioner complied with the said direction, but the DDA failed to
            <lb />
            finalise the bill. The petitioner had issued a Bank Guarantee, which
            <lb />
            was renewed from time to time as the preparation of the final bill was
            <lb />
            pending.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            4.
            <lb />
            The petitioner by its letter dated 09.04.2007 once again
            <lb />
            requested the DDA to finalise the bill. However, the same was not
            <lb />
            done.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            5.
            <lb />
            Aggrieved by the inaction on the part of the DDA in not
            <lb />
            releasing the payments and not finalising its bill, the petitioner
            <lb />
            approached the Grievance Cell of the DDA. On 26.06.2009, the
            <lb />
            petitioner&apos;s complaint to the Grievance Cell was referred to the
            <lb />
            concerned office.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            6.
            <lb />
            By a letter dated 10.12.2010, the Executive Engineer Eastern
            <lb />
            Division No.3, DDA informed the petitioner that its case was under
            <lb />
            active consideration. Thereafter, the DDA constituted a Committee to
            <lb />
            examine the petitioner&apos;s complaint. The said Committee submitted its
            <lb />
            report on 05.01.2011. The petitioner claims that the Committee
            <lb />
            recommended that the amount withheld, be released.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            7.
            <lb />
            The petitioner claims that thereafter, on 17.01.2011, the
            <lb />
            petitioner was informed that the Final Bill had been prepared and was
            <lb />
            lying in the DDA&apos;s office. The petitioner claims that the said Final
            <lb />
            Bill was not in conformity with the measurements recorded by the
            <lb />
            DDA in various measurement books. However, the said Bill was
            <lb />
            accepted by the petitioner under protest. Thereafter, on 31.01.2011,
            <lb />
            the petitioner submitted its Final Bill in accordance with the
            <lb />
            measurements recorded in various measurement books.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            8.
            <lb />
            Thereafter, the DDA released part payment for a sum of
            <lb />
            ₹1,64,000/-to the petitioner by a cheque dated 16.03.2011.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            9.
            <lb />
            The disputes between the parties persisted and after exchange of
            <lb />
            some correspondence, the petitioner issued a legal notice dated
            <lb />
            11.07.2011 for recovery of the balance payment. In all, the petitioner
            <lb />
            raised thirteen claims in its notice. The petitioner claims that by a
            <lb />
            letter dated 18.07.2011, the DDA responded to the said notice
            <lb />
            admitting two of the claims but denied the others.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            10. In view of the aforesaid disputes, by its letter dated 20.07.2011,
            <lb />
            the petitioner invoked the arbitration and sought reference of the
            <lb />
            disputes to an arbitrator. The petitioner also filed a petition under
            <lb />
            Section 9 of the A&amp;C Act (OMP No. 514/2013) before this Court,
            <lb />
            inter alia, praying that the DDA be directed to deliver the
            <lb />
            measurement books in the custody of the Chief Engineer, DDA. This
            <lb />
            was to ensure that the said measurement books are kept safely and are
            <lb />
            not tampered with.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            11. The above petition (OMP No. 514/2013) was disposed of by
            <lb />
            this Court by an order dated 09.09.2013, inter alia, recording the
            <lb />
            DDA&apos;s contention that six of the given measurement books would be
            <lb />
            produced before the learned Arbitrator and the balance three
            <lb />
            measurement books would be produced as and when directed by the
            <lb />
            learned Arbitrator.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            12.
            <lb />
            By its letter dated 12.07.2013, the DDA appointed Sh.
            <lb />
            Lakhvinder Chaudhary, S.E. (Arbn.), DDA as the Sole Arbitrator to
            <lb />
            adjudicate the disputes between the parties. Sh. Lakhvinder Chaudhary
            <lb />
            was thereafter transferred and in his place, Sh. S.K. Jain, S.E. (Arbn.)
            <lb />
            was appointed as the Sole Arbitrator on 14.02.2014.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            13.
            <lb />
            Sh. S.K. Jain also resigned as an Arbitrator as he too was
            <lb />
            transferred before the conclusion of the arbitral proceedings.
            <lb />
            Thereafter, the DDA appointed Sh. D.V. Raghav as the Sole
            <lb />
            Arbitrator. The learned Arbitrator made its award on 09.06.2016
            <lb />
            dismissing the petitioner&apos;s claim on the ground of limitation.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            14. Aggrieved by the arbitral award, the petitioner filed a petition
            <lb />
            for setting aside the award [OMP(COMM) 443/2016]. The said
            <lb />
            petition was allowed and by an order dated 27.03.2019, this Court set
            <lb />
            aside the arbitral award dated 09.06.2016.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            15. The DDA filed an appeal [FAO(OS)(COMM) 275/2019]
            <lb />
            against the said order, which was also dismissed by the Division
            <lb />
            Bench of this Court by an order dated 27.03.2019.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            16. Thereafter, on 23.05.2019, the competent authority of DDA
            <lb />
            appointed Sh. M.C.T. Pareva as the Sole Arbitrator to adjudicate the
            <lb />
            disputes between the parties. The learned Arbitrator made his award
            <lb />
            on 02.12.2020, which is impugned in the present petition.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            17.
            <lb />
            Before the Arbitral Tribunal, the petitioner raised seven claims
            <lb />
            which are briefly tabulated below:
        </p>
        <lb />
        <table>
            Claim No.1
            <lb />
            ₹1,00,000/-on account of refund of security
            <lb />
            deposit.
            <lb />
            Claim No.2
            <lb />
            ₹54,44,450/-on account of work executed and
            <lb />
            measured in the measurement books by DDA but
            <lb />
            not paid.
            <lb />
            Claim No.3
            <lb />
            ₹18,50,000/-on account of escalation in terms of
            <lb />
            Clause 10-CC of the General Conditions of
            <lb />
            Contract.
            <lb />
            Claim No.4
            <lb />
            ₹7,60,000/-on account of amount withheld in
            <lb />
            various bills.
            <lb />
            Claim No.5
            <lb />
            ₹5,65,892/-on account of interest on delayed
            <lb />
            payment of ₹1,64,000/-released on 16.03.2011.
            <lb />
            Claim No.6
            <lb />
            Pre-suit, pendente-lite and future interest at the
            <lb />
            rate of 12% per annum with monthly rest.
            <lb />
            Claim No.7
            <lb />
            Cost of arbitration.
            <lb />
        </table>

        <p>
            18. The DDA resisted the claims principally on the ground that the
            <lb />
            same were barred by limitation. The Arbitral Tribunal did not accept
            <lb />
            the aforesaid contention and partly allowed the claims made by the
            <lb />
            petitioner. The Arbitral Tribunal found that the security deposit of
            <lb />
            ₹1,00,000/-paid by the petitioner was liable to be released on
            <lb />
            21.03.2019. Accordingly, the Arbitral Tribunal allowed the
            <lb />
            petitioner&apos;s Claim No. 1 and awarded a sum of ₹1,00,000/-in its
            <lb />
            favour.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            19. The Arbitral Tribunal also found in favour of the petitioner in
            <lb />
            respect of Claim No. 2 and awarded a sum of ₹54,44,450/-in favour
            <lb />
            of the petitioner and against the respondent.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            20. The Arbitral Tribunal found that the petitioner was also entitled
            <lb />
            to escalation, however, the Arbitral Tribunal computed the amount of
            <lb />
            escalation payable under Clause 10-CC of the General Conditions of
            <lb />
            the Contract at ₹8,03,348/-instead of ₹18,50,000/-as claimed by the
            <lb />
            petitioner.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            21. Insofar as Claim No. 4 is concerned, the Arbitral Tribunal found
            <lb />
            that the petitioner was entitled to a sum of ₹7,60,000/-, which had
            <lb />
            been withheld by the DDA. Since the petitioner had already received a
            <lb />
            sum of ₹1,64,000/-on 16.03.2011, the Arbitral Tribunal awarded a
            <lb />
            sum of ₹5,96,000/-in favour of the petitioner against Claim No.4
            <lb />
            (₹7,60,000/-less ₹1,64,000/-)
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            22. The Arbitral Tribunal also allowed Claim No.5 and awarded
            <lb />
            interest at the rate of 12% per annum on the amount of ₹1,64,000/-,
            <lb />
            from the date it was payable till 16.03.2011 -the date on which the
            <lb />
            said amount was released to the petitioner.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            23. Insofar as the petitioner&apos;s claim for pre-reference, pendente lite
            <lb />
            and future interest is concerned, the Arbitral Tribunal awarded interest
            <lb />
            at the rate of 10% per annum against Claim Nos. 1 to 4 from
            <lb />
            20.07.20211 (the date of invocation of arbitration) to 02.12.2020. The
            <lb />
            Arbitral Tribunal further awarded future interest at the rate of 12% per
            <lb />
            annum on the awarded amounts, from the date of the award till the
            <lb />
            date of actual payment. In addition, the Arbitral Tribunal also awarded
            <lb />
            costs amounting to ₹3,00,000/-in favour of the petitioner.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            24. As noted above, the petitioner has challenged the impugned
            <lb />
            award only to the extent that the Arbitral Tribunal has not awarded
            <lb />
            any pre-reference interest on the amounts awarded against Claim Nos.
            <lb />
            1 to 4. It is seen on a plain reading of the award that it does not
            <lb />
            indicate any reason why the petitioner&apos;s claim for pre-reference
            <lb />
            interest has been rejected. Concededly, Claim No. 6 made by the
            <lb />
            petitioner included the petitioner&apos;s claim of pre-suit interest. However,
            <lb />
            the Arbitral Tribunal has completely ignored the same as the arbitral
            <lb />
            award does not expressly state that the said claim has been rejected
            <lb />
            and also indicates no reason for its rejection. The impugned award is
            <lb />
            completely silent as to the fate of the said claim, except that pre
            <lb />
            reference interest has not been awarded.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            25. The fact that the impugned award does not award pre-reference
            <lb />
            interest would in normal circumstances lead to the conclusion that the
            <lb />
            Arbitral Tribunal has rejected such a claim. However, the said
            <lb />
            inference cannot be readily drawn. This is because the Arbitral
            <lb />
            Tribunal has allowed the petitioner&apos;s Claim No.5 -the petitioner&apos;s
            <lb />
            claim for interest on ₹1,64,000/-, which was withheld by the DDA and
            <lb />
            released belatedly on 16.03.2011. The petitioner had claimed a sum of
            <lb />
            ₹7,60,000/-on that count (Claim No.4). The Arbitral Tribunal had
            <lb />
            found in favour of the petitioner and found that ₹7,60,000/-had been
            <lb />
            wrongfully withheld by the DDA. However, the Arbitral Tribunal
            <lb />
            awarded a sum of ₹5,96,000/-as the sum of ₹1,64,000/-was released
            <lb />
            to the petitioner on 16.03.2011. This Court finds no plausible reason
            <lb />
            why the Arbitral Tribunal did not award interest on the amount that
            <lb />
            had been withheld from the bills raised by the petitioner, but award
            <lb />
            interest on the part amount that was released to the petitioner on
            <lb />
            16.03.2011.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            26. The Arbitral Tribunal had found that the entire amount of
            <lb />
            ₹7,60,000/-had been withheld by the DDA from the bills raised by the
            <lb />
            petitioner but a sum of ₹1,64,000/-had been released belatedly. Thus,
            <lb />
            while the Arbitral Tribunal has awarded interest on amounts that were
            <lb />
            released belatedly, it has not awarded interest on the amount that had
            <lb />
            not been released.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            27. It appears that that the claim for pre-reference suit has escaped
            <lb />
            the attention of the Arbitral Tribunal. As noted above, there is no
            <lb />
            discussion regarding the said claim and the Arbitral Tribunal has not
            <lb />
            expressly rejected the same. This Court finds considerable merit in the
            <lb />
            contention that the Arbitral Tribunal has completely overlooked the
            <lb />
            petitioner&apos;s claim for pre-reference interest in respect of Claim Nos. 1
            <lb />
            to 4.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            28. In the case of Dyna Technologies Private Limited v. Crompton
            <lb />
            Greaves Limited: (2019) 20 SCC 1, the appellant, Dyna Technologies,
            <lb />
            and the respondent, Crompton Greaves, entered into a contract in 1994
            <lb />
            for Dyna Technologies to set up an aquaculture unit. After the
            <lb />
            issuance of the work order and the commencement of work, Crompton
            <lb />
            Greaves terminated the contract. Dyna Technologies sought
            <lb />
            compensation for premature termination and the dispute was referred
            <lb />
            to arbitration. One of the claims pertained to the unproductive use of
            <lb />
            machineries. The Tribunal granted compensation on this ground but
            <lb />
            failed to mention any reasoning for reaching this particular conclusion.
            <lb />
            While the single judge of the Madras High Court refused to set aside
            <lb />
            the award, however, the division bench of the Madras High Court set
            <lb />
            aside that part of the award with respect to unproductive use of
            <lb />
            machineries for lack of reasoning on the conclusion. On appeal, the
            <lb />
            Supreme Court while upholding the decision of the division bench of
            <lb />
            the Madras High Court, held as under:
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;34. The mandate under Section 31(3) of the Arbitration
            <lb />
            Act is to have reasoning which is intelligible and adequate
            <lb />
            and, which can in appropriate cases be even implied by the
            <lb />
            courts from a fair reading of the award and documents
            <lb />
            referred to thereunder, if the need be. The aforesaid
            <lb />
            provision does not require an elaborate judgment to be
            <lb />
            passed by the arbitrators having regard to the speedy
            <lb />
            resolution of dispute.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            35. When we consider the requirement of a reasoned order,
            <lb />
            three characteristics of a reasoned order can be fathomed.
            <lb />
            They are: proper, intelligible and adequate. If the
            <lb />
            reasonings in the order are improper, they reveal a flaw in
            <lb />
            the decision-making process. If the challenge to an award
            <lb />
            is based on impropriety or perversity in the reasoning, then
            <lb />
            it can be challenged strictly on the grounds provided under
            <lb />
            Section 34 of the Arbitration Act. If the challenge to an
            <lb />
            award is based on the ground that the same is
            <lb />
            unintelligible, the same would be equivalent of providing
            <lb />
            no reasons at all. Coming to the last aspect concerning the
            <lb />
            challenge on adequacy of reasons, the Court while
            <lb />
            exercising jurisdiction under Section 34 has to adjudicate
            <lb />
            the validity of such an award based on the degree of
            <lb />
            particularity of reasoning required having regard to the
            <lb />
            nature of issues falling for consideration. The degree of
            <lb />
            particularity cannot be stated in a precise manner as the
            <lb />
            same would depend on the complexity of the issue. Even if
            <lb />
            the Court comes to a conclusion that there were gaps in the
            <lb />
            reasoning for the conclusions reached by the Tribunal, the
            <lb />
            Court needs to have regard to the documents submitted by
            <lb />
            the parties and the contentions raised before the Tribunal
            <lb />
            so that awards with inadequate reasons are not set aside in
            <lb />
            casual and cavalier manner. On the other hand, ordinarily
            <lb />
            unintelligible awards are to be set aside, subject to party
            <lb />
            autonomy to do away with the reasoned award. Therefore,
            <lb />
            the courts are required to be careful while distinguishing
            <lb />
            between inadequacy of reasons in an award and
            <lb />
            unintelligible awards.
            <lb />
            XXX
            <lb />
            XXX
            <lb />
            XXX
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            37. In case of absence of reasoning the utility has been
            <lb />
            provided under Section 34(4) of the Arbitration Act to cure
            <lb />
            such defects. When there is complete perversity in the
            <lb />
            reasoning then only it can be challenged under the
            <lb />
            provisions of Section 34 of the Arbitration Act. The power
            <lb />
            vested under Section 34(4) of the Arbitration Act to cure
            <lb />
            defects can be utilised in cases where the arbitral award
            <lb />
            does not provide any reasoning or if the award has some
            <lb />
            gap in the reasoning or otherwise and that can be cured so
            <lb />
            as to avoid a challenge based on the aforesaid curable
            <lb />
            defects under Section 34 of the Arbitration Act.‖
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            29. It is also relevant to refer to the decision of the Supreme Court
            <lb />
            in Som Datt Builders Limited v. State of Kerala: (2009) 10 SCC 259.
            <lb />
            The relevant extract of the said decision is set out below:
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;20. Section 31(3) mandates that the arbitral award shall
            <lb />
            state the reasons upon which it is based, unless-(a) the
            <lb />
            parties have agreed that no reasons are to be given, or (b)
            <lb />
            the award is an arbitral award under Section 30. That the
            <lb />
            present case is not covered by clauses (a) and (b) is not in
            <lb />
            dispute. In the circumstances, it was obligatory for the
            <lb />
            Arbitral Tribunal to state reasons in support of its award in
            <lb />
            respect of Claims 1 and 4-B. By legislative mandate, it is
            <lb />
            now essential for the Arbitral Tribunal to give reasons in
            <lb />
            support of the award. It is pertinent to notice here that the
            <lb />
            1996 Act is based on UNCITRAL Model Law which has a
            <lb />
            provision of stating the reasons upon which the award is
            <lb />
            based.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            21. In Union of India v. Mohan Lal Capoor [(1973) 2 SCC
            <lb />
            836 : 1974 SCC (L&amp;S) 5] this Court said: (SCC p. 854,
            <lb />
            para 28)
            <lb />
            -28. … Reasons are the links between the materials on
            <lb />
            which certain conclusions are based and the actual
            <lb />
            conclusions.‖
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            22. In Woolcombers
            <lb />
            of
            <lb />
            India
            <lb />
            Ltd. v. Workers&apos;
            <lb />
            Union [(1974) 3 SCC 318 : 1973 SCC (L&amp;S) 551 : AIR
            <lb />
            1973 SC 2758] this Court stated: (SCC pp. 320-21, para 5)
            <lb />
            -5. … The giving of reasons in support of their
            <lb />
            conclusions by judicial and quasijudicial authorities when
            <lb />
            exercising initial jurisdiction is essential for various
            <lb />
            reasons. First, it is calculated to prevent unconscious
            <lb />
            unfairness or arbitrariness in reaching the conclusions. The
            <lb />
            very search for reasons will put the authority on the alert
            <lb />
            and minimise the chances of unconscious infiltration of
            <lb />
            personal bias or unfairness in the conclusion. The authority
            <lb />
            will adduce reasons which will be regarded as fair and
            <lb />
            legitimate by a reasonable man and will discard irrelevant
            <lb />
            or extraneous considerations.‖
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            23. In S.N. Mukherjee v. Union of India [(1990) 4 SCC
            <lb />
            594 : 1990 SCC (Cri) 669 : 1991 SCC (L&amp;S) 242 : (1991)
            <lb />
            16 ATC 445] the Constitution Bench held that recording of
            <lb />
            reasons
        </item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            -(i) guarantee consideration by the authority; (ii)
            <lb />
            introduce clarity in the decisions; and (iii) minimise
            <lb />
            chances of arbitrariness in decision-making.‖ (SCC p. 612,
            <lb />
            para 35)
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            25. The requirement of reasons in support of the award
            <lb />
            under Section 31(3) is not an empty formality. It guarantees
            <lb />
            fair and legitimate consideration of the controversy by the
            <lb />
            Arbitral Tribunal. It is true that the Arbitral Tribunal is not
            <lb />
            expected to write a judgment like a court nor is it expected
            <lb />
            to give elaborate and detailed reasons in support of its
            <lb />
            finding(s) but mere noticing the submissions of the parties
            <lb />
            or reference to documents is no substitute for reasons which
            <lb />
            the Arbitral Tribunal is obliged to give. Howsoever brief
            <lb />
            these may be, reasons must be indicated in the award as that
            <lb />
            would reflect the thought process leading to a particular
            <lb />
            conclusion. To satisfy the requirement of Section 31(3), the
            <lb />
            reasons must be stated by the Arbitral Tribunal upon which
            <lb />
            the award is based; want of reasons would make such award
            <lb />
            legally flawed.‖
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            30. Ms. Takiar, learned counsel appearing for the DDA, did not
            <lb />
            counter the contention that the Arbitral Tribunal had ignored the
            <lb />
            petitioner&apos;s claim for interest in respect of amounts awarded under
            <lb />
            Claim Nos. 1 to 4. She, however, stated that DDA was also aggrieved
            <lb />
            by the impugned award and had filed a petition before the District
            <lb />
            Judge (Commercial Court, North), being OMP(COMM) 5/2021
            <lb />
            captioned DDA v. Gupta and Co. She submits that if the impugned
            <lb />
            award awarding other claims in favour of the petitioner are rejected,
            <lb />
            the petitioner&apos;s claim for pre-reference interest on Claim Nos. 1 to 4
            <lb />
            would also meet the same fate.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            31. Mr. Jain, learned counsel appearing for the petitioner, submits
            <lb />
            that the District Judge would have no jurisdiction to entertain the said
            <lb />
            petition in view of Section 42 of the A&amp;C Act. He submits that the
            <lb />
            petitioner had already moved this Court way back on 15.05.2013 by
            <lb />
            filing an application under Section 9 of the A&amp;C Act (being OMP No.
            <lb />
            514/2013), which was disposed
            <lb />
            32. In view of the above, this Court considers it apposite to set aside
            <lb />
            the impugned award to the extent that the Arbitral Tribunal has not
            <lb />
            considered the petitioner&apos;s claim for pre-reference interest on Claims
            <lb />
            Nos. 1 to 4 awarded in its favour. It is so directed.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            33. It is clarified that nothing stated in this order shall preclude the
            <lb />
            DDA from pursuing its petition to set aside the impugned award
            <lb />
            [OMP (COMM) 5/2021].
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            34. Needless to state that the same would be considered on its own
            <lb />
            merits. All rights and contentions of the parties including on the
            <lb />
            question of maintainability of the petition are reserved.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            35. The petition is disposed of in the aforesaid terms. The pending
            <lb />
            application is also disposed of.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            VIBHU BAKHRU, J
            <lb />
            MAY 13, 2021
            <lb />
            RK/pkv
        </p>


    </text>
</tei>