<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<p>
			1.
			<lb />
			This hearing has been done through video conferencing.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<head>
			CM APPL. 16182/2021 (for exemption)
			<lb />
		</head>
		<p>
			2.
			<lb />
			Vide order dated 11 th May 2021, this court has already disposed of the
			<lb />
			present application. Accordingly, no further orders are called for.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<head>
			W.P.(C) 5263/2021
			<lb />
		</head>
		<p>
			3.
			<lb />
			The present writ petition has been filed by the Students Union and the
			<lb />
			Teachers Union at the Jawaharlal Nehru University (hereinafter, &quot;JNU&quot;), as
			<lb />
			also two Professors who teach at the University. The Petitioners are seeking
			<lb />
			various directions to the Respondents including a direction for setting up
			<lb />
			COVID care facilities in the University Campus, as also a COVID response
			<lb />
			team, and certain Oxygen facilities inside the University Campus premises.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			4.
			<lb />
			The case of the Petitioners is that due to the outbreak of the second
			<lb />
			wave of the COVID-19 pandemic, around the second week of April, the
			<lb />
			Petitioners wrote a letter to the Registrar of the Respondent University,
			<lb />
			highlighting the alarming situation due to COVID-19 on the JNU campus,
			<lb />
			seeking various steps to be taken for controlling the situation. Thereafter, the
			<lb />
			Petitioners were continuously sending letters to the Registrar of JNU, The
			<lb />
			Vice Chancellor of JNU as also the ADM/ SDM of the concerned area
			<lb />
			seeking immediate intervention for setting up COVID care facilities within
			<lb />
			campus in light of the massive surge of COVID-19 and the number of
			<lb />
			COVID positive cases within the JNU campus. Aggrieved by there being no
			<lb />
			response from any of the said authorities, and on any of the concerns raised
			<lb />
			by the Petitioners, the present petition was filed.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			5.
			<lb />
			Vide the previous order dated 11th May 2021, notice was issued to
			<lb />
			the Respondents, and the following directions were issued:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot;12. In view of the above, the following directions
				<lb />
				are issued:
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				i) The Registrar, JNU to immediately give instructions
				<lb />
				to the ld. counsel, and file a status report, as to what
				<lb />
				are the steps taken by the administration of the JNU in
				<lb />
				respect of the requests made and letters written by the
				<lb />
				Petitioners to the administration, for dealing with the
				<lb />
				COVID-19 pandemic situation in the JNU campus
				<lb />
				since 2020 and especially since 13th April, 2021.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				ii) The Vice Chancellor/Registrar of JNU to also
				<lb />
				ascertain the necessity and feasibility in respect of
				<lb />
				creation of the COVID care facility in the JNU campus
				<lb />
				and file a status report thereof. The report shall also
				<lb />
				take into consideration the proposals given by the
				<lb />
				Centre for Social Medicine and Community Health
				<lb />
				(CSMCH) as also the proposal for in-house production
				<lb />
				of oxygen, given by the School of Life Sciences. The
				<lb />
				authorities in JNU to consider if there is any
				<lb />
				modification required to the said proposals as has been
				<lb />
				suggested by the students and teachers associations.
				<lb />
				The modalities for creation of COVID care facility
				<lb />
				shall be mentioned in the report.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				iii) The SDM/ADM of the concerned area to also place
				<lb />
				on record a status report, as to whether such a COVID
				<lb />
				care facility can be created at JNU, in accordance with
				<lb />
				the guidelines applicable, and if so indicating the
				<lb />
				manner in which the doctors and paramedics, as also
				<lb />
				nurses, would be made available for the said facility,
				<lb />
				and whether they would be tied up with any particular
				<lb />
				hospital, and if so, name the said hospital after
				<lb />
				obtaining its concurrence.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				13. The Registrar of the Respondent University, shall
				<lb />
				convene a meeting today itself at 5 P.M, chaired by the
				<lb />
				Vice Chancellor along with the other internal
				<lb />
				administrative staff as also the concerned SDM/ADM
				<lb />
				of the area, to work out the formalities and the
				<lb />
				protocols, in this respect.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				14. A second meeting shall also be convened by the
				<lb />
				Registrar chaired by the Vice Chancellor, other
				<lb />
				administrative staff, SDM/ADM concerned along with
				<lb />
				six representatives of the Students and the Teachers
				<lb />
				Union, as also the departments which have given the
				<lb />
				proposals, at 11 AM tomorrow, i.e. 12th May 2021, to
				<lb />
				discuss the said proposals/ letters for setting up of a
				<lb />
				COVID care facility in the JNU campus. The said
				<lb />
				meetings can be held through a virtual platform.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				15. Let the status reports explaining the feasibility,
				<lb />
				modalities and timelines for setting up of a covid care
				<lb />
				centre, preferably with oxygenated beds, as directed,
				<lb />
				be emailed by both the JNU administration as also the
				<lb />
				ADM/SDM of the concerned area, to the Court Master
				<lb />
				by 9 A.M., on 13th May 2021.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			6.
			<lb />
			Further to the said order, today, four status reports have been received
			<lb />
			-one each from the Petitioners&apos; association of students and teachers; one on
			<lb />
			behalf of the SDM of the concerned area; and one on behalf of the
			<lb />
			Respondent-JNU itself.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			7.
			<lb />
			Mr. Anirban Chakraborti -Registrar, JNU, has also joined the
			<lb />
			proceedings today. On behalf of JNU, it is submitted that a COVID Task
			<lb />
			Force has already been set up by the University, consisting of nine members.
			<lb />
			It is submitted that since the same was constituted on 18th April, 2021,
			<lb />
			several patients, who contracted COVID-19 and who required
			<lb />
			hospitalisation, were rendered assistance by the said Task Force which was
			<lb />
			set up. It is further submitted that there are about 100 volunteers who are
			<lb />
			attending to telephone calls and emails from asymptomatic/symptomatic
			<lb />
			patients 24x7, along with the COVID Task Force.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			8.
			<lb />
			The Registrar, JNU, submits that the University has held four testing
			<lb />
			camps in which 385 persons were found to be positive with COVID-19.
			<lb />
			These included students, staff members, faculty and the family members of
			<lb />
			the staff and faculty who reside in the campus. Two vaccination camps have
			<lb />
			also been held in which over 690 persons have been vaccinated in the age
			<lb />
			group of 45+ and frontline workers. It is further submitted on behalf of the
			<lb />
			JNU that the JNU has written several letters to various Ministries in the
			<lb />
			Delhi Government as also the Ministry of Health and Family Welfare,
			<lb />
			Union of India, and has also been in touch with the two NGOs including the
			<lb />
			Art of Living and Khalsa Aid -for tying up with JNU for providing COVID
			<lb />
			relief.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			9.
			<lb />
			Ms. Arora, ld. Counsel appearing for JNU, also points out that 12
			<lb />
			doctors have been taken on the panel and that a medical counselling facility
			<lb />
			has also been set up with all their telephone numbers. These doctors are
			<lb />
			providing tele-consultation to various residents of the JNU campus, around
			<lb />
			the clock.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			10. Insofar as the status report of the SDM is concerned, it has been
			<lb />
			informed that there are three levels of COVID facilities that exist and have
			<lb />
			been approved. The relevant table, which is a part of the status report is
			<lb />
			extracted below:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<figure type="table">
			Acronym
			<lb />
			FACILITY CASES
			<lb />
			LOCATION
			<lb />
			OXYGEN
			<lb />
			CCC
			<lb />
			COVID
			<lb />
			Care Centre
			<lb />
			Asymptom
			<lb />
			atic / pre-
			<lb />
			symptomat
			<lb />
			ic
			<lb />
			and
			<lb />
			mild
			<lb />
			Hostels, hotels,
			<lb />
			school,
			<lb />
			stadiums,
			<lb />
			lodges etc
			<lb />
			No.
			<lb />
			DCHC
			<lb />
			Dedicated
			<lb />
			COVID
			<lb />
			Health
			<lb />
			Centre
			<lb />
			Moderate Full hospital
			<lb />
			or a separate
			<lb />
			block in a
			<lb />
			hospital
			<lb />
			Beds
			<lb />
			with
			<lb />
			assured Oxygen
			<lb />
			support
			<lb />
			DCH
			<lb />
			Dedicated
			<lb />
			COVID
			<lb />
			Hospital
			<lb />
			Severe
			<lb />
			Full hospital
			<lb />
			or a separate
			<lb />
			block in a
			<lb />
			hospital
			<lb />
			Fully equipped
			<lb />
			ICUs,
			<lb />
			Ventilators and
			<lb />
			beds
			<lb />
			with
			<lb />
			assured Oxygen
			<lb />
			support.
			<lb />
		</figure>
		<p>
			11. As per the said status report, unless and until there are proper
			<lb />
			oxygenated beds etc. and doctors and paramedics available around the clock,
			<lb />
			the only centre that could be set up is a COVID Care Centre, where there is
			<lb />
			no oxygen which is administered to patients. Such a Centre can cater to
			<lb />
			asymptomatic, pre-symptomatic and patients with mild symptoms.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			12. The SDM, who has joined the proceedings today, submits that he has
			<lb />
			inspected the infrastructure of the JNU campus, and has informed this court
			<lb />
			there are guest houses which are available, which can be converted into
			<lb />
			isolation wards for the residents of the JNU campus.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			13. On behalf of the Petitioners, Mr. Chimni, ld. Counsel submits that two
			<lb />
			proposals have been submitted where the faculty of Centre for Social
			<lb />
			Medicine and Community Health (CSMCH) have given proposals qua the
			<lb />
			manner in which they can assist in the setting up of the COVID Care
			<lb />
			Isolation Facility. He further submits that the proposal for manufacture or
			<lb />
			generation of oxygen, if required, has also been submitted.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			14. After hearing the ld. Counsels for the parties, as also the officers of
			<lb />
			the parties themselves, who have appeared before the Court, as also perusing
			<lb />
			the status reports, it is clear that the total number of persons residing in the
			<lb />
			campus residing in the JNU campus are between 12000 -15000, including
			<lb />
			students, staff members, faculty and their families. The number of people
			<lb />
			contracting COVID-19 inside the JNU campus is also quite high. However,
			<lb />
			there is no covid care facility at all. The medical centre which exists is also a
			<lb />
			small area with 1 Chief Medical Officer, 2 Medical officers and 2 staff
			<lb />
			nurses -some of whom are also not currently available. Thus, in case there
			<lb />
			is a sudden surge, the residents in the campus may face difficulties and there
			<lb />
			is a need to take further steps apart from what has already been taken by the
			<lb />
			Covid Task Force and the Covid Response Team.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			15. On behalf of the GNCTD, Mr. Tripathi submits that currently, there
			<lb />
			are sufficient beds in the various hospitals/COVID Care Centres, which are
			<lb />
			currently vacant. Specific mention is made by Ms. Arora of three facilities
			<lb />
			which could be tied up with JNU, such as the facility at Chattarpur, which is
			<lb />
			being run with the help of ITBP and the Delhi Government, Vishwa Yuva
			<lb />
			Kendra facility -Teen Murti, New Delhi, as also the facility at the Gurdwara
			<lb />
			Rakab Ganj Sahib.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			16. Considering the above submissions and the fact that the COVID Task
			<lb />
			Force and the COVID Response Team is already working within JNU
			<lb />
			campus, the following directions are further issued:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				i) In order to provide for immediate isolation of residents who are
				<lb />
				tested Covid positive, a `Covid Care Centre&apos; be set up inside the
				<lb />
				JNU. The premises for the same be identified by the COVID Task
				<lb />
				Force, in consultation with the concerned SDM. This would enable
				<lb />
				such affected persons to immediately isolate and for their basic
				<lb />
				parameters to be monitored. In the creation of the isolation facility,
				<lb />
				if the services of any of the faculty members who are part of the
				<lb />
				Petitioner
				<lb />
				association
				<lb />
				are
				<lb />
				required,
				<lb />
				their
				<lb />
				recommendations/assistance may also be availed of by the COVID
				<lb />
				Task Force.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				ii) To facilitate the monitoring of the basic parameters of those who
				<lb />
				are detected positive with COVID-19, if any paramedic/nursing
				<lb />
				staff are required, the SDM and JNU Task Force shall arrive at a
				<lb />
				consensus, as to how, the arrangement would be made for
				<lb />
				paramedic/nursing staff. The doctors on campus also could be
				<lb />
				empanelled for volunteering, if required, for any patient in the
				<lb />
				isolation centre;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				iii) Insofar as those patients who may need oxygenated beds are
				<lb />
				concerned, the JNU Task Force may coordinate with the SDM of
				<lb />
				the concerned area, as also with the Delhi Government, to identify
				<lb />
				as to with which of the above mentioned three facilities or any
				<lb />
				other facility JNU ought to tie up, so that there is an arrangement
				<lb />
				which is put in place for residents of the JNU campus, in case they
				<lb />
				require oxygenated beds or any ICU facility;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				iv) Insofar as the creation of a dedicated `COVID Health Centre&apos; with
				<lb />
				oxygenated beds in JNU is concerned, the feasibility, requirement
				<lb />
				and the necessity of the same may be discussed and deliberated
				<lb />
				upon by the COVID Task Force with the SDM of the concerned
				<lb />
				area and Delhi Govt. If any tie up needs to be created with any
				<lb />
				hospital in the vicinity, the same shall also be identified and the
				<lb />
				terms and conditions thereof would also be mentioned in the status
				<lb />
				report.
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			17. Let the status report in compliance with the above directions be filed
			<lb />
			at least one day before the next date of hearing. It is expected that the
			<lb />
			students and the faculty association, as also the administration of JNU,
			<lb />
			would work together for the betterment of the residents and students of the
			<lb />
			JNU campus and shall not take any adversarial measures against each other.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			18. List on 28 th May, 2021. If any of the parties wish to seek any further
			<lb />
			directions, they are given liberty to approach the Court.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			19. The digitally signed copy of this order, duly uploaded on the official
			<lb />
			website of the Delhi High Court, www.delhihighcourt.nic.in, shall be treated
			<lb />
			as the certified copy of the order for the purpose of ensuring compliance. No
			<lb />
			physical copy of orders shall be insisted by any authority/entity or litigant.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			PRATHIBA M. SINGH
			<lb />
			JUDGE
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			MAY 13, 2021/Rahul/Ak
		</p>
	</text>
</tei>
