<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<p>
			1.
			<lb />
			The petitioner (hereafter &quot;ACIL&quot;) has filed the present petition
			<lb />
			under Section 34 of the Arbitration and Conciliation Act, 1996
			<lb />
			(hereafter &quot;the A&amp;C Act&quot;) impugning an arbitral award dated
			<lb />
			30.05.2019 (hereafter &quot;the impugned award&quot;) rendered by an Arbitral
			<lb />
			Tribunal constituted by a Sole Arbitrator (hereafter &quot;the Arbitral
			<lb />
			Tribunal&quot;).
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			2.
			<lb />
			The impugned award was rendered in the context of disputes
			<lb />
			that had arisen between the parties in connection with the Work Order
			<lb />
			dated 07.03.2013 bearing reference number ACIL/Grim-
			<lb />
			Tech/1060313/2013 (hereafter the &quot;Principal Work Order&quot;) for
			<lb />
			carrying out pile foundation work for CHP at Muzaffarpur Thermal
			<lb />
			Power Plant of Kanti Bijlee Utpadan Nigam Limited, valued at
			<lb />
			₹10,73,94,000/-. The aforesaid Principal Work Order was
			<lb />
			subsequently amended on 24.07.2013 by a Work Order bearing
			<lb />
			reference
			<lb />
			number
			<lb />
			ACIL/Grim-Tech/1060313/2013/Amend-1
			<lb />
			(hereafter the &quot;Amended Work Order&quot;).
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			3.
			<lb />
			The respondent (hereafter &quot;GTPL&quot;) claimed that under the
			<lb />
			Amended Work Order, ACIL had failed to pay the outstanding dues
			<lb />
			and compensation for extended deployment of assets including interest
			<lb />
			thereon.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			4.
			<lb />
			GTPL submitted that twelve Running Account Bills were issued
			<lb />
			to ACIL for a total amount of ₹2,94,55,392/-. GTPL claimed that an
			<lb />
			amount of ₹1,00,07,985/-was due and payable by ACIL under the
			<lb />
			Amended Work Order after all statutory deductions. On 21.07.2016,
			<lb />
			GTPL sent an email to ACIL and sought confirmation on the
			<lb />
			outstanding dues. ACIL reverted on the same date confirming that an
			<lb />
			amount of ₹1,00,07,985/-was payable to GTPL.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			5.
			<lb />
			In terms of Clause 18 of the Amended Work Order, the works
			<lb />
			were to be completed within four months from the date of execution
			<lb />
			that is, by 24.11.2013. GTPL claimed that there was a delay in
			<lb />
			execution of the works for reasons attributable to ACIL. On
			<lb />
			12.11.2014, GTPL informed ACIL that the piling work was at a
			<lb />
			standstill as it had not provided the requisite steel and cement.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			6.
			<lb />
			GTPL claimed that assets being two Piling Rigs, two Cranes,
			<lb />
			one Hydra and one JCB deployed at the work site from December
			<lb />
			2013 till March 2015 remained idle. On 03.03.2015, ACIL issued an
			<lb />
			outward gate pass for the aforesaid equipment. GTPL contended that
			<lb />
			the equipment could have been deployed at other sites or let out on
			<lb />
			hire. It accordingly sought compensation for extended deployment of
			<lb />
			assets at the site of ACIL. GTPL further sought reimbursement for
			<lb />
			providing support staff including for expenses for their food and
			<lb />
			lodging during the period from December 2013 till March 2015.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			7.
			<lb />
			In view of the above disputes, GTPL issued a legal notice dated
			<lb />
			07.09.2016 seeking appointment of a Sole Arbitrator and for reference
			<lb />
			of disputes to arbitration in terms of Clause 27 of the Terms and
			<lb />
			Conditions appended to the Principal Work Order as applicable to the
			<lb />
			Amended Work Order.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			8.
			<lb />
			ACIL denied the claims raised by GTPL and did not take any
			<lb />
			steps for the appointment of an arbitrator. Consequently, GTPL filed a
			<lb />
			petition under Section 11 of the A&amp;C Act (being ARB P. 98/2017)
			<lb />
			before this Court. The said petition was disposed of by an order dated
			<lb />
			10.04.2017 and this Court directed that an arbitrator be appointed
			<lb />
			under the rules of Delhi International Arbitration Centre (DIAC).
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			9.
			<lb />
			Before the Arbitral Tribunal, GTPL raised the following claims:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<figure type="table">
			S. No. CLAIMS
			<lb />
			AMOUNT (Rs.)
			<lb />
			1.
			<lb />
			(A) Principal Outstanding Dues
			<lb />
			1,00,07,985
			<lb />
			(B) Damages/Compensation for
			<lb />
			extended deployment of assets
			<lb />
			4,09,41,540
			<lb />
			2.
			<lb />
			Interest
			<lb />
			Pre Reference and Pendente Lite
			<lb />
			On Claim (A) [18% from
			<lb />
			04.10.2014]
			<lb />
			On Claim (B) [March, 2015]
			<lb />
			49,62,803
			<lb />
			69,60,062
			<lb />
			Future Interest
			<lb />
			Not Determined
			<lb />
			3.
			<lb />
			Costs
			<lb />
			5,00,000
			<lb />
			Total
			<lb />
			6,33,72,390
			<lb />
		</figure>
		<p>
			10. The Arbitral Tribunal found that the Principal Work Order
			<lb />
			dated 07.03.2013 had not expired by efflux of time and the Amended
			<lb />
			Work Order (Work Order dated 24.07.2013) only amended the
			<lb />
			Principal Work Order and thus, could not be considered as an
			<lb />
			independent contract. The Arbitral Tribunal held that GTPL is entitled
			<lb />
			to the outstanding amount of ₹1,00,07,985/-, which was due on
			<lb />
			21.07.2016. The Arbitral Tribunal further directed ACIL to pay a
			<lb />
			lumpsum of ₹2,15,00,000/-to GTPL on account of compensation for
			<lb />
			extended deployment of staff and assets at the site of ACIL and further
			<lb />
			directed that in the event, the same was not paid within thirty days
			<lb />
			from the date of the award, ACIL shall be liable to pay simple interest
			<lb />
			at the rate of 6% per annum till its realization. The Arbitral Tribunal
			<lb />
			further awarded interest on the awarded amount of ₹1,00,07,985/-at
			<lb />
			the rate of 12% per annum from 21.07.2016 and further held that in
			<lb />
			the event, the same was not paid within thirty days from the date of
			<lb />
			the award, the interest would be paid at the compound rate of 12% till
			<lb />
			its realization.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<head>
			Submissions
			<lb />
		</head>
		<p>
			11. Mr. Jain, learned counsel appearing for ACIL has assailed the
			<lb />
			impugned award on three fronts.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			12. First, he submitted that the arbitral award is liable to be set aside
			<lb />
			in terms of Section 34(2)(a)(ii) of the A&amp;C Act. He submitted that
			<lb />
			there was no arbitration agreement between the parties and therefore,
			<lb />
			the Arbitral Tribunal had no jurisdiction to make the impugned award.
			<lb />
			He submitted that GTPL had played a fraud on this Court as well as
			<lb />
			ACIL, as it had fraudulently secured an order from this Court for
			<lb />
			appointment of an Arbitrator by producing the Amended Work Order
			<lb />
			dated 24.07.2013 along with certain terms and conditions. However, it
			<lb />
			was subsequently revealed that the Amended Work Order is a single
			<lb />
			page document and it was not accompanied with any terms and
			<lb />
			conditions, which included an arbitration clause. He stated that the
			<lb />
			witness (CW3) was confronted with the e-mail (Ex.CW3/1) dated
			<lb />
			24.07.2013 and he had admitted that the document attached to the said
			<lb />
			e-mail was only of one page. He contended that it was, thus, the
			<lb />
			Amended Work Order which was sent as an attachment to the said e-
			<lb />
			mail was only of one page. Next, he submitted that the arbitration
			<lb />
			agreement was not signed by GTPL. Mr. Jain referred to the decision
			<lb />
			of this Court in Priknit Retails Ltd. &amp; Ors. v. Aneja Agencies: OMP
			<lb />
			(COMM) No. 374/2016 decided on 22.03.2018 in support of his
			<lb />
			contention that an arbitration clause contained in a Work Order, which
			<lb />
			has not been signed would not constitute an arbitration agreement
			<lb />
			under Section 7(4) of the A&amp;C Act.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			13. Second, he submitted that the award of ₹2,15,00,000/-as
			<lb />
			lumpsum damages for idling of machinery, is patently illegal as it is
			<lb />
			without any basis or evidence.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			14. Third, he submitted that the interest awarded by the Arbitral
			<lb />
			Tribunal at the rate of 12% per annum is in excess of the claim made
			<lb />
			by GTPL. He contended that GTPL had claimed simple interest at the
			<lb />
			rate of 10.5% per annum but was awarded compound interest at the
			<lb />
			rate of 12% per annum. Thus, the impugned award being beyond of
			<lb />
			the claim made by GTPL, is vitiated by patent illegality.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			15. Mr. Shamshad, learned counsel appearing for GTPL countered
			<lb />
			the aforesaid submissions. He submitted that ACIL had not raised any
			<lb />
			plea of fraud to oppose GTPL&quot;s petition under Section 11 of the A&amp;C
			<lb />
			Act. Further, ACIL had also preferred a Special Leave Petition (SLP)
			<lb />
			before the Supreme Court impugning the order dated 10.04.2017
			<lb />
			passed by this Court allowing the GTPL&quot;s petition under Section 11 of
			<lb />
			the A&amp;C Act. However, even at that stage, GTPL had not raised any
			<lb />
			issue of fraud.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			16. Next, he submitted that award of damages was a reasonable
			<lb />
			estimate of the damages incurred by GTPL on account of idle
			<lb />
			machinery and withholding of gate passes by ACIL. He submitted that
			<lb />
			GTPL had produced evidence and material on record to justify its
			<lb />
			claim for damages and the Arbitral Tribunal had also noted the same.
			<lb />
			Nonetheless, the Arbitral Tribunal had awarded damages of a reduced
			<lb />
			amount based on its estimate of reasonable damages. He referred to
			<lb />
			the decision of the Supreme Court in Mcdermott International Inc. v.
			<lb />
			Burn Standard Co. Ltd.: (2006) 11 SCC 181 in support of his
			<lb />
			contention that it was open for the Arbitral Tribunal to award
			<lb />
			damages, which it considers reasonable, without any specific evidence
			<lb />
			as to the quantification of the said damages.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<head>
			Reasons &amp; Submissions
			<lb />
		</head>
		<p>
			17. The first and foremost question to be addressed is whether the
			<lb />
			impugned award is liable to be set aside as being without jurisdiction.
			<lb />
			The answer to this issue is dependent on the question whether an
			<lb />
			arbitration agreement exists between the parties. There is no dispute
			<lb />
			that ACIL had issued the Principal Work Order. The subject of the
			<lb />
			said Work Order indicated that it was for &quot;carrying out pile
			<lb />
			foundation work for CHP at Muzaffarpur Thermal Power Plan of
			<lb />
			Kanti Bijlee Utpadan Nigam Ltd. (Dist. Muzaffarpur -Bihar)&quot;. The
			<lb />
			first page of the Work Order indicated that the Terms and Conditions
			<lb />
			were specified in Annexure-1 to the said Work Order. Clause 27 of
			<lb />
			the said Terms and Conditions reads as under:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot;27. Arbitration: Any dispute in relation of this
				<lb />
				contract shall be subject to the final decision of
				<lb />
				M.D. -ACIL.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			18. The fact that ACIL had issued the Principal Work Order is not
			<lb />
			in dispute. ACIL now claims that the said Work Order was not signed
			<lb />
			and therefore, the arbitration agreement, which is included as Clause
			<lb />
			27 of the Terms and Conditions never came into existence. In the
			<lb />
			alternative, ACIL also claims that the Principal Work Order had
			<lb />
			expired by efflux of time since it was valid only for a period of four
			<lb />
			months.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			19. It is relevant to note that it is not disputed that GTPL had
			<lb />
			executed piling work for CHP at Kanti Bijlee Utpadan Nigam Ltd. at
			<lb />
			Muzaffarpur. It had raised Running Bills for the work done. The
			<lb />
			Arbitral Tribunal had also accepted that certain payments had been
			<lb />
			made in respect of the work done by GTPL. The invoices raised by
			<lb />
			GTPL specifically referred to &quot;Work Order No:ACIL/Grim-
			<lb />
			Tech/1060313/2013 Dated 07/03/2013&quot;. The Arbitral Tribunal did not
			<lb />
			accept the contention that GTPL had executed the works on an ad-hoc
			<lb />
			basis [referred to as &quot;Give and Take basis&quot;] and not in accordance
			<lb />
			with the terms of the Principal Work Order as amended. GTPL further
			<lb />
			contended that ACIL had issued an amendment to the Work Order
			<lb />
			dated 07.03.2013 (Principal Work Order), on 24.07.2013 (being the
			<lb />
			Amended Work Order). The bills had been raised as per the rates
			<lb />
			specified in the said Amended Work Order. In this regard, it is
			<lb />
			contended on behalf of ACIL that the Amended Work Order did not
			<lb />
			include an arbitration clause and therefore, there was no agreement
			<lb />
			between the parties for referring any dispute pertaining to the said
			<lb />
			amendment to arbitration.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			20. The Arbitral Tribunal had rejected the aforesaid contention and
			<lb />
			had found that the Amended Work Order dated 24.07.2013 was an
			<lb />
			amendment to the Principal Work Order dated 07.03.2013 and
			<lb />
			therefore, an agreement existed to refer the subject disputes to
			<lb />
			arbitration. Further the Amended Work Order dated 24.07.2013 also
			<lb />
			expressly mentions that &quot;Terms and Conditions remains same as per
			<lb />
			earlier order&quot;. Thus, the Arbitral Tribunal held that the arbitration
			<lb />
			agreement as included in the Terms and Conditions appended to the
			<lb />
			Work order dated 07.03.2013 would also be applicable to the
			<lb />
			Amended Work Order dated 24.07.2013. The relevant extract of said
			<lb />
			finding of the Arbitral Tribunal is set out below:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot;62. As against the contention of the Respondent qua the
				<lb />
				Work Orders dated 07.03.2013 (Ex.CW-1/3) and
				<lb />
				24.07.2013 (Ex.CW-1/4), case of the Claimant as per
				<lb />
				their statement of claim and as deposed by Sh. R.K.
				<lb />
				Singh (CW-1) is that the Respondent had issued the Work
				<lb />
				Order dated 07.03.2013 and thereafter issued Work Order
				<lb />
				dated 24.07.2013 as amendment to the earlier work order
				<lb />
				and the latter Work Order dated 24.07.2013 comprising
				<lb />
				one page only mentioning that &quot;Terms and conditions
				<lb />
				remain the same as per earlier order&quot;. The Claimant
				<lb />
				started to work as per the said Work orders and raised 12
				<lb />
				Running Bills totaling to Rs.2,94,55,392/-and the Net
				<lb />
				Outstanding was Rs.1,00,07,985/-which was confirmed
				<lb />
				by the Respondent being payable to the Complainant.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				63. It is submitted on behalf of the Claimant that the
				<lb />
				Work Order dated 07.03.2013 was subsequently amended
				<lb />
				by Work order dated 24.07.2013 which has to be read in
				<lb />
				continuation of the Work Order dated 07.03.2013 while
				<lb />
				the Respondent had sought an amendment in Work Order
				<lb />
				dated 07.03.2013 qua retention money as per Ex.RW-1/2,
				<lb />
				which is dated 18.03.2013 in reply to email dated
				<lb />
				11.03.2013 sent by the Claimant to the Respondent and
				<lb />
				subsequently, the Respondent issued Work Order dated
				<lb />
				24.07.2013. It is contended by the learned counsel for the
				<lb />
				Respondent that since March 2013 to December 2014,
				<lb />
				Respondent had not taken any stand that either of the
				<lb />
				Work Orders had expired or stood terminated, nor it was
				<lb />
				pleaded in this case that the parties had abandoned the
				<lb />
				contract or started relationship on &quot;GIVE AND TAKE&quot;
				<lb />
				basis or verbal basis. For the first time RW-1 in his
				<lb />
				affidavit, Ex. RW -1/A stated that the Claimant never
				<lb />
				accepted the Work Order or the Claimant failed to convey
				<lb />
				their acceptance to the Work Order dated 24.07.2013.
				<lb />
				Only in his cross examination PW-1 came out with the
				<lb />
				plea that work was executed by the Claimant on &quot;Give &amp;
				<lb />
				Take&quot; basis or verbal basis and continued till December
				<lb />
				2013, admitting that Respondent continuing making
				<lb />
				payment to the Claimant till 18.02.2015. He submitted
				<lb />
				that there was no termination of Work Order till 2014 and
				<lb />
				receipt of Bills is not denied and the Respondent admitted
				<lb />
				continuously making payment till 18.02.2015, which lead
				<lb />
				to the only inference that the Work Order dated
				<lb />
				07.03.2013 did not expire due to efflux of time but was
				<lb />
				amended vide Work Order dated 24.07.2013 and the
				<lb />
				contract remained open-ended till the date of issuance of
				<lb />
				last RA/Bill. According to the learned counsel, for the
				<lb />
				Claimant since the Work Order dated 24.07.2013 (Ex.
				<lb />
				RW-1/3) categorically mentions that terms and conditions
				<lb />
				of earlier Work Order would be the same, these have to
				<lb />
				be treated as part and parcel of the amended Work Order
				<lb />
				i.e. Work Order dated 24.07.2013.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				64. It is also submitted by the learned counsel for the
				<lb />
				Claimant that whatever is contrary to pleading or is not
				<lb />
				pleaded in the counter statement but has been stated in
				<lb />
				written arguments by the learned counsel for the
				<lb />
				Respondent cannot be considered because it is well
				<lb />
				settled law that no party can put forth a case or defence
				<lb />
				beyond pleadings. He pointed out that non-acceptance of
				<lb />
				Work Order dated 24.07.2013 was never insisted upon
				<lb />
				rather admitted that the Claimant continued working on
				<lb />
				the basis of Work Order dated 24.07.2013, as is evident
				<lb />
				from para 6 on page 11 of the counter statement, where it
				<lb />
				is stated by the Respondent that &quot;the Claimant executed
				<lb />
				the work on the basis of Work Order dated 24.07.2013.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				xxxx
				<lb />
				xxxx
				<lb />
				xxxx
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				69. … Claimant&apos;s case is that pursuant to the terms being
				<lb />
				arrived at a meeting, Work Order Ex. CW-1/3 was issued
				<lb />
				on 07.03.2013 which was amended on 18.03.2018
				<lb />
				agreeing upon reducing retention money @ 5% instead of
				<lb />
				7%, but later on another Work Order Ex. CW-1/4 was
				<lb />
				issued on 24.07.2013 on the terms and conditions earlier
				<lb />
				settled among the parties, while issuing Work Order Ex.
				<lb />
				CW-1/3, and relying upon those terms and conditions,
				<lb />
				Claimants executed the work as per Work Order Ex. CW-
				<lb />
				1/4 for which they had been raising: RA Bills of which
				<lb />
				six are admittedly received by the Respondent, against
				<lb />
				which the Claimant was even made the payment allegedly
				<lb />
				more than what was due. Admittedly received .RA Bills
				<lb />
				are Ex. CW-1/6, Ex. CW-1/7, Ex. CW-1/9, Ex. CW-1/
				<lb />
				10, Ex. CW-1/ 11 &amp; Ex. CW-1/ 12. Other RA Bills are
				<lb />
				mask A&apos;, &apos;B&apos;, &apos;C&apos;, &apos;D&apos;, &apos;E&apos;, &apos;F&apos; and &quot;G&quot;. All the RA Bills
				<lb />
				have been issued in reference to Work Order dated
				<lb />
				07.03.2013 including the last admitted, RA Bill Ex. CW-
				<lb />
				1/12 for the period from 01.04.2013 to 31.12.2013,
				<lb />
				implying that the Respondent continued paying against
				<lb />
				those bills in reference to Work Order Ex. CW-1/3, which
				<lb />
				according to the Claimant stood amended on 24.07.2013.
				<lb />
				In such circumstances, the contention of the Respondent
				<lb />
				that the two Work Orders were different and independent
				<lb />
				of each other is fallacious and cannot hold ground. Parties
				<lb />
				continued acting on the Work Order dated 07.03.2013
				<lb />
				(Ex. CW-1/3), Claimant executing the work as per Work
				<lb />
				Order dated 24.07.2013 (Ex. CW-1/4) treating it only as
				<lb />
				an amendment, as had happened in case of amendment
				<lb />
				dated 18.03.2013 and the Respondent making payment
				<lb />
				admittedly for the period from 01.04.2013 to
				<lb />
				31.12.2013.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			21. This Court concurs with the aforesaid conclusion. It is clear that
			<lb />
			the Amended Work Order dated 24.07.2013 was an amendment to the
			<lb />
			Principal Work Order dated 07.03.2013. The Amended Work Order
			<lb />
			dated 24.07.2013 bears a reference which reads as, &quot;ACIL/Grim-
			<lb />
			Tech/1060313/2013/Amend-1&quot;.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			22. It is clear that the Principal Work Order for executing the work
			<lb />
			of pile foundation was issued on 07.03.2013 and was subsequently
			<lb />
			amended by the Amended Work Order dated 24.07.2013, in respect of
			<lb />
			the quantities and rates for the works in question.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			23. GTPL had invoked arbitration in respect of the Amended Work
			<lb />
			Order dated 24.07.2013. It also suggested the names of three former
			<lb />
			Judges of this Court out of which one of whom could be appointed as
			<lb />
			the learned Arbitrator. ACIL did not concur on any such appointment.
			<lb />
			Consequently, GTPL filed a petition under Section 11 of the A&amp;C Act
			<lb />
			[ARB.P. No.98/2017 captioned Grim Tech Projects (I) Pvt. Ltd. v.
			<lb />
			Aneja Constructions (India) Ltd.]. The said petition was allowed by
			<lb />
			an order dated 10.04.2017. This Court noted that GTPL had invoked
			<lb />
			the arbitration clause in respect of the disputes that had arisen between
			<lb />
			the parties in respect of the Work Order dated 24.07.2013. At that
			<lb />
			stage, GTPL had relied on Clause 27 of the Terms and Conditions as
			<lb />
			appended to the Principal Work Order dated 07.03.2013. It is material
			<lb />
			to note that ACIL did not raise any objection to the effect that the
			<lb />
			Terms and Conditions as applicable to the Amended Work Order
			<lb />
			dated 24.07.2013 did not include Clause 27 as quoted above. The only
			<lb />
			objection raised on behalf of ACIL was that the said clause was not an
			<lb />
			arbitration agreement and it merely stipulated that any dispute would
			<lb />
			be subject to the final decision of the Managing Director of ACIL.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			24. The said contention was rejected. This Court held that Clause
			<lb />
			27 constituted an arbitration agreement. The Court further found that
			<lb />
			the Managing Director of ACIL was ineligible to act as an Arbitrator
			<lb />
			in terms of Section 12(5) of the A&amp;C Act and accordingly, directed
			<lb />
			appointment of an Arbitrator under the rules of Delhi International
			<lb />
			Arbitrator Centre (DIAC).
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			25. ACIL did not accept the said decision and challenged the same
			<lb />
			in the Supreme Court by filing a Special Leave Petition (SLP(C)
			<lb />
			No.15819/2017) which was dismissed by the Supreme Court by an
			<lb />
			order dated 18.08.2017. It is conceded that even before the Supreme
			<lb />
			Court, ACIL did not raise any objection that the Work Orders in
			<lb />
			question as issued by ACIL were not signed by GTPL and therefore,
			<lb />
			there was no agreement in terms of Section 7(4) of the A&amp;C Act.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			26. It is material to note that in its Statement of Claims filed before
			<lb />
			the Arbitral Tribunal, GTPL had asserted that the parties had
			<lb />
			negotiated a contract at a meeting held on 06.03.2013 and pursuant to
			<lb />
			the said meeting, ACIL had issued the Work Order dated 07.03.2013
			<lb />
			which was amended by the Work Order dated 24.07.2013. Paragraphs
			<lb />
			5 and 6 of the Statement of Claims are set out below:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot;5. That the contract to be entered into was negotiated
				<lb />
				by both the Parties in meeting dated 06.03.2013.
				<lb />
				Pursuant to terms being arrived at, the Respondent
				<lb />
				awarded the Work Order dated 07.03.2013 to the
				<lb />
				Claimant herein, in terms of the Work Order bearing
				<lb />
				Reference No.ACIL/Grim-Tech/1060313/2013 the
				<lb />
				work of carrying out pile foundation work for CHP,
				<lb />
				at Muzaffarpur Thermal Power Plant of Kanti Bijlee
				<lb />
				Utpadan Nigam (Ltd.) located in Muzaffarpur, Bihar
				<lb />
				valued at Rs.10,73,94,000 (Ten Crores Seventy
				<lb />
				Three Lacs Ninety Four Thousand) was awarded to
				<lb />
				the Claimant.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				6.
				<lb />
				That in terms of Work order dated 24.07.2013,
				<lb />
				bearing
				<lb />
				Reference
				<lb />
				No.ACIL/Grim-
				<lb />
				Tech/1060313/2013/Amend-1, the earlier Work
				<lb />
				Order dated 07.03.2013 was amended. In terms of
				<lb />
				the amended Work Order dated 24.07.2013, the total
				<lb />
				value of work to be done, being boring of pile
				<lb />
				foundation and fabrication of reinforcement steel
				<lb />
				including cutting, bending, binding, placing, welding
				<lb />
				etc. was valued at Rs.4,72,50,000.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			27. ACIL filed its Statement of Defence. It raised a preliminary
			<lb />
			objection stating that GTPL had invoked the arbitration clause on the
			<lb />
			basis of the Amended Work Order dated 24.07.2013, however, it had
			<lb />
			filed its claims on the basis of the Principal Work Order dated
			<lb />
			07.03.2013. Thus, adjudication of GTPL&quot;s claims was outside the
			<lb />
			scope of reference to arbitration.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			28. In respect of the contents of paragraph 5 of the Statement of
			<lb />
			Claims filed by GTPL, ACIL stated that the same is a matter of record
			<lb />
			and needed no comments. In respect of the contents of paragraph 6 of
			<lb />
			the Statement of Claims, ACIL had traversed the same by responding
			<lb />
			as under:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot;6. That the contents of para no.6 under reply are denied
				<lb />
				and disputed. It is specifically denied that the work
				<lb />
				order dated 07.03.2013 was amended by work order
				<lb />
				dated 24.07.2013. The time allowed for execution
				<lb />
				of work as per work order dated 07.03.2013 had
				<lb />
				expired due to efflux of time as there was no
				<lb />
				provision in work order for extension of time.
				<lb />
				Despite of rates more than market rates for the work
				<lb />
				under work order dated 07.03.2013, no substantial
				<lb />
				work was executed by the Claimant. The respondent
				<lb />
				on 24.07.2013 offered fresh rates to the Claimant for
				<lb />
				execution of work considering the market rates. The
				<lb />
				rates offered by the Respondent were then accepted
				<lb />
				by the Claimant. Accordingly the Respondent
				<lb />
				issued the work order dated 24.07.2013. Hence the
				<lb />
				work order dated 24.07.2013 is a fresh work order
				<lb />
				which has no relation to the earlier work order.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			29.
			<lb />
			It is clear from the above that there was no dispute that the
			<lb />
			Principal Work Order dated 07.03.2013 (which was mentioned at
			<lb />
			paragraph 3 of the Statement of Claims) was issued by ACIL and was
			<lb />
			accepted by GTPL. It is also clear from paragraph 6 of the Statement
			<lb />
			of Defence that ACIL had also agreed that it had issued the Amended
			<lb />
			Work Order dated 24.07.2013, which was accepted by GTPL.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			30. ACIL did not contest that the arbitration agreement as included
			<lb />
			under Clause 27 of the Terms and Conditions appended to the
			<lb />
			Principal Work Order dated 07.03.2013, did not exist as it was not
			<lb />
			signed by GTPL. In terms of Section 7(4) of the A&amp;C Act, an
			<lb />
			assertion of an arbitration agreement in a Statement of Claim, which is
			<lb />
			not denied in the Statement of Defence would be an arbitration
			<lb />
			agreement within the meaning of Section 7(4)(c) of the A&amp;C Act. In
			<lb />
			the present case, as noted above, ACIL had not disputed the existence
			<lb />
			of an arbitration agreement on the ground that the Work Orders were
			<lb />
			not singed by GTPL.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			31. The aforesaid contention is also an afterthought as it was not
			<lb />
			raised by ACIL in its Statement of Defence.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			32.
			<lb />
			The contention that an arbitration agreement did not exist
			<lb />
			between the parties is thus, unmerited and accordingly rejected.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			33. The next question to be addressed is whether there is any
			<lb />
			material before the Arbitral Tribunal to render an award of
			<lb />
			₹2,15,00,000/-(Rupees Two Crores Fifteen Lakhs only) on account of
			<lb />
			damages / compensation for extended deployment of assets at site.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			34. It was GTPL&quot;s case that the works were required to be
			<lb />
			completed within a period of four months, however, the same was
			<lb />
			stretched on account of non-availability of material and other factors
			<lb />
			which were solely attributable to ACIL. GTPL&quot;s assets (two Piling
			<lb />
			Rigs, two Cranes, one Hydra and one JCB) along with the requisite
			<lb />
			support staff remained deployed at the site for an extended period of
			<lb />
			time from December, 2013 to March, 2015. GTPL claimed that it
			<lb />
			could let out its machinery and equipment or could have deployed the
			<lb />
			same at other sites. GTPL had also led evidence to show that the rental
			<lb />
			that could be fetched by hiring out the said machinery and equipment.
			<lb />
			In addition, GTPL had also produced evidence for showing the
			<lb />
			monthly summary of indirect expenses incurred by it.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			35. GTPL&quot;s witness (CW1) had testified that GTPL had raised
			<lb />
			additional Running Account Bills for idle deployment of assets at
			<lb />
			work sites. The said bills were exhibited (Ex.CW1/43 to Ex.CW1/47).
			<lb />
			The aggregate value of the said bills was approximately
			<lb />
			₹1,24,07,942.54/-. ACIL disputed the receipt of these bills/invoices.
			<lb />
			On 07.09.2016, GTPL had issued a legal notice quantifying its claim
			<lb />
			on account of idle assets for the period from December, 2013 to
			<lb />
			March, 2015 at ₹2,98,94,835/-. In its Statement of Claims, GTPL
			<lb />
			claimed a sum of ₹4,09,41,540/-on that count for the period of fifteen
			<lb />
			months.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			36. Although, the Arbitral Tribunal had mentioned the material
			<lb />
			brought on record however, it found that there was &quot;no cogent and
			<lb />
			convincing evidence&quot; for calculating the compensation for the loss
			<lb />
			suffered by the claimant. However, the Arbitral Tribunal awarded a
			<lb />
			sum of ₹2,15,00,000/-on the basis of the average of additional
			<lb />
			Running Account Bills (Ex.CW1/43 to Ex.CW1/47) aggregating
			<lb />
			₹1,24,07,942.54/-and the sum of ₹2,98,94,854/-as claimed by GTPL
			<lb />
			in its notice dated 07.09.2016. The relevant extract of the impugned
			<lb />
			award in respect of the said award of ₹2,15,00,000/-is set out below:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot;90. Above documents proved on record by the Claimant
				<lb />
				include RA Bills issued during the period from 01.11.2013
				<lb />
				to 31.03.2014 which are Exs.CW-1/43 to Ex.CW-47 and
				<lb />
				these total approximately Rs.1,24,07,942.54 (approx.).
				<lb />
				Receipt of these invoices is not admitted by the
				<lb />
				Respondent. This amount of idling charges of machinery
				<lb />
				and equipment is upto 31 st March 2014. When the legal
				<lb />
				notice Ex.CW-1/52 was issued on 07.09.2016 it was
				<lb />
				claimed that if the said assets had been deployed else
				<lb />
				where it would have generated Rs.2,98,94,854/-from
				<lb />
				December, 2013 to March, 2015. However, when the
				<lb />
				statement of claim was filed Claimant prayed for payment
				<lb />
				of Rs.4,09,41,540/-@ Rs.27,29,436/-per month for 15
				<lb />
				months. There being no cogent and convincing evidence
				<lb />
				for calculating compensation for the loss suffered by
				<lb />
				Complainant to demobilize their machinery due to non-
				<lb />
				issue of exit gate pass on account of dispute ensued
				<lb />
				between the Respondent and their principals, it shall be
				<lb />
				reasonable to calculate the loss at an average of the amount
				<lb />
				shown in RA Bills E-1 to E-51 Ex.CW-1/43 to Ex.CW-
				<lb />
				1/47 and what had been asked for by the Claimant vide
				<lb />
				their legal notice dated 07.09.2016 (Ex.CW-1/52) receipt
				<lb />
				of which cannot be disputed by the Respondent who had
				<lb />
				even replied it by their letter dated 13.10.2016 (Ex.CW-
				<lb />
				1/53), vaguely denying that the Respondent had not kept
				<lb />
				deployed at site, the machinery, labour and staff from
				<lb />
				December, 2013 to March, 2015, whereas it is an admitted
				<lb />
				and proven fact that the machinery was mobilized at site at
				<lb />
				the cost of the Respondent, who could not arrange to get
				<lb />
				the Exist gate pass issued till March, 2015. I am,
				<lb />
				therefore, of the considered view that inability (or
				<lb />
				demobilization of assets from the site by the Claimant is
				<lb />
				attributable to the Respondent who shall have to
				<lb />
				compensate the Claimant at least to the extent of lumpsum
				<lb />
				Rs.2,15,00,000/-in this case for all the expenses incurred
				<lb />
				on machinery, equipment and staff etc. etc.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				[Underlined for emphasis]
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			37. It is clear from the above that there is no real basis for
			<lb />
			quantifying the damages at ₹2,15,00,000/-. The Arbitral Tribunal had
			<lb />
			noted that receipt of Ex.CW-1/43 to Ex.CW-1/47 was disputed by
			<lb />
			ACIL. The Arbitral Tribunal had also held that there was &quot;no cogent
			<lb />
			and convincing evidence for calculating compensation for the loss
			<lb />
			suffered by Complainant to demobilize their machinery due to non-
			<lb />
			issue of exit gate pass&quot;.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			38. In view of the finding of lack of cogent and convincing
			<lb />
			evidence regarding quantification of the damages, the award of
			<lb />
			₹2,15,00,000/-on an ad-hoc basis cannot be sustained. There is no
			<lb />
			basis for computing the said amount of damages. There is merit in the
			<lb />
			contention that there was material before the Arbitral Tribunal for
			<lb />
			quantification of the claims and, the Arbitral Tribunal had also noted
			<lb />
			that GTPL had proved additional Running Account Bills aggregating
			<lb />
			approximately ₹1,24,07,942.54/-. However, the basis on which the
			<lb />
			Arbitral Tribunal had ascertained the amount of ₹2,15,00,000/-as the
			<lb />
			loss suffered by GTPL being average of the invoices and the amount
			<lb />
			claimed, is patently erroneous.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			39. It is not permissible for this Court to re-appreciate the evidence
			<lb />
			to calculate the damages as established by GTPL and modify the
			<lb />
			award of damages. It is not open for this Court in this proceeding to
			<lb />
			modify the arbitral award. In view of the above, the impugned award
			<lb />
			to the extent that it awards damages in the sum of ₹2,15,00,000/-is
			<lb />
			liable to be set aside.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			40. The last question to be examined is whether the award of 12%
			<lb />
			compounded interest on the awarded amount of ₹1,00,07,985/-is
			<lb />
			beyond the claim made by GTPL.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			41. GTPL had sought pre-reference and pendente lite interest at the
			<lb />
			rate of 18% per annum on the aforesaid claim. It had further sought
			<lb />
			pre-reference and pendente lite interest at the rate of 10.5% (2% above
			<lb />
			the prevalent rate of interest of 8.5%) in respect of its claim of
			<lb />
			compensation for extended deployment of assets and reimbursement
			<lb />
			of expenditure. The Arbitral Tribunal had awarded interest at the rate
			<lb />
			of 12% per annum on the amount of ₹1,00,07,985/-which is less than
			<lb />
			GTPL&quot;s claim for interest at the rate of 18% per annum. Thus, the
			<lb />
			contention that the Arbitral Tribunal had awarded interest at a rate
			<lb />
			higher than as claimed by GTPL is erroneous. GTPL&quot;s claim for
			<lb />
			interest at the rate of 10.5% per annum was in respect of claim for
			<lb />
			compensation for deployment of machinery and not for the
			<lb />
			outstanding dues (Claim-A).
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			42. Having stated the above, there is merit in the contention that the
			<lb />
			Arbitral Tribunal could not have awarded any compound interest. The
			<lb />
			Arbitral Tribunal had awarded 12% simple interest on the amount of
			<lb />
			₹1,00,07,985/-. However, it further held that if the aforesaid amount
			<lb />
			is not paid within the period of thirty days of the award, interest shall
			<lb />
			be compounded at the rate of 12% till the date of realization. No such
			<lb />
			claim for compound interest was made by GTPL. The said award for
			<lb />
			compound interest on failure on the part of ACIL to pay the awarded
			<lb />
			amount within a period of thirty days, is clearly in terrorem and,
			<lb />
			therefore not sustainable.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			43. In view of the above, the impugned award is set aside to the
			<lb />
			extent that the Arbitral Tribunal had awarded a sum of ₹2,15,00,000/-
			<lb />
			as damages/compensation along with interest at the rate of 6% per
			<lb />
			annum. The award to the extent that it directs payment of compound
			<lb />
			interest if the amount of ₹1,00,07,985/-is not paid within a period of
			<lb />
			thirty days is also set aside.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			44. To make it abundantly clear, the impugned award of a sum of
			<lb />
			₹1,00,07,985/-along with simple interest at the rate of 12% per
			<lb />
			annum with effect from 21.07.2016 till the date of payment is not
			<lb />
			interfered with.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			45. The petition is disposed of in the aforesaid terms. All pending
			<lb />
			applications are also disposed of.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			VIBHU BAKHRU, J
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			FEBRUARY 10, 2022
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			&quot;gsr&quot;/v
			<lb />
		</p>
	</text>
</tei>
