<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<p>
			<lb />
			There are two plaintiffs and a sole defendant in the instant
			<lb />
			suit.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			2. Instant suit has been filed inter-alia complaining of
			<lb />
			Infringement of plaintiffs&apos; registered trademark and passing off qua
			<lb />
			plaintiffs&apos; registered trademark. Injunctive reliefs in this regard have
			<lb />
			been sought for and there are incidental /ancillary limbs of prayers
			<lb />
			also.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			3. Before this Commercial Division proceeds to examine the
			<lb />
			facts of this case, it is necessary to set out the trajectory of this suit
			<lb />
			thus far.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			4. As mentioned supra, there is a sole defendant in the suit.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			5. Service on sole defendant was effected on 21.07.2018
			<lb />
			before learned Master. Proceedings of learned Master dated
			<lb />
			09.10.2018 in this regard, reads as follows:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&apos;Sole defendant served on 21.07.2018. Hence
				<lb />
				post before Hon&apos;ble Court.&apos;
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			6. After the aforesaid proceedings of learned Master, this suit
			<lb />
			was placed before this Commercial Division, which in turn directed
			<lb />
			the suit to be listed in &apos;UNDEFENDED BOARD&apos; and ultimately, set the
			<lb />
			sole defendant ex-parte on 30.11.2018. The proceedings before this
			<lb />
			Commercial Division in this regard are dated 24.10.2018,
			<lb />
			30.10.2018 and 30.11.2018 which read as follows:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&apos;Proceedings on 24.10.2018
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				Read this in conjunction with and in continuation of earlier
				<lb />
				proceedings of this Commercial Division dated 20.08.2018,
				<lb />
				which reads as follows:
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				&apos;List this matter before learned Master for completion of
				<lb />
				service on the sole defendant in the main suit.&apos;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				2. Pursuant to the aforesaid proceedings, learned
				<lb />
				Master has made proceedings dated 09.10.2018, which reads
				<lb />
				as follows:
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				&apos;Sole defendant served on 21.07.2018. Hence post before
				<lb />
				Hon&apos;ble Court.&apos;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				3. From the proceedings of the learned Master, it
				<lb />
				comes to light that sole defendant has been duly served in
				<lb />
				this suit on 21.07.2018.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				4. Time limit for filing written statement prescribed
				<lb />
				under the amended &apos;The Code of Civil Procedure, 1908&apos;, (&apos;CPC&apos;
				<lb />
				for brevity) as amended by &apos;The Commercial Courts Act, 2015&apos;,
				<lb />
				(&apos;said Act&apos; for brevity) has expired. No one has entered
				<lb />
				appearance and no written statement has been filed.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				5. Registry is directed to list this matter in the
				<lb />
				&apos;UNDEFENDED BOARD&apos; on 30.10.2018. Registry to show the
				<lb />
				name of the sole defendant along with full/complete address
				<lb />
				as in the long and short cause titles of the plaint in the next
				<lb />
				listing.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				6. List this matter in &apos;UNDEFENDED BOARD&apos;
				<lb />
				on
				<lb />
				30.10.2018.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				&apos;Proceedings on 30.10.2018
			</item>
			<lb />
			<item>
				Read this in conjunction with and in continuation of
				<lb />
				earlier proceedings of this Commercial Division dated
				<lb />
				24.10.2018.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				2. Pursuant to earlier proceedings, this suit has been
				<lb />
				listed under the caption &apos;UNDEFENDED BOARD&apos; today.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				3. However Ms.Gladys Daniel, learned counsel for
				<lb />
				plaintiffs very fairly points out that time prescribed for
				<lb />
				completion of pleadings by the defendant is not over as yet,
				<lb />
				as the suit summons, according to her, were served on
				<lb />
				21.07.2018.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				List this matter under the same caption on 30.11.2018.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				Proceedings on 30.11.2018
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				Read this in conjunction with and in continuation of earlier
				<lb />
				proceedings of this Commercial Division dated 30.10.2018.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				2. Suit is listed under the caption &apos;UNDEFENDED BOARD&apos;
				<lb />
				today. There is no representation for the sole defendant.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				3. It is pointed out that the time prescribed for
				<lb />
				completion of pleadings is now over and no written statement
				<lb />
				has been filed. Sole defendant is set ex-parte.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				4. List this matter before learned Additional Master-II
				<lb />
				on 11.12.2018 for recording ex-parte evidence. Learned
				<lb />
				Additional Master-II is requested to record ex-parte evidence
				<lb />
				preferably on the same day and in any event on or before
				<lb />
				14.12.2018.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				5. Thereafter, list this matter before this Commercial
				<lb />
				Division under the caption &apos;ORAL ARGUMENTS&apos; on 19.12.2018.&apos;
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			7. After the aforesaid proceedings before this Commercial
			<lb />
			Division, suit was set down before learned Additional Master-II for
			<lb />
			recording ex-parte evidence. Before learned Additional Master-II,
			<lb />
			one B.Gnana Sambandam, who has been described as Assistant
			<lb />
			General Manager -Legal &amp; Secretarial of the second plaintiff
			<lb />
			company, has been examined as P.W.1. 14 documents i.e., Exs.P1
			<lb />
			to P14 have been marked. Thereafter, the suit file has now been
			<lb />
			placed before this Commercial Division again &apos;For Arguments&apos;.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			8. Ms.Gladys Daniel , learned counsel on record for plaintiffs is
			<lb />
			before this Commercial Division.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			9. Learned counsel for plaintiffs submits that crux and
			<lb />
			gravamen of the entire lis is constituted by plaintiffs&apos; two trademark
			<lb />
			registrations in Classes 35 and 41.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			10. Plaintiffs&apos; registration in Class 41 is vide Trademark
			<lb />
			No.3371009 and the Legal Use Certificate [Trademark Registration
			<lb />
			Certificate] for this has been marked as Ex.P9. Trademark
			<lb />
			Registration Certificate in Class 35 has not been marked, but there
			<lb />
			is an averment in the plaint in this regard which remains unrefuted.
			<lb />
			Trademark registration in class 35 is Trademark No.3371003 and it
			<lb />
			is dated 26.09.2016.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			11. Though the aforesaid two trademark registrations
			<lb />
			constitute the nucleus of this lis [which shall hereinafter collectively
			<lb />
			be referred to as &apos;suit TMs&apos; for brevity], plaintiffs on the date of
			<lb />
			filing the plaint, had as many as 127 registrations, enumeration of
			<lb />
			which has been set out in paragraph 15 in a Tabular Column and
			<lb />
			the same reads as follows:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			12. Learned counsel for plaintiffs submits that plaintiffs had a
			<lb />
			steady growth and the manner in which suit TMs and the other
			<lb />
			aforementioned trademark registrations vest in the plaintiffs is
			<lb />
			articulated in paragraph 7 of the plaint. Learned counsel refers to
			<lb />
			paragraph 7 of the plaint, which reads as follows:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&apos;7. A proprietary concern Aachi Spices and Foods was
				<lb />
				registered on 28.12.2006. Aachi Masala Foods (P) Ltd who
				<lb />
				acquired the trademark AACHI on 30.11.2006 from
				<lb />
				Abishek Enterprises and Naveen Products assigned the
				<lb />
				same in favour of the 1 st Plaintiff, on 30.03.2007. On
				<lb />
				01.04.2007, the Plaintiff executed a License User
				<lb />
				Agreement in favor of Aachi Masala Foods (P) Ltd. The sole
				<lb />
				proprietary concern of the 1 st Plaintiff owned the
				<lb />
				Intellectual Property Rights under the trademark AACHI.
				<lb />
				The Trademark AACHI expanded on its list of products.
				<lb />
				The business of AACHI was expanding in mammoth
				<lb />
				proportions. On 17.03.2010, Aachi Spices and Foods
				<lb />
				Private Limited was incorporated. At the time of
				<lb />
				incorporation of Aachi Spices and Foods Private Limited the
				<lb />
				Memorandum of Association of the company reiterated at
				<lb />
				clause B-11 that the Trademark AACHI along with its right,
				<lb />
				title and interst were vested with the 1 st Plaintiff who
				<lb />
				already owned the Trademark AACHI. On 21.04.2010 the
				<lb />
				1 st Plaintiff entered into a LICENSE USER AGREEMENT with
				<lb />
				Aachi Spices and Foods Private Limited to use the
				<lb />
				trademark AACHI. On 21.04.2010 the 1 st Plaintiff entered
				<lb />
				into a fresh LICENSE USER AGREEMENT with AACHI
				<lb />
				Masala Foods Private Limited.&apos;
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			13. Learned counsel also submits that huge sums of monies
			<lb />
			are being spent every financial year by the plaintiffs towards
			<lb />
			advertisement expenditure and learned counsel for plaintiff submits
			<lb />
			that a tabular column giving the turnover as well as the
			<lb />
			advertisement expenditure (financial year wise) has been set out in
			<lb />
			Paragraph 14 of the plaint. Tabular column in paragraph 14 of the
			<lb />
			plaint reads as follows:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<figure type="table">
			S.No.
			<lb />
			YEAR
			<lb />
			TURNOVER
			<lb />
			(in Rs)
			<lb />
			ADVERTISING
			<lb />
			EXPENDITURE
			<lb />
			(in Rs)
			<lb />
			1.
			<lb />
			1995-1996
			<lb />
			3,96,420.00
			<lb />
			9,893.00
			<lb />
			2.
			<lb />
			1996-1997
			<lb />
			4,37,568.00
			<lb />
			4,691.00
			<lb />
			3.
			<lb />
			1997-1998
			<lb />
			5,10,755.00
			<lb />
			352.00
			<lb />
			4.
			<lb />
			1998-1999
			<lb />
			14,68,159.00
			<lb />
			15,820.00
			<lb />
			5.
			<lb />
			1999-2000
			<lb />
			20,27,457.00
			<lb />
			16,775.00
			<lb />
			6.
			<lb />
			2000-2001
			<lb />
			52,03,979.00
			<lb />
			57,676.00
			<lb />
			7.
			<lb />
			2001-2002
			<lb />
			64,12,491.00
			<lb />
			2,13,512.00
			<lb />
			8.
			<lb />
			2002-2003
			<lb />
			1,69,44,334.00
			<lb />
			6,62,290.00
			<lb />
			9.
			<lb />
			2003-2004
			<lb />
			9,00,05,884.00
			<lb />
			19,63,479.00
			<lb />
			10.
			<lb />
			2004-2005
			<lb />
			24,46,95,540.00
			<lb />
			1,13,28,450.00
			<lb />
			11.
			<lb />
			2005-2006
			<lb />
			79,47,99,230.00
			<lb />
			4,63,96,880.00
			<lb />
			12.
			<lb />
			2006-2007
			<lb />
			1,36,54,50,781.00
			<lb />
			5,68,45,817.00
			<lb />
			13.
			<lb />
			2007-2008
			<lb />
			2,07,85,55,508.00
			<lb />
			7,87,06,261.00
			<lb />
			14.
			<lb />
			2008-2009
			<lb />
			4,14,12,42,106.00
			<lb />
			9,40,86,979.00
			<lb />
			S.No.
			<lb />
			YEAR
			<lb />
			TURNOVER
			<lb />
			(in Rs)
			<lb />
			ADVERTISING
			<lb />
			EXPENDITURE
			<lb />
			(in Rs)
			<lb />
			15.
			<lb />
			2009-2010
			<lb />
			4,73,98,26,852.00
			<lb />
			10,76,86,530.00
			<lb />
			16.
			<lb />
			2010-2011
			<lb />
			6,40,40,50,524.00
			<lb />
			11,63,97,497.00
			<lb />
			17.
			<lb />
			2011-2012
			<lb />
			7,59,35,14,309.00
			<lb />
			12,42,15,050.00
			<lb />
			18.
			<lb />
			2012-2013
			<lb />
			8,82,91,64,390.00
			<lb />
			13,72,06,476.00
			<lb />
			19.
			<lb />
			2013-2014
			<lb />
			11,27,06,92,876.00 19,57,87,446.00
			<lb />
			20.
			<lb />
			2014-2015
			<lb />
			13,20,61,70,537.00 21,00,17,044.00
			<lb />
		</figure>
		<p>
			14. According to learned counsel for plaintiffs, they came to
			<lb />
			know about the infringement of suit TMs sometime in January 2018
			<lb />
			and the manner in which they came to know and the details of the
			<lb />
			same have been articulated in Paragraph 19 of the plaint. This
			<lb />
			Commercial Division was taken through paragraph 19 of the plaint
			<lb />
			by learned counsel for plaintiffs and the same reads as follows:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&apos;19. That in around January 2018 to the shock of the
				<lb />
				plaintiffs, it was discovered that the Defendant&apos;s
				<lb />
				Trade Mark application for registration of their Trade
				<lb />
				Mark ACHI&apos;S SANTHAI under A.No.3707649 in class
				<lb />
				41 is advertised in the Trade Mark Journal No:1834
				<lb />
				dated 29/01/2018 at page No.6607. The Defendant is
				<lb />
				providing service with respect to arranging exhibitions
				<lb />
				in Class-41 under this impugned Trade Mark &quot;ACHI&apos;S
				<lb />
				SANTHAI&quot;. Immediately the Plaintiffs&apos; have initiated
				<lb />
				appropriate opposition proceedings under No:930864
				<lb />
				the Trade Mark Registry at Chennai opposing the
				<lb />
				Defendant&apos;s Trade Mark application from grant of
				<lb />
				registration. Shortly thereafter, in February 2018, the
				<lb />
				Defendant Trademark application No.3707648 for the
				<lb />
				mark ACHI&apos;S SANTHI in Class 35 was advertised in
				<lb />
				Trademark Journal No.1835. The Defendant has
				<lb />
				adopted the word ACHI&apos;S SANTHI per se which
				<lb />
				amounts to deception and confusion in the market
				<lb />
				and an infringement of the Plaintiff&apos;s Intellectual
				<lb />
				Property Rights.&apos;
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			15. Saying so , learned counsel submitted that the publication
			<lb />
			of plaintiffs&apos; application in the trademark journals have been marked
			<lb />
			as Exs.P11 and P13 in Classes 41 and 35 respectively. Exs.P11 and
			<lb />
			P13, which are publications in trademark journals in Classes 41 and
			<lb />
			35 respectively are as follows:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			Ex.P11
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			Ex.P35
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			16. Learned counsel for plaintiffs submits that plaintiffs have
			<lb />
			opposed the aforesaid applications for trademark registrations.
			<lb />
			Notices of opposition have been marked as Exs.P12 and P14.
			<lb />
			Learned counsel submits that even as of today, defendant&apos;s
			<lb />
			applications for aforesaid registrations in classes 41 and 35 are lying
			<lb />
			in / pending under objection. Learned counsel submits that stage is
			<lb />
			set in the Trade Mark Registry for hearing in the opposition
			<lb />
			proceedings.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			17. Be that as it may, the trajectory of this suit thus far has
			<lb />
			been captured in various proceedings of this Commercial Division,
			<lb />
			which have been extracted and reproduced supra. A perusal of the
			<lb />
			trajectory of this suit thus far, as captured in proceedings before
			<lb />
			learned Master as well as before this Commercial Division (extracted
			<lb />
			and reproduced supra elsewhere in this judgment will reveal that
			<lb />
			sole defendant, in spite of being served, albeit by substituted
			<lb />
			service (owing to difficulty in being served through normal modes),
			<lb />
			has not chosen to come before this Commercial Division either in
			<lb />
			person or through a counsel. Obviously, no written statement has
			<lb />
			been filed.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			18. In the aforesaid backdrop, learned counsel for plaintiff
			<lb />
			very fairly points out that defendant&apos;s applications are for proposed
			<lb />
			use and it is for arranging exhibitions and also for provision of an
			<lb />
			online marketplace for buyers and sellers of goods and services as
			<lb />
			is evident from Exs.P11 and P13 respectively.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			19. It has already been set out supra that as many as 14
			<lb />
			exhibits, namely Exs.P1 to P14 have been marked and the details of
			<lb />
			the 14 exhibits are as follows:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<figure type="table">
			S.No. Exhibits
			<lb />
			Description of Documents
			<lb />
			1
			<lb />
			P1
			<lb />
			The original Authorisation Letter dated
			<lb />
			08.12.2018
			<lb />
			2
			<lb />
			P2
			<lb />
			(series) (2 Nos.) are the copy of the
			<lb />
			certificate of Incorporation of Aachi Masala
			<lb />
			Food Pvt. Ltd., dated 30.06.2006 and the
			<lb />
			copy of the certificate of Incorporation of
			<lb />
			Aachi Spices and Foods P. Ltd., dated
			<lb />
			17.03.2010 (Compared with original)
			<lb />
			3
			<lb />
			P3
			<lb />
			(series) (3 Nos.) are the copies of (1) Deed of
			<lb />
			Assignment between Abishek Enterprises and
			<lb />
			Aachi Masala Foods P.Ltd., dated 01.12.2006.
			<lb />
			(2) Deed of Assignment between Naveen
			<lb />
			Product and Aachi Malasala Foods P. Ltd.,
			<lb />
			dated 01.12.2006, (3) Deed of Assignment
			<lb />
			between Aachi Masala Foods P. Ltd., and
			<lb />
			Mr.A.D.Padmasingh Isaac Trading as Aachi
			<lb />
			Spices and Foods dated 30.03.2007
			<lb />
			4
			<lb />
			P4
			<lb />
			The copy of Dissolution Deed between
			<lb />
			Mrs.Rani Pandian and MrA.D.Padmasingh
			<lb />
			Isaac dissolving the partnership firm, Naveen
			<lb />
			product dated 31.03.2007 (compared with
			<lb />
			original)
			<lb />
			5
			<lb />
			P5
			<lb />
			(series) (3 Nos) are the copies of certificate
			<lb />
			of Commercial Tax Registration of Aachi
			<lb />
			Masala and Foods P. Ltd., dated 10.07.2006,
			<lb />
			Certificate of Commercial Tax Registration
			<lb />
			and Central Sales Tax of Aachi Spices and
			<lb />
			Foods P. Ltd., dated 28.12.2006 and
			<lb />
			03.01.2007 (compared with original)
			<lb />
			S.No. Exhibits
			<lb />
			Description of Documents
			<lb />
			6
			<lb />
			P6
			<lb />
			The copy of Memorandum of Association of
			<lb />
			Aachi Spices and Foods P. Ltd., Dated
			<lb />
			06.03.2010 (Compared with original)
			<lb />
			7
			<lb />
			P7
			<lb />
			(Series) (3 Nos.) are the copies of Trade
			<lb />
			Mark License User Agreement between
			<lb />
			Mr.A.D.Padmasingh Isaac trading as Aachi
			<lb />
			Spices and Foods and Aachi Masala Foods (P)
			<lb />
			Ltd., Dated 01.04.2007, Trade Mark Licence
			<lb />
			User Agreement between Mr.A.D.Padmasingh
			<lb />
			Isaac and Aachi Spices and Food P.Ltd.,.
			<lb />
			Dated 21.04.2010, Trade Mark License User
			<lb />
			Agreement
			<lb />
			between
			<lb />
			Mr.A.D.Padmasingh
			<lb />
			Isaac and Aachi Masala Foods P. Ltd., Dated
			<lb />
			21.04.2010 (compared with original)
			<lb />
			8
			<lb />
			P8
			<lb />
			The copy of List of Products Manufactured
			<lb />
			and Marketed by the plaintiff&apos;s bearing the
			<lb />
			Trade Mark &quot;Aachi&quot;.
			<lb />
			9
			<lb />
			P9
			<lb />
			(series) (4 Nos) are copies of Legal Use
			<lb />
			Certificate and Trade Mark Under No.838786,
			<lb />
			1479159, 3371001 and 3371009 (Compared
			<lb />
			with original)
			<lb />
			10
			<lb />
			P10
			<lb />
			The copy of the Trademark Registration
			<lb />
			Certificate of the Mark Aachi in various
			<lb />
			countries around the world (compared with
			<lb />
			original)
			<lb />
			11
			<lb />
			P11
			<lb />
			The Defendant Trade Mark A.No.3707649
			<lb />
			dated 20.12.2017 Class 41 (under Section 65
			<lb />
			B Indian Evidence Act, 1872)
			<lb />
			12
			<lb />
			P12
			<lb />
			The Notice of opposition dated 26.04.2018
			<lb />
			under Section 65N Indian Evidence Act,
			<lb />
			1872)
			<lb />
			13
			<lb />
			P13
			<lb />
			The Defendant Trade Mark A.No.3707648
			<lb />
			dated 20.12.2017 Class 35 (under Section 65
			<lb />
			B Indian Evidence Act, 1872)
			<lb />
			14
			<lb />
			P14
			<lb />
			The Notice of opposition dated 26.04.2018
			<lb />
			(under Section 65B Indian Evidence Act,
			<lb />
			1872)
			<lb />
		</figure>
		<p>
			20. This Commercial Division has perused the deposition of
			<lb />
			PW1 as well as the aforesaid exhibits. Deposition of PW1 is cogent
			<lb />
			and convincing. The aforesaid exhibits (some of which have been
			<lb />
			alluded to supra) are such that they compliment, buttress and
			<lb />
			bolster the plaint averments. This takes us to the prayer paragraph
			<lb />
			in the plaint. Prayer paragraph in the plaint is Paragraph No.31 and
			<lb />
			the same reads as follows:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&apos; 31. The Plaintiffs, therefore, pray for a Judgement and
				<lb />
				Decree for:
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(a) granting a permanent injunction, restraining the
				<lb />
				Defendant, by itself, its servants, agents, distributors, or
				<lb />
				anyone claiming through him from manufacturing, selling,
				<lb />
				advertising and offering for sale of goods/service using the
				<lb />
				Trade Mark &quot;ACHI&apos;S SANTHAI&quot; or any other similar Trade
				<lb />
				Mark or similar sounding expression or in any media and use
				<lb />
				the same in invoices, letter heads and visiting cards or by
				<lb />
				using any other trade mark which is in any way visually or
				<lb />
				deceptively or phonetically similar to the Plaintiff&apos;s trade
				<lb />
				marks AACHI and use the same in pouches, or any other
				<lb />
				goods/service or use the mark in invoices, letters heads and
				<lb />
				visiting cards or any other trade literature or by using any
				<lb />
				other trade mark which is in any way visually, or phonetically
				<lb />
				similar to the Plaintiff&apos;s registered Trade Mark Nos.838786,
				<lb />
				1479159, 3371001 &amp; 3371009 or in any manner infringe the
				<lb />
				Plaintiff&apos;s registered Trade Mark.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(b) granting a permanent injunction, restraining the
				<lb />
				Defendant, by itself, its servants, agents, distributors, or
				<lb />
				anyone claiming through him from manufacturing, selling,
				<lb />
				advertising and offering for sale of goods/service using Trade
				<lb />
				Mark &quot;ACHI&apos;S SANTHAI&quot; or any other similar Trade Mark or
				<lb />
				in any media and use the same in invoices, letter heads and
				<lb />
				visiting cards or by using any other trade mark which is in
				<lb />
				any way visually or deceptively or phonetically similar to the
				<lb />
				Plaintiffs&apos; Trade Mark AACHI in respect of goods/service or
				<lb />
				use the mark in invoices, letters heads and visiting cards or
				<lb />
				any other trade literature or by using any other trade mark
				<lb />
				which is in any way visually, or phonetically similar to the
				<lb />
				Plaintiffs&apos; Trade Mark AACHI or in any manner pass off the
				<lb />
				Plaintiff&apos;s goods/service.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(c) directing the Defendant to surrender to the
				<lb />
				Plaintiffs all the packing material, cartons, advertisement
				<lb />
				materials and hoardings, letter-heads, visiting cards, office
				<lb />
				stationery and all other materials containing/bearing the
				<lb />
				Trade Mark &quot;ACHI&apos;S SANTHAI&quot; or other identical trade mark
				<lb />
				used in the pouches and packets bearing the word AACHI.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(d) directing the Defendant to render an account of
				<lb />
				profits made by them by the use of the impugned trademark
				<lb />
				&quot;ACHI&apos;S SANTHAI&quot; on the goods referred and decree the suit
				<lb />
				for the profits found to have been made by the Defendant,
				<lb />
				after the Defendant has rendered accounts:
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(e) directing the Defendant to pay to the Plaintiffs the
				<lb />
				cost to the suit, and
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(f) pass such further or other order, as this Hon&apos;ble
				<lb />
				Court may deem fit and proper in the circumstances of the
				<lb />
				case and thus render justice.&apos;
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			21. From the narrative supra, it is clear that plaintiffs are
			<lb />
			entitled to an injunctive decree in terms of sub-paragraph (a) of
			<lb />
			prayer paragraph. With regard to sub-paragraphs (b), (c) and (d)
			<lb />
			as the defendant is only a proposed user and as there is no material
			<lb />
			before this Commercial Division, as of today, to show the actual use
			<lb />
			of the mark by the defendant, these prayer limbs are not granted
			<lb />
			for the present reserving the rights of the plaintiffs in this regard, if
			<lb />
			cause of action arises in future.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			22. This Commercial Division now considers the prayer limb
			<lb />
			for costs contained in sub-paragraph (e) and the usual residuary
			<lb />
			limb in any prayer paragraph (contained in sub-paragraph (f))
			<lb />
			together.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			23. This suit has been presented on 10.07.2018. The
			<lb />
			defendant has applied for registration of marks [exhibits P11 and
			<lb />
			P13] as alluded to supra and are pursuing the same before the
			<lb />
			Trademark Registry, while it is being opposed and contested by the
			<lb />
			plaintiffs. Notwithstanding the fact that plaintiffs have taken all
			<lb />
			efforts for service of suit summons in usual mode, the defendant
			<lb />
			compelled the plaintiff to effect service through substituted service.
			<lb />
			The proceedings of learned Master extracted supra will reveal that
			<lb />
			the plaintiffs have ultimately effected service by way of substituted
			<lb />
			service as all conventional methods did not yield result. The
			<lb />
			obtaining position of simultaneously pursuing the applications before
			<lb />
			the Trademark Registry on the teeth of opposition / objection by the
			<lb />
			plaintiffs would show that the defendant has deliberately evaded
			<lb />
			service qua conventional methods.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			24. However, the defendant has been ultimately served by
			<lb />
			resorting to substituted service.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			25. Learned counsel for plaintiffs requests this Commercial
			<lb />
			Division to consider imposing compensatory costs/exemplary costs
			<lb />
			on defendant in the light of conduct of the defendant which has
			<lb />
			been referred to supra. Learned counsel also pointed out that the
			<lb />
			defendant has compelled plaintiffs to carry this matter for a
			<lb />
			substantial time in this Court, expending money, energy and effort.
			<lb />
			Reference to Section 35-A &apos;The Code of Civil Procedure, 1908&apos;
			<lb />
			(&apos;C.P.C.&apos; for brevity) as amended by &apos;The Commercial Courts Act,
			<lb />
			2015&apos; (&apos;said Act&apos; for brevity) was also made. Section 35-A provides
			<lb />
			for compensatory costs in respect of false or vexatious defences. In
			<lb />
			the instant case, defendant pursuing the trademark registration
			<lb />
			applications on the teeth of opposition, but evading conventional
			<lb />
			modes of service, compelling substituted service and not appearing
			<lb />
			before this Court even after service being effected through
			<lb />
			substituted service, in the considered view of this Commercial
			<lb />
			Division will qualify as a vexatious defence (within the meaning of
			<lb />
			Section 35-A of amended CPC as amended by said Act) as it is a
			<lb />
			vexatious manner of defending a suit. Be that as it may, in the light
			<lb />
			of the trajectory and in the light of the defendant&apos;s approach to this
			<lb />
			suit, this Commercial Division is convinced that it is appropriate to
			<lb />
			impose compensatory costs of Rs.1 lakh (Rupees One Lakh only) on
			<lb />
			the defendant.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			26. Plaintiffs will obviously be entitled to costs as the plaintiffs
			<lb />
			have incurred substantial expenditure in carrying this suit to its
			<lb />
			logical end.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			27. Suit is decreed with costs and compensatory costs as set
			<lb />
			out supra. Consequently, connected interlocutory applications are
			<lb />
			closed.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			20.12.2018
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			M.SUNDAR.J.
			<lb />
		</p>
	</text>
</tei>
