<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<p>
			Mr.S.Muthuvenkataraman, learned counsel on record for writ petitioner
			<lb />
			and Mr.V.Sundareswaran, learned Panel Counsel (GST) on behalf of the first
			<lb />
			respondent are before this Court. To be noted, second respondent is Branch
			<lb />
			Manager of the Bank in which the writ petitioner has an account, which is
			<lb />
			subject matter of attachment and therefore, the second respondent is only a
			<lb />
			formal party and in the nature of garnishee.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			2. In this backdrop, with consent of learned counsel on both sides, the
			<lb />
			main writ petition is taken up, heard out and is being disposed of.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			3. Be that as it may, the first respondent, who is the contesting
			<lb />
			respondent has filed counter affidavit dated 09.07.2019. The subject matter of
			<lb />
			instant writ petition arises under the &apos;Central Goods and Services Tax Act,
			<lb />
			2017&apos; (&apos;CGST Act&apos; for the sake of brevity).
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			and from 01.07.2017, dealers were entitled to get credits, which were available
			<lb />
			in their accounts or electronic ledger account (as was the practice under fiscal
			<lb />
			law which was operating upto 30.06.2017) can be transferred to the credit of
			<lb />
			the dealer under the CGST Regime.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			5. It is the case of the writ petitioner in the instant writ petition that the
			<lb />
			writ petitioner had certain credits in the form of &apos;Input Tax Credit&apos; (&apos;ITC&apos; for
			<lb />
			brevity) as on 30.06.2017, under the aforesaid circumstances, owing to the
			<lb />
			CGST regime becoming operational, the writ petitioner became liable to pay
			<lb />
			&apos;Good and Services Tax&apos;(&apos;GST&apos;for brevity) on a monthly basis from the month
			<lb />
			of July 2017. With regard to payment of GST from July of 2017, there is no
			<lb />
			disputation or disagreement before this Court that under the CGST Act there is
			<lb />
			a provision to pay tax either by cash or by way of credits which were available
			<lb />
			to the credit of a dealer as of 30.06.2017.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			6. In the light of the aforesaid undisputed position, it is the case of the
			<lb />
			writ petitioner that when the writ petitioner became liable to pay GST from July
			<lb />
			2017 it choose to pay the tax by way of ITC which stood to its credit as of
			<lb />
			30.06.2017. When the writ petitioner attempted to do so, there were a
			<lb />
			technical glitch and therefore, the writ petitioner encountered enormous
			<lb />
			difficulty having the payments made in such a manner is the specific
			<lb />
			receipt dated 20.10.2017 and the corresponding bank statement dated
			<lb />
			20.01.2018, to demonstrate that with regard to September and December
			<lb />
			months for the year 2017, there was a shortfall with regard to available ITC
			<lb />
			qua GST that had to be paid and the shortfall component was paid by cash.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			11. To be noted, with regard to instant case on hand, the writ petitioner
			<lb />
			has been called upon to pay interest of little over Rs.1.64 crores
			<lb />
			(Rs.1,64,49,541 to be precise) towards delay in payment of GST for seven
			<lb />
			months from July 2017 to January 2018 (both months inclusive).
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			12. There is no disputation or disagreement before this Court that post
			<lb />
			January 2018, the technical glitch of Tax Department&apos;s portal stood rectified
			<lb />
			and the writ petitioner has been paying GST through the relevant portal.
			<lb />
			Therefore, this entire writ petition is confined to payment of interest, for what
			<lb />
			according to the first respondent is, delayed payment of GST for seven months
			<lb />
			i.e., July 2017 to January 2018.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			13. Before this Court adverts to the technical glitch, there is no
			<lb />
			disputation that the dates on which the monthly GST became payable for the
			<lb />
			seven months and the dates on which they were actually paid.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			14. Based on the aforesaid dates of payment, according to the first
			<lb />
			respondent the number of days of delay in payment of GST for the aforesaid
			<lb />
			seven months is as follows:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<figure type="table">
			Sl.No
			<lb />
			.
			<lb />
			Month
			<lb />
			Due date to pay Tax
			<lb />
			Date of debit
			<lb />
			1.
			<lb />
			July-17
			<lb />
			25-Aug-2017
			<lb />
			20-Feb-2018
			<lb />
			2.
			<lb />
			Aug-17
			<lb />
			20-Sep-2019
			<lb />
			22-Feb-2018
			<lb />
			3.
			<lb />
			Sep-17
			<lb />
			20-Oct-2019
			<lb />
			22-Feb-2018
			<lb />
			4.
			<lb />
			Oct-17
			<lb />
			20-Nov-2019
			<lb />
			22-Feb-2018
			<lb />
			5.
			<lb />
			Nov-17
			<lb />
			20-Dec-2019
			<lb />
			24-Feb-2018
			<lb />
			6.
			<lb />
			Dec-17
			<lb />
			20-Jan-2019
			<lb />
			26-Feb-2018
			<lb />
			7.
			<lb />
			Jan-17
			<lb />
			20-Feb-2019
			<lb />
			26-Feb-2018
			<lb />
		</figure>
		<p>
			15. With regard to the technical glitch, first respondent in the counter
			<lb />
			affidavit has averred that the writ petitioner has not provided help desk details
			<lb />
			and therefore, the technical glitch plea is untenable. What is of utmost
			<lb />
			significance is that with regard to availability of ITC, there is no disputation. It
			<lb />
			is nobody&apos;s case that the writ petitioner did not have enough ITC credit as of
			<lb />
			30.06.2017 and it equally nobody&apos;s case that the technical glitch is now being
			<lb />
			used as an excuse for late-payment. Therefore, the whole issue boils down to
			<lb />
			one question as to whether the writ petitioner encountered technical glitch in
			<lb />
			payment of monthly GST for the aforesaid seven months i.e., from July 2017 to
			<lb />
			January 2018.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			16. Prima facie, the aforesaid complaint made by the writ petitioner to
			<lb />
			the GST Seva Kendra as well as the screen shots which have been reproduced
			<lb />
			(supra) show that the writ petitioner had encountered difficulty, but in the light
			<lb />
			of the disputation, this Court is of the considered view that it would be
			<lb />
			appropriate to leave it to the technical body concerned to decide whether there
			<lb />
			was a technical glitch at all.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			17. With regard to the technical body which would decide/resolve such
			<lb />
			issues, attention of this Court is drawn to a circular dated 03.04.2018 issued
			<lb />
			by the Government of India, Ministry of Finance, Department of Revenue
			<lb />
			Central Board of Indirect Taxes and Customs. Adverting to the opening
			<lb />
			paragraph and paragraph four of this Circular, it is submitted that Government
			<lb />
			has formed an IT-Grievance Redressal Mechanism. Opening paragraph and
			<lb />
			paragraph four read as follows:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				It has been decided to put in place an IT-Grievance Redressal
				<lb />
				Mechanism to address the difficulties faced by a section of tax payers owing to
				<lb />
				technical glitches on the GST portal and the relief that needs to be given to
				<lb />
				them. The relief could be in the nature of allowing filing of any Form or Return
				<lb />
				prescribed in law or amending any Form or Return already filed. The details of
				<lb />
				the said grievance redressal mechanism are provided below:
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<head>
			4. IT-Grievance Redressal Committee:
			<lb />
		</head>
		<list>
			<item>
				Any issue which needs to be addressed through this mechanism shall
				<lb />
				be identified by GSTN and the method of resolution approved by the GST
				<lb />
				glitches, the CEO, GSTN and the DG (Systems), CBEC shall participate in these
				<lb />
				meetings as special invites.
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			18. This Court is informed that any complaint to the aforesaid ITA
			<lb />
			Grievance Redressal Committee should be given to the jurisdictional Principal
			<lb />
			Commissioner, who in turn will forward it to the aforesaid Committee through
			<lb />
			the GST network or what is the known as GSTN.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			19. In the light of the narrative thus far, this Court deems it appropriate
			<lb />
			to pass the following order:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				a) Writ petitioner shall provide a bank guarantee for Rs.25
				<lb />
				lakhs in a format required by the first respondent within one
				<lb />
				week from the date of receipt of a copy of this order.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				b) One of the share holding directors of the writ petitioner
				<lb />
				company shall provide a personal bond in a format as required by
				<lb />
				first respondent for the balance sum within one week from the
				<lb />
				date of receipt of a copy of this order. To be noted after
				<lb />
				deducting 25 lakhs bank guarantee, the balance sum is
				<lb />
				Rs.1,39,49,541/-.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				c) Thereafter writ petitioner shall send a detailed
				<lb />
				communication addressed to the Principal Commissioner of GST
				<lb />
				and Central Excise, North Commissionerate, Chennai 34, within
				<lb />
				one week therefrom setting out details of the technical glitch
				<lb />
				inclusive i.e seven months in all).
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				d) The Jurisdictional Principal Commissioner shall do the
				<lb />
				needful in this regard as expeditiously as possible to ensure that
				<lb />
				the same is reached to the I.T.Grievance Redressal Committee
				<lb />
				via GSTN, so that the I.T. Grievance Redressal Committee can
				<lb />
				take a decision on the technical glitch within one week from the
				<lb />
				date of submission of the representation to the Principal
				<lb />
				Commissioner.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				e) It is open to the I.T. Grievance Redressal Committee to
				<lb />
				call for further information from the writ petitioner and/or afford
				<lb />
				a personal hearing, if deemed necessary, to take a decision on
				<lb />
				the complaint of technical glitch encountered by the writ
				<lb />
				petitioner.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				f) The decision of the Committee shall be communicated to
				<lb />
				the writ petitioner under due acknowledgement within seven
				<lb />
				working days from the date of the decision.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				g) As the Principal Commissioner is not arrayed as a party
				<lb />
				to the instant writ petition, learned standing counsel for Revenue
				<lb />
				shall communicate this order to the jurisdictional Principal
				<lb />
				Commissioner with a request to do the needful.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				h) Though obvious, the demand of interest being dropped,
				<lb />
				pursued or partly pursued will depend upon the decision taken by
				<lb />
				the I.T. Grievance Redressal Committee.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				i) On deposit of 25 lakhs and production of bank guarantee
				<lb />
				in the aforesaid manner, the attachment of the writ petitioner&apos;s
				<lb />
				account in second respondent bank will stand lifted/raised and
				<lb />
				the impugned communication dated 03.05.2019 bearing
				<lb />
				C.No.IV/16/22/2019-GST shall be in kept in abeyance till a
				<lb />
				decision is taken by the I.T. Grievance Redressal Committee and
				<lb />
				communicated to the Writ Petitioner in the aforesaid manner and
				<lb />
				within the aforesaid time frame.
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			20. With the above directions, this writ petition is disposed of.
			<lb />
			Consequently, connected miscellaneous petition is closed. However, there shall
			<lb />
			be no order as to costs.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			01.08.2019
			<lb />
		</p>
	</text>
</tei>
