<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<p>by the defendant, their men, agents, associates and/or assignees or<lb/> any person claiming rights from the defendant.<lb/></p>

			<p>(ii) Permanent injunction to restrain the defendant its men,<lb/> agents, associates and/or assignees or any person claiming rights<lb/> from therein from Passing Off their inferior product, as that of the<lb/> plaintiff&apos;s &quot;GOLDEN SUN&quot; edible refined sunflower oil by using the<lb/> offending words &quot;GOLDEN SUN&quot; or any other words or mark and<lb/> offending packing material and pouch deceptively similar to the<lb/> plaintiff&apos;s trade mark &quot;Gold Winner&quot; and Trade dress for &quot;Gold<lb/> Winner&quot;.<lb/></p>

			<p>(iii) Permanent injunction restraining the defendant from<lb/> violating the plaintiff&apos;s registered Copyright, A-68242/2005 dated<lb/> 27.01.2005 in the artistic work used in the plaintiff&apos;s packing<lb/> material/pouches used for packing refined edible sunflower oil and<lb/> bearing its reputed registered Trademark &quot;Gold Winner&quot; by<lb/> substituting the Trademark &quot;Gold Winner&quot; with the offending words<lb/> &quot;GOLDEN SUN&quot; bearing same trade dress, color scheme and get up<lb/> deceptively similar to that of the plaintiff&apos;s colour scheme and trade<lb/> dress in the packing material/pouch bearing trademark &quot;Gold<lb/> Winner&quot;.<lb/></p>

			<p>(iv) For preliminary decree directing the defendant to render<lb/> true account of profits made by the defendant by using the aforesaid<lb/> offending label of &quot;GOLDEN SUN&quot;.<lb/></p>

			<p>(v) Directing the defendant, its men, agents, assignees,<lb/> dealers and/or retailers, distributors, to surrender to the plaintiff all<lb/> offending pouch/packing material, label, advertising materials,<lb/> hoarding, letter heads, office stationary and all other material<lb/> J U D G M E N T<lb/> Today(12.09.2019), when the matter is called, the learned<lb/> counsel for plaintiff submitted that the parties have resolved their<lb/> disputes. He has also filed the Joint Compromise Memo dated<lb/> 30.08.2019, entered into between the parties, before this Court and<lb/> prayed that the suit may be decreed in terms of the said Joint<lb/> Compromise Memo entered between the parties.<lb/></p>

			<p>2. The said Joint Compromise Memo reads as follows:<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot;The Defendant undertakes not to use the<lb/> Trademark of the plaintiff, &quot;Gold Winner&quot; or any other<lb/> mark which is similar or identical to the plaintiff&apos;s<lb/> trademark, and the defendant has changed their mark as<lb/></item>

			<item>&quot;LUCKY GOLD&quot; as projected in the design of the label<lb/> attached with this memo in Annexure -A.<lb/></item>

			<p>2. The defendant undertakes not to use the get up,<lb/> colour scheme, arrangement of the colour which are<lb/> closely similar to it, get up and logo of the plaintiff&apos;s<lb/> product &quot;Gold Winner&quot; and the trade dressing of the<lb/> defendant&apos;s product will be hereafter as projected in the<lb/> design of label attached with this memo in Annexure-A.<lb/></p>

			<p>3.<lb/> The defendant undertakes to use the trade<lb/> dress, colour scheme and get up for their product &quot;Lucky<lb/> Gold&quot; as attached with this memo in Annexure-A.<lb/></p>

			<p>4. The defendant undertakes not to pass-off the<lb/> goods as and for those of the plaintiff&apos;s by adopting the<lb/> similar or identical get up, colour scheme, arrangement<lb/> of the colour, get up and logo of the plaintiff&apos;s product<lb/> &quot;Gold Winner&quot; and its pouch/packing material.<lb/></p>

			<p>5. The defendant shall erase, remove, or obliterate<lb/> from all infringing goods, materials, or articles in his<lb/> possession or control with the offending mark labels and<lb/> pouches claimed to be deceptively similar to the plaintiff&apos;s<lb/> &quot;Gold Winner&quot;.<lb/></p>

			<p>6.<lb/> The defendant shall not further violate the<lb/> plaintiff&apos;s Copyright in the artistic work used in the<lb/> packing pouches of the plaintiff from the date of signing<lb/> this Joint Memo of Compromise.<lb/></p>

			<p>7. The defendant undertakes to compensate the<lb/> plaintiff sufficiently with damages if it violates any of the<lb/> clauses of this Memo of Compromise.&quot;<lb/> mrr<lb/> 4. Considering the submission made by the plaintiff&apos;s counsel,<lb/> this Court is inclined to decree the suit in terms of the said Joint<lb/> Compromise Memo. Accordingly, this Civil Suit is decreed in terms<lb/> of the Joint Compromise Memo dated 30.08.2019, entered between<lb/> the parties. No costs. Consequently, connected Application is<lb/> closed.<lb/></p>

			<p>12.09.2019<lb/> mrr<lb/> Index : Yes/No<lb/> C.S.No.215 of 2019</p>


	</text>
</tei>
