<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<p>
			These petitions arise out of common background. They have
			<lb />
			been heard together and are being disposed of by this common
			<lb />
			judgment.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			2.
			<lb />
			The petitions can be divided into two groups. Civil Writ
			<lb />
			Petition No.6587/2021 filed by Mukesh Kumar Royal and others
			<lb />
			and connected petitions call in question the vires of the
			<lb />
			notification dated 28.06.2018 issued by the National Council for
			<lb />
			Teacher Education (&apos;NCTE&apos;, for short), by which the B.Ed. degree
			<lb />
			holders, subject to certain conditions, are made eligible for
			<lb />
			appointment to the post of primary school teacher grade-III
			<lb />
			(level-1) (classes-I to V), along with other qualifications already
			<lb />
			prescribed under its notification dated 23.08.2010 as amended
			<lb />
			from time to time. The writ petition No.2108/2021 filed by Sunita
			<lb />
			and other connected petitions are filed by the B.Ed. degree
			<lb />
			holders. They support the notification dated 28.06.2018 and have
			<lb />
			challenged the advertisement issued by the Board of Secondary
			<lb />
			Education, State of Rajasthan inviting applications for Rajasthan
			<lb />
			Eligibility Entrance Test (&apos;REET&apos;, for short) (level-1) in which the
			<lb />
			B.Ed. degree holders are excluded.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			3.
			<lb />
			In brief, the controversy revolves around the question
			<lb />
			whether the NCTE had correctly and legally included B.Ed. as
			<lb />
			essential qualification for eligibility for appointment to the post of
			<lb />
			primary school teacher (level-I). The petitioner Mukesh Kumar
			<lb />
			Royal and others were qualified as per the unamended
			<lb />
			notification.
			<lb />
			They possess the basic educational qualification
			<lb />
			(Higher Secondary Examination pass) and the certificate of
			<lb />
			Diploma in Elementary Education (D.El.Ed.) pass. They argue that
			<lb />
			B.Ed. course per se cannot be stated to be a higher qualification.
			<lb />
			According to them even the Ministry of HRD and NCTE have
			<lb />
			viewed the situation in this manner. It is, therefore, that while
			<lb />
			including B.Ed. degree as one of the eligibility criteria, the
			<lb />
			notification dated 28.06.2018 provides that such a candidate upon
			<lb />
			appointment shall have to pass a bridge course of six months
			<lb />
			within two years of the appointment. Counter petitioners Sunita
			<lb />
			and others contend that this amendment is proper and legal and
			<lb />
			the state government had no authority to ignore this additional
			<lb />
			qualification prescribed by NCTE while declaring the REET. It is a
			<lb />
			common ground that REET result is the source for appointment for
			<lb />
			the primary teachers in the State.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			4.
			<lb />
			In order to appreciate the controversy, we may note in brief
			<lb />
			the factual background as well as the statutory framework. Article
			<lb />
			21A was inserted in the Constitution by Constitution (Eighty-sixth
			<lb />
			Amendment) Act, 2002 with effect from 01.04.2010 which
			<lb />
			provides that the State shall provide free and compulsory
			<lb />
			education to all children of the age of 6 to 14 years in such
			<lb />
			manner as the State may, by law, determine. Long before the
			<lb />
			amendment of the Constitution and insertion of Article 21A, the
			<lb />
			right to primary education was recognized as a fundamental right
			<lb />
			being part of Article 21 by the Supreme court in the cases of
			<lb />
			Mohini Jain vs. State of Karnataka [(1992) 3 SCC 666] and
			<lb />
			in the case of Unni Krishnan J.P. vs. State of Andhra Pradesh
			<lb />
			[(1993) 1 SCC 645]. With the insertion of Article 21A, this right
			<lb />
			was recognized as an independent fundamental right in the
			<lb />
			Constitution. To operationalise this valuable right, the Parliament
			<lb />
			framed the Right of Children to Free and Compulsory Education
			<lb />
			Act, 2009 (&apos;RTE Act&apos;, for short). The term &apos;school&apos; has been
			<lb />
			defined in Section 2(n) as to mean any recognized school
			<lb />
			imparting elementary education and would include the schools
			<lb />
			established, owned or controlled by the appropriate Government
			<lb />
			or a local authority, schools receiving aid and even unaided
			<lb />
			schools. Clause (g) of Section 8 of the RTE Act, pertaining to
			<lb />
			duties of appropriate Government, requires that the appropriate
			<lb />
			Government shall ensure good quality elementary education
			<lb />
			conforming to the standards and norms specified in the Schedule.
			<lb />
			Section 18 requires compulsory recognition of all schools. Section
			<lb />
			19 of the RTE Act pertains to norms and standards for school.
			<lb />
			Sub-section (1) of Section 19 provides that no school shall be
			<lb />
			established or recognized under Section 18, unless it fulfills the
			<lb />
			norms and standards specified in the Schedule. The Schedule lists
			<lb />
			norms and standards for the schools imparting education for the
			<lb />
			classes-I to V. There are different prescriptions for the number of
			<lb />
			teachers for this section as compared to classes-VI to VIII.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			5.
			<lb />
			Section 23 of the RTE Act, which is of considerable
			<lb />
			importance pertains to qualifications for appointment and terms
			<lb />
			and conditions of service of teachers and reads as under:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot;23. Qualifications for appointment and terms and
				<lb />
				conditions of service of teachers-
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(1) Any person possessing such minimum qualifications,
				<lb />
				as laid down by an academic authority, authorised by
				<lb />
				the Central Government, by notification, shall be
				<lb />
				eligible for appointment as a teacher.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(2) Where a State does not have adequate institutions
				<lb />
				offering courses or training in teacher education, or
				<lb />
				teachers possessing minimum qualifications as laid
				<lb />
				down under sub-section (1) are not available in
				<lb />
				sufficient numbers, the Central Government may, if it
				<lb />
				deems necessary, by notification, relax the minimum
				<lb />
				qualifications required for appointment as a teacher, for
				<lb />
				such period, not exceeding five years, as may be
				<lb />
				specified in that notification:
				<lb />
				Provided
				<lb />
				that
				<lb />
				a
				<lb />
				teacher
				<lb />
				who,
				<lb />
				at
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				commencement of this Act, does not possess minimum
				<lb />
				qualifications as laid down under sub-section (1), shall
				<lb />
				acquire such minimum qualifications within a period of
				<lb />
				five years:
				<lb />
				[Provided further that every teacher appointed or
				<lb />
				in position as on the 31st March, 2015, who does not
				<lb />
				possess minimum qualifications as laid down under sub-
				<lb />
				section (1), shall acquire such minimum qualifications
				<lb />
				within a period of four years from the date of
				<lb />
				commencement of the Right of Children to Free and
				<lb />
				Compulsory Education (Amendment) Act, 2017.]
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(3) The salary and allowances payable to, and the
				<lb />
				terms and conditions of service of, teachers shall be
				<lb />
				such as may be prescribed.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			6.
			<lb />
			As per Sub-section (1) of Section 23, thus a person
			<lb />
			possessing such minimum qualifications as laid down by an
			<lb />
			academic authority authorised by the Central Government shall be
			<lb />
			eligible for appointment as a teacher. Sub-section (2) of Section
			<lb />
			23, empowers the Central Government to relax such minimum
			<lb />
			qualifications under certain circumstances subject to conditions.
			<lb />
			We would make a detailed reference to this Section at a later
			<lb />
			stage.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			7.
			<lb />
			Chapter-V of the RTE Act pertains to curriculum and
			<lb />
			completion of elementary education. Section 29 contained in the
			<lb />
			said part pertains to curriculum and evaluation procedure, and it
			<lb />
			reads as under:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot;29. Curriculum and evaluation procedure.-(1)
				<lb />
				The curriculum and the evaluation procedure for
				<lb />
				elementary education shall be laid down by an
				<lb />
				academic authority to be specified by the appropriate
				<lb />
				Government, by notification.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(2) The academic authority, while laying down the
				<lb />
				curriculum and the evaluation procedure under
				<lb />
				sub-section (1), shall take into consideration the
				<lb />
				following, namely:-
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(a) conformity with the values enshrined in the
				<lb />
				Constitution;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(b) all round development of the child;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(c) building up child&apos;s knowledge, potentiality and
				<lb />
				talent;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(d) development of physical and mental abilities to
				<lb />
				the fullest extent;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(e) learning through activities, discovery and
				<lb />
				exploration in a child friendly and child-centered
				<lb />
				manner;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(f) medium of instructions shall, as far as
				<lb />
				practicable, be in child&apos;s mother tongue;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(g) making the child free of fear, trauma and anxiety
				<lb />
				and helping the child to express views
				<lb />
				freely;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(h) comprehensive and continuous evaluation of
				<lb />
				child&apos;s understanding of knowledge and his or her
				<lb />
				ability to apply the same.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			8.
			<lb />
			Last section to be noted from the RTE Act is Section 35
			<lb />
			contained in Chapter-VII of Miscellaneous provisions and reads
			<lb />
			under:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot;35. Power to issue directions.-(1) The Central
				<lb />
				Government may issue such guidelines to the
				<lb />
				appropriate Government or, as the case may be, the
				<lb />
				local authority, as it deems fit for the purposes of
				<lb />
				implementation of the provisions of this Act.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(2) The appropriate Government may issue guidelines
				<lb />
				and give such directions, as it deems fit, to the
				<lb />
				local authority or the School Management Committee
				<lb />
				regarding implementation of the provisions of this
				<lb />
				Act.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(3) The local authority may issue guidelines and give
				<lb />
				such directions, as it deems fit, to the School
				<lb />
				Management Committee regarding implementation of
				<lb />
				the provisions of this Act.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			9.
			<lb />
			Sub-section (1) of Section 35 of the RTE Act, as noted
			<lb />
			above, empowers the Central Government to issue such guidelines
			<lb />
			to appropriate Government or the local authority, as it deems fit
			<lb />
			for the purpose of implementation of the provisions of the Act.
			<lb />
			Under Sub-section (2) of Section 35, the appropriate Government
			<lb />
			may issue guidelines and give directions, as it deems fit, to the
			<lb />
			local authority or the school management committee regarding
			<lb />
			implementation of the provisions of this Act. Under Sub-section
			<lb />
			(3) of Section 35, the local authority may issue such guidelines
			<lb />
			and directions as it deems fit to the school management
			<lb />
			committee.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			10. It is not in dispute that the Central Government has notified
			<lb />
			the NCTE as the &apos;academic authority&apos; for the purposes of Sub-
			<lb />
			section (1) of Section 23 as well as Sub-section (1) of Section 29
			<lb />
			of the RTE Act. In terms of Sub-section (1) of Section 23, thus, it
			<lb />
			is the NCTE which has the authority to prescribe the minimum
			<lb />
			eligibility qualifications for appointment as a teacher. Likewise,
			<lb />
			the NCTE is authorised in terms of Sub-section (1) of Section 29
			<lb />
			to lay down the curriculum and evaluation procedure for
			<lb />
			elementary education. It may be noted that the NCTE has been
			<lb />
			constituted under the National Council for Teacher Education Act,
			<lb />
			1993 (&apos;NCTE ACT&apos;, for short). In its original form, the preamble to
			<lb />
			the NCTE Act provided that it was an Act to provide for
			<lb />
			establishment of NCTE with a view to achieving planned and co-
			<lb />
			ordinated development of the teacher education system
			<lb />
			throughout the country, the regulations and proper maintenance
			<lb />
			of norms and standards in the teacher education system and for
			<lb />
			matters connected therewith. By Amendment Act 18 of 2011 with
			<lb />
			effect from 01.06.2012 the words &quot;including qualifications of
			<lb />
			school teachers&quot; were inserted in the preamble.
			<lb />
			Similar
			<lb />
			amendments were made in the Act and the applicability of the Act
			<lb />
			as provided in Sub-section (4) of Section 1 of the NCTE Act, was
			<lb />
			expanded to schools imparting pre-primary, primary, upper
			<lb />
			primary education. The functions of the NCTE as contained in
			<lb />
			Section 12 were expanded to include laying down of guidelines in
			<lb />
			respect of minimum qualifications for a persons to be employed as
			<lb />
			a teacher in recognized institutions. Section 12A was inserted
			<lb />
			with effect from 01.06.2012, which provides that for the purpose
			<lb />
			of maintaining standards of education in schools, the NCTE may,
			<lb />
			by regulations, determine the qualifications of persons for being
			<lb />
			recruited as teachers in any pre-primary, primary, upper primary,
			<lb />
			secondary, senior secondary or intermediate school or college, by
			<lb />
			whatever names called, established, run, aided or recognised by
			<lb />
			the Central Government or a State Government or a local
			<lb />
			authority or other authority. First proviso, while protecting the
			<lb />
			existing teachers, was subject to further proviso, which provides
			<lb />
			that the minimum qualifications of a teacher shall be acquired
			<lb />
			within the period specified in the NCTE Act or under the RTE Act.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			11. Section 29 of the NCTE Act pertains to directions by the
			<lb />
			Central Government. Sub-section (1) of Section 29 provides that
			<lb />
			the NCTE shall, in the discharge of its functions and duties under
			<lb />
			this Act, be bound by such directions on questions of policy as the
			<lb />
			Central Government may give in writing to it from time to time.
			<lb />
			Sub-section (2) of Section 29 provides that the decision of the
			<lb />
			Central Government as to whether a question is one of policy or
			<lb />
			not shall be final.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			12. Section 32 of the NCTE Act gives power to the NCTE to frame
			<lb />
			regulations. As per Sub-section (1) of Section 32, the NCTE may,
			<lb />
			by notification in the Official Gazette, make regulations not
			<lb />
			inconsistent with the provisions of this Act and the rules made
			<lb />
			thereunder, generally to carry out the provisions of this Act. Sub-
			<lb />
			section (2) of Section 32 which provides that in particular, and
			<lb />
			without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such
			<lb />
			regulations may provide for all or any of the following matters,
			<lb />
			namely those contained in various sub-clauses of the said Sub-
			<lb />
			section, which was amended by insertion of Clause (dd) pertaining
			<lb />
			to the minimum qualifications of teachers under Section 12A.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			13. Section 33 of the NCTE Act requires the rules and regulations
			<lb />
			framed by the NCTE to be laid before the Parliament, which reads
			<lb />
			as under:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot;33. Rules and regulations to be laid before
				<lb />
				Parliament.-Every rule and every regulation made
				<lb />
				under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may be after it
				<lb />
				is made, before each House of Parliament, while it
				<lb />
				is in session, for a total period of thirty days which
				<lb />
				may be comprised in one session or in two or more
				<lb />
				successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the
				<lb />
				session immediately following the session or the
				<lb />
				successive sessions aforesaid, both House agree in
				<lb />
				making any modification in the rule or regulation, or
				<lb />
				both House agree that the rule or regulation should
				<lb />
				not be made, the rule or regulation shall thereafter
				<lb />
				have effect only in such modified form or be of no
				<lb />
				effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any such
				<lb />
				modification or annulment shall be without prejudice
				<lb />
				to the validity of anything previously done under
				<lb />
				that rule or regulation.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			14. The NCTE in exercise of powers under Sub-section (1) of
			<lb />
			Section 23 of the RTE Act had issued a notification dated
			<lb />
			23.08.2010 prescribing minimum qualifications for a person to be
			<lb />
			eligible for appointment as teacher in classes-I to VIII in a school
			<lb />
			referred to in Clause (n) of Section 2 of the RTE Act. Clause (1) of
			<lb />
			this notification pertains to minimum qualifications. Sub-clause (i)
			<lb />
			prescribed minimum qualifications classes-I to V. This recognized
			<lb />
			persons with senior secondary or equivalent with diploma in
			<lb />
			elementary education (which is, as noted, is called D.El.Ed.) by
			<lb />
			whatever name called or senior secondary passed with prescribed
			<lb />
			percentage and 4 years Bachelor of Elementary Education and 2
			<lb />
			year Diploma in Education as qualified for appointment provided
			<lb />
			they possess Teacher Eligibility Test passed certificate as
			<lb />
			conducted in accordance with the guidelines framed by the NCTE.
			<lb />
			In contrast, for classes-VI to VIII, as per this notification a
			<lb />
			candidate must possess degree in B.A. or B.Sc. with Diploma in
			<lb />
			Elementary Education or such degree with minimum 50% marks
			<lb />
			with one year B.Ed. course and such similar qualifications.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			15. The notification dated 23.08.2010 was amended by the NCTE
			<lb />
			vide notification dated 29.07.2011. Certain modifications were
			<lb />
			made in the essential qualifications for appointment of a teacher
			<lb />
			for classes-I to V as well as classes-VI to VIII. We are not directly
			<lb />
			concerned with these changes brought about by the subsequent
			<lb />
			notification dated 29.07.2011. The entire controversy revolves
			<lb />
			around the notification dated 28.06.2018 issued by NCTE making
			<lb />
			certain amendments in the earlier notification dated 23.08.2010,
			<lb />
			as amended vide notification dated 29.07.2011.
			<lb />
			Since this
			<lb />
			notification is at the center of controversy, we may reproduce the
			<lb />
			same in its entirety:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot;NATIONAL COUNCIL FOR TEACHER EDUCATION
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				NOTIFICATION
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				New Delhi, the 28 th June, 2018
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				F. No. NCTE-Regl 012/16/2018-In exercise of
				<lb />
				the powers conferred by sub-section (1) of Section 23
				<lb />
				of Right of Children to Free and Compulsory Education
				<lb />
				Act. 2009 (35 of 2009) and in pursuance of notification
				<lb />
				number S.O. 750(E), dated the 31 st March, 2010
				<lb />
				issued by the Department of School Education and
				<lb />
				Literacy, Ministry of Human Resource Development,
				<lb />
				Government of India, the National Council for Teacher
				<lb />
				Education (NCTE) hereby makes the following further
				<lb />
				amendments to the notification number F.N. 61-
				<lb />
				03/20/2010/NCTE/(N&amp;S), dated the 23 rd August, 2010
				<lb />
				published in the Gazette of India, Extraordinary, Part
				<lb />
				III, Section 4, dated the 25 th August, 2010, hereinafter
				<lb />
				referred to as the said notification namely:-
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(1) In the said notification, in para 1 in sub-para (i),
				<lb />
				in clause (a) after the words and brackets &quot;Graduation
				<lb />
				and two year Diploma in Elementary Education (by
				<lb />
				whatever name known), the following shall be
				<lb />
				inserted, namely:-
				<lb />
				OR
				<lb />
				&quot;Graduation with at least 50% marks and
				<lb />
				Bachelor of Education (B.Ed.)&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				2. In the said notification in para 3, for sub-para(a),
				<lb />
				the following sub-para shall be substituted namely:-
				<lb />
				&quot;(a) who has acquired the qualification of
				<lb />
				Bachelor of Education from any NCTE recognized
				<lb />
				institution shall be considered for appointment
				<lb />
				as a teacher in classes I to V provided the person
				<lb />
				so appointed as a teacher shall mandatorily
				<lb />
				undergo a six month Bridge Course in Elementary
				<lb />
				Education recognized by the NCTE, within two
				<lb />
				years of such appointment as primary teacher.&quot;
				<lb />
				SANJAY AWASTHI, Member Secy.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(emphasis supplied by us)
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			16. The petitioners, who are opponents of this notification
			<lb />
			particularly in the case of Mukesh Kumar Royal and others sought
			<lb />
			information from the NCTE and Ministry of Human Resources
			<lb />
			Development under the Right to Information Act, 2005 (&apos;RTI Act&apos;,
			<lb />
			for short) as to the manner in which the decision to make
			<lb />
			amendments in the eligibility criteria was arrived at by NCTE.
			<lb />
			Through this process, they have brought on record certain
			<lb />
			documents and information, which need to be noted. It appears
			<lb />
			that on 30.05.2018 the Ministry of HRD had written to NCTE
			<lb />
			requiring the NCTE to amend the eligibility criteria for primary
			<lb />
			school teacher in classes-I to V as to include any person, who has
			<lb />
			acquired qualification of B.Ed. from a recognized institute provided
			<lb />
			the person so appointed shall compulsorily undergo a six month
			<lb />
			bridge course, which may be recognized by NCTE and such course
			<lb />
			would have to be completed within two years of appointment. This
			<lb />
			communication is also being challenged by the petitioners. It
			<lb />
			would be useful to take note of the contents thereof:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot;F.No. 11-15/2017-EE10-part(1)
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				Government of India
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				Ministry of School Education &amp; Liferary
				<lb />
				Shahstri Bhawan, New Delhi,
				<lb />
				Dated the 30 th May 2018
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				To,
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				The Chairperson NCTE,
				<lb />
				Haris Bhawan,
				<lb />
				Bahadur Shah Zafar Marg,
				<lb />
				New Delhi-110002
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				Dear Madam
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				Kindly refer to the letter of even no dated
				<lb />
				12.04.2018 regarding request of Kendriya Vidayalaya
				<lb />
				Sangathan for recruiting primary teachers with higher
				<lb />
				qualification i.e. B.A./B.Sc. B.ed. Plus TET pass and
				<lb />
				letter no. NCTE-REG1012/16/2018-IJS (Regulation)-HQ
				<lb />
				dated 23.05.2018 received from NCTE regarding the
				<lb />
				same.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				2.
				<lb />
				The above request has been considered in the
				<lb />
				ministry, to order to safeguard the interest of the
				<lb />
				students and ensure the quality of education, the
				<lb />
				competent authority has decided to agree to the request
				<lb />
				of KVS to recruit Primary Teacher with Higher
				<lb />
				Qualification. The insufficient number of eligible D.EI.Ed.
				<lb />
				candidates due to tow pass percentage of TET
				<lb />
				examination has also become as issue for recruitment of
				<lb />
				primary teacher. Further, with the roll out of four year
				<lb />
				B.Ed. Integrated course from next academic year, the
				<lb />
				existing D.EI.E.D./B.Ed. Course will be phased out is
				<lb />
				due course of time.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				3.
				<lb />
				NCTE
				<lb />
				vide
				<lb />
				their
				<lb />
				letter
				<lb />
				No.
				<lb />
				NCTE-
				<lb />
				REG1012/16/2018-IJS
				<lb />
				(Regulation)-HQ
				<lb />
				dated
				<lb />
				23.05.2018 stated that the MHRD may consider
				<lb />
				implementing the directions in the detailed noting of
				<lb />
				Hon&apos;ble Minister of Human Resource Development
				<lb />
				Government of India. Further in view of the fact
				<lb />
				presented by the commissioner, KV and since the NCTE
				<lb />
				did not have any objection to permit KV schools to
				<lb />
				recruit primary teachers with higher qualifications, then
				<lb />
				there should be no objection to standing the to other
				<lb />
				schools. Therefore considering the powers vested
				<lb />
				in MHRD Under Section 29 of the NCTE Act 1993.
				<lb />
				The NCTE regulation 25.08.2010 (determining of
				<lb />
				teacher to be appointed at primary level class 1 st
				<lb />
				to 5 th ) shall be amended to include that any
				<lb />
				person who has acquired the qualification of
				<lb />
				B./Ed. from any NCTE recognised course will also
				<lb />
				be considered for appointment as a teacher in
				<lb />
				classes 1 st to 5 th provided the person so appointed
				<lb />
				as a teacher shall mandatory undergo a 6 month
				<lb />
				bridge course, which is recognised by NCTE,
				<lb />
				within two years of such appointment as primary
				<lb />
				teacher.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				4.
				<lb />
				It is therefore requested that the draft qualification
				<lb />
				to amend the NCTE regulation may please be submitted
				<lb />
				to this Ministry. This may please be treated as most
				<lb />
				urgent.
				<lb />
				With regards.
				<lb />
				Yours sincerely
				<lb />
				Sd/-
				<lb />
				(Bashi Sharma)
				<lb />
				Director (TE)&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(emphasis supplied by us)
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			17. The petitioner Mukesh Kumar Royal had raised certain
			<lb />
			queries under the RTI Act, which were replied on 23.03.2021, in
			<lb />
			which it was provided that the bridge course had till then not been
			<lb />
			designed, however, a committee had been constituted to develop
			<lb />
			the norms and standards for six months bridge course and the
			<lb />
			report was awaited.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			18. Again through the means of RTI, the petitioners sought
			<lb />
			further information regarding deliberations, which took place
			<lb />
			before the impugned amendments were notified. Along with an
			<lb />
			order dated 28.10.2020 the appellate authority under the RTI Act
			<lb />
			provided certain internal documents, one of them was the minutes
			<lb />
			of the meeting dated 09.04.2018 of the officials of MHRD,
			<lb />
			according to which, the Kendriya Vidhyala Sangathan had
			<lb />
			informed the Ministry that up to the year 2011-2012 candidates
			<lb />
			having professional qualification of B.Ed. were also eligible for
			<lb />
			appointment in K.V.S. schools. However, from the year 2012-
			<lb />
			2013, in compliance with the guidelines of NCTE, K.V.S. did not
			<lb />
			allow those candidates to be appointed.
			<lb />
			It was noted that
			<lb />
			sufficient number of candidates having the eligibility qualifications
			<lb />
			were not available, which adversely affected the quality in
			<lb />
			selection of teachers.
			<lb />
			It was recorded that the competent
			<lb />
			authority had given conditional approval to the K.V.S. to appoint
			<lb />
			primary teachers with higher qualification of BA, B.Sc. or B.Ed, in
			<lb />
			case sufficient number of D.El.Ed. candidates are not available. It
			<lb />
			was, therefore, suggested that it would not be appropriate to
			<lb />
			remove first condition and the K.V.S. can decide as it is an
			<lb />
			autonomous body and competent to decide such matter. In short,
			<lb />
			the suggestion was not to include the B.Sc., B.A. or B.Ed. teachers
			<lb />
			in the eligibility criteria at par with other educational qualifications
			<lb />
			but to allow K.V.S. to expand the zone of consideration by
			<lb />
			including such qualifications, in case without inclusion of such
			<lb />
			candidates, it was not possible to fill up the posts. Significantly,
			<lb />
			these deliberations were with respect to K.V.S. schools alone.
			<lb />
			When this note was placed before the Hon&apos;ble Minister of HRD, he
			<lb />
			placed detailed note expressing his opinion as under:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot;There are DL.ED. colleges is few states. Therefore,
				<lb />
				applications for primary teachers come from limited
				<lb />
				states. B.Ed. is a post graduate degree. They are ready
				<lb />
				to serve as Primary Teachers. So we get best more
				<lb />
				equipped teachers. The issue
				<lb />
				The issue therefore are two
				<lb />
				1. When more educated teachers are available why
				<lb />
				students should not get benefit of better qualified
				<lb />
				teachers, therefore, we must allow B.Ed. teachers.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				2. Second issue is pedagogical for primary teacher
				<lb />
				which is available in DL.Ed. &amp; not in B.Ed. course. The
				<lb />
				member has been found by teaching one specific model
				<lb />
				through Swayam &amp; contact programmer also. Thus, it
				<lb />
				is very clear that students have the right to have better
				<lb />
				teachers B.Ed. are more equipped as it is graduate +,
				<lb />
				while Dl.Ed. is 12+
				<lb />
				Finally Decision should be
				<lb />
				1. Dl.Ed. will continue to the eligible to apply for
				<lb />
				Primary teacher post.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				2. Additionally, B.Ed. pass candidates will be also
				<lb />
				eligible to apply.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				3. When, Dl.Ed. candidates is selected they can start
				<lb />
				teaching after formalities.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				4. When B.Ed. candidate are selected, they will start
				<lb />
				teaching but will have to complete pedagogical module
				<lb />
				with in 2 years
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				5. Thus Dl.Ed. &amp; B.Ed. Candidates can apply for the job
				<lb />
				of Primary teacher in KV.
				<lb />
				Selected B.Ed. candidates will have to complete
				<lb />
				pedagogical module in 2 years of appointment.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			19. According to the Minister, thus B.Ed. should be recognized as
			<lb />
			an additional qualification and not an alternative qualification for
			<lb />
			appointment to primary school teachers. However, this opinion
			<lb />
			also was confined to K.V.S. schools alone.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			20. Shri R.D. Rastogi, learned Additional Solicitor General
			<lb />
			appearing for the NCTE had placed before us further
			<lb />
			correspondence, which took place between NCTE and MHRD in this
			<lb />
			regard. These documents are taken on record. Perusal of
			<lb />
			these documents would show that after the Minister put his
			<lb />
			remarks on 11.04.2018, MHRD wrote to NCTE pointing out that
			<lb />
			the Minister has directed the NCTE to amend the qualifications and
			<lb />
			make B.Ed. also an eligibility for teaching primary level with a
			<lb />
			proviso of passing the module within two years of joining the
			<lb />
			service. We also note that in a meeting held on 28.05.2018 the
			<lb />
			officials of MHRD and Minister concerned discussed and
			<lb />
			deliberated the issues and decided to recognize B.Ed. degree
			<lb />
			course as an additional eligibility criteria for appointment to the
			<lb />
			post of primary school teachers in classes-I to V. The relevant
			<lb />
			portion of the minutes of this meeting reads as under:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot;File was called for.
				<lb />
				Kendriya Vidalaya Sangathan Vide letter No. F.
				<lb />
				11054/3/KVS(HQ)/RPS dated 18.05.2016 requested
				<lb />
				National Bank Council For Teacher Education to allow
				<lb />
				KVS to recruit Primary Teachers with higher
				<lb />
				qualification than prescribed by National Council for
				<lb />
				Teacher Education i.e. graduation with 50% marks
				<lb />
				and B.Ed.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				2.
				<lb />
				The matter was considered in this Ministry and
				<lb />
				HRM has approved the proposal of KVS to recruit
				<lb />
				primary teacher with higher qualification (i.e.
				<lb />
				B.A./B.Sc., B.Ed.+TET). Further, HRM has also
				<lb />
				directed that NCTE may amend the qualification and
				<lb />
				make B.A./B.Sc., B.Ed. also eligible for teaching at
				<lb />
				Primary level with provision of completing Pedagogical
				<lb />
				module in 2 years of joining the service, these
				<lb />
				directions were conveyed to NCTE on 12.04.2018,
				<lb />
				however, the action is still pending at their part.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				3.
				<lb />
				The matter was again discussed and deliberated
				<lb />
				in detail in the meeting held today(28th May, 2018)
				<lb />
				chaired by HRM and attended by Special Secretary,
				<lb />
				Chairperson, NCTE, MS, NCTE, Joint Secretary (SE.I)
				<lb />
				and KVS Commissioner. KVS Commissioner raised the
				<lb />
				issues of insufficient number of candidates applying for
				<lb />
				the post of Primary teachers and candidates applying
				<lb />
				from few states rather than across the country. It was
				<lb />
				informed by MS, NCTE that approximately 7.5 lakh
				<lb />
				seat are available for D.El.Ed across the country out of
				<lb />
				which 50% seats are filled. However, the TET pass
				<lb />
				D.El.Ed. candidate would be much less as the result of
				<lb />
				TET varies from 6% to 16%. This makes the
				<lb />
				availability of eligible D.El.Ed. candidates much less
				<lb />
				than the desired. HRM also pointed out the need for
				<lb />
				better equipped teachers to ensure quality education
				<lb />
				in schools. Recruitment of Teachers with higher
				<lb />
				qualifications will ultimately be beneficial and in the
				<lb />
				interest of the students.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				4.
				<lb />
				In addition to above, NCTE will roll out four year
				<lb />
				B.Ed. integrated course from next academic year,
				<lb />
				therefore, the prevalent D.El.Ed./B.Ed. etc will phase
				<lb />
				out in time bound manner. Further, similar kind of
				<lb />
				request has also been from the state of Uttrakhand.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				5.
				<lb />
				In view of the above discussions, HRM directed
				<lb />
				NCTE to change its regulations, Directions are required
				<lb />
				to be given under section 29 of the NCTE Act, 1993.
				<lb />
				Section 29 of the NCTE Act is as follows:
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(1) The Council shall in the discharge of its functions
				<lb />
				and duties under this Act be bound by such directions
				<lb />
				on questions of policy as the Central Government may
				<lb />
				give in writing to it from time to time.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(2) The decision of the Central Government as to
				<lb />
				whether a question is one of policy or not shall be
				<lb />
				final.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				6.
				<lb />
				We may request NCTE to submit draft notification
				<lb />
				to amend NCTE regulations at the earliest. The draft
				<lb />
				letter is attached for approval please. Once the draft
				<lb />
				notification is received, the same will be sent to
				<lb />
				Legislative Department for vetting with the approval of
				<lb />
				HRM.
				<lb />
				Submitted.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			21. This decision was summed up in a note dated 29.05.2018,
			<lb />
			which reads as under:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot;Please place on file the latter from NCTE which was
				<lb />
				handed over to the HRM by the MS, NCTE during the
				<lb />
				meeting, the details of which have been referred to in
				<lb />
				the draft reply. The meeting clearly took the decision
				<lb />
				that in view of the facts presented by the
				<lb />
				Commissioner, KV and since the NCTE did not have any
				<lb />
				objection to permit KV schools to recruit primary
				<lb />
				teachers with higher qualifications, then there should
				<lb />
				be no objection to extending this to other schools, and
				<lb />
				therefore, this Ministry could issue directions to the
				<lb />
				NCTE under Section 29.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			22. The State Government holds a belief that such amendment
			<lb />
			was unconstitutional and could not have been thrust on the State.
			<lb />
			Ignoring such amendment, the State Government issued an
			<lb />
			advertisement dated 11 th January, 2021 inviting applications for
			<lb />
			REET aspirants. This advertisement did not recognize B.Ed degree
			<lb />
			holders as eligible for appearing in the test. In such scenario, the
			<lb />
			petitioner Mukesh Kumar Royal and others, who are non-B.Ed.
			<lb />
			degree holders have challenged the NCTE notification dated
			<lb />
			28.06.2018 Out of caution, they have also challenged the
			<lb />
			communication dated 30.05.2018 from MHRD to NCTE. The
			<lb />
			petitioner Sunita and others have supported the amendment and
			<lb />
			challenged the advertisement issued by the State Government
			<lb />
			inviting applications for REET. The State Government has
			<lb />
			supported the petitioners who have challenged the notification
			<lb />
			dated 28.06.2018.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			23. In such background, learned counsel appearing for the
			<lb />
			challengers of the notification dated 28.06.2018 including learned
			<lb />
			Advocate General appearing for the State Government have raised
			<lb />
			the following contentions:-
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				(i)
				<lb />
				B.Ed. qualification is not a higher qualification than D.El.Ed.
				<lb />
				and therefore, cannot be automatically included as eligibility
				<lb />
				criteria.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(ii) Under Sub-section (1) of Section 23 of the RTE Act, the
				<lb />
				authority for prescribing the qualifications for appointment
				<lb />
				as primary teachers lies with the NCTE. The Ministry of HRD
				<lb />
				had no authority to give any direction in this respect.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(iii) By virtue of the impugned notification, the candidates who
				<lb />
				are ineligible for appointment are made eligible subject to
				<lb />
				acquiring eligibility which is not permissible and in any case,
				<lb />
				is opposed to the basic idea of the responsibility of the State
				<lb />
				to provide quality primary education flowing from Article 21A
				<lb />
				of the Constitution.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(iv) Even under the NCTE Act, MHRD has power only to give
				<lb />
				directions in relation to the policy matters. The question of
				<lb />
				prescribing eligibility criteria for appointment as teachers is
				<lb />
				exclusively within the domain of NCTE and it is not a policy
				<lb />
				matter in which the MHRD can have any say.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(v) In terms of Section 35 of the NCTE Act any regulations
				<lb />
				framed by NCTE have to be placed before the Parliament for
				<lb />
				its approval, which has not been done in the present case.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(vi) The eligibility criteria could not have been modified without
				<lb />
				amending the notification dated 12.11.2014 in which such
				<lb />
				minimum qualifications have been prescribed.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(vii) It was contended that the power to relax the minimum
				<lb />
				qualifications were exercised without sufficient material
				<lb />
				available on record justifying exercise of such powers. It was
				<lb />
				argued that in the State of Rajasthan, there are large
				<lb />
				number of D.El.Ed. Pass candidates who are qualified for
				<lb />
				appointment as primary school teachers (classes I to V).
				<lb />
				Without examination of such data, the B.Ed. degree holders
				<lb />
				are made eligible.
				<lb />
				(viii) It was contended that the entire exercise before the Ministry
				<lb />
				of HRD was in relation to the request of the KVS to recognize
				<lb />
				B.Ed. degree as an alternative qualification, the source to be
				<lb />
				tapped when sufficient number of qualified candidates are
				<lb />
				not available. This was also the view of the officials of MHRD.
				<lb />
				The Minister alone over-ruled this suggestion and required
				<lb />
				that B.Ed. may be recognized as additional qualification and
				<lb />
				that such decision may be projected across all schools in the
				<lb />
				country.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(ix) It was argued by the learned Advocate General that the
				<lb />
				primary education is part of the Concurrent List in Schedule
				<lb />
				VII to the Constitution and under Article 309, it is the power
				<lb />
				of the State Government to make appointments to the posts
				<lb />
				created under the State Government. The Union Government
				<lb />
				while framing regulations contrary to the RTE Act and Rules
				<lb />
				framed thereunder, had usurped the power of the State
				<lb />
				Government to make appointment of qualified persons in the
				<lb />
				posts created under the State Government.
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			24. On the other hand, the learned counsel for NCTE and the
			<lb />
			petitioners, who have supported the NCTE notification dated
			<lb />
			28.06.2018 have raised the following contentions:-
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				(i) The powers are exercised under Sub-section (1) of Section
				<lb />
				23 and not under Sub-section (2) of Section 23 of the RTE
				<lb />
				Act. It is therefore not necessary to examine the data in
				<lb />
				different States.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(ii) The Ministry of HRD had the powers to give directions to the
				<lb />
				NCTE in relation to the policy matters. Essentially the
				<lb />
				educational qualification for appointment as primary teacher
				<lb />
				is an important policy issue.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(iii) After due deliberations the MHRD formed a view that B.Ed.
				<lb />
				degree should be recognized as an additional qualification
				<lb />
				subject to passing the bridge course.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(iv) In policy matters, particularly in the area of technical fields
				<lb />
				such as education, the Court would not substitute its wisdom
				<lb />
				for that of the authorities duly empowered under the Statute
				<lb />
				and aided by experts in the field.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(v) It was contended that the sufficiency of the materials before
				<lb />
				the Ministry for forming final opinion is not subject to judicial
				<lb />
				review. In any case, after full deliberations, the authority had
				<lb />
				come to the conclusion that the B.Ed. degree should be
				<lb />
				recognized as an additional qualification. It was pointed out
				<lb />
				that such qualification was recognized till the year 2012.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(vi) It was contended that the earlier decisions of the Courts
				<lb />
				holding that B.Ed. is not a higher qualification were rendered
				<lb />
				in different background. If eventually the rule making
				<lb />
				authority was of the opinion that a person holding B.Ed.
				<lb />
				degree was just as qualified to impart education in primary
				<lb />
				schools (classes-I to V), the Court would not over-rule such
				<lb />
				matured decision arrived at after due deliberations.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(vii) It was contended that not placing the regulations before the
				<lb />
				Parliament would not vitiate them since the provision under
				<lb />
				Section 35 of the NCTE Act, merely requires such regulations
				<lb />
				to be placed before the Parliament and does not attach any
				<lb />
				adverse consequences if this procedural requirement is not
				<lb />
				followed.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(viii)It was argued that the purpose of constituting NCTE was
				<lb />
				principally for coordinated development of teacher education
				<lb />
				system across the country and the dominant purpose for
				<lb />
				constitution of NCTE was not for laying down qualifications
				<lb />
				for school teachers.
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			25. Both sides have relied upon and referred to various
			<lb />
			judgments, reference to which will be made at appropriate stages.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			26. As noted above, the NCTE has been authorized by the
			<lb />
			Central Government for the purposes of Sub-section (1) of Section
			<lb />
			23 as well as Sub-section (1) of Section 29 of the RTE Act. Sub-
			<lb />
			section (1) of Section 23 pertains to minimum qualifications that a
			<lb />
			person must possess for eligibility for appointment as a teacher,
			<lb />
			whereas Sub-section (1) of Section 29 pertains to curriculum and
			<lb />
			evaluation procedure for elementary education to be laid down by
			<lb />
			the academic authority. The issues of eligibility for appointment as
			<lb />
			a teacher and the curriculum and evaluation procedure for
			<lb />
			elementary education are closely connected and interlinked. It is
			<lb />
			possibly for this reason, that in its wisdom, the Government of
			<lb />
			India has recognized NCTE as an academic authority for both the
			<lb />
			purposes. While exercising such powers, the NCTE evolves
			<lb />
			important criteria and guidelines for setting the curriculum and
			<lb />
			evaluation procedure for elementary education as well as
			<lb />
			prescribing minimum qualification for appointment as a teacher.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			27. Sub-section (1) of Section 23 thus authorizes NCTE as an
			<lb />
			academic authority duly notified by the Central Government for
			<lb />
			prescribing minimum qualifications for appointment as a teacher.
			<lb />
			The power and authority thus exclusively vests in NCTE. Sub-
			<lb />
			section (2) of Section 23 is a special provision under which the
			<lb />
			Central Government retains its authority to relax the qualifications
			<lb />
			for appointment as a teacher under certain circumstances. As per
			<lb />
			this provision where a state does not have adequate institutions
			<lb />
			offering courses or training in teacher education or teachers
			<lb />
			possessing minimum qualifications as laid down under Sub-section
			<lb />
			(1) are not available in sufficient numbers, the Central
			<lb />
			Government may, if it deems necessary, relax the minimum
			<lb />
			qualifications for appointment as a teacher for such period not
			<lb />
			exceeding 5 years as may be specified in the notification. First
			<lb />
			proviso of Sub-section (2) of Section 23 provides that a teacher
			<lb />
			who at the commencement of the Act does not possess minimum
			<lb />
			qualifications as laid down in Sub-section (1) shall acquire such
			<lb />
			qualification within a period of 5 years. Further proviso to Sub-
			<lb />
			section (2) provides that every teacher appointed or in position as
			<lb />
			on 31.03.2015, who does not possess minimum qualifications as
			<lb />
			laid down under Sub-section (1) shall acquire such minimum
			<lb />
			qualification within a period of 4 years from the date of
			<lb />
			commencement of RTE (Amendment) Act 2017.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			28. Analysis of Sub-section (2) of Section 23 would thus show
			<lb />
			that the Central Government has the power to relax the
			<lb />
			qualifications laid down for appointment of the teacher where
			<lb />
			adequate number of institutions offering courses or training in
			<lb />
			teacher education or teachers possessing minimum qualifications
			<lb />
			in a state are not available. Such powers are in the nature of
			<lb />
			relaxation to the essential qualifications that may be prescribed
			<lb />
			under Sub-section (1) of Section 23. In the main body of Sub-
			<lb />
			section (2) and the first and second proviso thereto reference is to
			<lb />
			the qualifications laid down under Sub-section (1). The emphasis
			<lb />
			is on the person to be appointed as a teacher to possess the
			<lb />
			qualification prescribed under Sub-section (1) of Section 23 which
			<lb />
			can be relaxed subject to fulfillment of conditions as provided.
			<lb />
			Thus, there is a clear distinction between the powers to be
			<lb />
			exercised under Sub-section (1) of Section 23 which are vested in
			<lb />
			the NCTE and those that can be exercised by the Central
			<lb />
			Government under Sub-section (2) of Section 23 of relaxing the
			<lb />
			standards laid down by NCTE under Sub-section (1) of Section 23.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			29. With this clarity if we revert back to the materials on record,
			<lb />
			it would emerge that the entire exercise has been undertaken
			<lb />
			initially by the MHRD and thereafter by the NCTE as one under
			<lb />
			Sub-section (1) of Section 23 of the RTE Act. In fact, the learned
			<lb />
			Additional Solicitor General Shri Rastogi had repeatedly argued
			<lb />
			before us that the powers are exercised by NCTE under Sub-
			<lb />
			section (1) of Section 23 and not Sub-section (2) of Section 23. If
			<lb />
			we proceed on such basis, immediate question of the authority of
			<lb />
			the Central Government to mandate the NCTE to make a certain
			<lb />
			change would arise. The RTE Act does not give power to the
			<lb />
			Central Government to give any such directions to the NCTE. We
			<lb />
			have reproduced Section 35 of the RTE Act which are in the nature
			<lb />
			of powers of the Central Government and other authorities to
			<lb />
			issue directions under Sub-section (1) of Section 35. The Central
			<lb />
			Government has the power to issue guidelines to the appropriate
			<lb />
			Government or the local authority for the purpose of
			<lb />
			implementation of the provisions of the Act. Local authority has
			<lb />
			been defined under clause (h) of Section 2 as to mean a Municipal
			<lb />
			Corporation or Municipal Council or Zila Parishad or Nagar
			<lb />
			Panchayat or Panchayat, by whatever names called and to include
			<lb />
			such authority or body having administrative control over the
			<lb />
			school or empowered by or under any law for the time being in
			<lb />
			force to function as local authority. Thus, the power of the Central
			<lb />
			Government to issue guidelines under Sub-section (1) of Section
			<lb />
			35 of the RTE Act does not extend to the NCTE as an academic
			<lb />
			authority notified under Sub-section (1) of Section 23 of the RTE
			<lb />
			Act. A reference of-course was made to Section 29 of the NCTE
			<lb />
			Act for such purpose. Under Sub-section (1) of Section 29, the
			<lb />
			NCTE shall in discharge of its functions and duties under the Act
			<lb />
			be bound by such directions on questions of policy as the Central
			<lb />
			Government may give in writing to it from time to time. However,
			<lb />
			in our opinion, the Central Government cannot trace the source of
			<lb />
			the power to give such directions to the NCTE in exercise of its
			<lb />
			power under Sub-section (1) of Section 23 of the RTE Act. The
			<lb />
			primary source of the powers of the NCTE to frame regulations
			<lb />
			prescribing the minimum qualifications for appointment of
			<lb />
			teachers is in Sub-section (1) of Section 23. In exercise of such
			<lb />
			powers, the NCTE is not to be guided or be bound by any directive
			<lb />
			that the Central Government may issue. We do not find any such
			<lb />
			powers retained by the Central Government under the RTE Act. In
			<lb />
			plain terms therefore, the Ministry of HRD could not have
			<lb />
			mandated the NCTE to make the amendments in question. It is
			<lb />
			beyond dispute that the amendment is not the original work of
			<lb />
			NCTE. In fact, the opinion of the NCTE was that B.Ed. may be
			<lb />
			recognized as an alternative qualification for the purpose of KVS,
			<lb />
			where adequate number of otherwise qualified candidates are in
			<lb />
			short supply. Over-ruling such opinion of NCTE, the Ministry of
			<lb />
			HRD mandated that B.Ed. may be recognized as an additional
			<lb />
			qualification for all schools. This was clearly beyond the power of
			<lb />
			the Central Government.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			30. The RTE Act was enacted to provide for free and compulsory
			<lb />
			education to all children of the age of 6 to 14 years. As noted, as
			<lb />
			per Sub-section (1) of Section 23, a person possessing such
			<lb />
			minimum qualifications, as laid down by the academic authority
			<lb />
			authorised by the Central Government (i.e. NCTE) by notification
			<lb />
			shall be eligible for appointment as a teacher. The primary source
			<lb />
			of the authority of the NCTE to lay down such minimum
			<lb />
			qualifications thus is Sub-section (1) of Section 23 of the RTE Act.
			<lb />
			We are not oblivion to the fact that Section 12A was inserted in
			<lb />
			NCTE Act with effect from 1.6.2012 which provides that for the
			<lb />
			purpose of maintaining standards of education in schools, the
			<lb />
			NCTE may, by regulations, determine the qualifications of persons
			<lb />
			for being recruited as teachers in various levels of schools and
			<lb />
			colleges. We may recall that the NCTE Act, as originally enacted,
			<lb />
			was to provide for establishment of a National Council for Teacher
			<lb />
			Education with a view to achieving planned and coordinate
			<lb />
			development of the teacher education system and for regulation
			<lb />
			and proper maintenance of norms and standards in the teacher
			<lb />
			education system. The purpose of qualifications of school teachers
			<lb />
			was inserted in the preamble only with effect from 1.6.2012.
			<lb />
			Essentially this Section 12A of the NCTE Act is an eco of the
			<lb />
			primary source of power of NCTE flowing from Section 23(1) of
			<lb />
			the RTE Act to lay down minimum qualifications for eligibility for
			<lb />
			appointment as a teacher. It is for this reason, therefore, in our
			<lb />
			opinion, the power of the Central Government to give directions to
			<lb />
			the NCTE under Section 29 of the NCTE Act cannot be utilized to
			<lb />
			require NCTE to frame regulations concerning eligibility for
			<lb />
			appointment as teacher under Section 23(1) of the RTE Act.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			31. Even otherwise, we do not think that the powers of the
			<lb />
			Central Government under Sub-section (1) of Section 29 of the
			<lb />
			NCTE Act are wide enough to require the NCTE to frame
			<lb />
			regulations for eligibility in a particular manner. As per Sub-
			<lb />
			section (1) of Section 29, the NCTE shall in the discharge of its
			<lb />
			functions and duties under the Act be bound by directions on
			<lb />
			question of policy as the Central Government may give in writing
			<lb />
			to it from time to time. The power of the Central Government to
			<lb />
			issue directions to the NCTE and its binding effect are confined to
			<lb />
			the question of policy. The legislature has advisedly limited the
			<lb />
			powers of the Central Government to issue directions only on the
			<lb />
			question of policy.
			<lb />
			The powers thus are not plenary or all
			<lb />
			pervasive but are restricted to the question of policy alone. Such
			<lb />
			provision, therefore, has to be interpreted strictly. The legislature
			<lb />
			has constituted the NCTE with specified duties, functions and
			<lb />
			powers and which Council consists of various experts in the field.
			<lb />
			The legislature has also while empowering the Central government
			<lb />
			to give directions to the Council, advisedly restricted such powers
			<lb />
			on the question of policy.
			<lb />
			The directions of the Central
			<lb />
			Government therefore cannot be for day to day functioning of the
			<lb />
			NCTE or for purposes other than the policy matters. Framing of
			<lb />
			regulations prescribing eligibility criteria or minimum qualifications
			<lb />
			for appointment as primary teachers certainly cannot be seen as a
			<lb />
			policy matter.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			32. In the case of A. Manoharan and others vs. Union of
			<lb />
			India and others [(2008) 3 SCC 641] while interpreting the
			<lb />
			powers of the Central Government to give directions to the Major
			<lb />
			Trust under Sub-section (1) of Section 111 of the Major Port Trusts
			<lb />
			Act, 1963, which provided that the authority in discharge of its
			<lb />
			functions under the Act be bound by such directions on questions
			<lb />
			of policy as the Central Government may give in writing from time
			<lb />
			to time, it was held and observed as under:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot;24. The power of the Central Government to issue
				<lb />
				directions as contained in Section 111 of the 1963 Act
				<lb />
				cannot be stretched to amend the Regulations. Power
				<lb />
				must be exercised by the Central Government only in
				<lb />
				regard to the administration of the Trust. Such a power
				<lb />
				to issue direction must be construed strictly. (See
				<lb />
				Ramana Dayaram Shetty v. International Airport
				<lb />
				Authority of India (1979) 3 SCC 489, Harjit Singh v.
				<lb />
				State of Punjab (2007) 9 SCC 582, Ashoka Smokeless
				<lb />
				Coal India (P) Ltd. v. Union of India (2007) 2 SCC 640
				<lb />
				and Poonam Verma v. DDA. (2007) 13 SCC 154)&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			33. We may also not be unduly perturbed by the finality attached
			<lb />
			to the decision of the Central Government under Section 29(2) of
			<lb />
			the NCTE Act on the question of what constitutes policy matter.
			<lb />
			Any such decision is open to judicial review of the court under
			<lb />
			Article 226 of the Constitution. Such judicial review being a basic
			<lb />
			feature of the Constitution as held by the judgment of the
			<lb />
			Supreme Court in the case of L. Chandra Kumar vs. Union of
			<lb />
			India and other [(1997) 3 SCC 261] cannot be barred.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			34. Though not so projected before us, if the Central
			<lb />
			Government was exercising powers under Sub-section (2) of
			<lb />
			Section 23, the same had to be upon fulfillment of conditions
			<lb />
			precedent for exercise of such powers. As noted, it is open for the
			<lb />
			Central Government to relax the qualifications prescribed under
			<lb />
			Sub-section (1) of Section 23, if adequate institutions offering
			<lb />
			courses or training in teacher education or teachers possessing
			<lb />
			minimum qualifications in a state are not available in sufficient
			<lb />
			numbers. Firstly, Sub-section (2) refers to such short fall arising in
			<lb />
			a state meaning thereby such powers have to be exercised state-
			<lb />
			wise. Secondly, the powers can be exercised only upon the Central
			<lb />
			Government finding that in such a state adequate institutions
			<lb />
			offering courses or training are not available or teachers
			<lb />
			possessing minimum qualifications are not available in sufficient
			<lb />
			numbers. Only if these conditions are satisfied, the power of
			<lb />
			relaxing the minimum qualification prescribed under Sub-section
			<lb />
			(1) of Section 23 can be exercised, not otherwise. In the present
			<lb />
			case, no such exercise has been undertaken. The broad discussion
			<lb />
			of number of vacancies and short fall in certain regions would not
			<lb />
			satisfy the requirements for exercise of powers under Sub-section
			<lb />
			(2) of Section 23. Further, as recorded above such powers were
			<lb />
			state specific and had to be exercised in relation to a particular
			<lb />
			state. Undoubtedly, within the state of Rajasthan no such exercise
			<lb />
			has been carried out.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			35. Learned counsel for the supporters of the impugned
			<lb />
			notification have argued before us that the State Government or
			<lb />
			the petitioners challenging the notification have not produced any
			<lb />
			data to show that sufficient number of candidates other than
			<lb />
			holding B.Ed. degree course were available. To our mind, this was
			<lb />
			not the requirement for exercise of powers under Sub-section (2)
			<lb />
			of Section 23. The requirement was establishing that the factors
			<lb />
			necessary for exercising the powers existed and the required
			<lb />
			collection of data as to the number of vacancies vis-a-vis number
			<lb />
			of eligible candidates available without relaxing the minimum
			<lb />
			qualifications was undertaken. Under the circumstances, it is not
			<lb />
			necessary to go into the details of the statements made before us
			<lb />
			either by the petitioners challenging the notification or the learned
			<lb />
			Advocate General appearing for the State Government, who had
			<lb />
			stated that in the REET conducted on 26.09.2021 for primary,
			<lb />
			upper primary school teacher (level-1), 3,50,000 odd candidates
			<lb />
			holding the qualifications of BSTC D.El.Ed. had participated against
			<lb />
			18850 vacant posts.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			36. Even going by the insertion of B.Ed. as a recognized
			<lb />
			qualification, it is manifest that the B.Ed. per se is not sufficient
			<lb />
			educational qualification. It is for this reason that the MHRD
			<lb />
			desired and NCTE has introduced the requirement of passing of
			<lb />
			the bridge course. It is only on passing of such bridge course that
			<lb />
			the candidate would become eligible to hold the post of primary
			<lb />
			school teacher (classes-I to V). This should not be misunderstood
			<lb />
			as an in-service training after recruitment. This is a part and
			<lb />
			parcel of the eligibility criteria prescribed in the Rules.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			37. We may recall that the amended qualifications are that the
			<lb />
			person may have a B.Ed. degree and may compete for the
			<lb />
			appointment, however after appointment within a period of two
			<lb />
			years, he must pass the bridge course of six months which will be
			<lb />
			designed by the NCTE. In clear terms, the intention is to design a
			<lb />
			course which will equip a candidate to impart education at the
			<lb />
			primary school level (classes-I to V). This is an indirect admission
			<lb />
			on the part of the authorities that minus such bridge course, a
			<lb />
			B.Ed. degree holder is not qualified to hold the post of a primary
			<lb />
			school teacher (classes-I to V). If upon fulfillment of conditions
			<lb />
			required for exercising powers under Sub-section (2) of Section
			<lb />
			23, the Central Government had relaxed the standards by
			<lb />
			enabling a B.Ed. degree holder to secure appointment but to clear
			<lb />
			the bridge course within the specified time, perhaps no challenge
			<lb />
			would lie against exercise of such powers. However, even the
			<lb />
			Union of India has not taken the stand that the powers are
			<lb />
			exercised by the Central Government under Sub-section (2) of
			<lb />
			Section 23 of the RTE Act. In any case, we have concluded that no
			<lb />
			such powers could have been exercised without satisfying that the
			<lb />
			conditions precedent for exercising such powers existed.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			38. Since the MHRD as well as NCTE through the process of
			<lb />
			framing the amendments and issuing the notification of
			<lb />
			amendment have recognized that B.Ed. degree per se is not a
			<lb />
			sufficient qualification for appointment as teacher in primary
			<lb />
			school (classes-I to V), it is not necessary to dilate on the
			<lb />
			question whether a B.Ed. degree is a higher qualification as
			<lb />
			compared to D.El.Ed. or not. To borrow mathematical phraseology,
			<lb />
			B.Ed. degree course does not form a super set of training of which
			<lb />
			D.El.Ed. Diploma training forms a sub set. In other words, a B.Ed.
			<lb />
			degree holder cannot argue that he has sufficient training to teach
			<lb />
			not only higher standards but also the primary level standard I to
			<lb />
			V and what is taught to a D.El.Ed. course is part and parcel of his
			<lb />
			training. This was rejected by the Supreme Court in the cases of
			<lb />
			P.M. Latha and others vs. State of Kerala and others [2003
			<lb />
			(3) SCC 541] and Yogesh Kumar and others vs. Government
			<lb />
			of NTC, Delhi and others [2003 (3) SCC 548].
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			39. In the case of P.M. Latha (supra), for recruitment to the post
			<lb />
			of lower and upper primary school teachers in Government
			<lb />
			schools, qualification prescribed was Trained Teachers Certificate
			<lb />
			(&apos;TTC&apos;, for short) pass. Instead of selecting the TTC holders, B.Ed.
			<lb />
			degree holders were selected on the basis that B.Ed. is higher
			<lb />
			qualification than TTC. It was in this background held that there is
			<lb />
			no force in the argument that B.Ed. qualification is higher
			<lb />
			qualification than TTC. Similar view was expressed in the case of
			<lb />
			Yogesh Kumar (supra). This is also a case where for the post of
			<lb />
			assistant teachers in primary schools of Municipal Corporation,
			<lb />
			qualifications prescribed were TTC holders. It was held that the
			<lb />
			candidates holding B.Ed. degree cannot be considered eligible as
			<lb />
			B.Ed. cannot be treated higher qualification than TTC.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			40. Learned Additional Solicitor General however painstakingly
			<lb />
			argued that these judgments were rendered in vastly different
			<lb />
			background and arose in a situation which no longer prevails. For
			<lb />
			two reasons, we are not prepared to accept this contention in its
			<lb />
			fullest form. Despite the above noted judgments of the Supreme
			<lb />
			Court, if the rule making authority had after due deliberations
			<lb />
			come to a conclusion that it is necessary to recognize B.Ed.
			<lb />
			degree as one of the eligibility criteria for appointment, in exercise
			<lb />
			of judicial review, out of due deference to the expertise of the
			<lb />
			academic authority, we would perhaps have not interfered.
			<lb />
			However, even the academic authority has not proceeded on the
			<lb />
			basis that B.Ed. is a sufficient training for imparting education at
			<lb />
			the lowest level of primary schools. It is therefore that the bridge
			<lb />
			course, which literally would bridge the training gap has been
			<lb />
			envisaged.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			41. With these conclusions, we may deal with a few peripheral
			<lb />
			issues and contentions.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			42. Since we have held that the NCTE has exercised powers
			<lb />
			under Sub-section (1) of Section 23 of the RTE Act and also held
			<lb />
			that in case the Central Government could not have given
			<lb />
			directions to the NCTE for framing the regulations in a particular
			<lb />
			manner for prescribing a particular eligibility criteria for
			<lb />
			appointment of a teacher under Section 29 of the NCTE Act, it is
			<lb />
			not necessary to examine the consequences of the regulations not
			<lb />
			being placed for approval before the Parliament.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			43. The learned counsel Shri Vigyan Shah was perhaps not
			<lb />
			correct in contending that NCTE could not have amended the
			<lb />
			eligibility criteria without amending the notification dated
			<lb />
			12.11.2014. Under this notification, Clause (4) provides for
			<lb />
			qualification for recruitment as provided in the schedule. The first
			<lb />
			schedule pertains to minimum academic and professional
			<lb />
			qualifications at different level of schools. Clause 3 contained in
			<lb />
			the schedule pertains to primary and upper primary (Class I to
			<lb />
			VIII) and the qualification prescribed are &quot;minimum qualifications
			<lb />
			as laid down by National Council for Teacher Education vide its
			<lb />
			notification dated 23.08.2010 as amended from time to time
			<lb />
			issued in exercise of the powers conferred under Sub-section (1)
			<lb />
			of Section 23 of the Right of Children to Free and Compulsory
			<lb />
			Education Act, 2009 (35 of 2009)&quot;. As per these Regulations thus,
			<lb />
			the essential qualifications for appointment are those as
			<lb />
			prescribed under the notification issued under Sub-section (1) of
			<lb />
			Section 23 of the Act, namely, one dated 23.08.2010 as amended
			<lb />
			from time to time. Thus, the moment the notification dated
			<lb />
			23.08.2010 is amended by NCTE in exercise of powers under Sub-
			<lb />
			section (1) of Section 23 automatically such change gets reflected
			<lb />
			and embedded in the qualifications prescribed in the first schedule
			<lb />
			of these regulations. Thereafter, therefore, there was no need to
			<lb />
			amend this notification. All challenges in the preliminary
			<lb />
			notification dated 23.08.2010 would automatically be recognized
			<lb />
			for the purpose of the said schedule.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			44. The debate has also taken place with respect to the stand of
			<lb />
			the State Government. Firstly, with respect to the State
			<lb />
			Government as a respondent challenging the notification of NCTE,
			<lb />
			it was argued by the learned Additional Solicitor General that such
			<lb />
			challenge without a counter petition being filed, was not
			<lb />
			maintainable as per the High Court Rules. Second contentious
			<lb />
			issue was the act of the State Government to ignore the NCTE
			<lb />
			notification making amendment in the eligibility criteria and not
			<lb />
			recognizing B.Ed. degree holders for the purpose of REET.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			45. Since there are independent petitions and petitioners before
			<lb />
			us who have challenged the notification of NCTE, it is not
			<lb />
			necessary for us to examine whether the State Government on its
			<lb />
			own as respondent could maintain its challenge without filing an
			<lb />
			independent petition. However, with respect to the second ground,
			<lb />
			we are of the opinion that the State Government could not have
			<lb />
			ignored the notification while inviting applications for REET. Even if
			<lb />
			the State Government was of the opinion that such notification
			<lb />
			was unconstitutional or for any reason illegal, the same had to be
			<lb />
			stayed or set aside by a competent court before it could be
			<lb />
			ignored.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			46. The contention of Shri Rastogi that the challengers to the
			<lb />
			notification have no locus standi to bring the petition because the
			<lb />
			amendment merely expands the zone of consideration, cannot be
			<lb />
			accepted. Whether by mere expansion of zone of consideration the
			<lb />
			challenge will succeed or not is a matter of a different context but
			<lb />
			a person who is already eligible finds himself in a wider
			<lb />
			competition on account of widening the zone of consideration for
			<lb />
			appointment or promotion holds a belief that such amendment is
			<lb />
			illegal he has every right to call in question. To reiterate the
			<lb />
			question of locus standi of such a person and maintainability of his
			<lb />
			or her petition stands on vastly different footing as compared to
			<lb />
			the success or failure of such challenge to widening of the zone of
			<lb />
			consideration for appointment or promotion. The judgments relied
			<lb />
			upon in this context by Shri Rastogi in the cases of Government
			<lb />
			of Andhra Pradesh vs. P. Dilip Kumar and others [1993 (2)
			<lb />
			SCC 310] and Shyama Charan Dash and others vs. State of
			<lb />
			Orissa and others [2003 (4) SCC 218] would fall in a latter
			<lb />
			category. It is open for him to argue that when the only
			<lb />
			consequence of the amendments in the regulations is expanding
			<lb />
			the zone of consideration, the Court should not strike down the
			<lb />
			amendment is entirely different from arguing that the persons
			<lb />
			recognized as eligible as per the existing regulations cannot
			<lb />
			question the amendment.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			47. We concede to the suggestion of the learned Additional
			<lb />
			Solicitor General that in policy matters and particularly in
			<lb />
			specialized and highly technical fields such as education, the Court
			<lb />
			always holds the opinion of the policy framers with highest
			<lb />
			regards and would not substitute its wisdom for that of the
			<lb />
			specialized body. The reference to the decisions of the Supreme
			<lb />
			Court in the case of All India Council for Technical Education
			<lb />
			vs. Surinder Kumar Dhawan and others [(2009) 11 SCC
			<lb />
			726] and Zahoor Ahmad Rather and others vs. Sheikh
			<lb />
			Imtiyaz Ahmad and others [(2019) 2 SCC 404] for such
			<lb />
			purpose is noted. However, in the present case, we have not
			<lb />
			questioned the wisdom of the rule making authority to make a
			<lb />
			certain change in the eligibility criteria. What we have held is that
			<lb />
			the same was done under the mandate of the Central Government
			<lb />
			without such powers being vested.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			48. The learned Advocate General is not quite accurate in
			<lb />
			contending that by prescribing these qualifications there is affront
			<lb />
			on the State&apos;s power to recruit persons on the posts under the
			<lb />
			State Government. Quite apart, the power under Article 309 of the
			<lb />
			Constitution to make recruitment by the State agencies, the
			<lb />
			eligibility criteria for various posts can be prescribed under
			<lb />
			respective statutes governing the terms and conditions of
			<lb />
			education and such similar positions. Even under Sub-rule (3) of
			<lb />
			Rule 266 of the Rajasthan Panchayat Raj Rules, 1996, the State
			<lb />
			legislature has provided that the qualifications of the teachers
			<lb />
			would be as prescribed by the NCTE.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			49. We summarize our conclusions as thus:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				(i)
				<lb />
				The impugned notification dated 28.06.2018 is unlawful
				<lb />
				because:-
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(a) it is under the direction of the Central Government,
				<lb />
				which power the Central Government under Sub-
				<lb />
				section (1) of Section 23 of the RTE Act did not have;
				<lb />
				and
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(b) it is not in exercise of power of the Central Government
				<lb />
				under Sub-section (2) of Section 23 of RTE Act relaxing
				<lb />
				the eligibility criteria prescribed by the NCTE, nor there
				<lb />
				has been any exercise for ascertaining existence of the
				<lb />
				conditions precedent for exercising such power.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(ii) The petitioners have locus standi to challenge the notification
				<lb />
				dated 28.06.2018. Merely because an additional qualification
				<lb />
				is recognized as one of the eligibility criteria, the petitioners
				<lb />
				cannot be prevented from challenging it.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(iii) Accepting a candidate with B.Ed. degree as eligible for
				<lb />
				appointment and thereafter subjecting him to complete the
				<lb />
				bridge course within two years of appointment is in the
				<lb />
				nature of relaxing the existing eligibility criteria, which the
				<lb />
				Central Government could have done only within Sub-section
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(2) of Section 23 and subject to existence of circumstances
				<lb />
				necessary for exercise of such power.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(iv) The State Government could not have ignored the
				<lb />
				notification of NCTE dated 28.06.2018 while issuing
				<lb />
				advertisement for REET. However, when we have declared
				<lb />
				that this notification is illegal and are in the process of
				<lb />
				setting aside, the issue becomes one of academic value.
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			50. In the result, the impugned notification dated 28.06.2018 is
			<lb />
			set aside. The latter dated 30 th May 2018 of the MHRD to NCTE
			<lb />
			being in the nature of internal communication, does not give rise
			<lb />
			to cause of action unless acted upon and therefore, it is not
			<lb />
			necessary to separately set it aside.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			51. The writ petitions being D.B. Civil Writ Petition No.
			<lb />
			6587/2021 filed by Mukesh Kumar Royal and other similar
			<lb />
			connected petitions are allowed.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			52. The writ petitions being D.B. Civil Writ Petition No.
			<lb />
			2108/2021 filed by Sunita and other similar connected petitions
			<lb />
			are dismissed.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			53. The interim orders granted earlier allowing the petitioners
			<lb />
			holding B.Ed. degree to appear in the REET are vacated. The
			<lb />
			candidature of those petitioners, who appeared in the REET under
			<lb />
			the interim orders of this Court, shall not be processed further.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			54. All applications stand disposed of accordingly.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(SUDESH BANSAL),J
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(AKIL KURESHI),CJ
			<lb />
		</p>
	</text>
</tei>
