<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">

			<p>(Video-Conferencing)<lb/></p>

			<p>1.<lb/> Shares, of M/s Omaxe Ltd., held by the petitioner Sunil Goel,<lb/> were pledged with the respondent M/s Indiabulls Housing Finance<lb/> Ltd. (hereinafter referred to as &quot;IHFL&quot;), against a loan, advanced by<lb/> IHFL to M/s. Omaxe Forest Spa and Hills Developers Ltd.<lb/> (hereinafter referred to as &quot;Omaxe Forest Spa&quot;).<lb/> pattern in Guild Builders has been set out, in a tabular form, in the<lb/> petition, thus:<lb/></p>

			<p>Particulars<lb/> No. of Shares<lb/> Approximage<lb/> percentage<lb/> shareholding<lb/> SUNIL GOEL GROUP<lb/> Sunil Goel<lb/> 90,70,722<lb/> 16.85%<lb/> Seema Goel<lb/> 26,74,267<lb/> 4.95%<lb/> Sunil Goel (HUF)<lb/> 14,91,595<lb/> 2.77%<lb/> Annay Realtors<lb/> Private<lb/> Limited<lb/> 39,690<lb/> 0.07%<lb/> 1,32,36,584<lb/> 24.57%<lb/> ROHTAS GOEL GROUP<lb/> Rohtas Goel<lb/> 3,06,11,558<lb/> 56.88%<lb/> Rohtas Goel (HUF)<lb/> 17,51,662<lb/> 3.25%<lb/> Sushma Goel<lb/> 63,29,142<lb/> 11.76%<lb/> Mohit Goel<lb/> 1,561<lb/></p>

			<head>0.003%<lb/> VSG Builders<lb/> Private Limited<lb/> 55,567<lb/> 0.11%<lb/> NJS Developers<lb/> Private<lb/> 55,567<lb/> 0.11%<lb/> 3,88,05,057<lb/> 72.11%<lb/> JAI BHAGWAN GOEL GROUP<lb/> Jai Bhagwan Goel<lb/> 17,08,067<lb/> 3.18%<lb/> Rekha Goel<lb/> 27,402<lb/> 0.05%<lb/> 17,35,469<lb/> 3.23%<lb/> Total<lb/></head>

			<p>5,38,16,800<lb/> 100%<lb/> (There appears to be some discrepancy in the afore-extracted tables,<lb/> which have been reproduced, verbatim, from the petition. However,<lb/> these figures do not seriously affect the outcome of this proceeding;<lb/> hence, I do not deem it to appropriate to dwell thereon.)<lb/></p>

			<p>4.<lb/> It is admitted, by the petitioner, that Guild Builders and its<lb/> subsidiaries, including Omaxe Ltd., are part of the Omaxe Group of<lb/> companies, which, it is stated, is a &quot;quasi-partnership&quot;, of the three<lb/> brothers, namely the petitioner, Rohtas Goel and Jai Bhagwan Goel.<lb/> The petitioner claims to own approximately 19% shares in Omaxe<lb/> Ltd. and its group companies, and to have been illegally ousted from<lb/> the position of Joint Managing Director of Omaxe Ltd. in September,<lb/> 2017, against which the petitioner has moved the learned National<lb/> Company Law Tribunal, Chandigarh (hereinafter referred to as &quot;the<lb/> learned NCLT&quot;).<lb/></p>

			<p>5.<lb/> Vide three separate Loan Agreements, dated 29 th September,<lb/> 2015, loans of ₹ 65 crores, ₹ 65 crores and ₹ 20 crores, totalling ₹ 150<lb/> crores, were availed, by Omaxe Forest Spa, from the respondent<lb/> IHFL. The covenants of all three Loan Agreements were identical,<lb/> and it is necessary, in view of the nature of dispute that has arisen in<lb/> the present case, to set out some of the relevant clauses thereof, thus:<lb/></p>

			<p>(i)<lb/> Clause 1.1 contained the Definitions, governing the Loan<lb/> Agreement. Of these, the following definitions are material:<lb/></p>

			<p>&quot;(i) &quot;Agreement&quot; or &quot;Loan Agreement&quot; means<lb/> this agreement, all schedules hereunder and all<lb/> amendment(s)/addendum(s) to this Agreement,<lb/> including such other document (s), which is made<lb/> apart to this Agreement by reference.<lb/> *****<lb/></p>

			<p>(iii) &quot;Borrower(s)&quot;<lb/> means<lb/> the<lb/> company(ies)/person(s)/firm(s) named in the Schedule<lb/> I hereunder as the Borrower(s) and whose address(s)<lb/> and other details are also mentioned in Schedule I<lb/> hereunder.<lb/></p>

			<p>(iv) &quot;Borrower&apos;s Dues&quot; means the outstanding<lb/> principal amount of the Loan and other amounts<lb/> payable by the Obligor(s) to the Lender as per the<lb/> Loan Documents and/or any other agreement(s)<lb/> entered between (a) the Obligor(s) and (b) the Lender,<lb/> including any interest, Default Interest, fees, costs,<lb/> charges, expenses and other sums whatsoever payable<lb/> by the Obligor(s) to the Lender.<lb/></p>

			<p>(v)<lb/> &quot;Co-Borrower(s)&quot;<lb/> means<lb/> the<lb/> company(ies)/person(s)/firm(s) named in the Schedule<lb/> I hereunder as the Co-Borrower(s) and whose<lb/> address(s) and other details are also mentioned in<lb/> Schedule I hereunder.<lb/></p>

			<p>*****<lb/> (viii) &quot;Event of Default&quot; means any event(s) or<lb/> circumstance(s) specified as such in this Agreement<lb/> and/or any other event(s) or circumstance(s) referred to<lb/> /defined as an Event of Default under any of the Loan<lb/> Documents.<lb/></p>

			<p>*****<lb/></p>

			<p>(x)<lb/> &quot;Group Borrower&apos;s Dues&quot; means<lb/></p>

			<p>(i)<lb/> the Borrower&apos;s Dues payable to the<lb/> Lender under the Loan Documents and<lb/> (ii)<lb/> all amounts payable to the Lender and/or<lb/> the other group/associate entity/entities of the<lb/> Lender under/pursuant to any other Loan<lb/> Agreement(s)/document(s)<lb/> executed/to<lb/> be<lb/> executed from time to time between<lb/></p>

			<p>(a)<lb/> the<lb/> Lender<lb/> and/or<lb/> other<lb/> group/associate entity/entities of the<lb/> Lender and<lb/></p>

			<p>(b) the Obligor(s) and/or other<lb/> group/associate entity/entities of the<lb/> Obligor(s)<lb/> provided if any Security under the Loan<lb/> Documents is and/or shall also be a security<lb/> under<lb/> such<lb/> other<lb/> Loan<lb/> Agreement(s)/document(s).<lb/></p>

			<p>*****<lb/></p>

			<p>(xiv) &quot;Loan&quot; means the loan amount mentioned in<lb/> Schedule I of this Agreement, which will be or has<lb/> been made available under this Agreement, as per the<lb/> terms and conditions contained in the Loan<lb/> Documents, to the extent the same is not cancelled,<lb/> reduced or transferred under this Agreement.<lb/></p>

			<p>(xv) &quot;Loan Documents&quot; means<lb/></p>

			<p>(a)<lb/> this Agreement,<lb/></p>

			<p>(b)<lb/> the Security Documents and/or<lb/></p>

			<p>(c)<lb/> all other agreement(s), application(s),<lb/> form(s), undertaking(s), document(s), letter(s),<lb/> deed(s), memorandum(s), declaration(s) and/or<lb/> power of attorney(s) evidencing, securing,<lb/> governing or otherwise pertaining/relating to<lb/> the Loan/Borrower&apos;s Dues and includes any<lb/> amendatory, modifactory or supplemental<lb/> agreement thereto.<lb/></p>

			<p>*****<lb/></p>

			<p>(xvii) &quot;Obligor(s)&quot; means the Borrower(s), the Co-<lb/>Borrower(s), the Guarantor(s), the Hypothecator(s),<lb/> the Pledgor(s), the mortgagor(s), and/or any other<lb/> person(s) providing any Security in favour of the<lb/> Lender under the Loan Documents and/or who is or<lb/> becomes a party (other than the Lender) to any Loan<lb/> Documents.<lb/></p>

			<p>(xx) &quot;Pledgor(s)&quot;<lb/> means<lb/> the<lb/> companies/person(s)/firm(s) named in Schedule-I as<lb/> Pledgor(s) and/or any other person(s)/entity,<lb/> who/which have agreed/will agree to create a<lb/> pledge/charged on its/their assets in favour of the<lb/> Lender to secure, inter alia, the fulfilment of the<lb/> Obligor(s)&apos; obligations under the Loan Documents<lb/> including payment of the Borrower&apos;s Dues to the<lb/> Lender.<lb/></p>

			<p>(xxi) &quot;Pledged/Charged Shares&quot; means the<lb/> shares/securities pledged, charged, arranged and/or<lb/> furnished as Security to secure the fulfilment of the<lb/> Obligor(s)&apos; obligations under the Loan Documents<lb/> (including payment of the Borrower&apos;s Dues to the<lb/> Lender) which shall include all the<lb/> (i)<lb/> shares/securities of the Pledgor(s)<lb/> credited or/to be credited from time to time in<lb/> the Pledgor(s)&apos; Demat Account(s) as mentioned<lb/> in the Schedule IV hereunder (&quot;Demat<lb/> Account(s)&quot;) including the shares/securities<lb/> mentioned in Schedule IV hereunder,<lb/></p>

			<p>(ii)<lb/> Share in the physical form, if any, as<lb/> more particularly mentioned in Schedule IV<lb/> hereunder,<lb/></p>

			<p>(iii) such<lb/> additional<lb/> shares/securities,<lb/> whether by way of bonus or rights issue or<lb/> otherwise and any letter of allotment in relation<lb/> thereto and instruments or other property from<lb/> time to time received, receivable in respect of or<lb/> in exchange for any and all of the<lb/> Pledged/Charged Shares from time to time<lb/> required by the Borrower(s), Co-Borrower(s)<lb/> and/or the Pledgor(s) in any other manner and<lb/> certificates representing such additional shares;<lb/> and/or<lb/></p>

			<p>(iv) Any<lb/> shares/securities<lb/> transferred/<lb/> deposited to/in the Demat Account(s) from time<lb/> to time in any manner whatsoever.<lb/> Such Pledged/Charged Shares maybe wholly in a<lb/> dematerialized state or in a physical state or partly in<lb/> one form and partly in another form. The applicable<lb/> provisions of the Loan Documents shall operate<lb/> irrespective whether the Pledged/Charged Shares (or<lb/> any part thereof) are in dematerialized state of physical<lb/> state.<lb/> *****<lb/></p>

			<p>(xxv) &quot;Security&quot; means, as the context may require,<lb/></p>

			<p>(a)<lb/> a mortgage, charge, hypothecation,<lb/> escrow, guarantee, pledge, lien and/or other<lb/> security interest created and/or to be created in<lb/> favour of the Lender securing the fulfillment of<lb/> all the obligation(s) of the Obligor(s) (including<lb/> payment of the Borrower&apos;s Dues to the Lender)<lb/> under the Loan Documents and/or<lb/></p>

			<p>(b)<lb/> assets of the Obligor(s) provided/to be<lb/> provided as security/collateral, by way of, inter<lb/> alia, a mortgage, charge, hypothecation,<lb/> escrow, encumbrance, guarantee, pledge, lien<lb/> and/or other security interest, in favour of the<lb/> Lender securing the fulfillment of all the<lb/> obligation(s) of the Obligor(s) (including<lb/> payment of the Borrower&apos;s Dues to the Lender)<lb/> under the Loan Documents and/or any other<lb/> arrangement(s)/agreement(s) having a similar<lb/> effect.<lb/></p>

			<p>(xxvi) &quot;Security Documents&quot; means, as the context<lb/> may require, mortgage deed(s), other documents<lb/> relating to mortgage, pledge/charge agreement, Power<lb/> of Attorney, escrow agreement(s), deed of<lb/> hypothecation, guarantee deed(s), demand promissory<lb/> note, letter of continuity, any other document(s)/<lb/> declaration(s)/ memorandum(s)/ undertaking(s) in<lb/> relation to the Security and/or any document(s)<lb/> designated as such by the Lender and any amendments<lb/> thereof from time to time.<lb/> (Emphasis supplied)<lb/></p>

			<p>(ii) Schedule I named Omaxe Forest Spa as the &quot;Borrower&quot;,<lb/> with no Co-Borrower, Omaxe Ltd., Guild Builders, Rohtas<lb/> Goel, Mohit Goel and the petitioner as the Guarantors, and<lb/> Omaxe Ltd., Guild Builders, and the petitioner as the Pledgors,<lb/> against the loan availed by Omaxe Forest Spa.<lb/></p>

			<p>(iii) Clause 2 dealt, exhaustively, with &quot;The Loan and The<lb/> Security&quot;. The various sub-clauses thereunder, to the extent<lb/> they are relevant, read thus:<lb/></p>

			<p>&quot;2.1 Loan Amount<lb/></p>

			<p>Subject to the provisions of the Loan<lb/> documents, the Pledgor agrees to lend to the<lb/> Borrower(s) and/or the Co-borrower(s), and the<lb/> Borrower(s) and/or the Co-Borrower(s) agreed<lb/> to borrow from the Lender, the Loan mentioned<lb/> in Schedule I hereunder. .…<lb/> *****<lb/></p>

			<p>2.2<lb/> Security and additional Security<lb/> *****<lb/></p>

			<p>(d)<lb/> Pledge/Charge of Shares<lb/> i)<lb/> At all times during the validity of<lb/> the Loan Documents, the Borrower(s)<lb/> and/or the Co-Borrower(s) shall cause to<lb/> be forthwith created a first-ranking and<lb/> exclusive pledge/charge in favour of the<lb/> Lender on agreed percentage (as<lb/> specified in Schedule I hereunder) of the<lb/> (present and future) shares, instrument(s)<lb/> convertible<lb/> into<lb/> shares<lb/> and/or<lb/> instrument(s) with voting rights issued/to<lb/> be issued by the company/companies<lb/> mentioned in Schedule IV hereunder and<lb/> in this regard, the Borrower(s) and/or the<lb/> Co-Borrower(s) shall cause the (present<lb/> and future) holders of the shares and/or<lb/> the<lb/> said<lb/> instruments<lb/> of<lb/> such<lb/> companies/companies<lb/> to<lb/> forthwith<lb/> execute a pledge/charge agreement, other<lb/> documents and a Power of Attorney in<lb/> the form and substance satisfactory to<lb/> the Lender. Further, without prejudice to<lb/> the aforesaid, the Borrower(s) and/or the<lb/> Co-Borrower(s)<lb/> shall<lb/> cause<lb/> the<lb/> Pledgor(s) to forthwith create a first-<lb/>ranking and exclusive pledge/charge on<lb/> the Pledged/Charged Shares in favour of<lb/> the Lender and/or any of its<lb/> agents/nominees/trustees, including all<lb/> shares/securities lying in, and/or<lb/> shares/securities which has been<lb/> credited/shall be credited from time to<lb/> time in the Pledgor(s)&apos; Demat<lb/> Account(s) mentioned in the Schedule<lb/> IV to this Agreement and in regard of<lb/> which the Borrower(s) and/or the Co-<lb/>Borrower(s) shall cause the Pledgor(s) to<lb/> execute a pledge/charge agreement, other<lb/> documents and a Power of Attorney in<lb/> the form and substance satisfactory to<lb/> the Lender. The demat Account(s) shall<lb/> be opened by the Pledgor(s) with a<lb/> depository participant(s) as approved by<lb/> the Lender.<lb/></p>

			<p>ii)<lb/> The Pledgor(s) is/are/shall be<lb/> pledging the Pledged/Charged Shares in<lb/> consideration that the Lender has agreed<lb/> to lend and advance the Loan to the<lb/> Borrower(s) and/or the Co-Borrower(s)<lb/> with the understanding that on or after<lb/> the occurrence of an Event of Default<lb/> under the Loan Documents the<lb/> Pledged/Charged Shares or any part<lb/> thereof may be sold, disposed off,<lb/> transferred, encumbered and/or dealt<lb/> with, in any manner whatsoever and on<lb/> such terms and conditions (including the<lb/> sale price) at the sole discretion of the<lb/> Lender.<lb/></p>

			<p>iii)<lb/> The Borrower(s) and/or the Co-<lb/>Borrower(s) confirm and undertake that<lb/> the Pledged/Charged Shares, as more<lb/> particularly described in the Schedule IV<lb/> hereunder and which are to be/are<lb/> pledged/charged in favour of the Lender,<lb/> are the absolute property of the<lb/> Pledgor(s) and that the same are and<lb/> shall be free from all encumbrances and<lb/> claims<lb/> (except<lb/> for<lb/> any<lb/> pledge/charge/claim of the Lender) at all<lb/> times till all the obligations of the<lb/> Obligor(s) under the Loan Documents<lb/> have been complied with to the<lb/> satisfaction of the Lender including<lb/> payment/repayment of Borrower&apos;s Dues<lb/> to the Lender by the Obligor(s) and all<lb/> requisite<lb/> consents,<lb/> regulatory<lb/> or<lb/> otherwise, and procedural formalities for<lb/> pledging the Pledged/Charged Shares are<lb/> obtained and complied with.<lb/></p>

			<p>iv)<lb/> The Borrower(s) and/or the Co-<lb/>Borrower(s) agree and shall cause the<lb/> Pledgor(s) to agree to obtain all consents<lb/> and permissions to execute such<lb/> documents, deeds and writings as may be<lb/> required by the Lender to create the<lb/> Security for payment and/or repayment<lb/> of the Borrower&apos;s Dues under the Loan<lb/> Documents. The Borrower(s) and/or the<lb/> Co-Borrower(s) shall ensure that the<lb/> Pledgor(s) meet the requirements of<lb/> Loan Documents to the extent applicable<lb/> to the Pledgor(s).<lb/> Unless otherwise agreed by the Lender, subject<lb/> to clause 2.4 of this Agreement, the<lb/> Pledged/Charged Shares shall not be permitted<lb/> to be de-pledged/released of pledge/charge<lb/> unless the entire Borrower&apos;s Dues have been<lb/> repaid to the Lender.<lb/></p>

			<p>2.3<lb/> Security Cover<lb/> The Borrower(s) and/or the Co-borrower(s)<lb/> shallots, and/or shall cause the Obligor(s) to,<lb/> maintain the Security, as stipulated in Schedule<lb/> I hereunder at all times during the validity of<lb/> the Loan Documents (&quot;Security Cover&quot;). For<lb/> the purposes of calculating the Security Cover,<lb/> only the value of the immovable properties<lb/> (&quot;Said Immovable Properties&quot;) mortgaged in<lb/> favour of the Lender to secure, inter alia, the<lb/> Group Borrower&apos;s Dues, shall be taken into<lb/> consideration.<lb/> If at any time during the<lb/> continuance of this Agreement, the Lender is of<lb/> the opinion that the value of the Said<lb/> Immovable Properties has become inadequate<lb/> to maintain the Security Cover, then whether or<lb/> not the Lender advising the Obligor(s) to that<lb/> effect, within two days the Borrower(s) and/or<lb/> the Co-Borrower(s) shall forthwith provide and<lb/> furnish and/or shall cause the Obligor(s) to<lb/> forthwith provide and furnish to the satisfaction<lb/> of the Lender, either cash or such other Security<lb/> (acceptable to the Lender) to the satisfaction of<lb/> the Lender to make good the shortfall in the<lb/> Security Cover so as to maintain the Security, at<lb/> all times. The Lender shall be entitled to make<lb/> a call for additional Security to the Borrower(s)<lb/> and/or the Co-Borrower(s) if the Security Cover<lb/> is not maintained and the Borrower(s) and/or<lb/> the Co-Borrower(s) shall be bound to forthwith<lb/> (within two days) provide/create additional<lb/> Security to the satisfaction of the Lender.<lb/> Without prejudice to the other provisions of the<lb/> Loan Documents, the Lender shall have the<lb/> right to recall the Loan/Borrower&apos;s Dues in part<lb/> or in full or exercise other rights under the Loan<lb/> Documents including sell, transfer, dispose off,<lb/> encumber and/or deal with the Security, or any<lb/> part thereof, in any manner if the Security<lb/> Cover is not maintained. The Lender shall be<lb/> entitled to get the valuation of the Said<lb/> Immovable Properties done (at the cost of the<lb/> Borrower(s) and/or the Co-Borrower(s)) by any<lb/> valuer(s) as and when the Lender reasonably<lb/> deems fit.<lb/></p>

			<p>In addition to the aforesaid Security Cover, the<lb/> Borrower(s) and/or the Co-Borrower(s) shall,<lb/> and/or shall cause the Pledgor(s) to, maintain<lb/> the margin of at least 108.33% (one hundred<lb/> eight point three three percent) of the Group<lb/> Borrower&apos;s Dues at all times during the validity<lb/> of the Loan Documents. For this purpose, only<lb/> the value of the Pledged/Charged Shares (which<lb/> are listed on stock exchanges in India) pledged<lb/> in favour of the Lender to secure the Group<lb/> Borrower&apos;s Dues shall be taken into<lb/> consideration, at all times during the validity of<lb/> the Loan Documents (&quot;Security Cover-<lb/>Securities&quot;).<lb/> If at any time during the-<lb/>continuance of this Agreement, the Lender is of<lb/> the opinion that the value of the<lb/> Pledged/Charged Shares (which are listed on<lb/> stock exchanges in India) provided as Security<lb/> has become inadequate to cover the margin of<lb/> at least 108.33% (one hundred eight point three<lb/> three percent) of the Group Borrower&apos;s Dues,<lb/> then whether or not the Lender advising the<lb/> Borrower(s) and/or Co-Borrower(s)/Pledgor(s)<lb/> to that effect, the Borrower(s) and/or the Co-<lb/>Borrower(s) shall forthwith provide and furnish<lb/> (within 2 working days) and/or the Borrower(s)<lb/> and/or the Co-Borrower(s) shall cause the<lb/> Pledgor(s) to forthwith (within 2 working days)<lb/> provide and furnish to the satisfaction of the<lb/> Lender, either cash or such number of<lb/> additional listed shares as Security and/or other<lb/> Security to the satisfaction of the Lender to<lb/> make good the shortfall in the said margin so as<lb/> to keep the said margin all times at or above<lb/> 108.33% (one hundred eight point three three<lb/> percent) of the Group Borrower&apos;s Dues.<lb/> Further, the Lender shall have the absolute right<lb/> to recall the Loan in part or in full or exercise<lb/> other rights under the Loan Documents<lb/> including sell, transfer, dispose off, encumbered<lb/> and/or deal with the Pledged/Charged Shares, or<lb/> any part thereof, in any manner if the value of<lb/> the (listed) Pledged/Charged Shares falls to<lb/> 97.50% (ninety seven point five zero percent)<lb/> of the Group Borrower&apos;s Dues and if the<lb/> Borrower(s) and/or the Co-Borrower(s) failed to<lb/> forthwith provide and furnish within 2 working<lb/> days additional listed shares as Security to the<lb/> satisfaction of the Lender and the Borrower(s)<lb/> and/or the Co-Borrower(s)/Pledgor(s) shall not<lb/> contest the same. The value of the (listed)<lb/> Pledged/Charged Shares shall be the average<lb/> closing price of last 30 days/trading Sessions, of<lb/> the (listed) Pledged/Charged Shares prevailing<lb/> on the Bombay Stock Exchange Limited and/or<lb/> National<lb/> Stock<lb/> Exchange<lb/> of<lb/> India.<lb/> Notwithstanding anything to the contrary, if the<lb/> value of the (listed) Pledged/Charged Shares of<lb/> any company falls any time during the Tenure<lb/> of the Loan more than 10% (ten percent) of the<lb/> closing price on the previous day on Bombay<lb/> Stock Exchange Limited and/or National Stock<lb/> Exchange of India, then the Borrower(s) and/or<lb/> the Co-Borrower(s) shall make good the<lb/> shortfall in the security cover by forthwith<lb/> paying cash to the Lender.&quot;<lb/> (Emphasis supplied)<lb/></p>

			<p>(iv) Clause 2.4 deals with the circumstances in which the<lb/> pledged as security could be released, and read as under:<lb/></p>

			<p>&quot;2.4 Release of Security<lb/> On the unconditional and irrevocable<lb/> repayment/payment of the entire Borrower&apos;s<lb/> Dues, costs and expenses, if any, incurred by<lb/> the Lender and fulfilment of all the obligations<lb/> of the Obligor(s) under the Loan Documents,<lb/> the Lender shall forthwith release the Security<lb/> created by the Obligor(s) in favour of the<lb/> Lender by executing, at the costs of the<lb/> Obligor(s) (including costs relating to stamp<lb/> duty and registration charges, if any) all such<lb/> documents as may be required for the said<lb/> purpose.<lb/> During the continuance of this Agreement,<lb/> subject to there being no breach of the Loan<lb/> Documents by the Obligor(s) and/or no event of<lb/> Default has occurred under the Loan<lb/> Documents,<lb/></p>

			<p>(a)<lb/> If, the value of the (listed)<lb/> Pledged/Charged Shares provided as<lb/> Security is 108.33% (one hundred eight<lb/> point three three percent) of the Group<lb/> Borrower&apos;s Dues, then, the Lender shall<lb/> at the request of the Borrower(s) and/or<lb/> the Co-Borrower(s) release such number<lb/> of (listed) Pledged/Charged Shares so as<lb/> to ensure that the value of the remaining<lb/> (listed)<lb/> Pledged/Charged<lb/> Shares<lb/> provided as Security is at least 108.33%<lb/> (one hundred eight point three three<lb/> percent) of the Group Borrower&apos;s Dues.<lb/> The<lb/> value<lb/> of<lb/> the<lb/> (listed)<lb/> Pledged/Charged Shares shall be the<lb/> average closing price of last 30<lb/> days/trading Sessions, of the (listed)<lb/> Pledged/Charged Shares prevailing on<lb/> the Bombay Stock Exchange Limited<lb/> and/or National Stock Exchange of<lb/> India; and/or<lb/></p>

			<p>(b)<lb/> On receipt of request for NOC for<lb/> sale for unit(s) (forming part of the<lb/> Properties mentioned in the Schedule III<lb/> hereunder) from the Borrower(s), the<lb/> Lender will issue such NOC provided if<lb/> the entire sale consideration has already<lb/> been<lb/> received<lb/> from<lb/> the<lb/> buyer(s)/allottee(s) of such unit(s) and<lb/> such sale consideration has been<lb/> deposited in the escrow account(s)<lb/> maintained as per the provisions of the<lb/> Loan Documents.&quot;<lb/></p>

			<p>(v) Clause 3 dealt with &quot;Repayment/Payment&quot; of the loan.<lb/> The relevant part, thereof, may be reproduced thus:<lb/></p>

			<p>&quot;3.<lb/> REPAYMENT/PAYMENT<lb/></p>

			<p>3.1.1 The Borrower(s) and/or the Co-Borrower(s)<lb/> shall repay/pay the entire Loan and interest thereon to<lb/> the Lender in such manner as agreed/specified by the<lb/> Lender from time to time and/or as per the<lb/> Payment/Repayment Schedule. Subject to Clause<lb/> 3.1.2, the Borrower(s) and/or the Co-Borrower(s)<lb/> agree to pay to the Lender interest on the Loan or such<lb/> part thereof as may be outstanding from time to time at<lb/> such Interest Rate(s) as mentioned in Schedule I of this<lb/> Agreement. Unless otherwise specified by the Lender<lb/> from time to time,<lb/></p>

			<p>(a)<lb/> interest shall be payable every month by<lb/> the Borrower(s) and/or the Co-Borrower(s) on<lb/> the Due Date(s) mentioned in the<lb/> Payment/Repayment Schedule;<lb/></p>

			<p>(b)<lb/> interest shall accrue from the Date of<lb/> Disbursement;<lb/></p>

			<p>(c)<lb/> interest shall be computed on the basis of<lb/> a year of 360 days and the actual number of<lb/> days elapsed;<lb/></p>

			<p>(d)<lb/> interest shall be compounded on monthly<lb/> rests or on such periodic rests as may be<lb/> decided by the Lender from time to time; and<lb/></p>

			<p>(e)<lb/> in case of any payment default on the<lb/> Due Date(s) by the Obligor(s) under the Loan<lb/> Documents, interest shall be compounded (at<lb/> the prevailing Interest Rate(s)) every month on<lb/> the overdue amount and the Obligor(s) shall be<lb/> liable to pay such compound interest to the<lb/> Lender.<lb/></p>

			<p>*****<lb/></p>

			<p>3.1.4 The Obligor(s) shall repay/pay the Borrower&apos;s<lb/> Dues and other monies payable under the Loan<lb/> Documents through the following modes as agreed<lb/> between the Borrower(s) and/or the Co-Borrower(s)<lb/> and the Lender -post-dated cheques/electronic<lb/> clearing system/through an escrow account(s)<lb/> maintained under the Loan Documents/RTGS/any<lb/> other method. The Lender may, in its sole discretion,<lb/> specify the mode(s) of payment/repayment under the<lb/> Loan Documents from time to time and the same shall<lb/> be binding on the Obligor(s). ….<lb/> *****<lb/></p>

			<p>3.1.5 The Borrower(s) and/or the Co-Borrower(s)<lb/> shall, on the execution of this Agreement, issue and<lb/> hand over to the Lender specified number of post-<lb/>dated/undated cheques as mentioned in Schedule I<lb/> hereunder for repayment/payment of the Loan and<lb/> interest. ….<lb/> (Emphasis Supplied)<lb/></p>

			<p>(vi) Clause 4, which dealt with &quot;Default Interest&quot;, rendered<lb/> the Borrower/Co-Borrower(s) liable to pay default interest, at<lb/> the rates specified in Schedule I to the Loan Agreement, if<lb/></p>

			<p>(a) the Obligor/Obligors failed to comply with their<lb/> obligations, under the Loan Documents, by the given<lb/> Due Date therefor, or<lb/></p>

			<p>(b) an Event of Default occurred.<lb/></p>

			<p>(vii) Clause 4A dealt with the requirement -or, rather, the<lb/> absence thereof -of any notice for payment, and read as under:<lb/></p>

			<p>&quot;No notice, reminder or intimation shall be given to<lb/> the Obligor(s) regarding its/their obligation to<lb/> repay/pay the Borrower&apos;s Dues and it shall be entirely<lb/> the Obligor(s)&apos; responsibility to ensure prompt and<lb/> regular payment of such amounts payable by the<lb/> Obligor(s) to the Lender when due and in the manner<lb/> provided in the Loan Documents.&quot;<lb/> (Emphasis supplied)<lb/></p>

			<p>(viii) Clause 5 provided for &quot;prepayment&quot;, and for &quot;foreclosure<lb/> and cancellation&quot;. It provided, inter alia, thus:<lb/></p>

			<p>&quot;If due to any law or any other reason(s), the Lender<lb/> shall be entitled to require the Borrower(s) and/or the<lb/> Co-Borrower(s) to repay/pay the Borrower&apos;s Dues (or<lb/> any part thereof) immediately or in shorter period and<lb/> in one lumpsump or such suitable instalment/s as may<lb/> be specified by the Lender notwithstanding the Tenure<lb/> of the Loan. There Borrower(s) and/or the Co-<lb/>Borrower(s) undertake to pay/repay the Borrower&apos;s<lb/> Dues (or any part thereof) on the date(s) as may be<lb/> specified in the notice issued by the Lender to the<lb/> Borrower(s) and/or the Co-Borrower(s) under this<lb/> clause. ….&quot;<lb/> (Emphasis supplied)<lb/></p>

			<p>(ix) Clause 9.2 required, inter alia, the Borrower / Borrowers<lb/> /Co-Borrowers to cause the Obligor/Obligors, to execute, in<lb/> favour of the Lender, any further/additional/Fresh deeds, or<lb/> documents, &quot;in respect of the Loan/Borrower&apos;s Dues/Security&quot;.<lb/></p>

			<p>(x) Clause 12 delineated, in its various sub-clauses, the<lb/> &quot;Events of Default&quot;, for the purposes of the Loan Agreement.<lb/> These were<lb/> (i)<lb/> non-payment of &quot;the Borrower&apos;s Dues (or part<lb/> thereof) and/or any amount payable pursuant to a Loan<lb/> Document&quot;, by the due date/dates, by the borrower(s)/co-<lb/>borrower(s),<lb/> (ii) utilisation of the loan for any unlawful purpose,<lb/></p>

			<p>(iii) breach, or default, of any provision/provisions of<lb/> the Loan Documents by the Obligor(s), not attributable to<lb/> any fault of the Lender, unless remedied within 3 days,<lb/></p>

			<p>(iv) misrepresentation,<lb/></p>

			<p>(v) the performance, of any obligations under the Loan<lb/> Documents, by the Obligor(s) becoming unlawful,<lb/> (vi) repudiation, by the Obligor(s), of the Loan<lb/> Document, or intention to do so,<lb/></p>

			<p>(vii) Governmental intervention, as a result of which<lb/></p>

			<p>(a) the management of the Obligor(s) was<lb/> wholly or partly displaced, or<lb/></p>

			<p>(b) the authority, of the Obligor(s), in the<lb/> conduct of its business, was wholly or partially<lb/> curtailed, or<lb/> (c) a majority of the issued shares of the<lb/> Obligor(s), or any part of the revenue or assets of<lb/> the Obligor(s) was seized or compulsorily<lb/> acquired, or<lb/></p>

			<p>(d) any attachment, distress, execution or other<lb/> process against the Obligor(s), or its properties,<lb/> was enforced or levied upon,<lb/></p>

			<p>(viii) any event, or circumstance, having a Material<lb/> Adverse Effect, or adversely affecting the ability of the<lb/> Obligor(s) to perform its obligations under the Loan<lb/> Documents, or to pay/repay the Borrower&apos;s Dues or any<lb/> part thereof,<lb/></p>

			<p>(ix) deterioration or impairment of the Security, in<lb/> whole or in part, or decline or depreciation in the value<lb/> thereof, resulting in the Security becoming unsatisfactory<lb/> in character or value, and the Borrower(s)/Co-<lb/>Borrower(s) failed to provide additional security,<lb/></p>

			<p>(x) failure in business, bankruptcy, general assignment<lb/> for the benefit of creditors, or suspension of payment, by<lb/> the Obligor(s),<lb/> (xi) inability, of the Obligor(s), to pay debts, or<lb/> appointment of any liquidator or receiver in respect of<lb/> any property or a state of the Obligor(s),<lb/> (xii) amalgamation, merger, arrangement, demerger or<lb/> reconstruction of any of the Obligor(s), without prior<lb/> approval of the Lender,<lb/></p>

			<p>(xiii) cessation of the business of the Obligor(s),<lb/> (xiv) the income/revenue/remuneration of the Obligor(s)<lb/> becoming, or becoming likely to be, inadequate,<lb/> (xv) death, mental unsoundness or imprisonment of any<lb/> of the Obligor(s),<lb/> (xvi) continuous losses in the business of the Obligor(s),<lb/> (xvii) disposal of, or creation of a charge on, the<lb/> Security, by the Obligor(s), without prior consent of the<lb/> lender,<lb/></p>

			<p>(xviii) threat to the Security given by the Obligor(s), or<lb/> (xix) any substantial change in the Constitution, or as<lb/> shareholding pattern/profit sharing of the Obligor(s),<lb/> without prior written consent of the Lender.<lb/></p>

			<p>(xi) The consequence of the happening of an &quot;Event of<lb/> Default&quot; was visualised by Clauses 12.2 and 12.3, which read<lb/> thus:<lb/></p>

			<p>&quot;12.2 Consequence of an Event of Default<lb/> On and at any time after the of occurrence of an<lb/> Event of Default, Lender may, with or without<lb/> any notice to any of the Obligor(s) and with or<lb/> without the intervention of the court/arbitrator,<lb/></p>

			<p>(i)<lb/> cancel/recall the Loan whereupon<lb/> the Borrower&apos;s Dues shall become<lb/> immediately repayable/payable by the<lb/> Obligor(s); and/or<lb/></p>

			<p>(ii)<lb/> initiate/exercise any or all of its<lb/> rights, actions, remedies and powers<lb/> under the Loan Documents and/or<lb/> applicable laws; and/or<lb/></p>

			<p>(iii) enforce, allot, sell, invoke,<lb/> deliver, deal with, take possession,<lb/> convey, transfer, assign, lease, sub-<lb/>lease, encumber and/or dispose off in<lb/> any manner (including by private treaty<lb/> and/or auction), on such terms and<lb/> conditions including the sale/transfer<lb/> price of the Security or any part/unit<lb/> thereof as deemed fit by the Lender,<lb/> any/all/part of the Security including the<lb/> guarantees<lb/> and/or<lb/> the<lb/> demand<lb/> promissory notes, and/or do such other<lb/> things in relation to and/or with respect<lb/> to the Security (or any part thereof)<lb/> which may be permitted under law.<lb/></p>

			<p>If the net sum realised through the<lb/> enforcement/sale/transfer of Security is<lb/> insufficient to cover the Borrower&apos;s Dues, then<lb/> without prejudice to the other rights and<lb/> remedies of the Lender under the Loan<lb/> Documents and/or in law, the Obligor(s)<lb/> agree(s) and undertake(s) to pay to the Lender<lb/> forthwith at the Lender&apos;s demand such amount<lb/> as will make up the shortfall. The decision<lb/> made by the Lender with respect to any matter<lb/> under the Loan Documents shall be final and<lb/> binding on the Obligor(s).<lb/></p>

			<p>12.3 If any Event of Default or any event which,<lb/> after the notice or lapse of time or both would<lb/> constitute an Event of Default shall have happened, the<lb/> Borrower(s) and/or the Co-Borrower(s) shall forthwith<lb/> give the Lender notice thereof in writing specifying<lb/> such Event of Default, or such event. The Borrower(s)<lb/> and/or the Co-Borrower(s) shall also promptly inform<lb/> the Lender if and when any statutory notice of<lb/> winding-up under the provisions of the applicable laws<lb/> or of any suit or legal process intended to be<lb/> filed/initiated against the Obligor(s) is received by the<lb/> Obligor(s). On the question whether any of the above<lb/> events/circumstances has occurred/happened, the<lb/> decision of the Lender shall be final, conclusive and<lb/> binding on the Borrower(s) and/or the Co-Borrower(s).<lb/> However, the Lender will act in a reasonable manner<lb/> while exercising any such discretion given to the<lb/> Lender under this Agreement. The rights, powers and<lb/> remedies given to the Lender by this Agreement shall<lb/> be in addition to all rights, powers and remedies given<lb/> to the Lender by virtue of any other security, statute or<lb/> the rule of law. The Lender may exercise a lender&apos;s<lb/> lien or right of set-off with respect to any obligation of<lb/> the Borrower(s) and/or Co-Borrower(s) to the Lender<lb/> and shall have a lien on all property or securities of the<lb/> Borrower(s) and/or the Co-Borrower(s) in the Lender&apos;s<lb/> possession or custody whether for safe keeping or<lb/> otherwise.<lb/> Without prejudice to what is stated<lb/> hereinabove, the Parties hereby expressly agree and<lb/> confirm that in the event of the Borrower(s) and/or the<lb/> Co-Borrower(s) failing to pay the Borrower&apos;s Dues or<lb/> on happening of an event of Default, in addition to any<lb/> General or Specific Lien to which the Lender may be<lb/> entitled by law, the Lender shall, without prejudice to<lb/> any of its specific rights under the Loan Documents,<lb/> be at liberty to apply any other money or amounts<lb/> standing to the credit of the Borrower(s) and/or the Co-<lb/>Borrower(s) in any account with the Lender in order<lb/> towards repayment of the Borrower&apos;s Dues, without<lb/> any notice to the Borrower(s) and/or the Co-<lb/>Borrower(s). ….&quot;<lb/> (Emphasis supplied)<lb/></p>

			<p>(xii) Clause 15 of the Loan Agreement -which constitutes, in<lb/> a way, the fulcrum of Mr. Sethi&apos;s submissions -provided for<lb/> &quot;Cross Liability&quot;, and read as under:<lb/></p>

			<p>&quot;15. CROSS LIABILITY<lb/> Notwithstanding anything to the contrary<lb/> contained in any agreement(s), the Obligor(s)<lb/> expressly accept(s) and agree(s) that if a<lb/> breach/default/an event of default occurs under<lb/> any agreement(s) (including the Loan<lb/> Documents) between (a) the Obligor(s) and/or<lb/> any group entity/entities/associate company of<lb/> the Obligor(s) and (b) the Lender and/or any of<lb/> the INDIABULLS Companies, then such a<lb/> breach/default/event of default under such<lb/> agreement(s) shall also be an Event of Default<lb/> under the Loan Documents and vice versa and<lb/> then in such events the Lender and/or any of the<lb/> INDIABULLS Companies shall, without<lb/> prejudice to any of its/their specific rights under<lb/> each of the agreements, be absolutely entitled to<lb/> exercise or any of its/their rights (including<lb/> Loan recall) under any of such agreements<lb/> (including the Loan Documents) at the sole<lb/> discretion of the Lender and/or the<lb/> INDIABULLS Companies.<lb/> The term<lb/> &apos;INDIABULLS Companies&apos; shall mean and<lb/> include the Lender, the promoter(s) of the<lb/> Lender and/or any other associate/group<lb/> companies/entities of the Lender, present or<lb/> future.&quot;<lb/></p>

			<p>6.<lb/> Simultaneously, on 27 th September, 2015 a Pledge/Charge<lb/> Agreement (hereinafter referred to as &quot;the Pledge Agreement&quot;) was<lb/> executed between Guild Builders and the petitioner, as the pledgors,<lb/> and IHFL, as the lender. The Pledge Agreement specifically recited<lb/> that, the pledgors had agreed to create a first-ranking and exclusive<lb/> Pledge, on the Pledged Shares, in favour of IHFL, for the loans<lb/> mentioned in Schedule IB to the Pledge Agreement, and advanced<lb/> under the Loan Agreement specified in the said Schedule. Schedule<lb/> IB to the Pledge Agreement referred only to three Loan Agreements,<lb/> being the Loan Agreements dated 29 th September, 2015 supra,<lb/> whereby loans of ₹ 65 crores, ₹ 65 crores and ₹ 20 crores were<lb/> advanced, by IHFL to Omaxe Forest Spa.<lb/></p>

			<p>7.<lb/> &quot;Loan Documents&quot;, for the purposes of the Pledge Agreement,<lb/> were defined, in sub-clause b) of Clause 1.1 of the Pledge Agreement,<lb/> thus:<lb/></p>

			<p>&quot; &quot;Loan Documents&quot;means (a) the Loan Agreement(s)<lb/> and/or (b) all other agreement(s), application(s), form(s),<lb/> undertaking(s),<lb/> document(s),<lb/> letter(s),<lb/> deed(s),<lb/> memorandum(s), declaration(s) and/or power of attorney(s)<lb/> evidencing, securing, governing or otherwise pertaining /<lb/> relating to the Loan(s) / Secured Obligations /security<lb/> /guarantee and includes any amendatory, modificatory the or<lb/> supplemental agreement thereto.&quot;<lb/></p>

			<p>&quot;Loan&quot; was, in turn, defined in sub-clause d), as meaning &quot;the loan(s)<lb/> of the total principal amount(s) as mentioned in Schedule IB<lb/> hereunder disbursed or to be disbursed under the Loan Agreement(s)<lb/> and the other related Loan Documents.&quot; A conjoint reading of sub-<lb/>clauses b) and d) of Clause 1.1 of the Pledge Agreement, and<lb/> Schedule IB thereto, make it apparent that the &quot;Loan Documents&quot;, for<lb/> the purposes of the Pledge Agreement, were the three Loan<lb/> Agreements dated 29 th September, 2015, whereunder loans of ₹ 65<lb/> crores, ₹ 65 crores and ₹ 20 crores had been extended by IHFL to<lb/> Omaxe Forest Spa, and none else.<lb/></p>

			<p>8.<lb/> Against the said loans, Schedule II to the Pledge Agreement<lb/> (read with the definition of &quot;Pledged/Charged Shares&quot;, in sub-clause<lb/> f) of Clause 1.1 of the Pledge Agreement) detailed the shares of Guild<lb/> Builders in Omaxe Ltd., and the shares of the petitioner in Omaxe<lb/> Ltd., as having been pledged. Clause 2 of the Pledge Agreement,<lb/> titled &quot;Pledge/Charge of Pledged/Charged Shares&quot;, contained the<lb/> following three sub-clauses:<lb/></p>

			<p>&quot;2.1 Pledge and Charge<lb/> This Agreement is for the benefit of the Lender and in<lb/> consideration of the Lender having agreed to lend and<lb/> advance/lent and advanced the Loan(s) to the<lb/> Borrower(s) and/or the Co-Borrower(s) and in order to<lb/> secure the Secured Obligations and the fulfilment of<lb/> all the obligations of the Obligor(s) under the Loan<lb/> Documents, the Pledgor(s): (i) hereby pledges/charges,<lb/> as security on a first-ranking charge/pledge basis<lb/> exclusively in favour of the Lender, the<lb/> Pledged/Charged<lb/> Shares<lb/> including<lb/> the<lb/> shares/securities as more particularly described in<lb/> Schedule II hereunder in respect thereof accompanied<lb/> by the Transfer Forms duly executed in blank, powers<lb/> of attorney, and/or other relevant instruments and/or<lb/> documents acceptable to the Lender; and (ii) hereby<lb/> assigns, Hypothecates, pledges and charges to the<lb/> Lender, as a continuing security interest, all of such<lb/> Pledgor(s) right, title, interest, benefits, claims and<lb/> demands whatsoever of such Pledgor(s) in, too, under<lb/> order in respect of the Collateral and any indemnity,<lb/> warranty or guarantee, payable by reason of laws to or<lb/> otherwise with respect to any of the pledged/charged<lb/> Shares to the Lender upon the terms and conditions set<lb/> forth in this Agreement.<lb/></p>

			<p>2.1.1 The Pledgor(s) is/are pledging/charging the<lb/> Pledged/Charged Shares in consideration of the<lb/> Lender having agreed to lend and advanced/lent and<lb/> advanced the Loan(s) to the Borrower(s) and/or the<lb/> Co-Borrower(s) with the understanding that upon<lb/> occurrence of an Event of Default under any of the<lb/> Loan Documents, the Pledged/Charged Shares (or any<lb/> part thereof) may be sold, transferred, assigned,<lb/> encumbered, disposed of, and/or dealt with in any<lb/> manner whatsoever and on such terms and conditions<lb/> (including the sale price) as deemed fit by the Lender.<lb/></p>

			<p>2.1.2 On the above representation of the Pledgor(s) and the<lb/> Pledgor(s) agreeing that upon the occurrence of an<lb/> Event of Default under any of the Loan Documents,<lb/> the Pledged/Charged Shares (or any part thereof) may<lb/> be sold, transferred, assigned, encumbered, disposed<lb/> off and/or dealt with, in any manner whatsoever and<lb/> on such terms and conditions (including the sale price)<lb/> as deemed fit by the Lender from time to time, the<lb/> Lender has agreed to lend and advance/lent and<lb/> advanced the Loan(s) to the Borrower(s) and/or the<lb/> Co-Borrower(s).&quot;<lb/> (Emphasis supplied)<lb/></p>

			<p>9.<lb/> Be it noted, even at this juncture, that it is nobody&apos;s case that<lb/> the shares of the petitioner, in Omaxe Ltd.., constituted subject matter<lb/> of any other Pledge Agreement, in existence and in force, or<lb/> stood/stands pledged against any other loan, yet to be liquidated.<lb/></p>

			<p>10. Reverting to the facts of the case, the petitioner claimed to have<lb/> understood that, as on 31 st March, 2020, the aforesaid loan amounts of<lb/> ₹ 65 crores, ₹ 65 crores and ₹ 20 crores, advanced by IHFL to Omaxe<lb/> Forest Spa, under the Loan Agreement dated 29 th September, 2015,<lb/> had been entirely recovered. The petitioner, thereby, it is claimed,<lb/> stood entitled to have its shares, in Omaxe Ltd., pledged with IHFL,<lb/> against the said loans, de-pledged and released.<lb/></p>

			<p>11. It is asserted, in the petition, that several representations, by the<lb/> petitioner to IHFL, for release of the aforesaid pledged shares, met<lb/> with no response. In the process, the value of the pledged shares, in<lb/> the market, also depleted significantly. Between September, 2018 and<lb/> January, 2020, the petitioner asserts that the price of the pledged<lb/> shares had declined from ₹ 218/-to ₹ 155.40, per share. The<lb/> reticence exhibited, by IHFL, in releasing the pledged shares, held by<lb/> the petitioner in Omaxe Ltd. was, therefore, the petitioner asserts,<lb/> subjecting it to recurrent and severe financial prejudice.<lb/></p>

			<p>12. Though the disputes that have thus arisen, between the<lb/> petitioner and IHFL, legitimately justifies the invocation of the<lb/> arbitration clause, in the Loan Agreements dated 29 th September, 2015<lb/> supra, the petitioner has invoked Section 9 of the Arbitration and<lb/> Conciliation Act, 1996 (hereinafter referred to as &quot;the 1996 Act&quot;), by<lb/> means of the present petition, on the ground that urgent pre-arbitration<lb/> interim reliefs, as sought in the petition, are necessary, in view of the<lb/> steady depletion of the value of the shares, held by the petitioner in<lb/> Omaxe Ltd., and the continuous financial prejudice being suffered by<lb/> the petitioner. The prayer clause, in the present petition, reads thus:<lb/></p>

			<p>&quot;In light of above mentioned facts and circumstances, it is<lb/> most humbly prayed before this Hon&apos;ble Court that this<lb/> Hon&apos;ble Court be pleased to:<lb/></p>

			<p>a)<lb/> Direct the Respondent to provide a true, fair and<lb/> full disclosure of all its transactions in relation to the<lb/> Loan Agreements dated 29.09.2015 referred to in para<lb/> 34.1 above, including an updated statement of accounts<lb/> till date, to the petitioner;<lb/></p>

			<p>b)<lb/> Pass an appropriate direction directing the<lb/> Respondent to issue No-Objection certificate to the<lb/> Petitioner in case the loans stand paid or on receipt of<lb/> payment from the Petitioner;<lb/></p>

			<p>c)<lb/> Pass an appropriate direction restraining the<lb/> Respondent taking any coercive steps in relation to the<lb/> pledged shares and personal guarantee of the Petitioner<lb/> till adjudication of present petition;<lb/></p>

			<p>d)<lb/> Pass an appropriate direction restraining the<lb/> respondent from using the securities and personal<lb/> guarantee of the petitioner and against any other<lb/> outstanding loan of Omaxe Limited or its subsidiaries;<lb/></p>

			<p>e)<lb/> Pass an appropriate direction directing the<lb/> Respondent to release to the Petitioner the shares of<lb/> Omaxe Limited owned by the Petitioner and also<lb/> absolve the personal guarantee extended by the<lb/> Petitioner;<lb/></p>

			<p>f)<lb/> Pass any other order(s), direction(s) or relief(s)<lb/> in favour of the Petitioner and against the Respondent<lb/> as may be deemed fit and proper by this Hon&apos;bIe Court<lb/> in the facts and circumstances of the present case and<lb/> In the interest of justice.&quot;<lb/></p>

			<p>13. Though the respondent, IHFL, has filed a reply, on merits, to<lb/> the petitioner, Mr. Sunil Dalal, learned counsel appearing for IHFL<lb/> submitted, on the very first date of hearing, i.e. 18 th June, 2020, that<lb/> the principal amounts of loan, of ₹ 65 crores, ₹ 65 crores and ₹ 20<lb/> crores, as advanced by IHFL to Omaxe Forest Spa, stood liquidated<lb/> and that, therefore, IHFL was willing to release the pledged shares,<lb/> held by the petitioner in Omaxe Ltd.. Thereafter, on 30 th June, 2020,<lb/> Mr. Dalal sought for some further time, in order to ascertain whether<lb/> the shares of the petitioner were pledged against any other loan,<lb/> advanced by IHFL. Today, Mr. Dalal has clarified that the shares<lb/> have not been pledged against any other loan and that, therefore,<lb/> IHFL is willing to release the said shares to the petitioner. This aspect<lb/> has also been placed, in writing, by IHFL, on affidavit, to which I<lb/> would be alluding at a somewhat later stage of this judgement.<lb/></p>

			<p>14. Vehement opposition, to the release of the pledged shares of the<lb/> petitioner, in Omaxe Ltd., surfaced, however, from Guild Builders<lb/> which, for the said purpose, preferred I.A. 4942/2020 and I.A.<lb/> 4943/2020, seeking impleadment, as a respondent, in the petition, and<lb/> issuance of interim directions, to IHFL, not to release the pledged<lb/> shares, despite the assurance, by Mr. Sunil Dalal, on 18 th June, 2020.<lb/> Additionally, I.A. 4943/2020 also seeks an order of restraint, against<lb/> the petitioner, from alienating the said shares, even if they had been<lb/> released by IHFL.<lb/></p>

			<p>15. The petitioner has filed a response, to the aforesaid I.A.<lb/> 4942/2020 and I.A. 4943/2020, filed by Guild Builders. It is asserted,<lb/> by the petitioner, in the said responses, that Guild Builders had no<lb/> locus to be impleaded in the present proceedings, and that the prayer,<lb/> of Guild Builders, to restrain IHFL from releasing the pledged shares,<lb/> held by the petitioner in Omaxe Ltd., even after liquidation of the loan<lb/> advanced by IHFL to Omaxe Forest Spa, was completely devoid of<lb/> merit.<lb/></p>

			<p>16. Inasmuch as IHFL had expressed its consent, to the release of<lb/> the pledged shares to the petitioner, arguments, before me, were<lb/> essentially on the aforesaid two applications of Guild Builders, i.e.<lb/> I.A. 4942/2020 and I.A. 4943/2020.<lb/></p>

			<p>17. I proceed, therefore, to advert to the rival contentions of Guild<lb/> Builders, represented by Mr. Sandeep Sethi, learned senior Counsel,<lb/> and the petitioner, represented by Mr. Rajshekhar Rao, on I.A.<lb/> 4942/2020 and I.A. 4943/2020.<lb/></p>

			<p>Rival Submissions<lb/> 18. The submissions of Mr. Sandeep Sethi, appearing for Guild<lb/> Builders, may be enumerated, for the sake of convenience, thus:<lb/></p>

			<p>(i)<lb/> The liquidation of the loan, advanced by IHFL to Omaxe<lb/> Ltd., did not, ipso facto, or ipso jure, entitle the petitioner to<lb/> release of the shares, held by it in Omaxe Ltd. and pledged with<lb/> IHFL, as the shares had been pledged, not merely to secure the<lb/> loans of ₹ 65 crores, ₹ 65 crores and ₹ 20 crores, under the<lb/> three Loan Agreements dated 25 th September, 2015, but also<lb/> against other loans, advanced to the companies of the Omaxe<lb/> group, by IHFL or its associated companies.<lb/></p>

			<p>(ii) The shares, forming subject matter of the petition, had<lb/> been pledged, by the petitioner, along with shares of Guild<lb/> Builders, held in Omaxe Ltd., which IHFL, in view of loan<lb/> granted, by M/s Indiabulls Financial Services Ltd to Omaxe<lb/> Ltd., of ₹ 200 crores, vide Pledge Agreement dated 9 th August,<lb/> 2011. (This aspect was, however, subsequently clarified, by<lb/> Mr. Rajshekhar Rao, who pointed out that the shares, forming<lb/> subject matter of these proceedings, were earlier pledged with<lb/> Indiabulls Financial Services Ltd., against a loan of ₹ 200<lb/> crores, advanced by Indiabulls Financial Services Limited to<lb/> Omaxe Ltd., against which loan the shares of Guild Builders<lb/> were also pledged. However, the said loan of ₹ 200 crores was,<lb/> subsequently, re-paid, thereafter the said shares were pledged<lb/> against the loans of ₹ 65 crores, ₹ 65 crores and ₹ 20 crores,<lb/> advanced by IHFL to Omaxe Ltd. under the Loan Agreements<lb/> dated 29 th September, 2015. Mr. Sandeep Sethi, too, fairly did<lb/> not press the issue of the earlier pledge, of the shares forming<lb/> subject matter of the present petition, under the Pledge<lb/> Agreement dated 9 th August, 2011, any further.)<lb/></p>

			<p>(iii) Clause 2.3 of the Loan Agreements, dated 29 th<lb/> September, 2015, required the Pledgors -which included the<lb/> petitioner -to maintain a margin of 108.33% of the Group<lb/> Borrower&apos;s dues, at all times during the validity of the Loan<lb/> Documents. &quot;Group Borrower&apos;s Dues&quot;, as defined in Clause<lb/> 1.1, included all amounts, payable to IHFL, as well as its<lb/> group/associate entity/entities, under any Loan Agreement<lb/> between IHFL, or its associate/group entity/entities, and the<lb/> obligors, or their group/associate entity/entities. This was<lb/> subject only to the condition that the security, under the Loan<lb/> Documents, i.e. the Loan Agreements dated 29 th September,<lb/> 2015, was also a security under such other Loan Agreements. It<lb/> was erroneous, therefore, for the petitioner to contend that their<lb/> shares, held by it in Omaxe Ltd. and pledged with IHFL,<lb/> secured only the loans covered by the Loan Agreements dated<lb/> 29 th September, 2015. They also covered &quot;Group Borrower&apos;s<lb/> Dues&quot;, as defined in the Loan Agreements. Clause 2.3 required<lb/> the petitioner, as one of the Pledgors, to maintain a margin of at<lb/> least 108.33% of the Group Borrower&apos;s dues at all times during<lb/> the validity of the Loan Documents.<lb/></p>

			<p>(iv) By virtue of the definition of &quot;Group Borrower&apos;s Dues&quot;,<lb/> as contained in Clause 1.1 of the Loan Agreements dated 29 th<lb/> September, 2015, all amounts payable to IHFL, by associate<lb/> entities of the petitioner, under any Loan Agreement,<lb/> constituted &quot;Group Borrower&apos;s Dues&quot;. Mr. Sethi referred me to<lb/> five Loan Agreements, the loans advanced under which,<lb/> according to him, were also secured by the shares in Omaxe<lb/> Ltd., held by the petitioner and pledged with IHFL. The details<lb/> of these five Loan Agreements, copies of which have been filed<lb/> by Guild Builders, may be provided, in a tabular fashion, thus<lb/> (&quot;Garv&quot; being an abbreviation of &quot;M/s Garv Buildtech Pvt<lb/> Ltd&quot;):<lb/> Date<lb/> of<lb/> Loan<lb/> Agreement<lb/> Lender Borrower Guarantor(s) Pledgor(s)<lb/> 30 th June,<lb/> 2017<lb/> IHFL<lb/> Garv<lb/> (1) Guild<lb/> Builders<lb/> (2) Omaxe Ltd.<lb/></p>

			<p>(3) Rohtas<lb/> Goel<lb/> Guild Builders<lb/> 26 th March,<lb/> 2018<lb/> IHFL<lb/> Garv<lb/> (1) Guild<lb/> Builders<lb/> (2) Omaxe Ltd.<lb/></p>

			<p>(3) Rohtas<lb/> Goel<lb/> Guild Builders<lb/> 25 th Septemb<lb/> er, 2018<lb/> IHFL<lb/> Garv<lb/> (1) Guild<lb/> Builders<lb/> (2) Omaxe Ltd.<lb/></p>

			<p>(3) Rohtas<lb/> Goel<lb/> Guild Builders<lb/> 3 rd<lb/> April,<lb/> 2019<lb/></p>

			<p>Indiabul<lb/> ls<lb/> Commer<lb/> cial<lb/> Credit<lb/> Ltd.<lb/> Omaxe<lb/> Ltd.<lb/></p>

			<p>(1) Guild<lb/> Builders<lb/> (2) Garv<lb/> (3) Omaxe<lb/> Forest Spa<lb/></p>

			<p>(4) Rohtas<lb/> Goel<lb/></p>

			<p>(1) Omaxe Ltd.<lb/></p>

			<p>(2) Rohtas Goel<lb/> 30 th March,<lb/> 2020<lb/> Indiabul<lb/> ls<lb/> Commer<lb/> cial<lb/> Credit<lb/> Ltd.<lb/> Omaxe<lb/> Ltd.<lb/></p>

			<p>(1) Omaxe<lb/> New<lb/> Chandigarh<lb/> Developers<lb/> Pvt Ltd<lb/> For ease of reference, the aforementioned Loan Agreements are<lb/> referred to, hereinafter, as the &quot;tabulated Loan Agreements&quot;.<lb/></p>

			<p>(iv) The pleadings of the petitioner, before the learned NCLT,<lb/> as also the pleadings before this Court in the present petition,<lb/> clearly established that Omaxe Ltd. and Guild Builders were<lb/> associate/group Companies of the petitioner.<lb/></p>

			<p>(v) The only other criterion, satisfaction of which was<lb/> required, in order to justify treatment of the loan amounts,<lb/> extended by IHFL, or by its associate Company M/s Indiabulls<lb/> Commercial Credit Ltd (hereinafter referred to as &quot;IBCC&quot;),<lb/> under the tabulated Loan Agreements, was commonality of<lb/> security. A comparison of the schedules to the said Loan<lb/> Agreements (specifically Schedule III), vis-à-vis Schedule III to<lb/> the Loan Agreements dated 29 th September, 2015, forming<lb/> subject matter of the present proceedings, indicated that the<lb/> same land was pledged as security in all the Loan Agreements.<lb/> Similarly, Guild Builders&apos; shares, which were pledged under<lb/> the Loan Agreements dated 29 th September, 2015, were also<lb/> pledged as security, against the loans advanced by IHFL to<lb/> Garv, under the Loan Agreements tabulated hereinabove. The<lb/> shares in Omaxe Ltd., held by Omaxe Forest Spa, similarly,<lb/> were pledged as security against the loan granted by IBCC to<lb/> Omaxe Ltd., under the Loan Agreements dated 3 rd April, 2019<lb/> and 30 th March, 2020. The physical shares, which were<lb/> pledged under the Loan Agreements dated 29 th September,<lb/> 2015, were also pledged as security against the loans advanced<lb/> by IBCC to Omaxe Ltd., under Loan Agreement dated 3 rd<lb/> April, 2019, and by IHFL to Omaxe Ltd., under Loan<lb/> Agreement dated 30 th April, 2020. Mutual commonality of<lb/> security, both qua landed property as well as shares, was,<lb/> therefore, forthcoming, among the various Loan Agreements.<lb/></p>

			<p>(vi) With the satisfaction of this last criterion, the amounts<lb/> borrowed, by the borrowers under the tabulated Loan<lb/> Agreements, also constituted &quot;Group Borrower&apos;s Dues&quot;, within<lb/> the meaning of the expression as defined in Clause 1.1 of the<lb/> Loan Agreements dated 29 th September, 2015, forming subject<lb/> matter of consideration in the present petition.<lb/></p>

			<p>(vii) This fact, seen in conjunction with Clause 15 of the Loan<lb/> Agreements dated 29 th September, 2015 (which provided for<lb/> &quot;Cross Liability&quot;), rendered the shares, held by the petitioner in<lb/> Omaxe Ltd., also liable to be proceeded against, for satisfaction<lb/> of the debts forming subject matter of the tabulated Loan<lb/> Agreements.<lb/></p>

			<p>(viii) Liquidation of the amounts loaned by IHFL to Omaxe<lb/> Ltd., under the Loan Agreements dated 29 th September, 2015<lb/> did not, therefore, ipso facto entitle the petitioner to claim that<lb/> the shares, held by it in Omaxe Ltd., pledged against the said<lb/> loans, be de-pledged and released to it.<lb/></p>

			<p>(ix) Were the shares of the petitioner, in Omaxe Ltd., pledged<lb/> against the loans extended under the Loan Agreements dated<lb/> 29 th September, 2015, by IHFL to Omaxe Forest Spa, to be<lb/> released to the petitioner, it would result in reduction of the<lb/> security, available under the tabulated Loan Agreements, and,<lb/> consequently, render the pledgors in the said Loan Agreements,<lb/> including Guild Builders, liable to make up the shortfall, by<lb/> furnishing additional securities. In fact, IHFL had already<lb/> written, to Guild Builders, to furnish additional securities,<lb/> thereby establishing the validity of the case set up by Guild<lb/> Builders.<lb/></p>

			<p>19. Mr. Sethi submitted, therefore, that, merely on account of the<lb/> loans, extended by IHFL to Omaxe Forest Spa, under the Loan<lb/> Agreements dated 29 th September, 2015, having been liquidated, the<lb/> petitioner could not stake a claim for release/de-pledge of the shares,<lb/> held by it in Omaxe Ltd., pledged against the said loans. These shares<lb/> could also be proceeded against, for satisfaction of the loans forming<lb/> subject matter of the tabulated Loan Agreements, whereunder loans<lb/> had been extended by IHFL, or its associate Company IBCC, to the<lb/> associated Companies of the petitioner. These loans, therefore,<lb/> constituted &quot;Group Borrower&apos;s Dues&quot;, within the meaning of the<lb/> expression as defined in Clause 1.1 of the Loan Agreements dated 29 th<lb/> September, 2015, and were also liable to be secured by the pledged<lb/> shares forming subject matter of consideration in the present petition.<lb/></p>

			<p>20. Responding to the submissions of Mr. Sethi, Mr. Rajshekhar<lb/> Rao, learned Counsel for the petitioner, submitted that the contention,<lb/> of Guild Builders, that the pledged shares, forming subject matter of<lb/> the present petition, were also to be treated as security against the<lb/> loans advanced by IHFL, or IBCC, under the tabulated Loan<lb/> Agreements, was completely devoid of merit. Mr. Rao pointed out<lb/> that the present proceedings were under Section 9 of the 1996 Act,<lb/> relatable to the Loan Agreements dated 29 th September, 2015, to which<lb/> IHFL and the petitioner, alone, were parties. IHFL had clearly stated<lb/> that the entire amount of loan, advanced under the said Loan<lb/> Agreements stood repaid and had, consequently, undertaken to return<lb/> the pledged shares. Guild Builders had no locus to interfere<lb/> therewith. The pledged shares, forming subject matter of the present<lb/> proceedings, stood pledged only against the loans of ₹ 65 crores, ₹ 65<lb/> crores and ₹ 20 crores, advanced by IHFL to Omaxe Forest Spa, under<lb/> the three Loan Agreements dated 29 th September, 2015, and had not<lb/> been pledged as security under any other Loan Agreement. There was<lb/> nothing, in any of the Loan Agreements tabulated hereinabove,<lb/> whereunder loans had been extended by IHFL, or IBCC, to Garv, or<lb/> to Omaxe Ltd., to indicate that the shares of the petitioner in Omaxe<lb/> Ltd., forming subject matter of the present proceedings, had been<lb/> pledged as security under the said Agreements. In fact, pointed out<lb/> Mr. Rao, all the said Loan Agreements, except for the Loan<lb/> Agreement dated 30 th June, 2017, had been entered into, after the<lb/> petitioner had been removed from the post of Joint Managing Director<lb/> of Omaxe Ltd. The petitioner was not, therefore, either party to the<lb/> said Loan Agreements, or even aware of the execution thereof. Debts,<lb/> aggregating to over ₹ 300 crores had, therefore, been availed, and<lb/> securities pledged thereagainst, after the petitioner had ceased to be<lb/> part of any of the borrower, guarantor or pledgor entities, in any of the<lb/> said Loan Agreements.<lb/></p>

			<p>21. With respect to the &quot;Cross Liability&quot; provision contained in<lb/> Clause 15 of the Loan Agreement dated 29 th September, 2015, Mr.<lb/> Rao submits that no occasion, even to consider invocation of the said<lb/> provision, arose at all, as the provision applied only in the case of<lb/> &quot;default under such agreement(s)&quot;, and, admittedly, there had been no<lb/> such default, under any Loan Agreement. Moreover, Mr. Rao points<lb/> out that the Clause operated &quot;at the sole discretion of the Lender&quot; and<lb/> did not, therefore, ipso facto render the shares, held by the petitioner<lb/> in Omaxe Ltd., liable to be proceeded against, even in the event of<lb/> default under any of the five tabulated Loan Agreements.<lb/></p>

			<p>22. Mr. Rao submits, further, that IHFL had, clearly, in its<lb/> communication dated 5 th September, 2018, to the petitioner, refuted,<lb/> in so many words, the possibility of the shares held by the petitioner<lb/> in Omaxe Ltd., pledged against the loans advanced under the Loan<lb/> Agreements dated 29 th September, 2015, operating as cross-<lb/>collateralized security, against loans advanced under other Loan<lb/> Documents. Further, the said communication clearly stated that the<lb/> pledged shares would not be released to the petitioner till the loans<lb/> availed by the borrowers from IHFL were repaid in full, as per the<lb/> Loan Agreements dated 29 th September, 2015. This position, pointed<lb/> out Mr. Rao, was also apparent from e-mail, dated 16 th June, 2020,<lb/> addressed by IHFL to the petitioner, which undertook to release the<lb/> security, associated with the loans, of ₹ 65 crores, ₹ 65 crores and ₹<lb/> 20 crores, advanced under the Loan Agreements dated 29 th<lb/> September, 2015, between IHFL and Omaxe Forest Spa, on the said<lb/> loans being liquidated. There was no whisper of any averment,<lb/> pointed out Mr. Rao, in any of the communications from IHFL to the<lb/> petitioner, indicating that the petitioner had evergreened its pledge.<lb/> Rather, he submits, Clause 2.4 of the Loan Agreements dated 29 th<lb/> September, 2015, clearly rendered the pledged shares liable to be the<lb/> pledged/released, consequent on the loan amounts being paid up.<lb/></p>

			<p>23. Insofar as the demand, by IHFL on Guild Builders, to furnish<lb/> additional security, was concerned, Mr. Rao submits that there is<lb/> nothing to indicate that the said demand was relatable to the release of<lb/> the shares, held by the petitioner in Omaxe Ltd. and pledged as<lb/> security under the Loan Agreements dated 29 th September, 2015. He<lb/> points out that there was no commonality of security, between the<lb/> Loan Agreements dated 29 th September, 2015, and the tabulated Loan<lb/> Agreements, as the shares of the petitioner, in Omaxe Ltd., had not<lb/> been pledged as security, under any of the tabulated Loan<lb/> Agreements, to which, indeed, the petitioner was a complete stranger.<lb/></p>

			<p>24. Relying on Section 2 (6) of the Companies Act, 2013, Mr. Rao<lb/> submits that Guild Builders, Garv and Omaxe Ltd. could not be<lb/> treated as &quot;associate companies&quot; of the petitioner, as the petitioner did<lb/> not possess the ability to influence the affairs of the said Companies.<lb/> Indeed, submits Mr. Rao, the petitioner being an individual and not a<lb/> Company, the concept of &quot;associated companies&quot; did not come in for<lb/> invocation at all.<lb/></p>

			<p>25. Mr. Rao also relied on the various covenants of the Pledge<lb/> Agreement, dated 29 th September, 2015, which already stands<lb/> reproduced hereinabove. He, inter alia, drew my attention to the<lb/> definition of &quot;loan&quot; and &quot;obligor&quot;, in the said Agreement as well as to<lb/> Clauses 2.1, 2.6 and 3 thereof. He also pointed out that the initial<lb/> covenants, in the said Pledge Agreement, clearly indicated that the<lb/> Pledgors, to the said agreement, had created an exclusive<lb/> pledge/charge on the Pledged/Charged Shares, in favour of IHFL, to<lb/> secure the Secured Obligations in the said Pledge Agreement. These<lb/> shares could not, therefore, be treated as having been pledged against<lb/> the loans advanced under any other agreements. Mr. Rao also drew<lb/> my attention, in this context, to the definition of &quot;Secured<lb/> Obligations&quot;, as contained in sub-clause (g) of Clause 1.1 of the<lb/> Pledge Agreement. He also invited attention to Clause 17 thereof,<lb/> which dealt with the release of the pledged shares.<lb/></p>

			<p>26. As such, submits Mr. Rao, the contention, of Mr. Sethi, that the<lb/> pledged shares, forming subject matter of consideration in the present<lb/> proceedings, also stood pledged against loans advanced under the<lb/> tabulated Loan Agreements, was devoid of merit. Guild Builders,<lb/> therefore, had no locus to interfere or intervene in the present<lb/> proceedings, and the prayer in the petition was necessarily required to<lb/> be allowed, in view of the submission, of Mr. Dalal, that IHFL was<lb/> ready and willing to return the pledged shares.<lb/></p>

			<p>27. I may note, at this stage, and before proceeding to deal with the<lb/> submissions advanced before me, that Mr. Dalal had, towards the<lb/> conclusion of the proceedings, sought to contend that the pledged<lb/> shares, forming subject matter of the present proceedings, could not<lb/> be released to the petitioner, till TDS was paid on the said loan<lb/> amount, or a Certificate, in that regard, was issued to IHFL. On a<lb/> query, being put to him by the Court, as to how the entitlement, of the<lb/> petitioner, to return of the pledged shares, could be made dependent<lb/> on payment of TDS, when TDS was required to be paid, not by the<lb/> petitioner, but by Omaxe Forest Spa, and was to be paid, not to IHFL,<lb/> but to the Income Tax authorities, Mr. Dalal withdrew his objection<lb/> and, on instructions, submitted that his client was willing to release<lb/> the pledged shares. Though Mr. Dalal did not seek to enter any caveat<lb/> to this concession, it is obvious that, even after release of the pledged<lb/> shares, the rights of IHFL, to proceed against Omaxe Forest Spa, on<lb/> the aspect of TDS and furnishing of the TDS Certificates, would<lb/> remain preserved.<lb/> Analysis and conclusion<lb/> 28. Viewed any which way, I am unable to convince myself that<lb/> Guild Builders has any locus to intervene in the present proceedings,<lb/> far less to interdict the release of the shares of the petitioner in Omaxe<lb/> Ltd., pledged with IHFL. The submission of Mr. Sandeep Sethi, that<lb/> the pledged shares, forming subject matter of consideration, in the<lb/> present petition, also constitute security against the loans advanced by<lb/> IHFL or IBCC, under the tabulated Loan Agreements, completely<lb/> fails to impress.<lb/></p>

			<p>29. Neither on the basis of the covenants of the Loan Agreements,<lb/> dated 29 th September, 2015, nor on the basis of the covenants of the<lb/> pledged agreement, dated 29 th September, 2015, nor, for that matter,<lb/> the covenants of the tabulated Loan Agreements on which Mr.<lb/> Sandeep Sethi relies, can it be said that the pledged shares, release of<lb/> which is being sought by the petitioner, were also pledged against the<lb/> loans advanced under the tabulated Loan Agreements.<lb/></p>

			<p>30. A reading of the three Loan Agreements, dated 29 th September,<lb/> 2015, whereunder IHFL had advanced loans of ₹ 65 crores, ₹ 65<lb/> crores, and ₹ 20 crores to Omaxe Ltd., covenant by covenant, make it<lb/> apparent that the Borrower&apos;s Dues, i.e. the dues of Omaxe Forest Spa<lb/> towards IHFL, under the said Loan Agreements, alone, constitutes<lb/> subject matter thereof, and the security, and security cover,<lb/> contemplated thereunder, were intended to secure only the said loans.<lb/> This may be demonstrated thus:<lb/></p>

			<p>(i)<lb/> &quot;Borrowers Dues&quot; was specifically defined, in Clause<lb/> 1.1. as meaning (a) the outstanding principal amount of the<lb/> loan, (b) other amounts payable by the obligors to the lender as<lb/> per<lb/></p>

			<p>(i)<lb/> the Loan Documents and/or,<lb/></p>

			<p>(ii) any other agreements entered into between the<lb/> obligors and the lender.<lb/> It is not in dispute that, presently, there is no other Loan<lb/> Agreement, entered into, between the petitioner and IHFL.<lb/></p>

			<p>(ii) &quot;Loan&quot; was defined as the loan amounts mentioned in<lb/> Schedule I of the Loan Agreement, i.e. under Schedule I of each<lb/> of the three Loan Agreements, dated 29 th September, 2015.<lb/></p>

			<p>(iii) &quot;Loan Agreement&quot; was itself defined, in Clause 1.1, as<lb/> &quot;this agreement&quot;, alongwith the amendments/addenda thereto,<lb/> and other documents made a part of the Loan Agreement by<lb/> reference. The five tabulated Loan Agreements, dated 30 th June,<lb/> 2017, 26 th March, 2018 , 25 th September, 2018, 3 rd April,<lb/> and 30 th March, 2020, have not, even by reference, been made<lb/> part of the &quot;Loan Agreement&quot;.<lb/></p>

			<p>(iv) Clause 2.1 specifically delineated the loans mentioned in<lb/> Schedule-I to the Loan Agreements, as the subject matter<lb/> thereof.<lb/></p>

			<p>(v) Schedule-I, to the three Loan Agreements dated 29 th<lb/> September, 2015, limited the applicability, thereof, to the said<lb/> Loan Agreements, and the loans advanced thereunder, of ₹<lb/> crores, ₹ 65 crores and ₹ 20 crores.<lb/></p>

			<p>(vi) Clause 2.2(d)(ii) specifically stated that the<lb/> pledged/charged shares could be sold, disposed of, or otherwise<lb/> encumbered, at the discretion of the IHFL only on occurrence<lb/> of an event of default under the Loan Documents.<lb/></p>

			<p>(vii) Clause 2.2(d)(iii) required the Borrower to undertake that<lb/> the pledged shares would be kept free from encumbrance till the<lb/> obligation of the Pledgors under the Loan Agreements were<lb/> complied with, including the payments/repayment of the<lb/> Borrowers dues.<lb/></p>

			<p>(viii) Clause 2.2(d)(iv) required the Borrower to cause the<lb/> Pledgors to obtain all consents and permissions required by the<lb/> lenders, to create the security for payment and/or repayment of<lb/> the Borrower&apos;s Dues under the Loan Documents.<lb/></p>

			<p>(ix) Clause 2.2 (d) went on to clarify that the pledged shares<lb/> would not be permitted to be de-pledged/released unless the<lb/> entire Borrower&apos;s Dues had been repaid to the lender.<lb/></p>

			<p>(x) Clause 2.4 -on which Mr. Rajshekhar Rao aptly relies -<lb/>required the lenders to release the security credited, by the<lb/> Pledgors in its favour on payment of the entire Borrowers&apos; dues<lb/> and fulfilment of all obligations of the obligors under the Loan<lb/> Documents. Here, at the cost of repetition, it may be<lb/> emphasised that &quot;Loan Documents&quot; were specifically defined,<lb/> in Clause 1.1, as meaning (a) the three Loan Agreements dated<lb/> 29 th September, 2015, (b) the Security Documents, and (c) all<lb/> other agreements, or documents, relating to the<lb/> Loan/Borrower&apos;s Dues. The five tabulated Loan Agreements<lb/> were not, therefore, &quot;Loan Documents&quot;, within the meaning of<lb/> Clause 1.1.<lb/></p>

			<p>(xi) Clause 3.1.1 required the Borrower to repay the entire<lb/> loan and interest thereon to the lender, in the manner specified<lb/> by the lender, along with interest on the loan or outstanding part<lb/> thereof, if any.<lb/></p>

			<p>(xii) Clause 3.1.4 obliged the obligors to pay the Borrower&apos;s<lb/> Dues and other monies payable under the Loan Documents.<lb/></p>

			<p>(xiii) Clause 3.1.5 required the Borrower to issue and<lb/> handover, to the lender, post-dated cheques for<lb/> repayment/payment of the loan and interest.<lb/></p>

			<p>(xiv) Clause 4A stipulated that no notice, reminder or<lb/> intimation would be given to the obligors regarding their<lb/> obligation to repay/pay the Borrower&apos;s Dues, the responsibility<lb/> whereof was entirely on the obligors.<lb/></p>

			<p>(xv) Clause 5 empowered the lender to require the Borrower<lb/> to repay the Borrower&apos;s Dues immediately or in a short-term,<lb/> and obligated the Borrower to repay the Borrowers dues, as so<lb/> required by the lender.<lb/></p>

			<p>(xvi) For the aforesaid purpose, Clause 9.2 required the<lb/> Borrower to cause the obliger to execute, in favour of the<lb/> lender, any additional deeds or documents, in respect of the<lb/> loan, the security or the Borrowers Dues.<lb/></p>

			<p>(xvii) Among the events of default, envisaged by Clause 12 of<lb/> the Loan Agreement, were<lb/></p>

			<p>(a) non-payment of the Borrower&apos;s Dues, or part<lb/> thereof and/or any amount payable pursuant to the Loan<lb/> Documents, and<lb/></p>

			<p>(b) any event or circumstance, having a Material<lb/> Adverse Effect, or adversely affecting the ability of the<lb/> obligors to perform their obligations under the Loan<lb/> Documents or to pay/repay the Borrower&apos;s Dues or any<lb/> part thereof.<lb/></p>

			<p>(xviii) On such an event of default occurring, the lender was<lb/> empowered, by clause 12.2 to recall the loan. Such recall<lb/> resulted in the Borrower&apos;s Dues becoming immediately<lb/> repayable/payable by the obligors. In case the net sum realised<lb/> by enforcement of security was insufficient to cover the<lb/> Borrower&apos;s Dues, the obligors undertook to pay, to the lender,<lb/> the shortfall therein.<lb/></p>

			<p>(xix) Similarly, Clause 12.3 empowered the lender, in the<lb/> event of the Borrower failing to pay the Borrower&apos;s Dues or on<lb/> happening an event of default, to apply any other amounts<lb/> standing to the Borrower&apos;s credit in any account of the lender,<lb/> towards payment of the Borrower&apos;s Dues.<lb/></p>

			<p>31. The golden thread, which runs through the Loan Agreements,<lb/> dated 29 th September, 2015, is, clearly, payment/repayment of the<lb/> Borrower&apos;s Dues. The &quot;Borrower&apos;s Dues&quot; were defined as the<lb/> amounts payable by obligors to the lender under the Loan Documents<lb/> or under any other agreements entered into between the obligors and<lb/> the lender.<lb/></p>

			<p>32. Insofar as the controversy in issue is concerned, the only<lb/> documents, entered into between the petitioner and the IHFL, were the<lb/> three Loan Agreements, dated 29 th September, 2015. The petitioner<lb/> was, admittedly, not a party to any of the five tabulated Loan<lb/> Agreements. The &quot;loan&quot;, too, was defined as the loan amount<lb/> mentioned in Schedule I to the Loan Agreement, dated 29 th<lb/> September, 2015.<lb/></p>

			<p>33. Similarly, the Loan Agreements, dated 29 th September, 2015,<lb/> the security documents and other agreements/documents,<lb/> pertaining/relating to the loan/or the Borrower&apos;s Dues, were defined<lb/> as &quot;Loan Documents&quot;. Prima facie, therefore, the submission, of Mr.<lb/> Sethi, that &quot;Group Borrower&apos;s Dues&quot; were also subsumed by the three<lb/> Loan Agreements, dated 29 th September, 2015, does not commend<lb/> acceptance.<lb/></p>

			<p>34. Mr. Sethi has, however, predicated his submission on<lb/> (i)<lb/> the definition of &quot;Group Borrowers Dues&quot; in Clause 1.1<lb/> of the Loan Agreements, dated 29 th September, 2015,<lb/> (ii) Clause 2.3 of the Loan Agreements, which dealt with the<lb/> Security Cover to be provided by the Borrowers/Pledgors, and<lb/> (iii) Clause 15, which dealt with cross-liability.<lb/></p>

			<p>35. Mr. Sethi acknowledges the fact that the petitioner was not a<lb/> party to any of the five tabulated Loan Agreements. Mr. Sethi&apos;s<lb/> submission is that the loans, under the said agreements, were<lb/> advanced by IHFL, or its associate company IBCC, to the associated<lb/> companies of Sunil Goel and were, therefore, part of the &quot;Group<lb/> Borrower&apos;s Dues&quot; as defined in Clause 1.1 of the Loan Agreements<lb/> dated 29 th September, 2015. These loans, too, therefore, Mr Sethi<lb/> would seek to submit, were required to be secured by the obligors to<lb/> the said Loan Agreements, including the security provided by the<lb/> petitioner, in the form of the shares of Omaxe Ltd, held by him.<lb/></p>

			<p>36. A juxtaposed reading of the various clauses of the Loan<lb/> Agreements dated 29 th September, 2015, however, does not lend itself<lb/> to such an interpretation.<lb/></p>

			<p>37. The definition of &quot;Group Borrower&apos;s Dues&quot; as contained in<lb/> Clause 1.1 of the Loan Agreements, dated 29 th September, 2015, being<lb/> a definition clause, has no independent existence, isolated from the<lb/> covenants of the Loan Agreements, in which the expression finds<lb/> place. It is well-settled that recourse and reference, to a definition<lb/> clause, whether in a statute or in a contractual document, would be<lb/> inappropriate, divorced from the statutory, or contractual covenant,<lb/> wherein the expression, so defined, finds mention. Definition clauses<lb/> are only aids to interpretation of the substantive clauses of the<lb/> statutory or contractual instrument, and have no independent existence<lb/> or applicability.<lb/></p>

			<p>38. In order to appreciate the submission of Mr. Sethi, qua the<lb/> definition of &quot;Group Borrower&apos;s Dues&quot;, as contained in Clause 1.1 of<lb/> the Loan Agreements dated 29 th September, 2015, it would be<lb/> necessary, therefore, to refer to Clause 2.3, wherein the expression<lb/> &quot;Group Borrower&apos;s Dues&quot; finds place, and on which Mr Sethi, too,<lb/> relies.<lb/></p>

			<p>39. Mr. Sethi has placed great emphasis on the opening sentence of<lb/> Clause 2.3, which reads thus:<lb/></p>

			<p>&quot;The borrower(s) and/or the co-Borrower(s) shall, and/or<lb/> shall cause the obligor(s) to maintain the security cover as<lb/> stipulated in Schedule I, hereunder, at all times during the<lb/> validity of the Loan Documents.&quot;<lb/> What, therefore, was required to be secured, by the security provided<lb/> by the obligors to the Loan Agreements dated 29 th September, 2015,<lb/> was, submits Mr. Sethi, not merely the loans advanced under the said<lb/> Loan Agreements, but also the security cover as stipulated in Schedule<lb/> I thereto.<lb/></p>

			<p>40. This stipulation, in clause 2.3, cannot, however, help Mr. Sethi,<lb/> as Schedule I to each of the Loan Agreements, dated 29 th September,<lb/> 2015, refers only to the amount of loan advanced under the said Loan<lb/> Agreements, i.e. to the amounts of ₹ 65 crores, ₹ 65 crores, and ₹ 20<lb/> crores respectively. Viewed thus, the opening sentence of Clause 2.3,<lb/> in fact, militates against the submission of Mr. Sethi, as it makes it<lb/> abundantly clear that the security cover, required to be provided under<lb/> each of the Loan Agreements, dated 29 th September, 2015, was only<lb/> required to cover the loan advanced under such Loan Agreement, and<lb/> not under any other Loan Agreement, including any of the five<lb/> tabulated Loan Agreements.<lb/></p>

			<p>41. Mr. Sethi has also invited my attention to the second<lb/> (unnumbered) para of Clause 2.3 of the Loan Agreement, dated 29 th<lb/> September, 2015, which reads thus:<lb/></p>

			<p>&quot;In addition to the aforesaid security cover, the Borrower(s)<lb/> and/or and co-borrower(s) shall, and/or shall cause the<lb/> pledgor(s) to maintain a margin of at least 108.33% of the<lb/> Group Borrowers Dues at all times during the validity of the<lb/> Loan Documents.&quot;<lb/> (Emphasis supplied)<lb/> According to Mr. Sethi, this stipulation, as contained in Clause 2.3,<lb/> seals the case of the petitioner, as it required the pledgors to maintain<lb/> a margin of at least 108.33% of the Group Borrower&apos;s Dues during<lb/> the validity of the Loan Agreement dated 29 th September, 2015.<lb/></p>

			<p>42. Mr. Sethi seeks to juxtapose this stipulation with the definition<lb/> of &quot;Group Borrowers Dues&quot; as contained in Clause 1.1, to submit that<lb/> the loans payable under the tabulated Loan Agreements, also partook<lb/> the character of &quot;Group Borrower&apos;s Dues&quot; as defined in the said<lb/> Clause, thereby rendering the petitioner liable to provide security<lb/> cover to maintain a margin of at least 108.33% thereof, during the<lb/> validity of the Loan Documents. Liquidation of the loan, advanced<lb/> under the three Loan Agreements, dated 29 th September, 2015,<lb/> therefore, Mr. Sethi would seek to submit, does not eviscerate this<lb/> responsibility of the Pledgors -including the petitioner -emanating<lb/> from Clause 2.3 of the Loan Agreements dated 29 th September, 2015.<lb/></p>

			<p>43. This submission of Mr. Sethi, too, though attractive at first<lb/> blush, fails, on a deeper reading, to convince.<lb/></p>

			<p>44. The error in the submission of Mr. Sethi is primarily<lb/> attributable to the sentence which immediately follows the afore-<lb/>extracted sentence from the second para of clause 2.3, which reads as<lb/> under:<lb/></p>

			<p>&quot;For this purpose only the value of pledged/charged shares<lb/> (which are listed on Stock Exchanges in India), pledged in<lb/> favour of the lender to secure the Group Borrower&apos;s Dues,<lb/> shall be taken into consideration, at all times during the<lb/> validity of the Loan Documents.&quot;<lb/> (Emphasis supplied)<lb/> The responsibility of the Pledgors to ensure maintenance of 108.33%<lb/> of the Group Borrower&apos;s Dues was, therefore, to be reckoned on the<lb/> basis of the shares pledged in favour of IHFL to secure the Group<lb/> Borrower&apos;s Dues, alone.<lb/> A distinction becomes immediately<lb/> apparent, between the shares, in Omaxe Ltd., held by the petitioner,<lb/> and the shares in Omaxe Ltd., held by Guild Builders Ltd., both of<lb/> which were pledged with IHFL, under the Loan Agreements dated<lb/> 29 th September, 2015. While the shares of Guild Builders Ltd. were<lb/> pledged, not only to secure the Borrower&apos;s Dues under the Loan<lb/> Agreements, dated 29 th September, 2015, but also as security under<lb/> the tabulated Loan Agreements, the shares of the petitioner were<lb/> pledged as security, only to secure the Borrower&apos;s Dues under the<lb/> Loan Agreements, dated 29 th September, 2015, and not the Group<lb/> Borrower&apos;s Dues.<lb/></p>

			<p>45. Even if, therefore, it were to be assumed, arguendo, that the<lb/> loans advanced under the five tabulated Loan Agreements were<lb/> &quot;Group Borrower&apos;s Dues&quot; , the shares of the petitioner held in Omaxe<lb/> Ltd., pledged with IHFL to secure the loans advanced under the three<lb/> Loan Agreements, dated 29 th September, 2015, not having been<lb/> pledged against the loans advanced under any of the five tabulated<lb/> Loan Agreements, their value would not be taken into account, while<lb/> operating the second para of Clause 2.3 (supra).The submission, of<lb/> Mr. Sethi, that the pledged shares, forming subject matter of the<lb/> present petition, also secured the loans advanced under the five<lb/> tabulated Loan Agreements, therefore, would be liable to fail even on<lb/> this ground.<lb/></p>

			<p>46.<lb/> That apart, when one refers to the definition of &quot;Group<lb/> Borrower&apos;s Dues&quot;, as contained in Clause 1.1 of the Loan Agreements<lb/> dated 29 th September, 2015, it would be seen that, in order for<lb/> amounts payable to IHFL, under any other agreement, to be liable to<lb/> be treated as &quot;Group Borrower&apos;s Dues&quot;, two conditions are<lb/> cumulatively required to be satisfied, viz.<lb/></p>

			<p>(i)<lb/> that the documents, whereunder the said amount was<lb/> payable to IHFL, was executed between IHFL or its associate<lb/> entity/entities, and the obligor(s) or its/their associate<lb/> entity/entities, and<lb/> (ii) that the security, under the Loan Documents, was also a<lb/> security under the said &quot;other&quot; Loan Agreement/Loan<lb/> Document.<lb/></p>

			<p>47. Neither of these requirements, properly assessed, stands<lb/> satisfied in the present case, insofar as the five tabulated Loan<lb/> Agreements are concerned. In the first place, as Mr. Rao correctly<lb/> points out, the petitioner, Sunil Goel, being an individual, it would be<lb/> difficult to hold that Guild Builders, Omaxe Ltd. or Garv were his<lb/> associated entities. The concept of &quot;associated entities&quot; necessarily<lb/> predicates corporate or quasi-corporate entities, and not individuals<lb/> vis-à-vis corporate entities. Secondly, the applicability of the<lb/> definition of &quot;Group Borrower&apos;s Dues&quot;, to amounts payable under<lb/> documents other than the three Loan Agreements dated 29 th<lb/> September, 2015, necessarily requires, as its sine qua non,<lb/> commonality of the security, under the said Loan Documents, vis-à-<lb/>vis the three Loan Agreements dated 29 th September, 2015. The intent<lb/> behind this stipulation, which is apparent, would stand entirely<lb/> defeated, were the submission of Mr. Sethi be accepted. For security,<lb/> under the Loan Agreements, to also cover liabilities, towards IHFL,<lb/> relatable to other Loan Agreements or Loan Documents, there had,<lb/> necessarily, to be commonality of the said security, between/among<lb/> the Loan Documents in question. In other words, it is only such<lb/> security, under the Loan Agreements dated 29 th September, 2015, as<lb/> expressly secured the loans advanced under other Loan Documents,<lb/> which could operate as security under such Loan Documents as well.<lb/> It is only thus, that the concept of commonality of security can<lb/> operate. This stipulation, as expressly and consciously engrafted in the<lb/> definition of &quot;Group Borrower&apos;s Dues&quot;, in Clause 1.1 of the Loan<lb/> Agreements dated 29 th September, 2015, completely militates against<lb/> treating the shares in Omaxe Ltd. held by the petitioner and pledged<lb/> as security under the Loan Agreements dated 29 th September, 2015,<lb/> being treated as security under any other Loan Documents, unless the<lb/> loans advanced under such Loan Documents expressly stand secured<lb/> by such shares. The shares held by the petitioner in Omaxe Ltd.,<lb/> pledged with IHFL as security for the loan, covered by the three Loan<lb/> Documents dated 29 th September, 2015, not having been pledged<lb/> against the loan advanced under any other Loan Document, cannot be<lb/> treated as security under such other document. The loan amounts,<lb/> payable under such documents, cannot, therefore, be regarded as<lb/> &quot;Group Borrower&apos;s Dues&quot;, as defined in Clause 1.1 of the Loan<lb/> Agreements dated 29 th September, 2015.<lb/></p>

			<p>48. Proceeding, now, to the &quot;Cross Liability&quot; provision, contained<lb/> in Clause 15 of the Loan Agreements dated 29 th September, 2015, a<lb/> holistic reading of the said clause, in my view, would entitle IHFL, as<lb/> the lender, to exercise its rights under the Loan Agreements,<lb/> consequent on a breach/default under any other agreement, only if<lb/> such other agreement is between the obligor (or its associate entity)<lb/> and any of the IndiaBulls&apos; Companies, qua the security provided by<lb/> such obligor.<lb/> The very concept of cross-liability or cross-<lb/>collateralisation, as applicable to commercial contracts, predicates<lb/> reciprocity of security and commonality of the parties to the contract.<lb/> This is, even etymologically, apparent, as &quot;cross-collateralisation&quot;<lb/> necessarily requires the same collateral being available, as security<lb/> against more than one loan. &quot;Cross-collateralisation&quot;, as a concept<lb/> known to commercial contracts, necessarily predicates the usage of<lb/> the collateral, available as security against one loan, as collateral<lb/> against a second loan. If, however, the two loans are governed by<lb/> independent loan agreements, the inclusion of a cross collateralisation<lb/> clause, in one of them, cannot, proprio vigore, justify proceeding<lb/> against the collateral, provided in the said loan agreement, for<lb/> satisfaction of the loan in the other agreements, unless the said<lb/> security is also collateral under such other agreements. It is open, to<lb/> contractual parties, to provide for such a dispensation in the loan<lb/> agreements. Absent such dispensation, however, the mere existence<lb/> of a cross collateralisation, or cross liability, clause in one of the<lb/> agreements, would be insufficient. It is, apparently, in awareness of<lb/> this legal position, that the definition of &quot;Group Borrower&apos;s Dues&quot;, as<lb/> contained in Clause 1.1 of the Loan Agreements dated 29 th September,<lb/> 2015, incorporated a condition of commonality of security. In a<lb/> similar vein, Clause 2.3 of the Loan Agreements dated 29 th<lb/> September, 2015, too, provides that, while reckoning 108.33% of the<lb/> Group Borrower&apos;s Dues, to be secured by the Security Cover, to be<lb/> provided by the pledgors, only such securities, as are pledged against<lb/> the Group Borrower&apos;s Dues, would be taken into account. The mere<lb/> existence of Clause 15, in the Loan Agreements dated 29 th September,<lb/> 2015, therefore, cannot justify the submission, of Mr. Sethi, that, even<lb/> after liquidation of the loans advanced under the said Loan<lb/> Agreements, the shares of the petitioner in Omaxe Ltd. should remain<lb/> pledged with IHFL, despite such shares not having been secured<lb/> against any Group Borrower&apos;s Dues. At the cost of repetition, it may<lb/> be pointed out that the shares of Guild Builders, pledged as security<lb/> against the loans advanced under the Loan Agreements dated 29 th<lb/> September, 2015, stood on a different footing, as Guild Builders was<lb/> also obligor, under the five tabulated Loan Agreements.<lb/></p>

			<p>49. That apart, Clause 15 can never operate, against an obligor, to<lb/> any of the Loan Agreements dated 29 th September, 2015, in respect of<lb/> a default, under some other agreement, to which the obligor is not a<lb/> party. In the present case, the situation is exacerbated by the fact that,<lb/> of the five tabulated Loan Agreements, save and except for the Loan<lb/> Agreement dated 30 th June, 2017, all other Loan Agreements were<lb/> executed after the petitioner had been ousted from the post of Joint<lb/> Managing Director in Omaxe Ltd. The petitioner was, therefore,<lb/> never associated with the execution of the tabulated Loan<lb/> Agreements, and was not even a director in Omaxe Ltd. at the time of<lb/> execution of four out of the five tabulated loan agreements, and it<lb/> would be preposterous, therefore, to treat the shares, pledged by the<lb/> petitioner with IHFL as security for the loans advanced under the<lb/> Loan Agreements dated 29 th September, 2015, also as security under<lb/> the tabulated loan agreements, executed after the petitioner ceased to<lb/> be a director in any of the companies in question, and to the execution<lb/> of which the petitioner was a complete stranger.<lb/></p>

			<p>50. Construction of the covenants of commercial contracts, it is<lb/> well settled, has to be guided by commercial sense. 1 The manner in<lb/> which Mr. Sandeep Sethi would seek to juxtapose the definition of<lb/> &quot;Group Borrower&apos;s Dues&quot; as contained in Clause 1.1, with Clauses<lb/> 2.2, 2.3 and 15, of the Loan Agreements dated 29 th September, 2015,<lb/> in the opinion of this Court, is opposed to all basic tenets of<lb/> commercial common sense.<lb/> On their face, therefore, these<lb/> submissions cannot be accepted.<lb/></p>

			<p>51. The need to interpret, in any greater detail, Clause 15 of the<lb/> Loan Agreements dated 29 th September, 2015, is obviated by Clause<lb/> 2.4 of the said Loan Agreements, which obliges IHFL to, forthwith,<lb/> release the security created by the obligors -including the petitioner -<lb/>consequent on repayment of the entire borrower&apos;s dues and fulfilment<lb/> of all the obligations of the obligors under the Loan Documents. This<lb/> stipulation, which expressly covers the release of the security pledged<lb/> under the Loan Agreements dated 29 th September, 2015, therefore,<lb/> militates, conclusively, against the submission of Mr. Sandeep Sethi,<lb/> that, even after liquidation of the loans advanced under the said Loan<lb/> Agreements, the shares of the petitioner, pledged with IHFL, should<lb/> not be released.<lb/></p>

			<p>52. That apart, IHFL, in its communication, dated 5 th September,<lb/> 2018 supra to the petitioner, has itself emphasised, in the following<lb/> passages, the above position, as is manifest by the italicised words<lb/> therein. The said communication may be reproduced, for ready<lb/> reference, thus:<lb/></p>

			<p>&quot;Date: 05.09.2018<lb/> To<lb/> Mr. Sunil Goel<lb/> Farm No. 37C, Radhey Mohan Drive,<lb/> Bandh Road, Asola, Fatehpuri Beri,<lb/> South Delhi, New Delhi -110 074<lb/> Dear Sir,<lb/> Ref: Your letter(s) dated August 6, 2018 and August 14,<lb/> 2018 addressed to, inter alia M/s Indiabulls Housing<lb/> Finance Limited (&quot;IHFL&quot;) for release of (a) shares of<lb/> Omaxe Limited pledged by Mr. Sunil Goel in favour of<lb/> IHFL (&quot;Said Shares&quot;) and (b) the guarantee (s)provided<lb/> by Mr. Sunil Goel in favour of IHFL (&quot;Said<lb/> Guarantee(s)&quot;) in connection with the loan(s) availed by<lb/> M/s. Omaxe Forest Spa and Hills Developers Limited<lb/> (&quot;Borrower(s)&quot;) from IHFL.<lb/> This has reference to the captioned letter(s).<lb/> At the outset, we deny the allegations made against us in your<lb/> captioned letter(s). You have raised these issues earlier as<lb/> well and we have already responded to you including vide our<lb/> letter dated November 23, 2017. In relation to the same, we<lb/> wish to reiterate the Said Shares and the Said Guarantee(s)<lb/> provided by you cannot be and shall not be released till the<lb/> loan(s) availed by the Borrower(s) from IHFL (&quot;Loan(s)&quot;) are<lb/> repaid in full as per the provisions of the Loan Documents<lb/> relating to the Loan(s) (&quot;Loan Documents&quot;).<lb/> Further, kindly note that it is the discretion of IHFL to decide<lb/> whether or not any security shall be released (including which<lb/> security shall be released, if any) till the obligations under the<lb/> Loan Documents are fulfilled/complied with by the<lb/> Obligor(s). Without prejudice to the foregoing, since you<lb/> have claimed in the captioned letter(s) that you hold/control<lb/> (directly or indirectly) more than 25% shares of M/s. Guild<lb/> Builders Private Limited, you have benefitted due to release<lb/> (by us) of pledge on some of the shares held by M/s. Guild<lb/> Builders Private Limited.<lb/></p>

			<p>In relation to your allegation of cross-collateralization of the<lb/> Said Shares and the Said Guarantee(s) for the other loan(s)<lb/> availed by M/s. Omaxe Limited and/or its group companies<lb/> without your consent, we deny such charges. We confirm that<lb/> the Said Shares and the said Guarantee(s) are security for the<lb/> loan(s) mentioned in the Loan Documents executed by you<lb/> (e.g. pledge agreement(s) and the guarantee deed(s)).<lb/> Your purported dispute(s)/differences with Mr. Rohtas Goel<lb/> or that you are no longer the JMD of Omaxe Limited or that<lb/> you no longer part of the management of Omaxe Limited<lb/> have no bearing on your obligations under such documents<lb/> executed by you in our favour. Please note that you are, and<lb/> shall continue to be, bound by the documents executed by you<lb/> in our favour including the pledge document(s) and the<lb/> guarantee deed(s). Without prejudice to the aforesaid, it is<lb/> noted that you have acknowledged in your captioned letter(s)<lb/> that you (and your family members) are still a promoter-<lb/>shareholder of Omaxe Limited (holding/controlling around<lb/> 20% shares directly or indirectly, as claimed by you) and the<lb/> Borrower(s) is a subsidiary of Omaxe Limited.<lb/> As per the contents of the captioned letter(s), it is clear that<lb/> you are trying to wriggle out of your obligations under the<lb/> Loan Documents executed by you and that you have an<lb/> intention to repudiate such Loan Documents. In view of this,<lb/> we may treat this as an Event of Default underclause 12.1.6 of<lb/> the Loan Agreement(s) relating to the Loan(s) and<lb/> consequently we shall be entitled to recall the entire<lb/> outstanding Loan(s) and the Borrower&apos;s Dues and upon failing<lb/> to pay the recalled amount(s) by the Obligor(s) to the Lender,<lb/> we shall be entitled to, inter-alai,enforce/sale/transfer/assign<lb/> all securities/collateral including the said Shares and the said<lb/> Guarantee(s).<lb/> We, therefore, request you to stop harassing us by writing to<lb/> us time and again with the same request/issues.&quot;<lb/></p>

			<p>53. The email dated 16 th June, 2020, addressed by IHFL to the<lb/> petitioner also emphasised this position, by stipulating thus:<lb/></p>

			<p>&quot;Dear Sir<lb/> This is in reference to your various communications<lb/> addressed to us, with respect to below loans, we hereby<lb/> confirm that upon receipt of the payment towards full and<lb/> final closure for following dues (as on date) to Indiabulls<lb/> Housing Finance Limited, we would release the security<lb/> associated with these loans.&quot;<lb/> (Emphasis supplied)<lb/></p>

			<p>54. The reliance, by Mr. Rao, on the covenants of the Pledge<lb/> Agreement, contemporaneously drawn up, with the three Loan<lb/> Agreements, on 29 th September, 2015, is also, in my opinion, well<lb/> taken. Before adverting thereto, it would be appropriate to reproduce<lb/> the relevant clauses, of the Pledge Agreement, thus:<lb/></p>

			<p>(i)<lb/> At the very commencement of the Pledge Agreement, it<lb/> was stipulated thus:<lb/></p>

			<p>&quot;The Pledgor(s) has/have agreed to create a first-<lb/>ranking and exclusive pledge/charge on the<lb/> Pledged/Charged Shares in favour of the Lender to<lb/> secure the Secured Obligations in consideration of the<lb/> Lender agreeing to lend/having lent their Loan(s)<lb/> pursuant to the Loan Agreement(s) and the related<lb/> Loan Documents. The pledge/charge created herein in<lb/> favour of the Lender over the Collateral by the<lb/> Pledgor(s) is a first-ranking and exclusive<lb/> pledge/charge.&quot;<lb/> (Emphasis supplied)<lb/></p>

			<p>(ii) &quot;Secured Obligations&quot; was defined, in sub-clause (h) of<lb/> Clause 1.1, thus:<lb/></p>

			<p>&quot; &quot;Secured Obligations&quot; shall mean the Loan(s)<lb/> together with all interests, default interests, costs,<lb/> charges, expenses and other monies payable by the<lb/> Obligor(s) to the Lender under the Loan Agreement(s)<lb/> and other Loan Document(s).&quot;<lb/> (Emphasis supplied)<lb/></p>

			<p>(iii) &quot;Loan&quot; was defined, in the same Clause, thus:<lb/></p>

			<p>(iv) Release of collateral, under the Pledge Agreement, was<lb/> covered by Clause 17 thereof, which read thus:<lb/></p>

			<p>&quot;17 RELEASE<lb/> Promptly upon the occurrence of the Final<lb/> Settlement Date, the Lender shall, at the<lb/> Pledgor(s) cost and expense, release the<lb/> Collateral from the pledge/charge granted<lb/> hereby, and take the following steps (i)<lb/> redeliver such of the Collateral as may be in the<lb/> possession of the Lender and has not therefore<lb/> been sold or otherwise applied or released; and<lb/> (ii) redeliver the Pledged/Charged Shares and<lb/> the powers of attorney executed in favour of the<lb/> Lender marked &apos;cancelled&apos;.&quot;<lb/></p>

			<p>(v) &quot;Final Settlement Date&quot; was defined, in sub-clause c) of<lb/> Clause 1.1, as having &quot;the meaning ascribed to it in Clause 2.6<lb/> of the Agreement&quot;. Clause 2.6 read, for its part, thus:<lb/></p>

			<p>&quot;2.6 Waivers and Acknowledgements<lb/> The Pledgor(s) hereby waive its/his/her/their<lb/> right to, and shall not, revoke this Agreement<lb/> (and the pledge/charge created hereunder in<lb/> favour of the Lender) until the Secured<lb/> Obligations have been paid in full to the<lb/> satisfaction of the Lender and there are no<lb/> outstanding obligations of the Obligor(s) under<lb/> the Loan Documents (&quot;Final Settlement<lb/> Date&quot;).&quot;<lb/></p>

			<p>(vi) To make matters more explicit, Clause 3 provided thus:<lb/></p>

			<p>&quot;3<lb/> CONTINUING SECURITY<lb/> This Agreement and the security created<lb/> hereunder, is and shall be a continuing security<lb/> and shall remain in full force and effect until the<lb/> Final Settlement Date, notwithstanding any<lb/> intermediate payment or satisfaction of the<lb/> whole or any part of the Secured Obligations or<lb/> the insolvency or liquidation or any incapacity<lb/> or change in the constitution or the status of the<lb/> Pledgor(s) or any intermediate settlement of<lb/> account. The pledge and charge created under<lb/> this Agreement is in addition to and<lb/> independent of the security created in<lb/> accordance with the terms of the other Loan<lb/> Documents or the enforcement thereof, or any<lb/> other action that may be commenced against the<lb/> Pledgor(s) or any person by the Lender or its<lb/> nominee(s) and any such other security shall not<lb/> in any way be prejudiced or affected by this<lb/> Agreement.&quot;<lb/> (Emphasis supplied)<lb/></p>

			<p>55. Clause 17 of the Pledge Agreement, therefore, obligated IHFL<lb/> to release the collateral -including the pledged shares of the petitioner<lb/> -on the occurrence of the Final Settlement Date. The date of<lb/> payment of the secured obligations, under the Pledge Agreement, in<lb/> full, was to be treated as &quot;Final Settlement Date&quot; under Clause 2.6 of<lb/> the Pledge Agreement read with the definition of &quot;Final Settlement<lb/> Date&quot; in Clause 1.1 thereof. &quot;Secured obligations&quot; was defined, in<lb/> sub-clause (h) of Clause 1.1 of the pledged agreement as meaning the<lb/> loan (with interests, costs and other monies, etc.) payable by the<lb/> obligor/obligors to IHFL under the Loan Agreement and other Loan<lb/> Documents. &quot;Loan&quot; was in turn, defined as the loan of the total<lb/> principal amounts as mentioned in Schedule IB of the pledge<lb/> agreement disbursed under the Loan Agreement and other related<lb/> Loan Documents.<lb/></p>

			<p>56. Schedule IB to the Pledge Agreement referred only to the three<lb/> Loan Agreements dated 29 th September, 2015 whereunder, loans of<lb/> ₹65 crores, ₹65 cores and ₹20 crores, which had been advanced by<lb/> IHFL to Omaxe Forest Spa and to no other document.<lb/></p>

			<p>57. Clause 2.1 of the Pledge Agreement, in a similar vein, stated,<lb/> clearly, that the Pledge Agreement secured the obligations, of the<lb/> obligors, only under the Loan Documents. Clause 3 further clarified<lb/> that the Pledge Agreement would remain in force till the Final<lb/> Settlement Date, and not thereafter.<lb/></p>

			<p>58. A cumulative reading of the aforesaid covenants of the Pledge<lb/> Agreement make it apparent that, with the amounts of ₹ 65 crores, ₹65<lb/> cores and ₹20 crores having been repaid to IHFL, the Final Settlement<lb/> Date, for the purposes of the Pledge Agreement had been reached,<lb/> IHFL was duty bound, therefore, to release the pledged shares,<lb/> including the shares of Omaxe Ltd., held by the petitioner.<lb/> Conclusion<lb/></p>

			<p>59. The attempt of Guild Builders, to oppose the release of the<lb/> shares in Omaxe Ltd., held by the petitioner and pledged by the<lb/> petitioner as security against the loans advanced under the three Loan<lb/> Agreements dated 29 th September, 2015, therefore, has necessarily to<lb/> fail.<lb/></p>

			<p>60. In view thereof, IHFL is directed to release, forthwith, the<lb/> shares in Omaxe Ltd., held by the petitioner and pledged against the<lb/> loans forming subject matter of the three Loan Agreements dated 29 th<lb/> September, 2015.<lb/></p>

			<p>61. I.A. 4942/2020 and I.A. 4943/2020, filed by Guild Builders,<lb/> therefore, are dismissed, and O.M.P.(I) (COMM.) 142/2020, filed by<lb/> the petitioner Sunil Goel stands disposed of accordingly, with no<lb/> orders as to costs.<lb/></p>

			<p>62. Interim applications, if any, do not survive for consideration<lb/> and are, accordingly, disposed of.<lb/></p>

			<p>C. HARI SHANKAR, J.<lb/> AUGUST 31, 2020<lb/> HJ<lb/> kr/dsn</p>


	</text>
</tei>
