<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<p>
			2. In the letters second and third read above, the Director of School Education
			<lb />
			has sent proposals of the Government seeking orders of the Government on the
			<lb />
			equivalence of the Diploma acquired by the Writ Petitioners in W.P.(MD)
			<lb />
			No.21650/2018 and other cases and also equivalence for certain other courses
			<lb />
			offered by Educational Institutions respectively.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			3. In the Government Order 4 th read above, the existing Equivalence
			<lb />
			Committee functioning under the Chairmanship of Tamil Nadu Public Service
			<lb />
			Commission was disbanded and a new Equivalence Committee has been constituted
			<lb />
			in its place, under the Chairmanship of the Principal Secretary to Government, Higher
			<lb />
			Education Department for issuance of equivalence to the courses offered by the
			<lb />
			Educational institutions for the purpose of employment in public services and for
			<lb />
			pursuing higher studies.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			4. Based on the minutes of the first Equivalence Committee meeting held on
			<lb />
			31.07.2019 received in letter 5 th read above, orders have been issued by the
			<lb />
			Government for equivalence of the Educational Qualifications in Government Order
			<lb />
			6 th read above and non equivalence of the Educational Qualifications in Government
			<lb />
			Order 7 th read above.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			5. In the letter 8 th read above the Chairman, Equivalence Committee/ the
			<lb />
			Principal Secretary to Government, Higher Education Department has forwarded the
			<lb />
			resolutions passed in the second Equivalence Committee meeting held on 6.11.2019
			<lb />
			on the Equivalence of the following courses offered by various universities to the
			<lb />
			similar courses for the purpose of employment in public service.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<figure type="table">
			Sl.No.
			<lb />
			Resolution
			<lb />
			Recommendation
			<lb />
			1.
			<lb />
			Resolution No:111
			<lb />
			Public Services -Educational Qualifications -
			<lb />
			Consideration of D.P.Ed. Offered by Annamalai
			<lb />
			university &amp; Bharathiar University as to
			<lb />
			whether equivalent to H.P.Ed., to the purpose
			<lb />
			of Employment in Public Services
			<lb />
			Equivalent
			<lb />
			2.
			<lb />
			Resolution No.112
			<lb />
			Public Services -Educational Qualification -
			<lb />
			Consideration of M.P.Ed., (Direct) 2 year
			<lb />
			degree course offered by University of Madras
			<lb />
			as to whether equivalent to B.P.Ed., (one
			<lb />
			year) and M.P.Ed., (One year) to the purpose
			<lb />
			of Employment in Public Services.
			<lb />
			Equivalent
			<lb />
			3.
			<lb />
			Resolution No.113
			<lb />
			Public Services -Educational Qualification -
			<lb />
			Consideration of C.P.Ed., offered by Karnataka
			<lb />
			State as to whether equivalent to Lower
			<lb />
			Grade/Higher Grade course of the Director of
			<lb />
			Government Exams, Tamil Nadu to the
			<lb />
			purpose of Employment in Public Services.
			<lb />
			Equivalent
			<lb />
		</figure>
		<p>
			6. The Government after careful consideration, decided to accept the above
			<lb />
			resolutions passed in the second Equivalence Committee Meeting held on 06.11.2019
			<lb />
			and direct that the above courses offered by various Universities are equivalent to
			<lb />
			that of the similar courses mentioned therein from the date of issuance of such
			<lb />
			degrees/diploma.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(By Order of the Governor)
			<lb />
			Pradeed Yadav,
			<lb />
			Principal Secretary to Government
			<lb />
			___________
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			5. A perusal of the above Government Orders shows that they
			<lb />
			are in compliance of the directions issued by the High Court
			<lb />
			(Madurai Bench), whereafter an Equivalence Committee was
			<lb />
			constituted and the Equivalence Committee vide its meetings, as
			<lb />
			referred in the Government Orders, proceeded to grant equivalence
			<lb />
			in the manner indicated therein. In the present set of appeals, the
			<lb />
			equivalence as set out is being claimed by the appellants and they
			<lb />
			contend that the said Government Orders cover their cases.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			6. Learned Additional Advocate General appearing for the
			<lb />
			State has not disputed the issuance of the Government Orders
			<lb />
			aforesaid, but contends that in the event the appellants are covered
			<lb />
			by the said Government Orders, the Government shall consider
			<lb />
			their candidature, provided they fulfill other eligibility conditions.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			7. Having considered the submissions, we find that the
			<lb />
			judgments of the learned Single Judge deserve to be set aside and
			<lb />
			accordingly, the impugned judgments dated 22.2.2019, 27.2.2019,
			<lb />
			4.3.2019 and 6.3.2019 are set aside with a direction to the
			<lb />
			___________
			Government to consider the candidature of the appellants in terms
			<lb />
			of the Government Orders, referred to herein above, and pass
			<lb />
			appropriate orders within six weeks, as prayed for.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			The appeals are accordingly allowed on the above terms. No
			<lb />
			costs. Consequently, connected miscellaneous petitions are closed.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(A.P.S., CJ.)
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(S.P., J.)
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			THE HON&apos;BLE CHIEF JUSTICE
			<lb />
			AND
			<lb />
			SUBRAMONIUM PRASAD,J.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(sasi)
			<lb />
		</p>
	</text>
</tei>
