<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<item>CORAM<lb/> THE HONOURABLE MR.JUSTICE M.SUNDAR<lb/></item>

			<item>W.P.Nos.1533 and 1534 of 2006<lb/> and W.M.P.Nos.1722 to 1725 of 2006<lb/> M/s.Vaishnovi Engineers,<lb/> 128, Madhavaram High Road,<lb/> Perambur, Chennai -11.<lb/> .. Petitioner<lb/> in both WPs<lb/> Vs<lb/></item>

			<item>1.The State of Tamil Nadu,<lb/> Rep. By its Secretary,<lb/> Home (Transport) Department,<lb/> Fort St.George, Chennai -9.<lb/></item>

			<p>2.The Commercial Tax Officer,<lb/> Greams Road,Chennai -6.<lb/></p>

			<p>3.The Regional Transport Officer,<lb/> Chennai North, Chennai.<lb/></p>

			<item>4.The Motor Vehicle Inspector,<lb/> Grade I, Regional Transport Office,<lb/> Chennai North, Chennai.<lb/> ... Respondents<lb/> in both WPs<lb/> Prayer in W.P. No.1533 of 2006: Petition filed under Article 226 of<lb/> the Constitution of India praying to issue a Writ of Mandamus<lb/> forbearing the respondents and their subordinates from demanding<lb/> or collecting entry tax on the petitioner&apos;s used Grove Crane Model<lb/> RT76-S SL No.44863 YOM 1991, to be registered and assigned new<lb/> registration mark by the third and fourth respondents.<lb/></item>

			<item>1/6<lb/> https://www.mhc.tn.gov.in/judis/<lb/> Prayer in W.P. No.1534 of 2006: Petition filed under Article 226 of<lb/> the Constitution of India praying to issue a Writ of Mandamus<lb/> forbearing the respondents and their subordinates from demanding<lb/> or collecting entry tax on the petitioner&apos;s used Grove Crane Model<lb/> RT75-S SL No.44635 YOM 1992, to be registered and assigned new<lb/> registration mark by the third and fourth respondents.<lb/></item>

			<item>For Petitioner<lb/> : Mr.V.Santharam<lb/> (in both cases)<lb/> For Respondents : Ms.Amirta Dinakaran<lb/> Government Advocate<lb/> (in both cases)<lb/></item>

			<p>COMMON ORDER<lb/> Mr.V.Santharam, learned counsel representing the counsel on<lb/> record for the writ petitioner and Ms.Amirta Dinakaran representing<lb/> the Revenue on behalf of all the respondents are before this virtual<lb/> court.<lb/></p>

			<p>2.Learned counsel submits that one of the counsel on record<lb/> Mr.V.S.Srikrishnan, who was handling the captioned writ petitions is<lb/> no more. Learned counsel also submits that the other counsel on<lb/> record have no instructions. Learned counsel submits that no<lb/> instruction memo has been filed and a scanned reproduction of the<lb/> same is as follows:<lb/></p>

			<p>2/6<lb/> https://www.mhc.tn.gov.in/judis/<lb/></p>

			<p>3.The contents of the memo are reiterated in the hearing<lb/> today.<lb/></p>

			<p>4.The writ petitions are of the year 2006 and they have been<lb/> filed on 20.01.2006 to be precise. This means that the writ petitions<lb/> are more than one and half decades old i.e., more than 15 years<lb/> old.<lb/></p>

			<p>5.Be that as it may, learned Revenue counsel pointed out that<lb/> nothing really survives in the captioned matter as the issue<lb/> pertaining to entry tax and imported cars has been decided by a<lb/> Hon&apos;ble Division Bench in V.Krishnamurthy Vs. State of Tamil<lb/> Nadu and Others reported in 2019 SCC Online Mad 8523 and<lb/> the captioned matter is squarely covered by the same.<lb/></p>

			<p>6.In the light of the aforementioned narrative, captioned writ<lb/> petitions are dismissed. There shall be no order as to costs.<lb/> Consequently, connected miscellaneous petitions are closed.<lb/></p>

			<p>27.09.2021<lb/> Index:Yes/ No<lb/> mmi/ssm<lb/> 4/6<lb/> https://www.mhc.tn.gov.in/judis/<lb/> To<lb/> 1.The State of Tamil Nadu,<lb/> Rep. By its Secretary,<lb/> Home (Transport) Department,<lb/> Fort St.George, Chennai -9.<lb/></p>

			<p>2.The Commercial Tax Officer,<lb/> Greams Road,Chennai -6.<lb/></p>

			<p>3.The Regional Transport Officer,<lb/> Chennai North, Chennai.<lb/></p>

			<p>4.The Motor Vehicle Inspector,<lb/> Grade I, Regional Transport Office,<lb/> Chennai North, Chennai.<lb/></p>

			<p>5/6<lb/> https://www.mhc.tn.gov.in/judis/<lb/> W.P.Nos.1533 and 1534 of 2006<lb/> M.SUNDAR,J.<lb/> mmi/ssm<lb/> W.P.Nos.1533 and 1534 of 2006<lb/></p>

			<p>27.09.2021<lb/> 6/6<lb/> https://www.mhc.tn.gov.in/judis/</p>


	</text>
</tei>
