<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<p>
			This common order will govern all the captioned four writ
			<lb />
			petitions.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			2. Mr.K.Selvaraj, learned counsel for writ petitioners in all four
			<lb />
			writ petitions are before this virtual Court. Learned counsel submits that
			<lb />
			there are four different writ petitioners, but the issue is same. Learned
			<lb />
			counsel submits that the writ petitioners were given two years license
			<lb />
			(from 2019 to 2021) for selling short eats and collecting empty bottles
			<lb />
			from Bars attached to four different retail liquor outlets run by &apos;Tamil
			<lb />
			Nadu State Marketing Corporation Limited&apos; [&apos;TASMAC&apos;], but in 2019-
			<lb />
			2021 period, Corona virus pandemic and consequent lock down which is
			<lb />
			collectively referred to as &apos;COVID 19 situation&apos;, which the writ petitioner
			<lb />
			could neither portend nor presage, intervened. Learned counsel for writ
			<lb />
			petitioners submits that there was lock down and therefore, writ
			<lb />
			petitioners could not have the benefit of entire two years period.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			3. Notwithstanding the expansive prayer in all the four writ
			<lb />
			petitions, learned counsel, on instructions, abridges the prayer and
			<lb />
			restricts the prayer to a simple Mandamus to dispose of representations
			<lb />
			all dated 27.08.2021 made by each of the four writ petitioners. The
			<lb />
			details are as follows:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<figure type="table">
			S.No Shop No./Retail
			<lb />
			Outlet No.
			<lb />
			Name of Writ
			<lb />
			Petitioner
			<lb />
			W.P.Nos
			<lb />
			1
			<lb />
			8799
			<lb />
			M.Balaraja
			<lb />
			22236 of 2021
			<lb />
			2
			<lb />
			8903
			<lb />
			V.Sendoorapandy 22238 of 2021
			<lb />
			3
			<lb />
			446
			<lb />
			V.Selvam
			<lb />
			22242 of 2021
			<lb />
			4
			<lb />
			9069
			<lb />
			N.Udayappa
			<lb />
			22244 of 2021
			<lb />
		</figure>
		<p>
			4. Mr.K.Sathish Kumar, learned standing counsel for TASMAC,
			<lb />
			accepts notice on behalf of all the 3 respondents in all the four writ
			<lb />
			petitions. On instructions, learned standing counsel submits that no fee
			<lb />
			was collected from the writ petitioners during the lock down period.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			5. However, owing to the extremely limited abridged/restricted
			<lb />
			prayer writ petitioners are now making, this Court deems it appropriate to
			<lb />
			accede to the limited abridged prayer.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			6. Before this Court proceeds further, it is deemed appropriate to
			<lb />
			extract and reproduce four representations that has been placed before
			<lb />
			Court (as part of the common typed set of papers). The four
			<lb />
			representations are as follows:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			7. Captioned four writ petitions are disposed of with a directive to
			<lb />
			first respondent to consider and dispose of all the four writ petitioners&apos;
			<lb />
			representations (all dated 27.08.2021) on its own merits, in accordance
			<lb />
			with law as expeditiously as the business of the first respondent would
			<lb />
			permit and in any event, within three weeks from today i.e., on or before
			<lb />
			15.11.2021.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			8. Proceedings/orders disposing all the aforementioned four
			<lb />
			representations of the four writ petitioners shall be communicated to the
			<lb />
			respective writ petitioners under due acknowledgment within five
			<lb />
			working days from the dates of disposal of the representations. Though
			<lb />
			obvious, it is made clear that this Court has not expressed any opinion or
			<lb />
			view on the merits of the matter and the first respondent shall consider
			<lb />
			the representations on their own merits and in accordance with law.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			9. Captioned four Writ Petitions are disposed of in the aforesaid
			<lb />
			manner by this common order. There shall be no order as to costs.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			M.SUNDAR.J.,
			<lb />
		</p>
	</text>
</tei>
