<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc xml:id="0" />
    </teiHeader>
    <item xml:lang="en">
        <p>
            1.
            <lb />
            Both the writ petitions are being disposed of by a common
            <lb />
            judgment because in both the petitions, challenge is to the selection made
            <lb />
            by the Chhattisgarh Public Service Commission (hereinafter called &apos;the
            <lb />
            Commission&apos;) in the Public Service Commission Examination for the year
            <lb />
            2003 on various grounds.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            2.
            <lb />
            The undisputed facts are that the Commission issued an
            <lb />
            advertisement on 04.07.2003 inviting applications for 177 posts in the
            <lb />
            said Civil Services ranging from Deputy Superintendent of Police to Sub
            <lb />
            Inspector (Excise Department). The test was to be conducted in three
            <lb />
            parts viz. preliminary examination, main examination and interview. The
            <lb />
            preliminary examination consists of two papers of objective type. The
            <lb />
            main examination consists of seven papers of conventional type
            <lb />
            questions and the interview was to carry 250 marks. The preliminary
            <lb />
            examination was conducted on 21.12.2003. Thereafter, the main
            <lb />
            examination was conducted. The Petitioners were called for interview but
            <lb />
            their names did not find place in the final merit list. They sought certain
            <lb />
            information from the Commission and thereafter filed the present writ
            <lb />
            petitions.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            3.
            <lb />
            The allegations of the Petitioners in a nutshell are that the selection
            <lb />
            process of the Commission is full of irregularities, corruption and
            <lb />
            mistakes. At every stage of the examination, there has been bungling
            <lb />
            and corruption, and as such, the entire selection process needs to be
            <lb />
            quashed. The Petitioners firstly submit that the question papers of the
            <lb />
            main examination were not properly marked and they have attempted to
            <lb />
            show that the marking is highly improper. By drawing the attention of this
            <lb />
            Court to certain answer-papers, it is submitted that since the marking at
            <lb />
            this stage is improper, the answer sheets of all the candidates who
            <lb />
            appeared in the main examination should be got evaluated again.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            4.
            <lb />
            The second submission is that the Commission followed a system
            <lb />
            of scaling. It outsourced scaling to some other agency namely Noybl Lab.
            <lb />
            According to the Petitioners, the scaling has not been done properly. They
            <lb />
            have pointed out various instances where the persons having the same
            <lb />
            raw marks have been given different marks after scaling. Scaling has to
            <lb />
            be done according to a mathematical formula and if the raw marks are
            <lb />
            same, the marks after scaling cannot be different.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            5.
            <lb />
            The next submission is that the scaling was also improper because
            <lb />
            if a particular paper was attempted by a candidate as a first option and he
            <lb />
            got &apos;x&apos; number of marks before scaling, after scaling he was given &apos;y&apos;
            <lb />
            number of marks. However, if any candidate attempted the same paper in
            <lb />
            the same subject not as first option but as second option and got the
            <lb />
            same marks i.e. &apos;x&apos; then he was not given &apos;y&apos; marks and was totally given
            <lb />
            different marks i.e. &apos;z&apos; marks. This according to the Petitioners, clearly
            <lb />
            shows that scaling was improper.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            6.
            <lb />
            The Petitioners also submit that in the subject of Anthropology, two
            <lb />
            different methods were followed for evaluating the same paper. The
            <lb />
            Petitioners have placed reliance on the statement of charges of
            <lb />
            misconduct Dr. B.P. Kashyap, Examination Controller of the Commission
            <lb />
            in this regard. In the paper of Anthropology, papers of some candidates
            <lb />
            were evaluated by only evaluating 4 answers with each carrying a value
            <lb />
            of 75 marks and in case of some other candidates, five answers were
            <lb />
            evaluated out of which two were evaluated against 75 marks and other
            <lb />
            three were evaluated against 50 marks. In the second paper of
            <lb />
            Anthropology, question No. 8 was found fit to be cancelled. In some
            <lb />
            cases, despite question No. 8 being found fit to be cancelled, marks were
            <lb />
            awarded against question No. 8 and in some cases, no such marks were
            <lb />
            awarded.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            7.
            <lb />
            Further allegation of Ku. Varsha Dongre is that Scheduled Caste
            <lb />
            candidates who had got selected on their own merits without taking
            <lb />
            benefit of reservation were wrongly adjusted in the Scheduled Caste
            <lb />
            category list. Her prayer is that they should have been given appointment
            <lb />
            out of general category.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            8.
            <lb />
            The Petitioners have also pointed out various interpolations and
            <lb />
            manipulations in the selection process and prayed that the entire
            <lb />
            selection process be quashed.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            9.
            <lb />
            The writ petitions were contested by the State Government,
            <lb />
            Chhattisgarh Public Service Commission and the selected private
            <lb />
            Respondents on various grounds. However, at the time of arguments, it
            <lb />
            was not disputed that the scaling was highly improper. Virtually, most of
            <lb />
            the averments made by the Petitioners were admitted by the Commission.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            10.
            <lb />
            Mainly, the stand of the Respondents is that both the writ petitions
            <lb />
            are belated and in the second petition i.e. Writ Petition No. 3028 of 2006
            <lb />
            filed by Shri Chaman Lal Sinha and Ravindra Singh, all the selected
            <lb />
            candidates have not been arrayed as party-Respondents and therefore,
            <lb />
            the writ petitions deserve to be rejected.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            11.
            <lb />
            It is next contended that one petition being Writ Petition No. 4852
            <lb />
            of 2006 arising out of the same selection process, filed by Santosh Kumar
            <lb />
            Kunjan, has been rejected by the learned Single Judge on 16.7.2013 and
            <lb />
            the appeal being Writ Appeal No. 592 of 2013 has also been rejected, and
            <lb />
            as such, no relief can be granted to the present Petitioners.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            12.
            <lb />
            Few of the private Respondents have half-heartedly challenged the
            <lb />
            allegations made by the Petitioners, especially Petitioner-Ku.Varsha
            <lb />
            Dongre, but it is apparent from the latest written submissions made by the
            <lb />
            Commission that it stands virtually admitted that the selection process
            <lb />
            was totally illegal and full of errors. The stand of the private Respondents
            <lb />
            is that they are working for almost 10 years now and therefore no relief
            <lb />
            should be granted against them.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            13.
            <lb />
            At the outset, I may first deal with the preliminary objections.
        </p>
        <lb />
        <head>
            Are the Writ Petitions belated?
            <lb />
        </head>

        <p>
            14.
            <lb />
            The first preliminary objection is that the writ petitions are belated.
            <lb />
            At the outset, reference may be made to Rule 18 of the State Service
            <lb />
            Examination Rules which reads as follows:
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;The Commission shall not provide the list of marks for
            <lb />
            preliminary examination because that is only a screening
            <lb />
            examination. No correspondence in this regard will be
            <lb />
            entertained. However, the marks obtained in the main
            <lb />
            examination shall be provided to the candidates after the final
            <lb />
            result is declared.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            15.
            <lb />
            Reliance placed by the Respondents on G.C.Gupta &amp; Others v.
            <lb />
            N.K.Pandey &amp; Others {(1988) 1 SCC 316}; S.S. Balu &amp; Another v. State
            <lb />
            of Kerala &amp; Others (AIR 2009 SC 1994) and Esha Bhattacharjee v.
            <lb />
            Managing Committee of Raghunathpur Nafar Academy &amp; Others {(2013)
            <lb />
            12 SCC 649} is totally misplaced. In my view, there is no delay in filing the
            <lb />
            writ petitions. It is the Respondents who are guilty of trying to delay the
            <lb />
            matter and derail the judicial process. G.C.Gupta (supra) was not a case
            <lb />
            of gross illegality or criminal activity. In this regard reliance has also been
            <lb />
            placed on State of M.P. and Others v. Nandlal Jaiswal &amp; Others (AIR
            <lb />
            1987 SC 251) in which the Apex Court observed as follows:
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;23. Now, it is well settled that power of the High Court to
            <lb />
            issue an appropriate writ under Article 226 of the
            <lb />
            Constitution is discretionary and the High Court in the
            <lb />
            exercise of its discretion does not ordinarily assist the tardy
            <lb />
            and the indolent or the acquiescent and the lethargic. If there
            <lb />
            is inordinate delay on the part of the petitioner in filing a writ
            <lb />
            petition and such delay is not satisfactorily explained, the
            <lb />
            high Court may decline to intervene and grant relief in the
            <lb />
            exercise of its writ jurisdiction. The evolution of this rule of
            <lb />
            laches or delay is premised upon a number of factors. The
            <lb />
            high Court does not ordinarily permit a belated resort to the
            <lb />
            extraordinary remedy under the writ jurisdiction because it is
            <lb />
            likely to cause confusion and public inconvenience and bring
            <lb />
            in its train new injustices. The rights of third parties may
            <lb />
            intervene and if the writ jurisdiction is exercised on a writ
            <lb />
            petition filed after unreasonable delay, it may have the effect
            <lb />
            of inflicting not only hardship and inconvenience but also
            <lb />
            injustice on third parties. When the writ jurisdiction of the
            <lb />
            High Court is invoked, unexplained delay coupled with the
            <lb />
            creation of third party rights in the meanwhile is an important
            <lb />
            factor which always weights with the High Court in deciding
            <lb />
            whether or not to exercise such jurisdiction. We do not think
            <lb />
            it necessary to burden this judgement with reference to
            <lb />
            various decisions of this Court where it has been emphasised
            <lb />
            time and again that where there is inordinate and unexplained
            <lb />
            delay and third party rights are created in the intervening
            <lb />
            period, the High Court would decline to interfere, even if the
            <lb />
            State action complained of is unconstitutional or illegal. We
            <lb />
            may only mention in the passing two decisions of this Court
            <lb />
            one in Ramanna Dayaram Shetty v. International Airport
            <lb />
            Authority of India (1979) 3 SCR 1014 : (AIR 1979 SC 1628)
            <lb />
            and the other in Ashok Kumar v. Collector, Raipur (1989) 1
            <lb />
            SCR 491 : (AIR 1980 SC 112). We may point out that in
            <lb />
            R.D.Shetty&apos;s case (supra) even though the State action was
            <lb />
            held to be unconstitutional as being violative of Article 14 of
            <lb />
            the Constitution, this Court refused to grant relief to the
            <lb />
            petitioner on the ground that the writ petition had been filed
            <lb />
            by the petitioner more than five months after the acceptance
            <lb />
            of the tender of the fourth respondent and during that period,
            <lb />
            the fourth respondent had incurred considerable expenditure,
            <lb />
            aggregating to about Rs. 1.25 lakhs, in making arrangements
            <lb />
            for putting up the restaurant and the snack bar. Of course, this
            <lb />
            rule of laches or delay is not a rigid rule which can be caste in
            <lb />
            a straitjacket formula, for there may be cases where despite
            <lb />
            delay and creation of third party rights the High Court may
            <lb />
            still in the exercise of its discretion interfere and grant relief
            <lb />
            to the petitioner. But such cases where the demand of justice
            <lb />
            is so compelling that the High Court would be inclined to
            <lb />
            interfere in spite of delay or creation of third party rights
            <lb />
            would be their very nature be few and far between.
            <lb />
            Ultimately it would be a matter within the discretion of the
            <lb />
            Court; ex hypothesi every discretion must be exercised fairly
            <lb />
            and justly so as to promote justice and not to defeat it. &quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            16.
            <lb />
            In the present case, the interviews were conducted on 17.06.2005
            <lb />
            and the final result was declared on 24.08.2005. However, the marks
            <lb />
            were not provided to the candidates. In fact, writ petitioner-Ku. Varsha
            <lb />
            Dongre was compelled to file Writ Petition No. 6256 of 2005 in which one
            <lb />
            of the grounds raised by her was that marks have not been provided/
            <lb />
            published. During pendency of this petition, the mark-sheet was provided
            <lb />
            to the Petitioner-Ku. Varsha Dongre on 23.06.2006 and thereafter, she
            <lb />
            withdrew the writ petition on 5.7.2006 and filed the present writ petition on
            <lb />
            29.07.2006. The writ petition has been filed within a month of the mark-
            <lb />
            sheet being provided. The second writ petition i.e. Writ Petition No. 3028
            <lb />
            of 2006 was also filed on 26.6.2006 itself. Therefore, in my view, both the
            <lb />
            writ petitions were filed well within time and cannot be said to be belated
            <lb />
            and the preliminary objection is overruled.
            <lb />
        </p>
        <head>
            All the Selected Candidates have not been arrayed as
            <lb />
            party-Respondents
            <lb />
        </head>

        <p>
            17.
            <lb />
            The second preliminary objection is that all the selected candidates
            <lb />
            have not been arrayed as party-Respondents, especially in Writ Petition
            <lb />
            No. 3028 of 2006. As far as Writ Petition No. 4028 of 2006 filed by Ku.
            <lb />
            Varsha Dongre is concerned, all the selected candidates were arrayed as
            <lb />
            party-Respondents at the initial stage itself. As far as Writ Petition No.
            <lb />
            3028 of 2006 is concerned, all the selected candidates were not arrayed
            <lb />
            as party-Respondents at the initial stage. However, it would be pertinent
            <lb />
            to mention that on 18.07.2007, this Court passed a detailed order, which
            <lb />
            reads as follows:
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;The respondents No. 2 and 3/Public Service
            <lb />
            Commission (for short &apos;the PSC&apos;) states in its reply
            <lb />
            dated 4.5.2007, as under:
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            &quot;In the preliminary enquiry after receipt of the
            <lb />
            complaints it is found that the computer agency has
            <lb />
            adopted a defective scaling pattern because the
            <lb />
            computer agency has scaled the marks obtained in
            <lb />
            4 questions papers of optional subjects separately
            <lb />
            and on the basis of options chosen by the
            <lb />
            candidates. This defect in scaling has taken place
            <lb />
            because different candidates may opt one particular
            <lb />
            subject either as first option or as second option,
            <lb />
            therefore, in view of the method of scaling adopted
            <lb />
            by the computer agency candidates securing
            <lb />
            similar marks in question paper of a given subject
            <lb />
            but as option one or two has been awarded
            <lb />
            different scaled numbers. The value obtained by
            <lb />
            this method of scaling for different values -like M,
            <lb />
            S, m, s has been calculated in a wrongful manner.&quot;
        </item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            It is further case of the respondents No. 2 and 3 that
            <lb />
            the PSC has recommended 147 candidates for
            <lb />
            appointment in the service and they have been
            <lb />
            wrongly appointed.
        </item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            In view of the fact that the irregularities committed in
            <lb />
            the selection process has been admitted by the PSC, it
            <lb />
            is, therefore, necessary to issue to all the selected
            <lb />
            candidates, who, as a result of this examination, have
            <lb />
            been recommended for appointment and thereafter
            <lb />
            have been appointed.
        </item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            The PSC is directed to issue notice to all the selected
            <lb />
            candidates, stating that the dispute with regard to their
            <lb />
            selection, involving irregularity in the examination, is
            <lb />
            pending consideration before this Court and the
            <lb />
            selected candidates may file their reply in the pending
            <lb />
            matter within a period of three weeks. The needful be
            <lb />
            done within a period of one week.
        </item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            Respective respondents/Interveners are granted two
            <lb />
            weeks time as a last opportunity to file return/reply,
            <lb />
            failing which it may be presumed that they have
            <lb />
            nothing to say in the petition.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            List it on 22 nd August, 2007 for final hearing.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            18.
            <lb />
            The following authorities, Prashant Ramesh Chakkarwar v. Union
            <lb />
            Public service Commission &amp; Others {(2013) 12 SCC 489}; Jiten Kumar
            <lb />
            Saho &amp; Others v. Chief General Manager, Mahanadi Coalfields Limited &amp;
            <lb />
            Others {(2011) 11 SCC 520); Ku. Rashmi Mishra v. M.P Public Service
            <lb />
            Commission &amp; Others {(2006) 12 SCC 724}; K.H. Siraj v. High Court of
            <lb />
            Kerala and Others {(2006) 6 SCC 395} relied upon by the Respondents
            <lb />
            are not relevant since this Court has come to the conclusion that all the
            <lb />
            relevant parties are arrayed as Respondents in this case.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            19.
            <lb />
            This Court had directed that notices be issued to all the selected
            <lb />
            candidates and they were informed that the writ petition relating to
            <lb />
            irregularities in the examination is pending consideration before this Court
            <lb />
            and they were given time to file reply to the petition. Therefore, this
            <lb />
            preliminary objection is without any basis and is also rejected.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <head>
            Writ Petitions are hit by the principles of res-judicata
            <lb />
        </head>

        <p>
            20.
            <lb />
            The third preliminary objection is that the writ petitions are hit by
            <lb />
            the principles of res-judicata. In this behalf, it would be pertinent to
            <lb />
            mention that one other person namely Santosh Kumar Kunjan had filed
            <lb />
            Writ Petition No. 4852 of 2006 in which also he has challenged the
            <lb />
            selection made but at that stage, he had not impleaded all the selected
            <lb />
            candidates as party-Respondents. The said writ petition was rejected on
            <lb />
            16.07.2013 on the ground that the successful candidates, who have been
            <lb />
            in service for long time, had not been impleaded as party-Respondents
            <lb />
            despite sufficient opportunity granted to the Petitioner. Writ Appeal filed
            <lb />
            against the said order was also dismissed on similar grounds. It would be
            <lb />
            pertinent to mention that in the appeal, the Appellant had sought to
            <lb />
            implead two other persons as party-Respondents but the Court did not
            <lb />
            allow the prayer since more than seven years had already elapsed since
            <lb />
            they had been appointed. In my view, this is not a judgment in rem and
            <lb />
            this is a judgment in personem. No issue has been decided on merits and
            <lb />
            all that has been held is that since all the selected candidates have not
            <lb />
            been impleaded, no relief can be granted to the Petitioner. That is not the
            <lb />
            situation in the present writ petitions and as such, the preliminary
            <lb />
            objection is overruled.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            21.
            <lb />
            Some of the Respondents have taken hyper technical objection
            <lb />
            that there are no pleadings against the private Respondents and the
            <lb />
            challenge is only to the select list and not to the appointment issued. In
            <lb />
            my view, this objection has been taken only for the purpose of being
            <lb />
            rejected. In a case where gross irregularities have been brought to light,
            <lb />
            the Court cannot shirk its constitutional duty to ensure that rule of law is
            <lb />
            followed. Reliance placed on Amlan Jyoti Borooah v. State of Assam &amp;
            <lb />
            Others {(2009) 3 SCC 227} and State of Madhya Pradesh v. Narmada
            <lb />
            Bachao Andolan and Another {(2011) 7 SCC 639} is totally misplaced.
            <lb />
            Factual Matrix
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            22.
            <lb />
            Coming to the merits of the case, before going into detailed
            <lb />
            discussion of the matter, it would be pertinent to mention certain facts.
            <lb />
            Petitioner-Ku. Varsha Dongre had been complaining to all the authorities
            <lb />
            that there had been large scale corruption and bungling in this
            <lb />
            examination. As usual, she did not receive any response from most of the
            <lb />
            authorities. It would be pertinent to mention that even before she was
            <lb />
            given the mark-sheet, on 16.07.2006, she had filed complaints to many
            <lb />
            authorities including His Excellency the Governor, Hon&apos;ble the Chief
            <lb />
            Minister, Chhattisgarh Public Service Commission and the Inspector
            <lb />
            General of Police, Anti Corruption Bureau, Raipur alleging large scale of
            <lb />
            bungling and corruption in the selection process. She had clearly
            <lb />
            mentioned that the mark-sheets are not being provided to the candidates.
            <lb />
            She alleged that though she belonged to the Scheduled Caste category,
            <lb />
            and even as per the Commission, she had been given 1290 marks but
            <lb />
            she had not been offered appointment though Scheduled Caste
            <lb />
            candidates below her in merit had been offered appointment. She also
            <lb />
            complained that whenever she applied for information to the Commission
            <lb />
            under the Right to Information Act, 2005, the same was refused on one
            <lb />
            pretext or the other. She also alleged that Shri Khela Ram Jangde was
            <lb />
            acting as head of the Commission and his daughter Santan Devi had
            <lb />
            been selected as Deputy Collector. She also raised many other issues.
            <lb />
            On 29.05.2006, she was informed by the Commission that after enquiry,
            <lb />
            it was found that there was no merit in her allegations and the matter was
            <lb />
            closed. Similar reply was sent by the Commission to the office of Hon&apos;ble
            <lb />
            Chief Minister. It appears that Petitioner-Ku. Varsha Dongre also made a
            <lb />
            complaint to the Hon&apos;ble President of India. It is apparent from the record
            <lb />
            that the Secretary to the Hon&apos;ble President of India sent the complaint of
            <lb />
            the Petitioner to the State on 23.02.2006 and the State Government was
            <lb />
            asked to look into the matter. The Petitioner kept applying to the
            <lb />
            Commission for information under the Right to Information Act but on one
            <lb />
            excuse or the other, her request was rejected. The answer given by the
            <lb />
            Commission to her was that there were no mistakes or irregularities in the
            <lb />
            selection process.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            23.
            <lb />
            However, the Anti Corruption Bureau carried out detailed
            <lb />
            investigation and in its investigation report dated 02.06.2007 found a lot of
            <lb />
            irregularities. These irregularities were brought to the notice of His
            <lb />
            Excellency the Governor who asked the State to take further action in the
            <lb />
            matter. Reference in this behalf may be made to the letter sent by the
            <lb />
            Secretary to the His Excellency the Governor of Chhattisgarh to the
            <lb />
            Secretary, General Administration Department, Government of
            <lb />
            Chhattisgarh, Raipur on 12.06.2007, which reads as follows:
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;To,</item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            The Secretary,
            <lb />
            General Administration Deptt.,
            <lb />
            Government of Chhattisgarh,
            <lb />
            Mantralaya,
            <lb />
            Raipur.
        </item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            Sub: Investigation report of ACB on CPSC Exam 2003</item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            Ref: IG, ACB Raipur&apos;s confidential letter No. IG/ACB/
            <lb />
            323/2007 dated June 2, 2007.
        </item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            In view of the discrepancies pointed out by the ACB in
            <lb />
            its investigation report dated 2.6.2007, pendency of the case in
            <lb />
            the Court which may take time to conclude and the fact that
            <lb />
            the petitioner has a strong case in her favour, HE. the
            <lb />
            Governor is of the view that the PSC cold approach the Court
            <lb />
            and make a prayer that in the light of the ACB&apos;s findings and
            <lb />
            their own internal audit bringing out some flaws, they would
            <lb />
            like to revise the entire result within a time frame of three
            <lb />
            months and shall adopt such measures to undergo the wrongs
            <lb />
            and thereafter fix responsibility. H.E. also believes that merely
            <lb />
            awaiting the outcome of the Court case will only result in
            <lb />
            undue delay and cost to the petitioners.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            I have been directed to communicate the above views of
            <lb />
            H.E. the Governor for consideration and decision taken in this
            <lb />
            regard may be communicated to us accordingly.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            Sd/-
            <lb />
            Joint Secretary to Governor.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            24.
            <lb />
            The aforesaid letter clearly indicates that the His Excellency the
            <lb />
            Governor had found the complaint of the Petitioner to be genuine and
            <lb />
            directed the Commission to approach the Court with a prayer that in light
            <lb />
            of the Anti Corruption Bureau&apos;s report, they themselves should correct
            <lb />
            their wrong doings.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            25.
            <lb />
            The report of the Anti Corruption Bureau was made available to the
            <lb />
            Petitioner only in the year 2013. This report is a very detailed report. It
            <lb />
            would be pertinent to make reference to certain portions of the report. The
            <lb />
            first relevant portion of the report is as follows:
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;(1) Non selection of 3 candidates obtaining higher marks.
            <lb />
            The final selection list of Civil Services Exam 2003 conducted
            <lb />
            by C.G.P.S.C. was published on 24.07.2005. Despite obtaining
            <lb />
            higher marks, 1. Ku. Varsha Dongre 2. Shri Pradeep Kumar
            <lb />
            Bhoi and 3. Ku. Manisha Daheriya were not selected whereas
            <lb />
            candidates who obtained marks less than them were selected.
            <lb />
            This is prima facie proved from the joint merit list prepared by
            <lb />
            C.G.P.S.C. The joint merit list (Annexure-1) with respect to all
            <lb />
            3 candidates is quoted as follows in the table below:-
            <lb />
        </item>

        <head>
            Ku. Varsha Dongre
            <lb />
        </head>

        <table>
            Sl.
            <lb />
            No.
            <lb />
            Name
            <lb />
            of
            <lb />
            candidate
            <lb />
            No. of
            <lb />
            joint
            <lb />
            merit
            <lb />
            list
            <lb />
            Roll No. Total
            <lb />
            obtained
            <lb />
            marks
            <lb />
            Post for which
            <lb />
            selected
            <lb />
            Category
            <lb />
            1.
            <lb />
            Varsha
            <lb />
            Dongre
            <lb />
            183
            <lb />
            53443 1290.41 Not Selected
            <lb />
            S.C
            <lb />
            2.
            <lb />
            Mahendra
            <lb />
            Kuldeep
            <lb />
            209
            <lb />
            55730 1277.35 Excise
            <lb />
            Sub-
            <lb />
            Inspector
            <lb />
            S.C.
            <lb />
            3.
            <lb />
            Manoj
            <lb />
            Laroker
            <lb />
            210
            <lb />
            41697 1267.88 Excise
            <lb />
            Sub-
            <lb />
            Inspector
            <lb />
            S.C.
            <lb />
            4.
            <lb />
            Usha kiran
            <lb />
            Barai
            <lb />
            214
            <lb />
            27187 1274.51 Asst. Director,
            <lb />
            Public Relation
            <lb />
            S.C.
            <lb />
            5.
            <lb />
            Sarika
            <lb />
            Ramteke
            <lb />
            217
            <lb />
            41275 1273.23 Nayab
            <lb />
            Tahsildar
            <lb />
            S.C.
            <lb />
            6.
            <lb />
            Sunil Kumar 237
            <lb />
            20953 1268.03 Excise
            <lb />
            Sub-
            <lb />
            Inspector
            <lb />
            S.C.&quot;
            <lb />
        </table>

        <p>
            26.
            <lb />
            With regard to the allegations of the Petitioner that her preference
            <lb />
            form has been manipulated, forged and tampered at the level of the
            <lb />
            Commission and that she had given a preference for being appointed as
            <lb />
            Excise Sub Inspector, the relevant portion of the Anti Corruption Bureau&apos;s
            <lb />
            report is as follows:
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;In the case of candidates who have cut the column of posts
            <lb />
            after filling them, no determined code number have been
            <lb />
            mentioned by the Commission in those columns of posts,
            <lb />
            where as code AEXI has been mentioned in the column of
            <lb />
            post of Excise Sub Inspector in agramanyata patrak of
            <lb />
            Ku. Varsha Dongre. From the above evidence it is prima
            <lb />
            facie proved that Ku. Varsha Dongre did not cut this post in
            <lb />
            agaramanyata patrak but any or some of the public servants
            <lb />
            of the Commission itself later cut this post in furtherance of
            <lb />
            some criminal conspiracy.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (iii) Agramanyata patrak of 29 candidates, who all appeared
            <lb />
            for interview of Scheduled Caste Category, were duly seized
            <lb />
            and sent to Government Disputed Documents Examiner,
            <lb />
            Government of C.G., on the basis of report received from
            <lb />
            whom, it is proved that hand writing of Ku. Varsha Dongre
            <lb />
            and the tint as well as texture of line drawn by herself is
            <lb />
            different from the line cut on the column of post of Excise
            <lb />
            Sub-Inspector.
        </item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            It is also mentioned in the report of Government Disputed
            <lb />
            Documents Examiner that impression of cut on this post has
            <lb />
            also appeared in agramanyata patrak of other candidates kept
            <lb />
            below which is only possible on keeping all
            <lb />
            agramanyatapatrak together. Appearance of same cutting
            <lb />
            impression in the sheets of some other candidates is not
            <lb />
            possible if a candidate cuts only on his sheets. Report of
            <lb />
            Government Disputed Documents Examiner Government of
            <lb />
            C.G. is annexed as Annexure-4.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            27.
            <lb />
            The Anti Corruption Bureau also reported that the Petitioner-
            <lb />
            Ku. Varsha Dongre had met Hon&apos;ble the Chief Minister to complain about
            <lb />
            the irregularities, but when the Hon&apos;ble Chief Minister asked the
            <lb />
            Commission to enquire into the same, the reply given was that there were
            <lb />
            no irregularities. The Hon&apos;ble Chief Minister was informed that Ku. Varsha
            <lb />
            Dongre had less marks. The Anti Corruption Bureau in its report found
            <lb />
            that this communication of the Commission was totally false and
            <lb />
            reference may be made to the relevant portion of the report, which reads
            <lb />
            as follows:
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;Ku. Varsha Dongre sent the complaint in same matter to His
            <lb />
            Excellency the President and the Government of India,
            <lb />
            Personnel Public Grievances and pension Ministry, New
            <lb />
            Delhi sent letter to the Secretary of the Commission on
            <lb />
            03.10.06 for appropriate action (Annexure 8).
        </item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            The said letter has been dealt in page no. 3 to 7 of File no.
            <lb />
            65/05/P on the note-sheet of C.G. P.S.C. In this note sheet, it
            <lb />
            is admitted in point no. 01 and 02 of the Official comment of
            <lb />
            Commission that obtained marks of Ku. Varsha Dongre is
            <lb />
            higher than Ku. Usha Kiran Borai, selected for the post of
            <lb />
            Asst. Director Public Relation, and Ku. Sarika Ramteke,
            <lb />
            selected for the post of Nayab Tehsildar, and this female
            <lb />
            candidate has even given preference in the &apos;agra manyata
            <lb />
            patrak&apos; for these posts. It is even clearly mentioned in point
            <lb />
            no. 2 of said note-sheet of commission that possibly Ku.
            <lb />
            Varsha Dongre was to be selected on the post of Nayab
            <lb />
            Tehsildar, but Smt. R. Shandilya, Examination Controller on
            <lb />
            31.10.06, advised the commission not to do so as is evident
            <lb />
            from her not which reads as follows:
        </item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            &quot;Complainant Ku. Varsha Dongre has filed writ petition
            <lb />
            before the High Court of C.G. regarding irregularity in the
            <lb />
            result of State Civil Services Exam 2003. The matter being
            <lb />
            pending no action can be taken at the Commission level as
            <lb />
            per rule.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            28.
            <lb />
            The Anti Corruption Bureau&apos;s report also makes the following
            <lb />
            startling revelations, which reads as follows:
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;(5) Selection of candidate of unreserved category showing
            <lb />
            him as candidate of Scheduled Caste Category.
            <lb />
            10 Posts have been reserved in State Accounts Services. In
            <lb />
            the Selection list, at Sl. No. 11, Shri Rajeev Singh Chouhan,
            <lb />
            Roll No. 31106 who belongs to unreserved category,
            <lb />
            selection was not possible but showing him as SC category,
            <lb />
            he has been selected in this category though Shri Rajeev
            <lb />
            Singh has mentioned himself as candidate of unreserved
            <lb />
            category. Thus, the candidate of unreserved category has been
            <lb />
            selected against the post reserved for SC candidate instead of
            <lb />
            the candidate belonging to SC category(Annexure 23).
            <lb />
            According to Supplementary list, Shri Jeetendra Nagesh
            <lb />
            should have been selected.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            29.
            <lb />
            With regard to errors in scaling, the report of the Anti Corruption
            <lb />
            Bureau is very clear that the scaling was highly improper and to highlight
            <lb />
            these facts, reference may be made to the chart prepared by the Anti
            <lb />
            Corruption Bureau, which is as follows:
        </p>
        <lb />
        <table>
            No Roll
            <lb />
            no.
            <lb />
            Name
            <lb />
            Subject
            <lb />
            Code
            <lb />
            Actual
            <lb />
            Obtained mark
            <lb />
            in the subject
            <lb />
            prior to scaling
            <lb />
            Marks
            <lb />
            obtained
            <lb />
            after
            <lb />
            scaling
            <lb />
            1. 16834 Jitendra Nagesh
            <lb />
            23
            <lb />
            200
            <lb />
            170.01
            <lb />
            2. 40912 Chaman Lal
            <lb />
            23
            <lb />
            200
            <lb />
            205.68
            <lb />
            3. 77632 Durgesh Diwedi
            <lb />
            23
            <lb />
            200
            <lb />
            196.74
            <lb />
            4. 52522 Avanti Gupta
            <lb />
            23
            <lb />
            200
            <lb />
            201.28
            <lb />
            8. 20290 Rajesh Kumar
            <lb />
            Dewangan
            <lb />
            23
            <lb />
            200
            <lb />
            201.28
            <lb />
            9. 21115 Deep Mahish
            <lb />
            17
            <lb />
            169
            <lb />
            185.24
            <lb />
            10. 21020 Ajay Kesharwani
            <lb />
            17
            <lb />
            169
            <lb />
            172.60
            <lb />
            11. 83649 Prakhar Sharma
            <lb />
            18
            <lb />
            140
            <lb />
            144.44
            <lb />
            12. 97641 Smita Kumari
            <lb />
            18
            <lb />
            140
            <lb />
            134.47
            <lb />
        </table>

        <p>
            30.
            <lb />
            From the aforesaid chart, it is apparent that all the candidates who
            <lb />
            had appeared in one paper having code No. 23 had obtained 200 marks
            <lb />
            from the examiner and after scaling their marks should have been same.
            <lb />
            However, the marks ranged from 170.01 to 239.22. Therefore, though, the
            <lb />
            raw marks i.e. marks awarded by the examiner were 200, after scaling,
            <lb />
            one candidate at Roll No. 16834 was awarded only 170.01 marks
            <lb />
            whereas a candidate having Roll No. 102526 was awarded 239.22 marks.
            <lb />
            This shows that scaling was done in an unscientific and illegal manner. It
            <lb />
            appears marks were granted after scaling at the whims and fancies of
            <lb />
            officials in the Commission. The Anti Corruption Bureau found that there
            <lb />
            is corruption and bungling at all the stages. However, the Commission did
            <lb />
            not correct its own mistakes which are admitted and this raises doubts
            <lb />
            with regard to working of the Commission itself. The Anti Corruption
            <lb />
            Bureau also found that the Commission was aware about these large
            <lb />
            scale irregularities in the scaling for a long time but it has not taken any
            <lb />
            action. Reference may be made to the following portion of the report of
            <lb />
            the Anti Corruption Bureau:
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;The aforesaid irregularities are clear from the naked eyes.
            <lb />
            Approval of such results even then by the commission itself
            <lb />
            put question marks on the procedure of commission.
            <lb />
            It is in the knowledge of C.G. Public Service Commission
            <lb />
            since long that irregularities of large scale has been
            <lb />
            committed in scaling due to which they have played with the
            <lb />
            future of eligible candidates. The commission had issued
            <lb />
            direction to the company who prepared result, in respect of
            <lb />
            irregularities occurred in scaling, to correct the irregularities
            <lb />
            in scaling. Thereafter, the Commission in its letter dated
            <lb />
            20/07/2006 written to company has admitted that in a fresh
            <lb />
            scaling, change has been occurred in marks of almost all
            <lb />
            candidates. (Annexure-26), but this pious constitution body
            <lb />
            inspite of being bounded by Constitution and law has not
            <lb />
            initiated proceeding to provide justice to the candidates even
            <lb />
            after 9 months.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            31.
            <lb />
            The Anti Corruption Bureau found that there were 17 such
            <lb />
            candidates who were not entitled to be selected. It also found that there
            <lb />
            were 17 candidates who were entitled to be selected but were not
            <lb />
            selected. It also found that if proper scaling is done, then 56 candidates
            <lb />
            who were selected would be given a post in some other service. It also
            <lb />
            found that there were 52 candidates who were eligible for being called for
            <lb />
            interview but were not called for interview. Instead of 52 candidates who
            <lb />
            were not eligible and were lower in merit were called for interview. In this
            <lb />
            behalf, reference may be made to the relevant portion of the report of the
            <lb />
            Anti Corruption Bureau, which reads as under:
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;(I) 17 such candidates, who have been selected in various
            <lb />
            post by C.G. Public Service Commission are not eligible for
            <lb />
            selection (Annexure-A)
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (II) 17 such candidates are eligible for selection but they
            <lb />
            were not selected earlier in any post by C.G. PSC (Annexure
            <lb />
            B).
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (III) Posts of 56 such candidates, who have been selected by
            <lb />
            C.G. Public service commission will change on the basis of
            <lb />
            merit due to difference of marks occurred by new scaling
            <lb />
            (Annexure C).
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (IV) 52 such candidates have been found, who were not
            <lb />
            called for interview by CGPSC and 52 ineligible candidates
            <lb />
            were called for interview in place of them (Annexure-D).&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            32.
            <lb />
            At this stage, it would be pertinent to mention that after the letter
            <lb />
            was sent from the Secretariat of His Excellency the Governor that the
            <lb />
            Commission itself should rectify its own mistakes and should approach
            <lb />
            the High Court for permission to do so, the Commission filed an
            <lb />
            application being IA No. 1 in Writ Petition No. 3028 of 2006. The relevant
            <lb />
            portion of the application reads as follows:
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;2. In the return filed by the respondents No. 2 &amp; 3, it
            <lb />
            has been stated that the scaling formula applied by the
            <lb />
            Commission is correct, however there were mistakes
            <lb />
            committed by the Computer Agency engaged by the
            <lb />
            Commission for conducting the scaling work. It has
            <lb />
            also been stated that in case a detailed enquiry is
            <lb />
            conducted and the results are declared afresh, it will
            <lb />
            have wide implications, therefore, Public Service
            <lb />
            Commission is awaiting result of the instant writ
            <lb />
            petition.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            3. That, the CG Public Service Commission, in order to
            <lb />
            remove any suspicion from the minds of candidates
            <lb />
            who have appeared in the examination, is willing to
            <lb />
            conduct re-totaling, decoding, data entry, scaling
            <lb />
            preparation of list for interview in the ratio of 1:3 by
            <lb />
            observing reservation rules, identifying the fresh
            <lb />
            eligible and ineligible candidates, submission of list
            <lb />
            before the Hon&apos;ble Court, conduct of interview of such
            <lb />
            candidates who will become eligible afresh, preparation
            <lb />
            of overall merit list, allotment of post on the basis of
            <lb />
            preference and merit and lastly submission of revised
            <lb />
            select list before this Hon&apos;ble Court, as detailed in the
            <lb />
            particulars of proceedings filed herewith as Annexure
            <lb />
            D/1.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            4. That, for the above quoted proceedings the CG
            <lb />
            Public Service Commission needs at least 4 months
            <lb />
            time, however, since the matter is pending before this
            <lb />
            Hon&apos;ble Court, CG Public Service Commission is
            <lb />
            seeking permission before this Hon&apos;ble Court to take up
            <lb />
            the proceedings as per Annexure D-1 and inform this
            <lb />
            Hon&apos;ble Court accordingly, in the interest of justice and
            <lb />
            in public interest. &quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            33.
            <lb />
            From the reply filed by the Commission on 04.05.2007 and the
            <lb />
            application IA No. 1, filed on 19.06.2007, it is apparent that the
            <lb />
            Commission itself had admitted as far back as June 2007 that there were
            <lb />
            mistakes in the selection process which it wanted to rectify. However, the
            <lb />
            Commission made no reference to the report of the Anti Corruption
            <lb />
            Bureau. On this application (IA No. 1), this Court passed the following
            <lb />
            order on 26.10.2007, which reads as under:
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;This is an application on behalf of Chhattisgarh
            <lb />
            Public Service Commission seeking direction to
            <lb />
            rectify the mistakes committed.
        </item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            We are of the considered opinion that no permission
            <lb />
            is required from this Court to rectify the mistakes. It
            <lb />
            would be open to the Chhattisgarh Public Service
            <lb />
            Commission to rectify any inherent mistake
            <lb />
            committed. However, the same would be subject to
            <lb />
            final decision of this petition.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            34.
            <lb />
            This Court held that the Commission was entitled to correct its own
            <lb />
            mistakes and therefore left it to the Commission to rectify the same.
            <lb />
            Unfortunately, instead of rectifying its mistakes, the Commission after
            <lb />
            having admitted, as far back as in the year 2007, that major mistakes
            <lb />
            have been committed, it continued to contest the petition and took no
            <lb />
            steps to correct the mistakes. This Court also passed no orders and the
            <lb />
            case, for one reason or the other and the case was not taken up for final
            <lb />
            hearing for more than 9 years.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            35.
            <lb />
            Thereafter, this matter came up before this Court on 24.06.2016
            <lb />
            and keeping in view the nature of dispute, this Court directed that the
            <lb />
            matter be taken up on 01.07.2016 for hearing. On the said date,
            <lb />
            arguments were heard in part and the Petitioners concluded their
            <lb />
            arguments. After conclusion of the arguments of the Petitioners, this Court
            <lb />
            had directed the Commission to clarify certain issues. On 04.07.2016, the
            <lb />
            Commission submitted a short note to this Court and the translated
            <lb />
            version of the said note reads as follows:
            <lb />
        </p>

        <head>
            &quot;State Public Services Exam, 2003</head>
        <lb />
        <item>
            Point wise information for the litigation of Ku. Varsha
            <lb />
            Dongre.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (1) Total marks obtained by Ku. Varsha Dongre in the
            <lb />
            State Services Exam is 1290.91. As per her mark sheet
            <lb />
            obtained from Noybl Lab, it has been mentioned that she
            <lb />
            scored 399.06 marks in Anthropology, which is not
            <lb />
            correct. Marks obtained by her in the first paper of
            <lb />
            Anthropology unscaled is 184 and in second paper
            <lb />
            unscaled is 199. Thus, total marks obtained in
            <lb />
            Anthropology is 383. As per scaling detail, in first paper
            <lb />
            of Anthropology 205 marks were scored and scaled
            <lb />
            marks in second paper is 209.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (2) On 02/06/2007, the Preliminary Report of Anti
            <lb />
            Corruption Bureau was sent to GAD, which was received
            <lb />
            by Ayog (Commission) by the letter dt. 29/06/2007 of
            <lb />
            GAD. In this regard, by the letter dt. 29/06/2007 of
            <lb />
            Commission its report was sent to GAD.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (3) With respect to wrong scaling in the optional
            <lb />
            subjects of main exam, the Secretary GAD of State of C.
            <lb />
            G. was informed by the D. O. letter 23/03/2007 of the
            <lb />
            Commission. For rectifying the discrepancies, errors an
            <lb />
            application was submitted before Hon&apos;ble High Court of
            <lb />
            C.G., Bilaspur on 09/06/2007.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (4) The Agency has made wrong entry about this
            <lb />
            subject code of the candidates. For all the four question
            <lb />
            papers of both the optional subjects, separate scaling was
            <lb />
            done subject wise and option wise. This procedure of
            <lb />
            scaling is erroneous, as one student can opt same subject
            <lb />
            as first or second optional subject and thus, on such
            <lb />
            scaling, for the same question paper for the same subject,
            <lb />
            candidate obtaining similar raw marks score different
            <lb />
            scaled mark on taking the said subject as first optional
            <lb />
            subject and is different on taking the said subject as
            <lb />
            second optional subject. The calculation of various value
            <lb />
            ( M, m, S, s) of scaling is erroneous. The entire selection
            <lb />
            procedure of exam of State Public Service Exam, 2003 is
            <lb />
            vitiated due to grave error committed by the computer
            <lb />
            agency in scaling of optional subjects of main exam of
            <lb />
            State Public Service Exam, 2003.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (5) In compliance of Interim Order dated 26/10/2007 of
            <lb />
            Hon&apos;ble High Court of C. G., on the 10 point meeting
            <lb />
            dated 12/11/2007 of the Commission, the Commission
            <lb />
            taking decision no.168 for action on following 1 to 5,
            <lb />
            prepared list of candidates. With respect to point no. 6 to
            <lb />
            10 of the decision, further proceedings shall be done as
            <lb />
            per directions of Hon&apos;ble High Court. The information
            <lb />
            regarding aforesaid proceeding have been submitted
            <lb />
            before the Hon&apos;ble High Court by the application dated
            <lb />
            25/12/2008 for directions.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (6) As per Sl. No. 11 of the main list Shri Rajeev Singh
            <lb />
            Chauhan, Roll No. 31106 has been selected to the post of
            <lb />
            Accounts Officer as S. C. Candidate. The Commission,
            <lb />
            considering it erroneous, has asked the department
            <lb />
            through its letter no. 2119, dt. 22/02/2007 not to appoint
            <lb />
            Shri Rajeev Singh Chauhan. By the letter no. 263 dt.
            <lb />
            02/06/2007 of Commission, consent for appointment was
            <lb />
            not given by the Commission.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (7) One of the candidates viz. Kundan Kumar, Roll No.
            <lb />
            79001 appeared in main exam of State Public Service
            <lb />
            Exam, 2003. This candidate scored 472 marks in the
            <lb />
            compulsory subject and 921 in optional subject. For the
            <lb />
            scored 921 marks in optional subject he has been scaled
            <lb />
            712.19. Thus, total of 472 marks obtained in the
            <lb />
            compulsory subject of main exam and the scaled marks
            <lb />
            712.19 scored in optional subject is 1184.19 total marks
            <lb />
            obtained.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (8) Petitioner viz. Ku Varsha Dongre in the
            <lb />
            Agramanyata Patrak at paint no. 10 wrote Asst. Excise
            <lb />
            Sub Inspector and then struck the same. No initial made
            <lb />
            by the person who struck off and in the column for the
            <lb />
            office use, code of post AEXI has been filled. In this
            <lb />
            regard the then Examination Controller Dr. B.P. Kashyap
            <lb />
            may better reply, as Agramanyata Patrak is one of the
            <lb />
            important confidential documents of the Examination
            <lb />
            results, which was kept in the custody of Shri Kashyap.
            <lb />
            With respect to the irregularity charge sheet (No. 2300
            <lb />
            dt. 20/03/2007) has been issued to Dr. B.P. Kashyap.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            9. In the preliminary enquiry of the final select list of
            <lb />
            State Public Services Exam 2003, for some posts of the
            <lb />
            reserved category the candidates were in the merit list yet
            <lb />
            were not shown in the Unreserved category, which is
            <lb />
            erroneous.
        </item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            Sd/-
            <lb />
            (B.S.Dhruv)
            <lb />
            Sub Divisional Officer (Selection)
            <lb />
            C.G.Public Service Commission&quot;
        </item>
        <lb />
        <p>
            From the aforesaid submission of the Chhattisgarh Public Service
            <lb />
            Commission, it is more than apparent that the Commission received the
            <lb />
            report of the Anti Corruption Bureau on 29.06.2007. It is also obvious that
            <lb />
            Petitioner-Ku. Varsha Dongre should have been awarded 414 marks in
            <lb />
            Anthropology against 399 marks awarded to her, which will make a
            <lb />
            substantial difference. The Commission itself admits that Petitioner-Ku.
            <lb />
            Varsha Dongre was eligible to be appointed to the post of Deputy
            <lb />
            Superintendent of Police. The Commission also admits that there has
            <lb />
            been total wrong application of scaling formula. It is very important to note
            <lb />
            that the Commission has stated that the entire selection process of the
            <lb />
            Examination, 2003 is vitiated due to grave errors in scaling of optional
            <lb />
            subjects of main examination. The Commission also admits that Shri
            <lb />
            Rajeev Singh Chauhan was a general category candidate and was never
            <lb />
            recommended for the post of reserved category. The Commission also
            <lb />
            admits that after the year 2007, it took no action in the matter. It is in the
            <lb />
            background of the aforesaid facts that this case has to be decided.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <head>
            Errors in Scaling
            <lb />
        </head>

        <p>
            36.
            <lb />
            In the Public Service Commission Examination for the year 2003,
            <lb />
            the Commission had applied scaling system. The purpose of applying the
            <lb />
            scaling system was to rationalize the marks given in different subjects.
            <lb />
            None of the parties is objecting to application of scaling system, the
            <lb />
            objective of which is to ensure rationalization of marks so that if the
            <lb />
            marking is strict in a particular subject or lesser marks are awarded to all
            <lb />
            the candidates in one subject, then by applying a mathematical formula,
            <lb />
            marks of the candidate in that subject would be increased. There could
            <lb />
            also be downward scaling where marks were given very liberally in one
            <lb />
            subject, the same could be reduced by applying mathematical formula of
            <lb />
            scaling.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            37.
            <lb />
            This scaling system was not to apply to the compulsory subjects
            <lb />
            but only to the optional subjects. The purpose was to ensure that in the
            <lb />
            optional subjects, some candidates may opt for subjects in which marks
            <lb />
            are awarded more liberally and therefore, the candidates in other subjects
            <lb />
            suffer and by applying the scaling formula parity and rationalization is
            <lb />
            brought about. The formula provides that scaled marks shall be arrived at
            <lb />
            by applying the following formula:
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;Scaled Number = M+(X-m)S/s&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            There were 23 optional subjects offered by the Commission.
            <lb />
            &apos;M&apos; represents overall mean of the raw marks (unscaled) obtained by the
            <lb />
            candidates in these 23 optional subjects. &apos;X&apos; stands for the raw marks
            <lb />
            (unscaled) obtained by the candidate in the optional subject i.e. marks
            <lb />
            obtained without scaling. &apos;m&apos; represents mean of raw marks (unscaled)
            <lb />
            obtained by all the candidates in that optional subject. &apos;S&apos; stands for
            <lb />
            standard deviation in the raw marks in all 23 optional subjects. &apos;s&apos; stands
            <lb />
            for standard deviation in raw marks (unscaled) in a particular optional
            <lb />
            subject. This is a mathematical formula where the values of &apos;M&apos;, &apos;m&apos;, &apos;S&apos;,
            <lb />
            and &apos;s&apos; will remain same and only value of &apos;X&apos; i.e. raw marks obtained by a
            <lb />
            candidate in a particular paper will vary. Therefore, if &apos;X&apos; is the same, the
            <lb />
            final scaled marks have to be the same. This fact is now not disputed by
            <lb />
            the Commission also, which in its reply and in various documents has
            <lb />
            admitted that the Computer Agency (Noybl Lab) engaged by it to carry out
            <lb />
            the process of scaling has committed glaring mistakes.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            38.
            <lb />
            In this regard, as pointed out earlier, in the subject of Anthropology
            <lb />
            many candidates had obtained 200 raw marks. After scaling their scaled
            <lb />
            marks ranged from 170.01 and 239.22 and therefore, there was a huge
            <lb />
            variation in the marks, which could not have happened if the scaling
            <lb />
            formula had been applied correctly.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            39.
            <lb />
            I fail to understand that that while applying the mathematical
            <lb />
            formula, how could such a mistake occur. This gives strength and
            <lb />
            credence to the allegations of the Petitioners that there was a large scale
            <lb />
            corruption and while scaling the marks, certain officers in the Commission
            <lb />
            helped some of the candidates by ensuring that such undeserving
            <lb />
            candidates got selected or they got much higher posts than they deserved
            <lb />
            and the candidates who did not have connections in high places were not
            <lb />
            given proper marks. Even in the latest submissions made by the
            <lb />
            Commission on 04.07.2016, it is admitted that scaling was done in a
            <lb />
            highly improper manner and there are serious mistakes which vitiate the
            <lb />
            selection process. It would be pertinent to mention that the Commission in
            <lb />
            para 4 of its submission had itself stated that in the main examination of
            <lb />
            the said Civil Services Examination, 2003, the scaling in the optional
            <lb />
            subjects done by the Computer Agency (Noybl Lab) is full of serious
            <lb />
            mistakes and therefore, the entire selection process is vitiated. Once the
            <lb />
            Commission itself admits that the entire selection process is tainted, I do
            <lb />
            not think that anything further is required to be said by this Court. In fact,
            <lb />
            none of the counsel for the Respondents argued that the scaling has been
            <lb />
            properly done. Therefore, this Court is clearly of the view that the process
            <lb />
            of scaling was full of mistakes and as now fairly admitted by the
            <lb />
            Commission, the entire selection process is tainted and vitiated and has
            <lb />
            to be rectified.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            40.
            <lb />
            The Commission in its reply has admitted the mistakes in scaling
            <lb />
            and has stated that a charge-sheet has been issued to the Examination
            <lb />
            Controller, Dr. B.P.Kashyap. Taking action against the Examination
            <lb />
            Controller will not be of any use to the candidates who have been
            <lb />
            deprived of their genuine right to get the posts.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            41.
            <lb />
            Shri Ravindra Singh, Petitioner No. 2 in Writ Petition No. 3028 of
            <lb />
            2006 also appeared in person and he has again pointed out the
            <lb />
            anomalies in the marks given after scaling. He points out that in History
            <lb />
            Paper II, one candidate who had raw marks of 158 had been awarded
            <lb />
            205 marks after scaling and in the same History Paper II, another
            <lb />
            candidate who had 188 marks was awarded only 150 marks in the same
            <lb />
            paper after scaling. This on the face of it clearly shows that the entire
            <lb />
            process of scaling was illegal and improper. This fact having been
            <lb />
            accepted by the Commission, it is not necessary to deal with this issue in
            <lb />
            detail. It would however be necessary to mention that the judicial
            <lb />
            conscience of the Court is shocked by the manner in which the scaling
            <lb />
            has been done. It is apparent that scaling was used as ruse for benefiting
            <lb />
            some candidates and harming some candidates. As pointed out in the
            <lb />
            report of the Anti Corruption Bureau, the officials in the Commission
            <lb />
            helped those who had connection in the right places at the cost of much
            <lb />
            more meritorious candidates who had no such connections.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <head>
            Error in the Actual Marks Awarded to Ku. Varsha Dongre
            <lb />
        </head>

        <p>
            42.
            <lb />
            Petitioner-Ku. Varsha Dongre has pointed out that in the merit list
            <lb />
            (Annexure P/7) she has been awarded 1290.41 marks. She had obtained
            <lb />
            184 raw marks in Paper I and 199 raw marks in Paper II in the subject of
            <lb />
            Anthropology. Therefore, she had obtained a total marks of 383 in
            <lb />
            Anthropology. She has been awarded 399.06 marks in the Anthropology
            <lb />
            after scaling, whereas on applying the formula of the Respondent-
            <lb />
            Commission itself, she would have got 414 marks. The Commission now
            <lb />
            in its latest submission admitted that Ku. Varsha Dongre was entitled to
            <lb />
            205 marks in Paper I of Anthropology and 209 marks in Paper II which
            <lb />
            would mean that her total marks would raise to 414. Therefore, her total
            <lb />
            marks would raise to 1305.85. This would mean that she would be placed
            <lb />
            much higher in the merit list. Since she belongs to Scheduled Caste
            <lb />
            category, she would have been eligible to be appointed as Deputy
            <lb />
            Superintendent of Police in the year 2006. The Commission now admits
            <lb />
            that Ku. Varsha Dongre was eligible to be appointed to the Police Service
            <lb />
            as Deputy Superintendent of Police and are now willing to recommend
            <lb />
            her name to the said post. The State is also willing to give said post to Ku.
            <lb />
            Varsha Dongre.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            43.
            <lb />
            The further allegation with regard to scaling is that either the
            <lb />
            Commission or the Computer Agency engaged by it has totally
            <lb />
            misunderstood and misapplied the formula. As pointed out above, a
            <lb />
            candidate has to appear in the compulsory subjects, i.e. General Studies
            <lb />
            and General Hindi alongwith two other optional subjects. In the case of
            <lb />
            Ku. Varsha Dongre, her first optional subject was Zoology and second
            <lb />
            optional subject was Anthropology. There could be some other candidates
            <lb />
            who may have chosen Anthropology as their first option and any other
            <lb />
            subject as their second option. By totally misapplying the formula, if a
            <lb />
            person has obtained 200 marks in Paper I of Anthropology, he has been
            <lb />
            given different marks after applying the method of scaling if Anthropology
            <lb />
            was his first option and different scaled marks have been awarded who
            <lb />
            has obtained identical raw marks i.e. 200 but in his case, Anthropology is
            <lb />
            the second option. This fact is admitted in writing to this Court wherein the
            <lb />
            Commission has said that the process of scaling is full of mistakes
            <lb />
            because it is immaterial whether the candidate has chosen the subject as
            <lb />
            first option or second option.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            44.
            <lb />
            The Commission now also admits that after this Court passed an
            <lb />
            order on 26.10.2007 permitting the Commission to correct its mistakes, a
            <lb />
            meeting of the Commission was held on 12.11.2007 wherein after
            <lb />
            considering all these factors the following decisions were taken:
            <lb />
        </p>

        <head>
            &quot;CHHATTISGARH PUBLIC SERVICE
            <lb />
            COMMISSION, RAIPUR
        </head>
        <lb />
        <item>
            Decision No. -168 File No. 54/2006
            <lb />
            In the meeting dated 12.11.2007, in the light of
            <lb />
            Interim Order dated 26.10.2007 passed by Hon&apos;ble
            <lb />
            High Court of Bilaspur in Writ Petition
            <lb />
            No.3028/2006 Chamman Lal Sinha and others
            <lb />
            versus State of C.G. another, the Commission has
            <lb />
            decided to proceed as per follows:-
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            1.
            <lb />
            All the students of the Main Exam of year
            <lb />
            2003 after decoding the answer sheets of all the
            <lb />
            subjects, roll number flaps be again affixed in
            <lb />
            answer sheets and thereafter compared with the
            <lb />
            total
            <lb />
            obtained marks mentioned in original
            <lb />
            tabulation sheets and main page of answer sheets,
            <lb />
            the data entry work will be done properly. As a
            <lb />
            result of this proceeding if any difference occurs in
            <lb />
            the mark of candidate, separate list of such
            <lb />
            candidate shall be prepared and list of such
            <lb />
            candidates be kept before the Commission for
            <lb />
            perusal/examination along with the answer sheets.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            2.
            <lb />
            The scaling of optional subject will be
            <lb />
            done Subject wise and paper-wise of the total
            <lb />
            obtained marks.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            3.
            <lb />
            For interview after scaling, three times of
            <lb />
            vacant post and following the reservation rules, the
            <lb />
            category-wise list shall be prepared.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            4.
            <lb />
            So for as possible, the list of unqualified
            <lb />
            candidates from the qualified list, shall be prepared
            <lb />
            prior to the interview.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            5.
            <lb />
            In a fresh qualification list such a new
            <lb />
            candidate shall be marked whose interview were
            <lb />
            not conducted earlier.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            6.
            <lb />
            The said list be produced before the
            <lb />
            Hon&apos;ble High court and as per order of Honorable
            <lb />
            High Court as for as possible the interview of the
            <lb />
            candidates included in fresh list shall be taken.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            7.
            <lb />
            That after interview, as per marks of
            <lb />
            written examination and interview a combined
            <lb />
            merit list shall be prepared.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            8.
            <lb />
            On the basis of Agramanatya Patrak, in the
            <lb />
            merit sequence, the post will be allotted to the
            <lb />
            candidates.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            9.
            <lb />
            The revised selection list be produced
            <lb />
            before the Hon&apos;ble High Court and further direction
            <lb />
            shall be taken.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            10.
            <lb />
            After preparation of revised list, a list of
            <lb />
            candidates shall be prepared whose earlier allotted
            <lb />
            post has been changed. The candidate who were
            <lb />
            selected earlier but whose name has not in revised
            <lb />
            selection list, the separate list shall be prepared.
            <lb />
            Separate list shall also be prepared whose name is
            <lb />
            not in earlier selection list but his name is in revised
            <lb />
            list.
            <lb />
            Sd/-
            <lb />
            Sd/-
            <lb />
            N.S.Bhadoriya
            <lb />
            Dr. Durgasharan Chandra
            <lb />
            Chairman
            <lb />
            Member
            <lb />
            CGPSC
            <lb />
            CGPSC
            <lb />
            Raipur
            <lb />
            Raipur&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            45.
            <lb />
            It is apparent from the aforesaid minutes of the Commission itself
            <lb />
            that the Commission as far back as in the year 2007 had taken a decision
            <lb />
            to ensure proper scaling of marks and to virtually restart the selection
            <lb />
            process after re-scaling is done. No explanation has been given as to why
            <lb />
            the Commission on its own did not take any steps to correct these
            <lb />
            mistakes which were known to it. I am also constrained to observe that in
            <lb />
            the last 9 years, the Commission filed many affidavits but did not feel it
            <lb />
            proper to bring these minutes to the notice of this Court.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            46.
            <lb />
            On 19.11.2007, a letter was written by the Commission to the
            <lb />
            Secretary, Government of Chhattisgarh in this regard, relevant portion of
            <lb />
            which reads as follows:
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;Substantially, extensive mistake/irregularities occurred in
            <lb />
            public Service Examination 2003 in which considerable are:-
            <lb />
            Erroneous scaling of marks received in optional subjects of
            <lb />
            public service written examination 2003. Due to which the
            <lb />
            result itself of public service main Examination, 2003 is
            <lb />
            erroneous and the list of eligible candidates prepared for
            <lb />
            interview on this basis is also erroneous. The proceedings of
            <lb />
            post distribution to the candidates on the basis of further
            <lb />
            preference and total marks obtained after interview is
            <lb />
            erroneous in itself. In this way, entire selection process is
            <lb />
            vitiated.
            <lb />
            xxx
            <lb />
            xxx
            <lb />
            xxx
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (1) Not selecting 3 candidates getting higher marks
            <lb />
             It is true that the then examination Controller committed
            <lb />
            mistake. In post determination in accordance with
            <lb />
            Agramanyata (Further preference). From the preliminary
            <lb />
            examination by the commission in March, 2007 in respect of
            <lb />
            post determination in accordance with Agramanyata (Further
            <lb />
            preference) this facts is clear that Varsha Dongre was to be
            <lb />
            selected on the post of Assistant Director, Public relations.
            <lb />
            Pradeep kumar Bhoi was to be selected on the post of
            <lb />
            commercial tax inspector and the place of Rajendra Kumar
            <lb />
            Jaiswal was to be on the post of commercial Tax Inspector, in
            <lb />
            supplementary list of other backward classes and on getting
            <lb />
            higher marks Miss Manisha Dahariya was to be selected on
            <lb />
            the post of Excise Sub Inspector before Miss Nirupma
            <lb />
            Lohare
            <lb />
            (2) Fraudulently doing alteration in agramanyata patrak
            <lb />
            (further preference sheet) of Miss Varsha Dongre. In
            <lb />
            combined merit list Mahendra Kuldeep&apos;s merit number is
            <lb />
            210, Usha Kiran Badaek&apos;s merit number is 214, Sarika
            <lb />
            Ramteke&apos;s merit number is 217 and Sunil kumar&apos;s merit
            <lb />
            number is 237. It is true that on 05/04/2006 C.G. P.S.C. sent
            <lb />
            letter to Human Rights Commission. It is also true that the
            <lb />
            applicant Varsha Dongre has mentioned ten posts out of
            <lb />
            twelve posts in Agramanyata patrak and on 10 th number the
            <lb />
            entry of the post of Excise Sub-Inspector is cut. It is also true
            <lb />
            that the candidates of SC category who obtained marks lower
            <lb />
            to her were selected on different posts.
            <lb />
            xxx
            <lb />
            xxx
            <lb />
            xxx
            <lb />
            Substantially for the error in determination of posts as
            <lb />
            per agramanyata, the then Examination Controller Dr. B.P.
            <lb />
            Kashyap is completely responsible.
            <lb />
            xxx
            <lb />
            xxx
            <lb />
            xxx
        </item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            ... With a view to put the case of Commission in the case
            <lb />
            pending before the High Court, on preliminary examination
            <lb />
            of the proceedings with respect to the determination of posts
            <lb />
            as per agramanyata regarding State Services 2003, it was
            <lb />
            found that there were considerable errors in agramanyata
            <lb />
            determination for the posts of (Deputy Superintendent of
            <lb />
            Police), State Accounts Services (Accounts Officer),
            <lb />
            Assistant Director Public Relation, District woman and child
            <lb />
            Development Officer, Assistant Director Local fund Audit,
            <lb />
            Subordinate Civil Services (Nayab Telshildar), Commercial
            <lb />
            Tax Inspector and Excise Sub-Inspector, due to which,
            <lb />
            recommendation for selection of certain non-eligible
            <lb />
            candidates has been made in place of certain eligible
            <lb />
            candidates for various posts. Thus, including Varsha Dongre,
            <lb />
            many other eligible candidates have not been selected.
            <lb />
            xxx
            <lb />
            xxx
            <lb />
            xxx
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            3. Depriving 5 candidates of their selection violating
            <lb />
            reservation rules.
            <lb />
            &gt; It is true that Neha Pandey should not have been selected
            <lb />
            on the post of Deputy Superintendent of Police, Shri Heeralal
            <lb />
            Dewangan Roll No. 23140 from OBC category should have
            <lb />
            been selected.
        </item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            &gt; It is true that at 6th No. of District woman and Child
            <lb />
            Development Officer, Shri Saudagar Singh (SC) Roll no.
            <lb />
            68551 should have been selected at the place of Ajay
            <lb />
            Sharma. As, it is mentioned above that the then Examination
            <lb />
            Controller has not prepared the proceeding details regarding
            <lb />
            distribution of posts on the basis of agramanyata. Present
            <lb />
            Sub-Divisional Officer (Selection) has erred in understanding
            <lb />
            the facts, due to which, information of para 4 is wrongly
            <lb />
            shown in the reply sent to the Human Rights Commission.
        </item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            &gt; For the post of Asst. Director Local fund Audit, except
            <lb />
            selection of Govind Singh Kumeti (S.T.), selection of rest 3
            <lb />
            namely Saudagar Singh Tandey (S.C.), Ajay Birthare and
            <lb />
            Bharti Singh Rajput are erroneous.
        </item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            &gt; It is true that for the 23 unreserved posts of excise Sub-
            <lb />
            Inspector, candidate of any category could be selected on the
            <lb />
            basis of merit. In this list, on the basis of merit, Roll no.
            <lb />
            22322 Rajendra Kumar Jaiswal (OBC) finds a place in
            <lb />
            unreserved category selection of Roll no. 72985 Umesh
            <lb />
            Kumar Agrawal, Roll no. 66937 Rajendra Nath Tiwari is
            <lb />
            erroneous as their marks are lower. Roll no. 59467 Santram
            <lb />
            Kurmi and Roll no. 26676 Ramakant Dewangan should have
            <lb />
            been selected from OBC Categary. Roll no. 90448 Ghasi
            <lb />
            Ram Adey and Roll no. 66577 Manisha Daheriya should
            <lb />
            have been selected in category of Scheduled Castes. There
            <lb />
            has been error in following the reservation rules.
        </item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            &gt; There is no error in the selection of Neetu Notani at the
            <lb />
            post of District Excise Officer, her selection has been made
            <lb />
            under unreserved (female) category.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (4) Discrimination in the case of temporary Caste
            <lb />
            Certificate regarding 1 candidate of reservation category.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            &gt; According to the note sheet regarding selection result of the
            <lb />
            State Services Mains Examination, prepared by the then
            <lb />
            Examination Controller, Roll no. 22790 Navodita Para and
            <lb />
            Roll no. 23576 Hasan Lal Gohiya have been selected under
            <lb />
            unreserved category as they have not produced the permanent
            <lb />
            Caste Certificate of S.T. and S.C. respectively. Factual
            <lb />
            situation with respect to not producing Caste Certificate by
            <lb />
            rest five candidates is as follows:-
        </item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            1. Muktanand Khute-Caste Certificate issued by Tehsildar
            <lb />
            Nagari (Revenue Case no. 376/B 121 Year 95-96)
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            2. Renu Prakash:-Caste Certificate no. 14470/2837/93 issued
            <lb />
            by the Collector (Caste Certificate Section) Durg.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            3. Arvind Kumar Vani -Temporary Caste Certificate Case
            <lb />
            no. 515/2003-04 issued by Tehsildar Pamgarh.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            4. Saudagar Tandey-Certificate no. 927 Dt. 10.08.89 (only
            <lb />
            for education and scholarship) issued by Area-Co-ordinator
            <lb />
            for District Co-coordinator, Harijan Development Raipur.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            5. Sushma Thakur-has produced the permanent Caste
            <lb />
            Certificate issued by sub-Divisional officer Balod, Durg
            <lb />
            regarding scheduled Tribes.
        </item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            The above makes it clear that error has been
            <lb />
            committed in examination of Certificates and accordingly
            <lb />
            determination of category regarding no. 3 and 4.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (5) Selection of 1 candidate of unreserved category in
            <lb />
            reserved category.
        </item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            &gt; That Shri Rajeev Singh Chauhan Roll no. 31106 is the
            <lb />
            candidate of unreserved category. Showing Rajeev Singh
            <lb />
            Chauhan in Scheduled Caste Category, he has been selected
            <lb />
            against that post, which is erroneous.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (2) Irregularity in Scaling</item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            Brief Comment, with respect to the irregularity in scaling
            <lb />
            and conclusion drawn by Anti-Corruption Bureau in this
            <lb />
            regard, is as follows:-
        </item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            After information provided under RTI Act, 2005 to various
            <lb />
            candidates regarding State Services Examination, 2003,
            <lb />
            certain candidates made complaint to the commission
            <lb />
            regarding error in scaling. On receipt of Complaint, it was
            <lb />
            found on preliminary enquiry that the computer Agency
            <lb />
            appointed by the Commission had made considerable errors.
            <lb />
            Errors are as follows:-
        </item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            1. Agency has done erroneous entry of subject codes chosen
            <lb />
            by the candidates.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            2. Scaling of all four question papers of both optional
            <lb />
            subjects has been done option wise and subject wise
            <lb />
            separately. This method of Scaling is erroneous, because a
            <lb />
            candidate may choose only one subject as first or second
            <lb />
            optional subject and on scaling in said manner, the candidate
            <lb />
            who has obtained similar raw marks in the same question
            <lb />
            paper of same subject, receives different scaled marks on
            <lb />
            choosing first optional subject and second optional subject.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            3. Calculation of various measures (M,m,S,s) of scaling are
            <lb />
            also erroneous.
        </item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            Since, the computer Agency has made considerable
            <lb />
            errors in scaling of optional subjects of State Services
            <lb />
            Examination, 2003 entire selection process of State Services
            <lb />
            Examination 2003 has vitiated.
        </item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            Thus since the scaling work of obtained marks of
            <lb />
            optional subject is erroneous, result of State Servies Mains
            <lb />
            Examination 2003 has also become erroneous and list of
            <lb />
            candidates, qualified for interview, prepared on the basis of
            <lb />
            (on the basis of said scaling) also becomes erroneous. And
            <lb />
            thus, since the proceeding of post distribution on the basis of
            <lb />
            agramanyata after interview itself becomes erroneous
            <lb />
            therefore entire selection process has been vitiated. ... &quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            47.
            <lb />
            The aforesaid communication clearly indicates that the
            <lb />
            Commission had admitted most of the mistakes. The Commission had
            <lb />
            admitted that there was extensive irregularities in the examination. It had
            <lb />
            also admitted that Petitioner-Ku. Varsha Dongre was deprived of her
            <lb />
            selection and action should be taken against the officers who prepared
            <lb />
            and declared a vitiated result depriving her from selection. With regard to
            <lb />
            the allegations made by the Anti Corruption Bureau, the Commission
            <lb />
            admitted that three candidates who had higher marks were not selected. It
            <lb />
            also admitted that reservation rules were not applied properly depriving
            <lb />
            five candidates of selection. It also admitted that there was discrimination
            <lb />
            and in one case, a person without permanent caste certificate was
            <lb />
            appointed whereas in other cases, the candidates similarly situated were
            <lb />
            not appointed. It also admitted that one general category candidate was
            <lb />
            appointed against the post of reserved category. With regard to
            <lb />
            interpolation in the preference form of Ku. Varsha Dongre, there is no
            <lb />
            clear cut admission, but it is not disputed that there is some element of
            <lb />
            bungling. It is indeed surprising that despite the mistakes being admitted
            <lb />
            by the Commission, no action was taken to rectify the same.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            48.
            <lb />
            In the reply filed by the Commission to the application for
            <lb />
            amendment filed by the Petitioner-Ku. Varsha Dongre, the Respondents
            <lb />
            admitted that she should be awarded 205.6053 in the first paper of
            <lb />
            Anthropology and 209.3309 marks in the second paper of Anthropology.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            49.
            <lb />
            In view of the aforesaid discussion, it is actually not necessary to
            <lb />
            decide all other issues, however, large scale bungling is not limited to
            <lb />
            scaling only and there are other aspects also and therefore, I propose to
            <lb />
            deal with them.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <head>
            Was the Preference Form of Ku. Varsha Dongre Interpolated?
            <lb />
        </head>

        <p>
            50.
            <lb />
            As pointed earlier, the examination was conducted to fill up various
            <lb />
            services under the State. A candidate at the time of interview is required
            <lb />
            to fill a preference form to show what is his/her order of preference for the
            <lb />
            post to be filled up. In the preference form of Ku. Varsha Dongre, her first
            <lb />
            preference was the post of Deputy Superintendent of Police, second
            <lb />
            preference was Deputy Collector, third preference was for Accounts
            <lb />
            Officer, fourth preference for Sales Tax Officer, fifth preference was for
            <lb />
            District Women and Child Development Officer, sixth preference was for
            <lb />
            Assistant Public Relation Officer, seventh preference was for District
            <lb />
            Registrar, eighth preference was for Naib Tahsildar, ninth preference was
            <lb />
            for Sales Tax Inspector and the disputed entry is entry No. 10 against
            <lb />
            which Ku. Varsha Dongre, in her handwriting, has written &apos;Excise Sub
            <lb />
            Inspector&apos;. The word &apos;Excise Sub Inspector&apos; has been scored off in her
            <lb />
            form. The case of the Petitioner-Ku. Varsha Dongre is that this was not
            <lb />
            done by her but it was done at the level of the Commission. In support of
            <lb />
            this submission, she states that all other corrections in the form have
            <lb />
            been initialed by her. She also submits that the words &apos;Excise Sub
            <lb />
            Inspector&apos; are clearly visible and a line has been put across these words
            <lb />
            but according to her, she has not put that line and this was done at the
            <lb />
            level of the Commission to deprive her right to get a job at least as Excise
            <lb />
            Sub Inspector. In support of her plea, she has drawn the attention of the
            <lb />
            Court to a column in this form which has to be filled in by the Office and
            <lb />
            the code of the post had been filled in by the office of the Commission.
            <lb />
            Against the words &apos;Excise Sub Inspector&apos; AEXI has been filled in. If this
            <lb />
            scoring off had existed when she submitted the form with the
            <lb />
            Commission, then no coding would have been done. In this regard, she
            <lb />
            has drawn the attention of this Court to similar forms of other candidates
            <lb />
            who had scored off the post and there are initials of the candidates
            <lb />
            against the scored off posts and the office has not filled the code of such
            <lb />
            scored off posts. We find merit in the submission of Ku. Varsha Dongre.
            <lb />
            Even in the report of Anti Corruption Bureau quoted hereinabove, it has
            <lb />
            been clearly found that this scoring off has been made by some official in
            <lb />
            the Commission only with a view to deprive Ku. Varsha Dongre of her
            <lb />
            right to get a job. It would also be pertinent to mention that the Anti
            <lb />
            Corruption Bureau has found that the scoring which has been done in Ku.
            <lb />
            Varsha Dongre&apos;s preference form has left its imprint on the other forms
            <lb />
            just below her form. If Ku. Varsha Dongre had scored off the words
            <lb />
            &apos;Excise Sub Inspector&apos;, then as pointed out by the Anti Corruption Bureau,
            <lb />
            there would be no imprint on the other forms. The imprint is on the other
            <lb />
            forms because those forms were in the possession of some officials of the
            <lb />
            Commission and when the words &apos;Excise Sub Inspector&apos; was scored off in
            <lb />
            Ku. Varsha Dongre&apos;s form, an imprint was left in the forms below that.
            <lb />
            Furthermore, the Anti Corruption Bureau has found the pen and ink used
            <lb />
            in scoring off is different from one which Ku. Varsha Dongre had used to
            <lb />
            fill up the form. It is an admitted case of the parties that this form is filled in
            <lb />
            only at the time when the candidate goes to face interview. Therefore,
            <lb />
            question of Ku. Varsha Dongre having used two pens does not arise.
            <lb />
            Therefore, I have no hesitation in coming to the conclusion that the 10 th
            <lb />
            preference for the post of &apos;Excise Sub Inspector&apos; was scored off by some
            <lb />
            official of the Commission and not by Ku. Varsha Dongre. Though, the
            <lb />
            Commission has denied this allegation, but it has failed to answer the
            <lb />
            submission made by Ku. Varsha Dongre in this regard. Only one counsel
            <lb />
            tried to argue that in fact Petitioner-Ku. Varsha Dongre had scored off all
            <lb />
            the posts except Deputy Superintendent of Police. However, on going
            <lb />
            through the preference form, I find that this allegation is totally incorrect.
            <lb />
            Therefore, I have no hesitation in coming to the conclusion that her
            <lb />
            preference form was interpolated at the level of Commission itself, for
            <lb />
            extraneous reasons just to deny her her post.
            <lb />

        </p>
        <head>
            Meritorious Reserved Category Candidates Not Adjusted Against
            <lb />
            General Category.
            <lb />
        </head>
        <p>
            51.
            <lb />
            Another point urged by the Petitioner-Ku. Varsha Dongre is that
            <lb />
            when the candidates belonging to the reserved category get selected on
            <lb />
            their own merit, they had to be treated as unreserved category
            <lb />
            candidates. However, the Commission has not done this. This fact is
            <lb />
            admitted by the Commission itself. The law is well settled that if a
            <lb />
            candidate belonging to the reserved category gets a position on the merit
            <lb />
            list which entitled him to selection/appointment without taking the aid of
            <lb />
            the crutches of reservation, he has to be treated as a general category
            <lb />
            candidate. Resultantly, no reduction is made from the number of
            <lb />
            candidates entitled from the reserved category. To give an example, if 10
            <lb />
            posts are reserved for Scheduled Castes and seven scheduled caste
            <lb />
            candidates get selected on their own merit, then total number of
            <lb />
            scheduled candidates who have to be appointed is 17 because seven
            <lb />
            candidates will be treated as unreserved category since they have not
            <lb />
            taken the benefit of reservation. It is virtually admitted that the
            <lb />
            Commission has not followed this system and therefore, the entire
            <lb />
            selection process will be affected.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <head>
            Injustice Done to Petitioner-Ku. Varsha Dongre
            <lb />
        </head>

        <p>
            52.
            <lb />
            Petitioner-Ku. Varsha Dongre has pointed out that even if she had
            <lb />
            1290 marks as were originally awarded by the Commission, people who
            <lb />
            were much below her have been selected. Respondent No. 7-Manoj
            <lb />
            Kumar Larorker had obtained 1277.35 marks which is much below
            <lb />
            Petitioner-Ku. Varsha Dongre, but has been appointed as Excise Sub
            <lb />
            Inspector. Similarly, Petitioner No. 137-Sunil Kumar had obtained only
            <lb />
            1262 marks but was also appointed as Excise Sub Inspector. With regard
            <lb />
            to these two candidates, the version of the Respondent-Commission is
            <lb />
            that Petitioner-Ku. Varsha Dongre has scored off the post of Excise Sub
            <lb />
            Inspector and therefore, she was not considered against this post. As
            <lb />
            already held above, the scoring off has not been done by her but it was
            <lb />
            done later by somebody in the Commission with a view to deprive Ku.
            <lb />
            Varsha Dongre of her right to get the post. The matter does not end here.
            <lb />
            Assuming for the sake of deciding this issue that the Petitioner had scored
            <lb />
            off the post of Excise Sub Inspector, Respondent No. 4-Usha Kiran Barai
            <lb />
            was appointed as Assistant Public Relations Officer whereas she had only
            <lb />
            1274.41 marks and Respondent No. 5-Sarika Ramteke, who had only
            <lb />
            1273.23 marks, has been appointed as Naib Tahsildar. There is no reply
            <lb />
            on behalf of the Commission or the State to explain how these two ladies
            <lb />
            who were lower than the Petitioner-Ku. Varsha Dongre even in the marks
            <lb />
            as have been awarded by the Commission, have been offered
            <lb />
            appointment without offering appointment to Petitioner-Ku. Varsha
            <lb />
            Dongre.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <head>
            Different Yardstick Applied for Evaluation of Anthropology Paper
            <lb />
        </head>

        <p>
            53.
            <lb />
            In this behalf, Petitioner No. 2-Ravindra Singh has drawn the
            <lb />
            attention of the Court to the statement of charge of misconduct framed by
            <lb />
            the Commission against Dr. B.P.Kashyap, Examination Controller of the
            <lb />
            Chhattisgarh Public Service Commission and the charge reads as follows:
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;1. Different yardsticks have been adopted in evaluation
            <lb />
            of the first paper of Anthropology in Provincial Service
            <lb />
            Examination 2003 by the Chief Examiner, evaluator and
            <lb />
            checker. In some cases 4 answers of the candidates are
            <lb />
            checked and all are evaluated 75-75 against each.
            <lb />
            Whereas, in some cases 5 answers of the candidates are
            <lb />
            checked out of which 2 are evaluated against 75-75 and
            <lb />
            others 3 are evaluated 50-50 marks against each (Exhibit
            <lb />
            point No. 6, 7 and 8).
        </item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            The direction regarding the solving of first paper of
            <lb />
            Anthropology (subject code 23), provincial service main
            <lb />
            examination 2003 were defected. In this paper 5
            <lb />
            questions are solved by every candidate. According to
            <lb />
            office advertisement part 1 of the first paper of
            <lb />
            Anthropology was mandatory. And they could have take
            <lb />
            A of part 2 or B of part 2. For the each part 1 and 2, 150
            <lb />
            marks were fixed. Chief examiner of first paper of
            <lb />
            Anthropology forwarded to evaluate it as per
            <lb />
            advertisement to you. On the basis of that you obtained
            <lb />
            permission by the Chairman to evaluate it on the basis of
            <lb />
            advertisement it is also clear from the perusal of asked
            <lb />
            erstwhile note that on the basis of report of subject expert
            <lb />
            question No. 2A of first part of first paper and question
            <lb />
            no. 4A of second part, question No. 8 of second part was
            <lb />
            found fit to be cancelled and you supplied the copy of
            <lb />
            that to the evaluator, checker and chief examiner. In this
            <lb />
            way, evaluator, checker and chief examiner received 2
            <lb />
            different directions instead of clear direction -first
            <lb />
            evaluate according to advertisement and second on the
            <lb />
            basis of representation given by subject expert for
            <lb />
            evaluation, because of this first paper of Anthropology
            <lb />
            was evaluated in 2 different ways.
        </item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            Roll No. 91884 and roll no. 40912 of the candidates
            <lb />
            answer sheet were evaluated deeming each 4 question of
            <lb />
            75 marks, both candidates have solved the question No. 4
            <lb />
            the marks were not given on those answers by treating
            <lb />
            them cancelled. Roll No. 38329 is evaluated 5 questions
            <lb />
            but question No. 8 is not cancelled. The marks evaluated
            <lb />
            of the same subject of the questions are shown
            <lb />
            differently. Though evaluation of every candidate has
            <lb />
            been done against 300 marks and they have obtained the
            <lb />
            marks accordingly. It has diminished the image of
            <lb />
            Commission because of different grounds taken in the
            <lb />
            one paper of one subject in the important examination of
            <lb />
            Public Service Commission. It is clear that you failed to
            <lb />
            issue clear direction regarding evaluation of first paper of
            <lb />
            Anthropology in provincial service main examination
            <lb />
            2003 to evaluator, checker and chief examiner as
            <lb />
            examination controller.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            54.
            <lb />
            The aforesaid charge itself clearly proves that two separate
            <lb />
            yardsticks were applied while evaluating paper of Anthropology. The
            <lb />
            paper was to carry 300 marks. In some cases, four answers were
            <lb />
            evaluated with each carrying a value of 75 marks and in some cases, five
            <lb />
            answers were evaluated out of which two were evaluated against 75
            <lb />
            marks and other three were evaluated against 50 marks. There cannot be
            <lb />
            two systems of evaluation for the same paper and therefore, this
            <lb />
            evaluation goes to the very root of the matter and has to be corrected.
            <lb />
            The other aspect is that question No. 8 of second paper of Anthropology
            <lb />
            paper was found fit to be cancelled as two different directions have been
            <lb />
            received for evaluation of the paper in Anthropology. It was also pointed
            <lb />
            out that in some answer papers, question No. 8 was marked, but in some
            <lb />
            it was not marked. It may also be pointed out that in this very charge-
            <lb />
            sheet with regard to Petitioner-Chaman Lal Sinha, the charge-sheet reads
            <lb />
            as follows:
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;2. There were total 30 marks for question no. 8 in
            <lb />
            second question paper of General Study. Candidate
            <lb />
            Chaman Lal Sinha, roll no. 40912 has obtained 10
            <lb />
            mars but in preparing the mark sheet fault has been
            <lb />
            permitted by evaluator, checker and chief evaluator.
            <lb />
            8 marks are shown in place of 10 marks. In this
            <lb />
            case, it shows laxity in side of you. Each marks has
            <lb />
            importance in provincial service main examination,
            <lb />
            it is natural to rise discontentment in the candidates
            <lb />
            because of such faulty evaluation. &quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            55.
            <lb />
            Thus, the Commission has admitted that Petitioner-Chaman Lal
            <lb />
            Sinha was entitled to at least 2 more marks. If the papers are marked in
            <lb />
            such a cursory manner where mistakes abound there can be no reliance
            <lb />
            placed on such assessment of marks.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            56.
            <lb />
            The Petitioners also pointed out that there is wrong checking of
            <lb />
            certain questions and they have tried to show that even in the main paper,
            <lb />
            checking is improper. The Petitioners have obtained a lot of answer
            <lb />
            papers and have pointed out that in some cases, even the totalling is not
            <lb />
            proper.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            57.
            <lb />
            Shri Chaman Lal Sinha-Petitioner No. 1 in Writ Petition No. 3028 of
            <lb />
            2006, has argued in person and states that he has been awarded 2 marks
            <lb />
            less in General Knowledge paper which in fact is more than apparent and
            <lb />
            this fact is also proved from the second charge against Dr. B.P.Kashyap,
            <lb />
            quoted hereinabove. He also states that if the formula was properly
            <lb />
            applied, he would have got 217.43 marks in the first paper of
            <lb />
            Anthropology and 184.3 marks in the second paper, whereas he has been
            <lb />
            awarded 151.07 and 163.95 marks. The total marks awarded to him in the
            <lb />
            subject of Anthropology is 315.02, whereas they should have been 401.73
            <lb />
            marks. Therefore, the difference is 86.71 marks, adding 2 marks i.e.
            <lb />
            less 2 marks awarded to him earlier, the difference would come to 88.71
            <lb />
            marks and his total would be 1369.12 as against 1280.41 marks awarded
            <lb />
            to him. This clearly shows that the difference has become too large to be
            <lb />
            ignored.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            58.
            <lb />
            Petitioner-Chaman Lal Sinha, who is an OBC candidate also points
            <lb />
            out that persons from the OBC category who had less marks than
            <lb />
            1369.12 have been appointed. He has also pointed out other errors in
            <lb />
            scaling etc.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            59.
            <lb />
            The Petitioners have also pointed out that the person who topped
            <lb />
            the Civil Services Examination at Roll No. 79001, had obtained 1523 raw
            <lb />
            marks but after scaling his marks have come down to 1314.19. He
            <lb />
            belongs to general category and has not been offered any post
            <lb />
            whatsoever. On the contrary, it is pointed out that one of the Respondents
            <lb />
            having Roll No. 23560 had only 1200-raw marks but his marks have been
            <lb />
            increased to 1484.01. I had asked the Respondent-Commission to
            <lb />
            answer this query also. The Commission has only given a reply that Shri
            <lb />
            Kundan Kumar in his optional subject was awarded 921 marks but after
            <lb />
            scaling they have been reduced to 712.19 marks and therefore, his total
            <lb />
            marks came down. No explanation has been given as to how his marks
            <lb />
            would fall so drastically. There is no answer given with regard to the other
            <lb />
            persons.
            <lb />

        </p>
        <head>
            Appointment of Shri Rajeev Singh Chouhan Against Scheduled
            <lb />
            Caste Category, Whereas He Had Applied Under General Category
            <lb />
        </head>
        <p>
            60.
            <lb />
            The allegation raised in the complaint of Ku. Varsha Dongre and in
            <lb />
            this petition is that one candidate Shri Rajeev Singh Chouhan had applied
            <lb />
            as a general category candidate but was appointed against Scheduled
            <lb />
            Caste category. In the report submitted by the Anti Corruption Bureau, it
            <lb />
            has been clearly stated that the appointment of Shri Rajeev Singh
            <lb />
            Chouhan by showing him to be reserved category candidate is totally
            <lb />
            illegal. Not only this, even in the initial report prepared by the Commission
            <lb />
            on 19.11.2007, it was mentioned that it is correct that Shri Rajeev Singh
            <lb />
            Chouhan, Roll No. 31106 is a general category candidate. In the select
            <lb />
            list, he has been shown as selected against reserved category which is a
            <lb />
            mistake. This mistake was known to the Commission in the year 2007.
            <lb />
            Even now in the reply filed by the Commission, it has admitted that Shri
            <lb />
            Rajeev Singh Chouhan was wrongly appointed as against reserved
            <lb />
            category. It is pointed out that the Commission issued a letter on
            <lb />
            02.06.2007 in this regard. However, Shri Rajeev Singh Chouhan
            <lb />
            continues to be in job. This clearly shows that despite having found the
            <lb />
            allegations made by the Petitioners to be correct, the Respondent-
            <lb />
            Commission took no steps to correct the list.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <head>
            Finding
            <lb />
        </head>

        <p>
            61.
            <lb />
            In view of the above discussion, I have no hesitation in holding that
            <lb />
            there were large number of irregularities in the selection process for the
            <lb />
            Civil Services Examination, 2003. It is also more than apparent that these
            <lb />
            are not minor mistakes, but mistakes which totally vitiate the entire
            <lb />
            selection process. As pointed out above, there are mistakes in totalling of
            <lb />
            marks. There are mistakes in applying the scaling formula. Even after the
            <lb />
            formula has been applied, there are mistakes in calculating and totally the
            <lb />
            marks. Interpolations have been made by officials of the Commission. The
            <lb />
            candidates who were not eligible for being called for interview have been
            <lb />
            called for interview. Those candidates who were eligible to be called for
            <lb />
            interview, have not been called for the same. The candidates who belong
            <lb />
            to general category have been given undue benefit by appointing them
            <lb />
            against the reserved category. All these amongst other mistakes have
            <lb />
            been pointed out by the Anti Corruption Bureau in June, 2007 but no
            <lb />
            steps were taken to rectify the same even though an application was filed
            <lb />
            before the High Court seeking permission to rectify the mistakes. This
            <lb />
            Court almost 9 years back told the Commission that it should rectify the
            <lb />
            mistakes, but unfortunately that has not been done.
            <lb />

        </p>
        <head>
            What Relief Should be Granted?
            <lb />
        </head>
        <p>
            62.
            <lb />
            At this stage, it would be pertinent to mention that the arguments of
            <lb />
            all counsel for the Respondents revolved around the issue as to what
            <lb />
            relief should be granted. Both the learned Advocate General as well as
            <lb />
            learned counsel for the Commission urged that Ku. Varsha Dongre will be
            <lb />
            given her due and if necessary, she will be appointed as Deputy
            <lb />
            Superintendent of Police with retrospective effect. It is prayed that since
            <lb />
            all other Respondents have worked for almost 10 years, now their
            <lb />
            appointments should not be set aside.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            63.
            <lb />
            On behalf of the private Respondents, it is urged that they are not
            <lb />
            at fault, there is no way of finding out who are the tainted candidates and
            <lb />
            who are the candidates entitled to get selected on their own merits and
            <lb />
            therefore since now the State has agreed to give the benefit to Ku. Varsha
            <lb />
            Dongre, the matter should be closed.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            64.
            <lb />
            On the other hand, the Petitioners including Petitioner-Ku. Varsha
            <lb />
            Dongre have urged this Court to reopen the entire process right from the
            <lb />
            checking of examination papers themselves. They urged that to maintain
            <lb />
            the purity of selection process, let the entire papers be rechecked under
            <lb />
            the directions and supervision of a sitting High Court Judge. They also
            <lb />
            urged that grave injustice has been done not only to the three Petitioners,
            <lb />
            but to many others including the person who actually topped the Civil
            <lb />
            Services Examination.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            65.
            <lb />
            After going through the entire records, especially the report of the
            <lb />
            Anti Corruption Bureau, I have no doubt in my mind that the errors were
            <lb />
            not mistakes as has now been pointed out. One error can be a mistake.
            <lb />
            Two or three errors may be termed to be mistakes, but in the present
            <lb />
            case, there are systematic errors on the record, which clearly shows that
            <lb />
            even after wrong marks were awarded by the Commission, it appointed
            <lb />
            those candidates who had lower marks even as per its own merit list, but
            <lb />
            did not appoint many candidates including the Petitioner Ku. Varsha
            <lb />
            Dongre, who had much higher marks. It is also found that different
            <lb />
            yardsticks were applied and some candidates who were higher in merit in
            <lb />
            the Scheduled Caste and Scheduled Tribe category, were not treated to
            <lb />
            be reserved category candidates on the ground that they failed to produce
            <lb />
            the permanent caste certificates. However, five other candidates who did
            <lb />
            not produce such certificates but were lower in merit to Ku. Navodita were
            <lb />
            selected in the Scheduled Caste and Scheduled Tribe category. This
            <lb />
            Court has also come to the conclusion that a deliberate attempt was
            <lb />
            made to alter the preference form of the Petitioner-Ku. Varsha Dongre at
            <lb />
            the level of the Commission and this is an act of forgery. It is also found
            <lb />
            that the Commission gave false and wrong replies to His Excellency the
            <lb />
            Governor, the Hon&apos;ble Chief Minister etc. As far back as year 2006, the
            <lb />
            Commission had realised that there are errors and it filed an application
            <lb />
            before this Court in the year 2007 seeking permission to correct the
            <lb />
            mistakes. Even after the permission was granted, its mistakes were not
            <lb />
            corrected. This clearly shows that there was a mala fide intention and
            <lb />
            therefore relief has to be granted taking into consideration these facts.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            66.
            <lb />
            On behalf of the Respondents, it was urged that there are no
            <lb />
            allegations of mala fides and there are not specific allegations against the
            <lb />
            selected candidates. When this Court had found that the entire selection
            <lb />
            process is tainted and vitiated and is based not only on incorrect scaling
            <lb />
            but a conscious attempt on behalf of the Commission to recommend the
            <lb />
            names of those candidates who were not eligible and in fact a criminal
            <lb />
            attempt was made in the case of Petitioner-Ku. Varsha Dongre to
            <lb />
            somehow deny her appointment, mala fides are writ large.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            67.
            <lb />
            While dealing with the issue of relief, I cannot help but comment on
            <lb />
            the role of the Public Service Commission. The Public Service
            <lb />
            Commission is a constitutional body constituted under Article 315 of the
            <lb />
            Constitution. The Chairman and Members of the Commission enjoy high
            <lb />
            status and emoluments. It is the duty of the Commission to ensure that its
            <lb />
            conduct is of an exemplary manner and it should ensure that the
            <lb />
            selections are made in a totally impartial fashion. Reference may be made
            <lb />
            to the observations of the Apex Court in Ashok Kumar Yadav &amp; Others v.
            <lb />
            State of Haryana &amp; Others {(1985) 4 SCC 417} wherein the Apex Court
            <lb />
            held as follows:
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;30. Before we part with this judgment we would like to
            <lb />
            point out that the Public Service Commission occupies a
            <lb />
            pivotal place of importance in the State and the integrity
            <lb />
            and efficiency of its administrative apparatus depends
            <lb />
            considerably on the quality of the selections made by
            <lb />
            the Public Service Commission. It is absolutely
            <lb />
            essential that the best and finest talent should be drawn
            <lb />
            in the administration and administrative services must
            <lb />
            be composed of men who are honest, upright and
            <lb />
            independent and who are not swayed by the political
            <lb />
            winds blowing in the country. The selection of
            <lb />
            candidates for the administrative services must therefore
            <lb />
            be made strictly on merits, keeping in view various
            <lb />
            factors which go to make up a strong, efficient and
            <lb />
            people oriented administrator. This can be achieved
            <lb />
            only if the Chairman and members of the Public Service
            <lb />
            Commission are eminent men possessing a high degree
            <lb />
            of caliber, competence and integrity, who would inspire
            <lb />
            confidence in the public mind about the objectivity and
            <lb />
            impartiality of the selections to be made by them. We
            <lb />
            would therefore like to strongly impress upon every
            <lb />
            State Government to take care to see that its Public
            <lb />
            Service Commission is manned by competent, honest
            <lb />
            and independent persons of outstanding ability and high
            <lb />
            reputation who command the confidence of the people
            <lb />
            and who would not allow themselves to be deflected by
            <lb />
            any extraneous considerations from discharging their
            <lb />
            duty of making selections strictly on merits. Whilst
            <lb />
            making these observations we would like to make it
            <lb />
            clear that we do no for a moment wish to suggest that
            <lb />
            the Chairman and members of the Haryana Public
            <lb />
            Service Commission in the present case were lacking in
            <lb />
            caliber, competence or integrity.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            68.
            <lb />
            The foremost duty of the Commission is to ensure fair selection.
            <lb />
            When the Commission finds that it has committed certain mistakes, then a
            <lb />
            duty is cast upon the Commission to correct the mistakes. The
            <lb />
            Commission or its officials cannot take shelter that since judicial
            <lb />
            proceedings are pending, it will not even correct its own mistakes. As far
            <lb />
            as the present case is concerned, in the year 2007 itself, this Court had
            <lb />
            clearly told the Commission that it can go ahead and rectify its mistakes.
            <lb />
            Thereafter, the Commission held a meeting and in the meeting a decision
            <lb />
            was taken to rectify the mistakes. A communication was also sent to the
            <lb />
            State Government in this regard. But thereafter, the Commission for
            <lb />
            reasons only known to it and which have not been set forth in this writ
            <lb />
            petition, decided to keep mum, do nothing and virtually let unfairness and
            <lb />
            injustice to go on. I hope and expect that in future, the Commission will
            <lb />
            not behave in such a manner. The Commission also did not produce the
            <lb />
            records of its meetings or its communication before this Court and it is
            <lb />
            only in the year 2016 when this Court asked pointed questions that the
            <lb />
            Commission filed these documents on record.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            69.
            <lb />
            At the stage of final hearing, an offer was made by the Commission
            <lb />
            as well as by the State that Petitioner-Ku. Varsha Dongre was entitled to
            <lb />
            be selected as Deputy Superintendent of Police, which is the highest post
            <lb />
            available. It was submitted that she would be given her rightful place and
            <lb />
            the matter be closed. I am afraid that this Court cannot become a party to
            <lb />
            a clandestine operation to bury the misdeeds of the Commission which is
            <lb />
            a constitutional body. This Court cannot be a party to cover up such
            <lb />
            criminal acts. This Court cannot join hands with the Respondents to give a
            <lb />
            quietus to the case. The need of the hour is to ensure that justice is not
            <lb />
            only done but also seems to have been done.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            70.
            <lb />
            In large number of cases, cited by the Respondents, the relief was
            <lb />
            not given to the Petitioner because it was found that the private
            <lb />
            Respondents had been working for a long period of time and the Apex
            <lb />
            Court therefore held that it would be unjust and harsh to quash their
            <lb />
            selection at that stage. In most of these cases, the Petitioner succeeded
            <lb />
            on technical grounds where the selection was made by misinterpretation
            <lb />
            of the rules or more candidates were appointed from a feeder category
            <lb />
            than their entitlement. These are not cases where there is a criminality
            <lb />
            involved. These are also not cases where there is a rank corruption and
            <lb />
            dishonesty and an obstinate attitude on the part of the Commission, which
            <lb />
            refused to correct its own mistakes despite knowing the same.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            71.
            <lb />
            In State Dy. Executive Engineers&apos; Association v. State of Gujarat &amp;
            <lb />
            Others {(1994) Supp 2 SCC 591} the Apex Court, refused to grant benefit
            <lb />
            to the Petitioners since the Respondents had been working for more than
            <lb />
            five years. It would however be pertinent to mention that the selection of
            <lb />
            the Respondents was held to be invalid only because they were
            <lb />
            appointed after expiry of the period of waiting list. Similarly, in Asha Kaul
            <lb />
            (Mrs.) &amp; Another v. State of Jammu &amp; Kashmir &amp; Others {(1993) 2 SCC
            <lb />
            573} the Apex Court refused to interfere in the matter. In this case, the
            <lb />
            Petitioners had approached the Court after more than 20 months and the
            <lb />
            persons who were appointed had worked as Judicial Officers during that
            <lb />
            period and there was no malpractice involved in the selection of the
            <lb />
            candidates. In Buddhi Nath Chaudhary &amp; Others v. Abahi Kumar &amp;
            <lb />
            Others {(2001) 3 SCC 328}, the Apex Court only held that if any improper
            <lb />
            appointments were made long time back, they need not be disturbed.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            72.
            <lb />
            The observations of the Apex Court in Union of India &amp; Others v.
            <lb />
            Rajesh P.U. Puthuvalnikathu &amp; Another {(2003) 7 SCC 285} are relevant
            <lb />
            and read as follows:
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;6. On a careful consideration of the contentions on
            <lb />
            either side in the light of the materials brought on
            <lb />
            record, including the relevant portions of the report
            <lb />
            said to have been submitted by the Special Committee
            <lb />
            constituted for the purpose of inquiring into the
            <lb />
            irregularities, if any, in the selection of candidates,
            <lb />
            filed on our directions -which report itself seems to
            <lb />
            have been also produced for the perusal of the High
            <lb />
            Court -there appears to be no scope for any
            <lb />
            legitimate grievance against the decision rendered by
            <lb />
            the High Court. There seems to be no serious
            <lb />
            grievance of any malpractices as such in the process
            <lb />
            of the written examination -either by the candidates
            <lb />
            or by those who actually conducted them. If the Board
            <lb />
            itself decided to dictate the question on a loudspeaker
            <lb />
            in English and Hindi and none of the participants had
            <lb />
            any grievance in understanding them or answering
            <lb />
            them, there is no justification to surmise at a later
            <lb />
            stage that the time lapse in dictating them in different
            <lb />
            languages left any room or scope for the candidates to
            <lb />
            discuss among them the possible answer. The posting
            <lb />
            of invigilators for every ten candidates would belie
            <lb />
            any such assumption. Even that apart, the Special
            <lb />
            Committee constituted does not appear to have
            <lb />
            condemned that part of the selection process relating
            <lb />
            to conduct of the written examination itself, except
            <lb />
            noticing only certain infirmities only in the matter of
            <lb />
            evaluation of answer-sheets with reference to correct
            <lb />
            answers and allotment of marks to answer some of the
            <lb />
            questions. In addition thereto, it appears that the
            <lb />
            Special Committee has extensively scrutinized and
            <lb />
            reviewed situation by re-evaluating the answer sheets
            <lb />
            of all the 134 successful as well as the 184
            <lb />
            unsuccessful candidates and ultimately found that
            <lb />
            except 31 candidates found to have been declared
            <lb />
            successful though they were not really entitled to be
            <lb />
            so declared successful and selected for appointment
            <lb />
            there was no infirmity whatsoever in the selection of
            <lb />
            other successful candidates than the 31 identified by
            <lb />
            the Special Committee. In the light of the above and
            <lb />
            in the absence of any specific or categorical finding
            <lb />
            supported by any concrete and relevant material that
            <lb />
            widespread infirmities of an all pervasive nature,
            <lb />
            which could be really said to have undermined the
            <lb />
            very process itself in its entirety or as a whole and it
            <lb />
            was impossible to weed out the beneficiaries of one or
            <lb />
            the other irregularities, or illegalities, if any, there
            <lb />
            was hardly any justification in law to deny
            <lb />
            appointment to the other selected candidates whose
            <lb />
            selections were not found to be, in any manner,
            <lb />
            vitiated for any one or the other reason. Applying a
            <lb />
            unilaterally rigid and arbitrary standard to cancel the
            <lb />
            entirety of the selections despite the firm and positive
            <lb />
            information that except 31 of such selected
            <lb />
            candidates, no infirmity could be found with reference
            <lb />
            to others, is nothing but total disregard of relevancies
            <lb />
            and allowing to be carried away by irrelevancies,
            <lb />
            giving a complete go-by to contextual considerations
            <lb />
            throwing to the winds the principle of proportionality
            <lb />
            in going farther than what was strictly and reasonably
            <lb />
            to meet the situation. In short, the competent authority
            <lb />
            completely misdirected itself in taking such an
            <lb />
            extreme and unreasonable decision of cancelling the
            <lb />
            entire selections, wholly unwarranted and unnecessary
            <lb />
            even on the factual situation found to, and totally in
            <lb />
            excess of the nature and gravity of what was at stake,
            <lb />
            thereby virtually rendering such decision to be
            <lb />
            irrational. &quot;
        </item>
        <lb />
        <p>
            It is important to note that in this case the Apex Court itself came to the
            <lb />
            conclusion that there is no serious grievance of any malpractices in the
            <lb />
            process of written examination. The observations of the Apex Court have
            <lb />
            to be read in this context. It found that there were certain infirmities with
            <lb />
            regard to 31 candidates but no infirmity could be found with reference to
            <lb />
            others, therefore, the Apex Court held that the extreme decision of
            <lb />
            cancelling the entire selection process was not warranted.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            73.
            <lb />
            In Inderpreet Singh Khalon &amp; Others v. State of Punjab &amp; Others
            <lb />
            {(2006) 11 SCC 356}, the Apex Court held as follows:
        </p>
        <lb />
        <item>
            &quot;40. ...An appointment made in violation of Articles
            <lb />
            14 and 16 of the Constitution of India would be void.
            <lb />
            It would be a nullity. {See Secy. State of Karnataka v.
            <lb />
            Umadevi (3) 1 ]. But before such a finding can be
            <lb />
            arrived at, the appointing authority must take into
            <lb />
            consideration the foundational facts. Only when such
            <lb />
            foundational facts are established, the legal principles
            <lb />
            can be applied.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            41. If the services of the appointees who had put in
            <lb />
            few years of service were terminated, compliance with
            <lb />
            three principles at the hands of the State was
            <lb />
            imperative viz. (1) to establish satisfaction in regard to
            <lb />
            the sufficiency of the materials collected so as to
            <lb />
            enable the State to arrive at its satisfaction that the
            <lb />
            selection process was tainted; (2) to determine the
            <lb />
            question that the illegalities committed go to the root
            <lb />
            of the matter which vitiate the entire selection process.
            <lb />
            Such satisfaction as also the sufficiency of materials
            <lb />
            were required to be gathered by reason of a thorough
            <lb />
            investigation in a fair and transparent manner; (3)
            <lb />
            whether the sufficient material present enabled the
            <lb />
            State to arrive at a satisfaction that the officers in
            <lb />
            majority have been found to be part of the fraudulent
            <lb />
            purpose or the system itself was corrupt.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            42. Once such findings were arrived at, all
            <lb />
            appointments traceable to the officers concerned could
            <lb />
            be cancelled....&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            74.
            <lb />
            Strong reliance has been placed by some of the Respondents on
            <lb />
            Sanjay Singh &amp; Another v. UP Public Service Commission, Allahabad &amp;
            <lb />
            Another {AIR 2007 SC 950 = (2007) 3 SCC 720} in which the Apex Court
            <lb />
            observed as follows:
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;41. The petitioners have requested that their petitions
            <lb />
            should be treated as being in public interest and the entire
            <lb />
            selection process in regard to Civil Judge (Junior
            <lb />
            Division) Examination, 2003 should be set aside. We are
            <lb />
            unable to accept the said contention. What has been
            <lb />
            made out is certain inherent defects of a particular
            <lb />
            scaling system when applied to the selection process of
            <lb />
            the Civil Judges (Junior Division) where the problem is
            <lb />
            one of examiner variability (strict/liberal examiners).
            <lb />
            Neither mala fides nor any other irregularities in the
            <lb />
            process of selection is made out. The Commission has
            <lb />
            acted bona fide in proceeding with the selection and
            <lb />
            neither the High Court nor the State Government had any
            <lb />
            grievance in regard to selections. In fact, the scaling
            <lb />
            system applied had the seal of approval of this Court in
            <lb />
            regard to the previous selection in S.C.Dixit (supra). The
            <lb />
            selected candidates have also been appointed and
            <lb />
            functioning as Judicial Officers. Further as noticed
            <lb />
            above, the scaling system adopted by the Commission
            <lb />
            has led to irrational and arbitrary results only in cases
            <lb />
            falling at the ends of the spectrum, and by and large did
            <lb />
            not affect the major portion of the selection. We,
            <lb />
            therefore, direct that our decision holding that the scaling
            <lb />
            system adopted by the Commission is unsuited in regard
            <lb />
            to Civil Judge (Junior Division) Examination and
            <lb />
            directing moderation, will be prospective in its
            <lb />
            application and will not affect the selections and
            <lb />
            appointments already made in pursuance of the 2003
            <lb />
            Examination. &quot;
        </item>
        <lb />
        <p>
            In my view, this judgment is not applicable because the Apex Court has
            <lb />
            held that no irregularity in the process of selection were made out but only
            <lb />
            scaling system was wrongly applied which led to certain irrational and
            <lb />
            arbitrary results only, but by and large, did not affect the major portion of
            <lb />
            the selection. As far as the present case is concerned, the scaling is so
            <lb />
            grossly improper that it affects the entire selection process, as admitted
            <lb />
            by the Commission itself.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            75.
            <lb />
            In Tridip Kumar Dingal &amp; Others v. State of West Bengal &amp; Others
            <lb />
            {(2009) 1 SCC 768}, the Apex Court held as follows:
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;53. In our considered opinion, the law laid down by
            <lb />
            this Court in aforesaid and other cases applies to the
            <lb />
            present situation also. We are of the considered view
            <lb />
            that it would be inequitable if we set aside
            <lb />
            appointments of candidates selected, appointed and
            <lb />
            are working since 1998-1999. We, therefore, hold that
            <lb />
            the Tribunal and the High Court were right in not
            <lb />
            setting aside their appointments.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            54. It is undisputed that by the time we are called
            <lb />
            upon to decide the matter, the selected and appointed
            <lb />
            candidates have completed ten years. They are thus
            <lb />
            having rich experience in the field. There are several
            <lb />
            vacancies. The stand of the State Government is
            <lb />
            equally fair and reasonable. It was stated that those
            <lb />
            candidates who had grievance against the selection
            <lb />
            and had not waived their right to get similar treatment
            <lb />
            and had approached the Tribunal, the High Court and
            <lb />
            this Court, may be granted similar relief. We are also
            <lb />
            of the view that such relief can be granted in favour of
            <lb />
            the appellants who were agitated and had raised voice
            <lb />
            against the selection of candidates before the
            <lb />
            Tribunal, before the High Court and before us.
        </item>
        <lb />
        <p>
            It would be pertinent to mention that in this case, there were 4000
            <lb />
            candidates for 80 posts of Medical Technologists and the State decided to
            <lb />
            conduct a written test wherein cut off marks was fixed at 40%. 1070
            <lb />
            candidates were left in the field and they were interviewed and a select list
            <lb />
            was prepared. The issue was whether shortlisting could be done by
            <lb />
            holding a written test and whether the select list would be prepared solely
            <lb />
            on the basis of interview. The Apex Court held that the written test could
            <lb />
            be conducted but it affirmed the judgment of the High Court that for
            <lb />
            drawing up the merit list, marks of both written test and the interview
            <lb />
            should be counted and not the only marks in the interview. That was a
            <lb />
            case where marks of the written tests were not added while computing the
            <lb />
            merit list. It was not a case of gross irregularity or corruption and the
            <lb />
            observations have to be read in this context.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            76.
            <lb />
            In Ramesh Chandra Sankla etc. v. Vikram Cement etc. {AIR (2009)
            <lb />
            SC 713}, the Apex Court held as follows:
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;89. From the above cases, it clearly transpires that
            <lb />
            powers under Article 226 and 227 are discretionary
            <lb />
            and equitable and are required to be exercised in the
            <lb />
            larger interest of justice. While granting relief in
            <lb />
            favour of the applicant, the Court must take into
            <lb />
            account balancing interests and equities. It can mould
            <lb />
            relief considering the facts of the case. It can pass an
            <lb />
            appropriate order which justice may demand and
            <lb />
            equities may project. As observed by this Court in
            <lb />
            Shiv Shankar Dal Mills v. State of Haryana (1980) 1
            <lb />
            SCR 1170, Courts of equity should go much further
            <lb />
            both to give and refuse relief in furtherance of public
            <lb />
            interest. Granting or withholding of relief may
            <lb />
            properly be dependent upon considerations of justice,
            <lb />
            equity and good conscience.&quot;
        </item>
        <lb />
        <p>
            It would be pertinent to mention that in this case also, the appointment of
            <lb />
            the Respondents were not quashed on equitable grounds. Again this was
            <lb />
            case where there were no gross irregularities or malpractices or
            <lb />
            corruption.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            77.
            <lb />
            In Rajesh Kumar &amp; Others v. State of Bihar &amp; Others {(2013) 4
            <lb />
            SCC 690 the Apex Court while dealing with a case where there was
            <lb />
            erroneous evaluation because of use of wrong answer key, the Apex
            <lb />
            Court held that even though those examinees who succeeded on the
            <lb />
            basis of such erroneous evaluation may not be at fault, the proper
            <lb />
            direction is to direct re-evaluation. It did not approve the order of the High
            <lb />
            Court setting aside the entire examination, however held that re-
            <lb />
            evaluation must be done. The relevant portion of the judgment reads as
            <lb />
            follows :
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;15. There is, in our view, no merit in that contention
            <lb />
            of Mr Rao. The reasons are not far to seek. It is true
            <lb />
            that the writ petitioners had not impleaded the selected
            <lb />
            candidates as party-respondents to the case. But it is
            <lb />
            wholly incorrect to say that the relief prayed for by the
            <lb />
            petitioners could not be granted to them simply
            <lb />
            because there was no prayer for the same. The writ
            <lb />
            petitioners, it is evident, on a plain reading or the writ
            <lb />
            petition questioned not only the process of evaluation
            <lb />
            of the answer script by the Commission but
            <lb />
            specifically averred that the &quot;model answer key&quot;
            <lb />
            which formed the basis for such evaluation was
            <lb />
            erroneous. One of the question that, therefore, fell for
            <lb />
            consideration by the High Court directly was whether
            <lb />
            the &quot;model answer key&quot; was correct. The High Court
            <lb />
            had aptly referred that question to experts in the field
            <lb />
            who, as already noticed above, found the &quot;model
            <lb />
            answer key&quot; to be erroneous in regard to as many as
            <lb />
            45 questions out of a total of 100 questions contained
            <lb />
            in &apos;A&apos; series question paper. Other errors were also
            <lb />
            found to which we have referred earlier. If the key
            <lb />
            which was used for evaluating the answer sheets was
            <lb />
            itself defective the result prepared on the basis of the
            <lb />
            same could be no different. The Division Bench of the
            <lb />
            High Court was, therefore, perfectly justified in
            <lb />
            holding that the result of the examination insofar as
            <lb />
            the same pertained to &apos;A&apos; series question paper was
            <lb />
            vitiated. This was bound to affect the result of the
            <lb />
            entire examination qua every candidate whether or not
            <lb />
            he was a party to the proceedings. It also goes without
            <lb />
            saying that if the result was vitiated by the application
            <lb />
            of a wrong key, any appointment made on the basis
            <lb />
            thereof would also be rendered unsustainble. The High
            <lb />
            Court was, in that view, entitled to mould the relief
            <lb />
            prayed for in the writ petition and issue directions
            <lb />
            considered necessary not only to maintain the purity of
            <lb />
            the selection process but also to ensure that no
            <lb />
            candidate earned an undeserved advantage over others
            <lb />
            by application of an erroneous key.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            16. The decisions of this Court in Bharat Amratlal
            <lb />
            Kothari v. Dosukhan Samadkhan Sindhi 5 and State of
            <lb />
            Orissa v. Mamata Mohanty 6 , relied upon by Mr Rao
            <lb />
            are clearly distinguishable. The power of the court to
            <lb />
            mould the relief, according to the demands of the
            <lb />
            situation was never the subject-matter of dispute in
            <lb />
            those cases. That power is well recognized and is
            <lb />
            available to a writ court to do complete justice
            <lb />
            between the parties. The first limb of the argument
            <lb />
            advanced by Mr Rao fails and is accordingly rejected.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            19. The submission made by Mr Rao are not without
            <lb />
            merit. Given the nature of the defect in the answer key
            <lb />
            the most natural and logical way of correcting the
            <lb />
            evaluation of the scripts was to correct the key and get
            <lb />
            the answer scripts re-evaluated on the basis thereof.
            <lb />
            There was, in the circumstances, no compelling
            <lb />
            reasons for directing a fresh examination to be held by
            <lb />
            the Commission especially when there was no
            <lb />
            allegation about any malpractice fraud or corrupt
            <lb />
            motives that could possibly vitiate the earlier
            <lb />
            examination to call for a fresh attempt by all
            <lb />
            concerned. The process of re-evaluation of the answer
            <lb />
            script with reference to the correct key will in addition
            <lb />
            be less expensive apart from being quicker. The
            <lb />
            process would also not give any unfair advantage to
            <lb />
            anyone of the candidates on account of the time lag
            <lb />
            between the examination earlier held and the one that
            <lb />
            may have been held pursuant to the direction of the
            <lb />
            High Court. Suffice it to say that the re-evaluation was
            <lb />
            and is a better option, in the facts and circumstances of
            <lb />
            the case.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            20. That brings us to the submission by Mr Rao that
            <lb />
            while re-evaluation is a god option not only to do
            <lb />
            justice to those who may have suffered on account of
            <lb />
            an erroneous key being applied to the process but also
            <lb />
            to the writ petitioners, Respondents 6 to 18 in the
            <lb />
            matter of allocating to them their rightful place in the
            <lb />
            merit list. Such evaluation need not necessarily result
            <lb />
            in the ouster of the appellants should they be found to
            <lb />
            fall below the &quot;cut-off&quot; mark in the merit list. Mr Rao
            <lb />
            gave two reasons in support of that submission.
            <lb />
            Firstly, he contended that the appellants are not
            <lb />
            responsible for the error committed by the parties in
            <lb />
            the matter of evaluation of the answer scripts. The
            <lb />
            position may have been different if the appellants were
            <lb />
            guilty of any fraud, misrepresentation or malpractice
            <lb />
            that would have deprived them of any sympathy from
            <lb />
            the court or justified their ouster. Secondly, he
            <lb />
            contended that the appellants have served the State
            <lb />
            efficiently and without any complaint for nearly seven
            <lb />
            years now and most of them, if not all, may have
            <lb />
            become overage for fresh recruitment within the State
            <lb />
            or outside the State. They have also lost the
            <lb />
            opportunity to appear in the subsequent examination
            <lb />
            held in the year 2007. Their ouster from service after
            <lb />
            their
            <lb />
            employment on the basis of a properly
            <lb />
            conducted competitive examination not itself affected
            <lb />
            by any malpractice or other extraneous consideration
            <lb />
            or misrepresentation will cause hardship to them and
            <lb />
            ruin their careers and lives. The experience gained by
            <lb />
            these appellants over the years would also, according
            <lb />
            to Mr Rao, go waste as the State will not have the
            <lb />
            advantage of using valuable human resources which
            <lb />
            was found useful in the service of the people of the
            <lb />
            State of Bihar for a long time. Mr Rao, therefore,
            <lb />
            prayed for a suitable direction that while re-evaluation
            <lb />
            can determined the inter se position of the writ
            <lb />
            petitioners and the appellants in these appeals, the
            <lb />
            result of such re-evaluation may not lead to their
            <lb />
            ouster from service, if they fell below the cut-off line.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            21. There is considerable merit in the submission of
            <lb />
            Mr Rao. It goes without saying that the appellants
            <lb />
            were innocent parties who have not, in any manner,
            <lb />
            contributed to the preparation of the erroneous key or
            <lb />
            the distorted result. There is no mention of any fraud
            <lb />
            or malpractice against the appellants who have served
            <lb />
            the State for nearly seven years now. In the
            <lb />
            circumstances, while inter se merit position may be
            <lb />
            relevant for the appellants, the ouster of the latter need
            <lb />
            not be an inevitable and inexorable consequence of
            <lb />
            such a re-evaluation. The re-evaluation process may
            <lb />
            additionally benefit those who have lost the hope of an
            <lb />
            appointment on the basis of a wrong key applied for
            <lb />
            evaluating the answer script. Such of those candidates
            <lb />
            as may be ultimately found to be entitled to issue of
            <lb />
            appointment letters on the basis of their merit shall
            <lb />
            benefit by such re-evaluation and shall pick up their
            <lb />
            appointments on that basis according to their inter se
            <lb />
            position on the merit list.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            78.
            <lb />
            In Vikas Pratap Singh &amp; Others v. State of Chhattisgarh &amp; Others
            <lb />
            {(2013) 14 SCC 494} erroneous and incorrect answer key was used and
            <lb />
            some candidates were selected. This was not done with a bad intention
            <lb />
            but it was a pure and simple mistake. The relevant observations of the
            <lb />
            Apex Court are as follows:
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;22. The pristine maxim of fraus et jus nunquam
            <lb />
            cohabitant (fraud and justice never dwell together) has
            <lb />
            never lost its temper over the centuries and it
            <lb />
            continues to dwell in spirit and body of service law
            <lb />
            jurisprudences. It is settled law that no legal right in
            <lb />
            respect of appointment to a said post vests in a
            <lb />
            candidate who has obtained the employment by fraud,
            <lb />
            mischief, misrepresentation or mala fide. (See
            <lb />
            Vizianagaram Social Welfare Residential School
            <lb />
            Society
            <lb />
            v.
            <lb />
            M.
            <lb />
            Tripura
            <lb />
            Sundari
            <lb />
            Devi 5 ,
            <lb />
            S.P.Chengalvaraya Naidu v. Jagannath 6 and Union of
            <lb />
            India v. M. Bhaskaran 7 .) It is also settled law that a
            <lb />
            person appointed erroneously on a post must not reap
            <lb />
            the benefits of a wrongful appointment jeopradising
            <lb />
            the interest of the meritorious and worthy candidates.
            <lb />
            However, in cases where wrongful or irregular
            <lb />
            appointment is made without any mistake on the part
            <lb />
            of the appointee and upon discovery of such error or
            <lb />
            irregularity the appointee is terminated, this Court has
            <lb />
            taken a sympathetic view in the light of various
            <lb />
            factors including bona fide of the candidate in such
            <lb />
            appointment and length of service of the candidate
            <lb />
            after such appointment. (See Vinodan T. v. University
            <lb />
            of Calicut 8 ; State of U.P. v. Neeraj Awasthi 9 ).
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            23. In Girijesh Shrivastava v. State of M.P. 10 , the High
            <lb />
            Court had invalidated the rule prescribing selection
            <lb />
            procedure which awarded grace marks of 25 per cent
            <lb />
            and age relaxation to the candidates with three years&apos;
            <lb />
            long non-formal teaching experiences as a
            <lb />
            consequence of which several candidates appointed as
            <lb />
            teachers at the formal education institutions under the
            <lb />
            said rule stood ousted. This Court while concurring
            <lb />
            with the observations made by the High Court kept in
            <lb />
            view that upon rectification of irregularities in
            <lb />
            appointment after a considerable length of time an
            <lb />
            order for cancellation of appointment would severely
            <lb />
            affect economic security of a number of candidates
            <lb />
            and observed as follows: (SCC p. 714, para 31)
        </item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            31. ...Most of them were earlier teaching in
            <lb />
            non-formal education centres, from where they
            <lb />
            had resigned to apply in response to the
            <lb />
            advertisement. They had left their previous
            <lb />
            employment in view of the fact that for their
            <lb />
            three-year long teaching experiences, the
            <lb />
            interview process in the present selection was
            <lb />
            awarding them grace marks of 25%. It had also
            <lb />
            given them a relaxation of 8 years with respect
            <lb />
            to their age. Now, if they lose their jobs as a
            <lb />
            result of the High Court&apos;s order, they would be
            <lb />
            effectively unemployed as they cannot even
            <lb />
            revert to their earlier jobs in the non-formal
            <lb />
            education centres, which have been abolished
            <lb />
            since then. This would severely affect the
            <lb />
            economic security of many families. Most of
            <lb />
            them are between the age group of 35-45 years,
            <lb />
            and the prospects for them of finding another
            <lb />
            job are rather dim. Some of them were in fact
            <lb />
            awaiting their salary rise at the time of
            <lb />
            quashing of their appointment by the High
            <lb />
            Court.&quot;
        </item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            Therefore, mindful of the aforesaid circumstances this
            <lb />
            Court directed non-ouster of the candidates appointed
            <lb />
            under the invalidated rule.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            27. Admittedly, in the instant case the error committed
            <lb />
            by the respondent Board in the matter of evaluation of
            <lb />
            the answer script could not be attributed to the
            <lb />
            appellants as they have neither been found to have
            <lb />
            committed any fraud or misrepresentation in being
            <lb />
            appointed qua the first merit list nor has the
            <lb />
            preparation of the erroneous model answer key or the
            <lb />
            specious result contributed to them. Had the contrary
            <lb />
            been the case, it would have justified their ouster upon
            <lb />
            re-evaluation and deprived them of any sympathy
            <lb />
            from this Court irrespective of their length of service.
            <lb />
            28. In our considered view, the appellants have
        </item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            successfully undergone training and are efficiently
            <lb />
            serving the respondent State for more than three years
            <lb />
            and undoubtedly their termination would not only
            <lb />
            impinge upon the economic security of the appellants
            <lb />
            and their dependents but also adversely affect their
            <lb />
            careers. This would be highly unjust and grossly
            <lb />
            unfair to the appellants who are innocent appointees
            <lb />
            of an erroneous evaluation of the answer script.
            <lb />
            However, their continuation in service should neither
            <lb />
            give any unfair advantage to the appellants nor cause
            <lb />
            undue prejudice to the candidates selected qua the
            <lb />
            revised merit list.&quot;
        </item>
        <lb />
        <p>
            In this case, the Apex Court held that fraud and justice can never dwell
            <lb />
            together. The Apex Court also held that no legal right in respect of
            <lb />
            appointment to a said post vests in a candidate who has obtained the
            <lb />
            employment by fraud, mischief, misrepresentation or mala fide. The Apex
            <lb />
            Court also held that it was settled law that a person appointed erroneously
            <lb />
            on a post must not reap the benefits of wrongful appointment jeopardising
            <lb />
            the interest of the meritorious and worthy candidate.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            79. The judgment delivered by the Apex Court in Joginder Pal and Others
            <lb />
            v. State of Punjab &amp; Others {(2014) 6 SCC 644} is very important and it
            <lb />
            would be relevant to refer the following observations:
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;10.3 A distinction exists between a proven case of
            <lb />
            mass cheating for a board examination and an
            <lb />
            unproven imputed charge of corruption where the
            <lb />
            appointment of a civil servant is involved. Only in the
            <lb />
            event it is found to be impossible or highly
            <lb />
            improbable that the tainted cases can be separated
            <lb />
            from the non-tainted cases could en masse orders of
            <lb />
            termination be issued. Both the State Government as
            <lb />
            also the High Court in that view of the matter should
            <lb />
            have made all endeavours to segregate the tainted
            <lb />
            from the non-tainted candidates.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            10.4 Cases which may arise where the selection
            <lb />
            process is perceived to be tainted may be categorised
            <lb />
            in the following manner;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (i) Cases where the &quot;event&quot; has been
            <lb />
            investigated.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (ii) Cases where CBI inquiry took place
            <lb />
            and was completed or a preliminary
            <lb />
            investigation was concluded.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (iii) Cases where the selection was made
            <lb />
            but appointment was not made.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (iv) Cases where the candidates were also
            <lb />
            ineligible and the appointments were
            <lb />
            found to be contrary to law or rules.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            If the services of appointees who had put in a few years
            <lb />
            service were terminated, compliance with three principles
            <lb />
            at the hands of the State was imperative viz. (1) to
            <lb />
            establish satisfaction in regard to the sufficiency of the
            <lb />
            materials collected so as to enable the State to arrive at its
            <lb />
            satisfaction that the selection process was tainted; (2) to
            <lb />
            determine the question that the illegalities committed
            <lb />
            went to the rot of the matter, which vitiated the entire
            <lb />
            selection process. Such satisfaction as also the sufficiency
            <lb />
            of materials were required to be gathered by reason of a
            <lb />
            thorough investigation in a fair and transparent manner;
            <lb />
            (3) whether the sufficient material present enabled the
            <lb />
            State to arrive at a satisfaction that the officers in majority
            <lb />
            had been found to be part of the fraudulent purpose or the
            <lb />
            system itself was corrupt.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            10.5 Once the necessary
            <lb />
            factual findings as
            <lb />
            enumerated above are arrived at, or it is found
            <lb />
            impossible or highly improbable to separate tainted
            <lb />
            from untainted cases, all appointments traceable to the
            <lb />
            officers concerned could be cancelled. But admittedly,
            <lb />
            in the present case, although there had been serious
            <lb />
            amputations against Ravinderpal Singh Sidhu being at
            <lb />
            the helm of the affairs of the State Public Service
            <lb />
            Commissions, all decisions made by the Commission
            <lb />
            during his tenure are yet to be set aside.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            80.
            <lb />
            As far as the present case is concerned, the facts clearly depict
            <lb />
            corruption and large scale manipulation at all levels. This Court has no
            <lb />
            doubt that there was a conspiracy to appoint certain candidates who were
            <lb />
            not within the field of choice and were less meritorious or were not even
            <lb />
            eligible to be called for interview. With this criminal intent in mind, certain
            <lb />
            candidates who were unfit were selected. This is obvious from the fact
            <lb />
            that not only scaling was improper but marks and forms have been
            <lb />
            interpolated. The candidates with lower marks have been offered
            <lb />
            appointment. The candidates who belonged to the general category
            <lb />
            were appointed against the reserved category post and certain candidates
            <lb />
            in the reserved categories were granted appointment though they had not
            <lb />
            produced any permanent caste certificate but some who were in the same
            <lb />
            boat and were more meritorious were denied appointment. The present
            <lb />
            case is not a case of mistakes but as is apparent from the report of the
            <lb />
            Anti Corruption Bureau, is a case of criminal conspiracy.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            81.
            <lb />
            On behalf of some of the Respondents, it was urged that the
            <lb />
            amendment in the writ petition with regard to scaling was brought out in
            <lb />
            the year 2014. That may be true but the fact remains that from the very
            <lb />
            beginning, the claim of the Petitioners was also that scaling is improper.
            <lb />
            The Commission itself had moved an application in the year 2007 seeking
            <lb />
            permission of the Court to correct its own mistakes even with regard to
            <lb />
            scaling. Therefore, in my view, the Respondents cannot derive any benefit
            <lb />
            from the same.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            82.
            <lb />
            In Secretary, State of Karnataka &amp; Others v. Umadevi (3) &amp; Others
            <lb />
            {(2006) 4 SCC 1} the Apex Court held that those who had been
            <lb />
            appointed irregularly and whose appointment affects the rights of others
            <lb />
            had no right to be claimed equity that they should be regularised without
            <lb />
            following the rules. The case of the Petitioners stand on better footing
            <lb />
            because in the present case it is more than amply proved that the
            <lb />
            selection process was tainted with gross irregularities, criminal acts of
            <lb />
            forgery, wrong information being given to the higher authorities and a
            <lb />
            constitutional body like Public Service Commission not being ready to
            <lb />
            rectify its mistakes even after those mistakes were pointed out to it and
            <lb />
            the Commission admitted and knew that those mistakes have been
            <lb />
            committed. The manner in which the Commission has behaved itself
            <lb />
            leads to the conclusion that highest official of the Commission were not
            <lb />
            only aware of the mistakes of scaling but were aware of other
            <lb />
            irregularities and condoned the errors in scaling with ulterior and
            <lb />
            extraneous motive.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            83.
            <lb />
            The following judgments relied upon by the Respondents are not
            <lb />
            at all relevant to this case, namely -Managing Committee, Sayed S. High
            <lb />
            School v. State of Orissa &amp; Others {(1995) Supp. 4 SCC 546}, Rungta
            <lb />
            Engineering College, Bhilai &amp; Another v. Chhattisgarh Swami Vivekanand
            <lb />
            Technical University &amp; Another {(2015) 11 SCC 291}, Richa Mishra v.
            <lb />
            State of Chhattisgarh &amp; Others {(2016) 4 SCC 179 : AIR (2016) SC 753};
            <lb />
            Rajesh Kumar Daria v. Rajasthan Public Service Commission &amp; Others
            <lb />
            {(2007) 8 SCC 785}; Calcutta Gas Company (Proprietary) Ltd. v. State of
            <lb />
            West Bengal &amp; Others {AIR 1962 1044 (V 49 C 141)}; Pranshu Indurkhya
            <lb />
            v. State of M.P. &amp; Others (AIR 2005 MP 152); Vinod Kumar v. State of
            <lb />
            U.P. &amp; Others {(2001) 4 SCC 734}.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            84.
            <lb />
            Though not strictly germane to the case, it would be pertinent to
            <lb />
            mention that Shri Ashok Darbari, who was Chairman of the Public Service
            <lb />
            Commission was subjected to proceedings under Clause (1) of Article
            <lb />
            317 of the Constitution of India. In that case, it was the stand of the State
            <lb />
            that ever-since Shri Ashok Darbari had been working in the Commission,
            <lb />
            there were complaints in respect of working ability and impartiality of the
            <lb />
            Chairman of the Commission. Though specific charges against Shri
            <lb />
            Ashok Darbari were not proved, it is apparent that working of the
            <lb />
            Commission where he was Chairman was not proper. The judgment
            <lb />
            rendered in the matter of Shri Ashok Darbari, Chairman, Chhattisgarh
            <lb />
            Public Service Commission is reported in AIR 2009 SC 3028.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            85.
            <lb />
            In view of the aforesaid discussion, it is apparent that this Court
            <lb />
            has to balance the claims and rights of the Petitioners against the equity
            <lb />
            claimed by the private Respondents. In my view, the main guidelines in
            <lb />
            the aforesaid judgments is that a pragmatic approach has to be taken. I
            <lb />
            am of the considered view that though the there are serious irregularities,
            <lb />
            the entire examination process cannot be set aside. I am also not in
            <lb />
            agreement with the Petitioners that the original papers of all the
            <lb />
            candidates be also got revalued. That cannot be done. This Court is also
            <lb />
            unable to grant a general relief because other than the Petitioners no
            <lb />
            other persons are before this Court. Only one person, namely, Santosh
            <lb />
            Kumar Kunjan had filed a petition and his petition has been dismissed and
            <lb />
            the said order had also been affirmed by a Division Bench of this Court.
            <lb />
            This Court cannot reopen the order passed against him. Therefore, it is
            <lb />
            not possible to grant relief to others. As such, this Court is unable to
            <lb />
            accede to the request of the Petitioners that papers of all the candidates
            <lb />
            be checked afresh.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            86.
            <lb />
            At the same time, this Court is of the considered view that it cannot
            <lb />
            overlook the crass corruption, dishonesty and mala fides which are
            <lb />
            apparent from the facts of this case.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            87.
            <lb />
            In light of the aforesaid observations, I am clearly of the view that
            <lb />
            this is a fit case where relief must be granted to the Petitioners.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            88.
            <lb />
            Corruption is a disease which is threatening the very existence of
            <lb />
            the country. Corruption is a malaise which affects each and every citizen
            <lb />
            of this country. This case reeks of corruption and it would not be proper
            <lb />
            to condone corruption. When a person feels unwell, administering him a
            <lb />
            placebo sometimes works. When more symptoms of illness erupt, a
            <lb />
            palliative dose is needed. If things do not improve, analgesics are
            <lb />
            administered. If these also do not help, then antibiotics are administered.
            <lb />
            But if the wound keep festering and threatening the existence of entire
            <lb />
            body, then amputation is also resorted to. This is a case where
            <lb />
            amputation may have to be resorted to in respect of those candidates who
            <lb />
            were not even entitled to be called for interview and have been called for
            <lb />
            the same. These candidates are holding their posts not because they
            <lb />
            were meritorious and selected on merits, but they are holding their posts
            <lb />
            because somebody in the Public Service Commission was guilty of
            <lb />
            nepotism, favourtism and corruption in helping such candidates. These
            <lb />
            candidates, who have not been selected on merit, but due to an unholy
            <lb />
            nexus which has unfortunately been tried to be covered up by the
            <lb />
            Commission itself, cannot be given any benefit. It is not at all difficult to
            <lb />
            find out who are tainted candidates and who are not. This can easily be
            <lb />
            done only after re-scaling the marks in the optional subjects and ensuring
            <lb />
            that the mistakes which are known to the Commission are corrected and
            <lb />
            rectified. Therefore, the writ petitions are disposed of with the following
            <lb />
            directions:
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            (i) The State shall take immediate steps to remove Shri Rajeev
            <lb />
            Singh Chauhan from service since he was a general
            <lb />
            category candidate and was illegally appointed against
            <lb />
            Scheduled Caste category. This be done within two weeks.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (ii) Petitioner-Ku. Varsha Dongre has not asked for
            <lb />
            re-assessment of her answer paper. The main answer paper
            <lb />
            of Petitioners in Writ Petition No. 3028 of 2006 only shall be
            <lb />
            re-totalled. It is clarified that there shall be no re-evaluation,
            <lb />
            but re-totalling shall be done to ensure that the marks have
            <lb />
            been correctly added.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (iii) The Commission is also directed to issue one instruction with
            <lb />
            regard to checking of the papers of Anthropology and shall
            <lb />
            ensure that one yardstick is applied. The papers need not be
            <lb />
            re-evaluated again, but the marks can be proportionately
            <lb />
            increased or decreased. In case, the Commission decides
            <lb />
            that only four questions are to be evaluated, then answers in
            <lb />
            the best four questions of all the candidates shall only be
            <lb />
            taken into consideration. In case, previously some questions
            <lb />
            have been evaluated out of 60 and 40 marks have been
            <lb />
            awarded, and now question shall be taken to be of 75 marks
            <lb />
            then 50 marks can be awarded. Similarly, if question No. 8 is
            <lb />
            excluded, it shall be excluded for all the candidates. In a
            <lb />
            nutshell, the Commission shall ensure that only one yardstick
            <lb />
            is applied in the papers of Anthropology.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (iv) That the scaling of answer papers in the optional subject of
            <lb />
            all the persons, who had appeared in the main examination
            <lb />
            including those who are not before this Court, shall be done
            <lb />
            afresh on the basis of formula as approved by the Public
            <lb />
            Service Commission. This scaling is only mathematical in
            <lb />
            nature and can be done by any reputed organisation. The
            <lb />
            Public Service Commission may itself get this scaling done
            <lb />
            all over again. The process of fresh scaling be completed by
            <lb />
            31 st October, 2016. Thereafter, the merit on the basis of
            <lb />
            written test shall be drawn up and if it is found as alleged by
            <lb />
            the Anti Corruption Bureau that 52 candidates, who were not
            <lb />
            eligible to be called for interview, have been called for
            <lb />
            interview, then those 52 candidates or any number of
            <lb />
            candidates may be less or more than 52, who were not even
            <lb />
            entitled to be qualified for interview cannot be retained in
            <lb />
            service and their services shall be terminated within one
            <lb />
            month thereafter.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (v) Since these persons were not eligible to be called for
            <lb />
            interview, they cannot claim that their appointment is merely
            <lb />
            irregular and they should continue as such. The only
            <lb />
            equitable relief which can be granted to these persons, who
            <lb />
            have been illegally appointed, is that the State shall not
            <lb />
            recover the pay and perks which these persons have illegally
            <lb />
            enjoyed for almost ten years.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (vi) Thereafter, in case any of the three Petitioners are entitled to
            <lb />
            be placed in any particular service, they shall be placed in
            <lb />
            the said service and they shall be given all the benefits of
            <lb />
            being placed in service including seniority, promotion,
            <lb />
            monetary benefits etc.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (vii) It is clarified that since nobody has challenged the marks in
            <lb />
            the interview, after re-scaling is done no fresh interviews
            <lb />
            shall be conducted. Only the marks already awarded for viva
            <lb />
            voce shall be added to the marks given after re-scaling and
            <lb />
            fresh final seniority list will be drawn up after excluding the
            <lb />
            persons who were not entitled to be called for interview.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (viii) The Petitioners have fought a long drawn out battle. It is only
            <lb />
            because of the persistence and tenacity of the Petitioners,
            <lb />
            especially Ku. Varsha Dongre that these irregularities, acts of
            <lb />
            corruption, nepotism, favourtism etc. have been brought out.
            <lb />
            Therefore, Chhattisgarh Public Service Commission is
            <lb />
            burdened with costs of Rs.5,00,000/-in the writ petition of
            <lb />
            Petitioner Ku. Varsha Dongre, which shall be paid to her and
            <lb />
            Rs. 2,00,000/-in the other writ petition where both the Writ
            <lb />
            Petitioners will get Rs.1,00,000/-each. Exemplary costs have
            <lb />
            been awarded because of the totally false stand taken by the
            <lb />
            Chhattisgarh Public Service Commission earlier and its
            <lb />
            obstinacy in not correcting the mistakes for which permission
            <lb />
            was granted to it on its own application by this Court vide
            <lb />
            order dated 26.10.2007. The costs be paid on or before
            <lb />
            31 st October, 2016.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            89.
            <lb />
            The writ petitions are disposed of with the aforesaid directions.
        </p>
        <lb />
        <p>
            Sd/-
            <lb />
            (Deepak Gupta)
            <lb />
            CHIEF JUSTICE
            <lb />
            Subbu
        </p>

    </item>
</tei>