<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc xml:id="0" />
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <p>
            1.
            <lb />
            As common question of law and facts are involved in all the
            <lb />
            aforesaid bunch of Writ Petitions (Cr.) &amp; Writ Petition (C), they
            <lb />
            heard analogously and are being disposed of by this common
            <lb />
            order.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            2.
            <lb />
            By filing all these Writ Petitions (Cr.), the petitioners who are
            <lb />
            either Government Officials or the land losers have assailed the
            <lb />
            report dated 30.07.2019 given by respondent No.2/Collector
            <lb />
            Bastar and on the basis of this report, First Information Report
            <lb />
            dated 04.08.2019 was registered in connection with Crime No.
            <lb />
            409/2019 at Police Station Kotwali, Jagdalpur, District-Bastar
            <lb />
            under Sections 109, 120-B, 467, 468, 471, 406, 407, 408 and
            <lb />
            409 of IPC and two letters bearing Nos. 1274 and 1283 dated 5-
            <lb />
            8-2019 issued by respondent No.3/Station House Officer to
            <lb />
            respondent No.4 Bank seeking to freeze the Bank Account Nos.
            <lb />
            101202000007188, 10120400000117 and 10120100010115 of
            <lb />
            the respective petitioners on various facts and grounds which
            <lb />
            will be dealt with separately with regard to individual petitioners
            <lb />
            in foregoing paragraphs of this order.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <head>
            WPCR No. 1031 of 2019
            <lb />
        </head>

        <p>
            3.
            <lb />
            The brief facts as projected by the petitioner in WPCR No. 1031
            <lb />
            of 2019 are that the petitioner is a tribal belonging to Nagwanshi
            <lb />
            Tribe. The State of Chhattisgarh by issuing the notification dated
            <lb />
            02.07.2014 has notified Ward No.37 of Jagdalpur as Lok Manya
            <lb />
            Tilak Ward and its boundaries are near to and adjoining village
            <lb />
            Palli in Bastar District. On 28.08.2015 the Central Government
            <lb />
            issued a notification exercising powers under Section 105(3) of
            <lb />
            the Right to Compensation Act 2013 (for short, &quot;the Act, 2013&quot;),
            <lb />
            by which certain provisions of the Act, 2013 have been made
            <lb />
            applicable. Thereafter, on 04-04.2016 the Government of India
            <lb />
            issued a notification under Section 2(37-A) of the Railways Act
            <lb />
            for notifying the Special Railway Project in the State of
            <lb />
            Chhattisgarh between Rowghat -Jagdalpur (140 km.) part of
            <lb />
            Dailirajhara -Jagdalpur 235 km. railway line. The said special
            <lb />
            railway project was to be constructed for providing better
            <lb />
            infrastructure. It has been further stated that the Central
            <lb />
            Government notified the rules for the purpose of special railway
            <lb />
            projects vide notification dated 23.06.2016 and thereafter vide
            <lb />
            order dated 20.01.2017 has appointed competent authority as
            <lb />
            defined under Section 2(7A) of the Railways Act to perform the
            <lb />
            functions of the competent authority for such area as may be
            <lb />
            specified in the notification and accordingly for Bastar District,
            <lb />
            Additional Collector was appointed as competent authority to
            <lb />
            determine the compensation.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            4.
            <lb />
            It has been further stated that the petitioner has submitted his
            <lb />
            objections for the acquisition of his lands situated at village Palli
            <lb />
            and his objections were rejected, by the competent authority on
            <lb />
            31.01.2018. Thereafter, the Central Government issued
            <lb />
            notification dated 21.08.2017 under Section 20-A of the Railways
            <lb />
            Act inviting objections with respect to the lands proposed to be
            <lb />
            acquired for the purpose of special railway project under the said
            <lb />
            notification. In pursuance of the notification dated 21.08.2017
            <lb />
            issued by the Central Government, objections were received and
            <lb />
            decided by the Additional Collector/Competent Authority and
            <lb />
            thereafter the Central Government issued notification dated
            <lb />
            21.12.2017 under Section 20-E of the Railways Act declaring the
            <lb />
            acquisition of the land mentioned therein. According to the
            <lb />
            petitioner, the lands specified in schedule of notification dated
            <lb />
            21.12.2017 vested with the Central Government. It has been
            <lb />
            further contended that the learned Additional Collector after
            <lb />
            considering the provisions of the Railway Act has passed the
            <lb />
            award on 12.02.2018 granting compensation for acquiring the
            <lb />
            lands of the petitioner.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            5.
            <lb />
            It has been further contended that the compensation payable to
            <lb />
            the petitioner for his land was computed strictly in accordance
            <lb />
            with the provisions of the Railways Act and according to First
            <lb />
            Schedule read with Section 26 of the Act 2013. It has been
            <lb />
            further contended that the total area of the land acquired from
            <lb />
            the petitioner in Khasra No. 123/1 and 123/2 admeasuring 2.69
            <lb />
            hectares out of which 0.4 hectare of land was agricultural land
            <lb />
            converted to commercial use, as such the petitioner is entitled to
            <lb />
            25% more compensation than the rate prescribed under the
            <lb />
            guidelines for the same area. The prescribed rate for the land
            <lb />
            acquired under the guidelines for the year 2017-18 is Rs.
            <lb />
            13,800/-, as such for 0.4 hectares, the petitioner is entitled to get
            <lb />
            compensation to the tune of Rs. 17,250 per square meter, but
            <lb />
            the petitioner has not been paid a single rupee in excess of what
            <lb />
            the petitioner was entitled to receive as compensation in
            <lb />
            accordance with guidelines of 2017-2018. It has been further
            <lb />
            submitted that since the petitioner has not received the
            <lb />
            compensation in accordance with guidelines, therefore, baseless
            <lb />
            and frivolous allegations were made by the respondent No. 2 in
            <lb />
            the report wherein it has been stated that the petitioner allegedly
            <lb />
            committed fraud in collusion with the revenue authorities to get
            <lb />
            the excessive amount of compensation in lieu of his land. It has
            <lb />
            been further contended that since the land has been vested
            <lb />
            absolutely in the Central Government and the Central
            <lb />
            Government represented through Ministry of Railways has not
            <lb />
            made any complaint to any judicial authority in the State of
            <lb />
            Chhattisgarh indicating any kind of fraud or foul play in
            <lb />
            acquisition of land, therefore, the said report submitted by the
            <lb />
            Collector is without authority of law and without jurisdiction.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            6.
            <lb />
            It has been further contended that since respondent No.6/BRPL
            <lb />
            has no objection with regard to quantum of the compensation,
            <lb />
            therefore, they sanctioned to deposit Rs.1,88,82,66,402/-as the
            <lb />
            total compensation for the said acquisition under the Railways
            <lb />
            Act. The said amount was to be deposited for all the land
            <lb />
            oustees whose lands have been acquired for the special Railway
            <lb />
            project. It has been further contended that the petitioner has filed
            <lb />
            an application under the Right to Information Act, 2005 and has
            <lb />
            received information on 06.11.2018 that the rate is applicable to
            <lb />
            the petitioner&apos;s land bearing khasra No. 123/1 and 123/2 in
            <lb />
            terms of the guidelines is Rs.13,800/-per square meter in
            <lb />
            respect of the area on the road side from MGM School Zone to
            <lb />
            Palli Nakka, therefore, he raised objection before the arbitrator
            <lb />
            and filed an application for enhancement of compensation.
            <lb />
            Thereafter, the Commissioner was appointed as Arbitrator for the
            <lb />
            purpose of Section 20F(6) of the Railways Act by the Central
            <lb />
            Government vide notification dated 24.01.2019, as if the amount
            <lb />
            of compensation as provided under sub-section (3) is not
            <lb />
            acceptable to either of the parties then they can file an
            <lb />
            application before the Arbitrator, who in turn will decide the
            <lb />
            same.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            7.
            <lb />
            It has been further contended that the respondent No.2/Collector
            <lb />
            who has no jurisdiction under the Railways Act to enquire into
            <lb />
            acquisition though the Collector vide its order dated 19.07.2019
            <lb />
            constituted a Enquiry Committee headed by the Sub Divisional
            <lb />
            Officer-Shri G.R. Markam as Enquiry Officer, Shri Madhukar
            <lb />
            Sirmor as Assistant Enquiry Officer and Shri Pankaj Singh as
            <lb />
            Assistant Enquiry Officer. It has been further contended that
            <lb />
            three members enquiry committee conducted roving enquiry into
            <lb />
            the award dated 12.02.2018 without giving any opportunity of
            <lb />
            hearing to the petitioners and the other Revenue Officers
            <lb />
            associated with the acquisition proceeding and reached to
            <lb />
            conclusion that there was foul play on a large scale. It has been
            <lb />
            further contended that the Committee has no jurisdiction and
            <lb />
            authority directed to conduct an investigation into the acquisition
            <lb />
            proceedings which was initiated by the Central Government for
            <lb />
            the purpose of Indian Railways and the Committee without
            <lb />
            considering the entire material has recommended for recovery of
            <lb />
            compensation amount allegedly paid to the petitioner and also
            <lb />
            recommended for registration of FIR. Thereafter, on the basis of
            <lb />
            report, FIR has been registered under Sections 109, 120-B, 467,
            <lb />
            468, 471, 406, 407, 408 and 409 of IPC. The relevant portion of
            <lb />
            FIR is extracted below (Annexure P/2):-
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;मम थथानथा ककोतवथालल जगदलपपु र मम थथानथा प्रभथारल कक पद पर पदस्थ हह ह कक
            <lb />
            कथारथार्या लर कलक क्टर (भभ -अजर्या न शथाखथा) जजलथा बस्तर जगदलपपु र कक
            <lb />
            जथापन क्रमथामां क/क/भभ -अजर्या न/2019 जगदलपपु र कदनथामां क-30.07.
            <lb />
            2019 कक मथाध्रम सक कथारथार्या लर कलक क्टर एवम जजलथा दण्डथाजधिकथारल
            <lb />
            बस्तर जजलथा बस्तर कथा जथापन क्रमथामां क 196/भभ -अजर्या न/2019
            <lb />
            जगदलपपु र कदनथामां क 30.07.2019 प्रथाप हह आ जजसमम जगदलपपु र रथावघथाट
            <lb />
            रक ल्वक परररकोजनथा सक समां बमां जधित नवभथारत ददै कनक कदनथामां क 19.07.2019 मम
            <lb />
            प्रकथाकशत समथाचथार जगदलपपु र रक ल्वक स्टक शन कक आड मक 250 करकोड खक ल
            <lb />
            कक पररपक क्ष्र मम प्रथारमां कभक जथामां च प्रकतवक दन कथा अवलकोकन करनक पर बस्तर
            <lb />
            रक ल प्रकोजक क्ट रथावघथाट सक जगदलपपु र कक जलए भभ अजधिग्रहण नथामथामां ककत भभ -
            <lb />
            अजर्या न अजधिकथारल दथारथा कक गई और मपु अथावजथा तथथा ब्रथाज कथा कनधिथार्या रण
            <lb />
            ककरथा गरथा । उसमक कलक क्टर, बस्तर दथारथा टलम बनथाकर भभ अजधिग्रहण,
            <lb />
            रक ल पथ कथा कनधिथार्या रण, अजधिग्रकहत भभ कम कथा मपु आवजथा, ब्रथाज और
            <lb />
            तत्समां बमां धिल कनरमथावलल कक आधिथार पर भभ कम चरन, ब्रथाज मपु आवजथा
            <lb />
            कनधिथार्या रण कवषरक जजॉच कथारर्या वथाहल कक गई । कलक क्टर, बस्तर दथारथा अपनल
            <lb />
            जजॉच प्रकतवक दन मम पलल ग्रथाम कक भभ कम स्वथामल बलल नथागवमां शल एवमां शलमतल
            <lb />
            कनजलमथा कको प्रदत मपु आवजथा और ब्रथाज कको अवदै धि एवमां कनधिथार्या ररत मपु आवजथा
            <lb />
            तथथा ब्रथाज कको अत्रजधिक बतथारथा हदै । इस प्रकतवक दन मक सम्बजधित भभ -
            <lb />
            अजर्या न मक कवकभन शथासककर अजधिकथारल/कमर्या चथारररको कक भभ कमकथा स्पष्टतत
            <lb />
            कवजधि कवरूद पथारथा गरथा हदै । रथाजस्व कक नथामथामां ककत अजधिकथारल/कमर्या चथारररको
            <lb />
            एवमां अन्र कक कवरूद प्रथाथकमकक दजर्या करनक हक तपु सभ चनथा दल हदै । उक
            <lb />
            प्रकतवक दन कक आधिथार पर कनम्न प्रथाथकमकक दजर्या कक जथातल हदै । भभ -अजर्या न
            <lb />
            अजधिकथारल दथारथा मपु आवजथा कनधिथार्या रण हक तपु अजधिकनरम एवम तत्सम्बमां धिल
            <lb />
            कनरमम कथा पथालन नहह ककरथा हदै । रह भभ -अजधिग्रहण कवशक ष रक ल
            <lb />
            परररकोजनथा हक तपु कक जथानल थल । अतत रक ल्वक एक्ट कक प्रथावधिथानको कक अन्तगर्या त
            <lb />
            मपु आवजथा कथा कनधिथार्या रन हकोनथा थथा, ककन्तपु इसकथा पथालन नहह ककरथा गरथा
            <lb />
            और भभ -अजर्या न, पपु नवथार्या सन, पपु नर्या व्रवस्थथापन मम उकचत प्रकतकर और
            <lb />
            पथारदकशर्या तथा अजधिकथार अजधिकनरम 2013 कक अन्तगर्या त मपु आवजथा तथथा
            <lb />
            सकोलक जसरम कनधिथार्या रण अवदै धि हदै । जगदलपपु र तहसलल मम कपु ल 108 खथातको
            <lb />
            मक भभ -अजर्या न कक कथारर्या वथाहल कक गई । इनमक सक 15 खथातक एदै सक थक जजनमक
            <lb />
            एक सक अजधिक खसरक अजजर्या त हह ए और उन 15 खथातको मक सक कक वल
            <lb />
            02 खथातको मक प्रत्रक क खसरक अलग मथानतक हह ए गणनथा कक गई जबकक अन्र
            <lb />
            13 खथातको मक एक सक अजधिक अजजर्या त खसरथा नमां बर हकोनक कक बथावजभ द इसकको
            <lb />
            एक हल खथातथा मथानकर गणनथा कक गई जजन 02 खथातको कक जलए मथागर्या दकशर्या क
            <lb />
            जसदथामां तको कथा उलमां घन ककरथा गरथा वह खथातक कनम्नथानपु सथार हदै -(1) बलल
            <lb />
            नथागवमां शल कपतथा बपु टक र नथागवमां शल दथारथा धिथाररत भभ कम खसरथा नमां बर 123/1,
            <lb />
            123/2 कथा पपृ थक-पपृ थक गणनथा ककरथा गरथा हदै । (2) कनजलमथा पकत
            <lb />
            टल.व्हल. रकव दथारथा धिथाररत भभ कम खसरथा नमां बर 125/1 सक 125/29,
            <lb />
            125/31, 125/33, सक 125/37 तक कपु ल खसरथा नमां बर 35 कथा
            <lb />
            पपृ थक-पपृ थक गणनथा ककरथा गरथा हदै । जको कक बथाजथार मभ ल्र मथागर्या दकशर्या कथा
            <lb />
            जसदथामां त कक प्रथावधिथानम कक कवपरलत हदै । गणनथाकतर्या ओ नक कमां गकोलल कक 07
            <lb />
            खथातको, घथाटपदभभ र कक 03 तथथा अघनपपु र कक 03 खथातको मम जहथामां एक सक
            <lb />
            अजधिक खसरथा नमां बर अजजर्या त हह ए हदै , उनमक जसदथामां त कथा पथालन करतक हह ए
            <lb />
            एक खथातक कक गणनथा एक चक्र मम कक गई हदै । ककमां तपु उपरकोक कक वल 02
            <lb />
            हल खथातको मक स्पष्ट रूप सक उलमां घन करतक हह ए गणनथा कक हदै । भभ -अजर्या न
            <lb />
            हक तपु धिथारथा 20-ए रक लवक अजधिकनरम कक अमां तगर्या त भभ -अजर्या न हक तपु प्रपत 10
            <lb />
            तदै रथार ककरथा गरथा हदै । इसमक पलल ग्रथाम कक कनजलमथा पकत टल.व्हल. रकव कक
            <lb />
            खथातक कक समां बमां धि मम 125/1 सक 125/29, 125/31, 125/33 सक
            <lb />
            125/37 सभल कको एक हल खथातक मक अमां ककत करतक हह ए पटवथारल
            <lb />
            धिमर्या नथारथारण सथाहह दथारथा पभ णर्या रकबक कको एक चक्र मम गणनथा करतक हह ए दशथार्या रथा
            <lb />
            गरथा हदै । जजसमक रथाजस्व कनरलक्षक अजभ र्या न शलवथास्तव नक भल परर्या वक क्षण न
            <lb />
            कर पटवथारल कको आपरथाजधिक षड़रमां त मम शथाकमल हह ए इसल तरह तहसललदथार
            <lb />
            दलनदरथाल मण्डथावल भल आपरथाजधिक गकतकवजधिरम मम समां जलप रहक उप
            <lb />
            पमां जलरक कको कक वल पलल ग्रथाम मम गणनथा हक तपु पत प्रक कषत ककरथा गरथा जजसमक
            <lb />
            उप पमां जलरक नक 30 जनवरल कको गणनथा पतक तदै रथार करतक हह ए भभ -अजर्या न
            <lb />
            शथाखथा कको भक जथा इस गणनथा पतक मम भल कनजलमथा पकत टल.व्हल. रकव कक
            <lb />
            खथातक कक समां दभर्या मक 125/1 सक 125/29, 125/31, 125/33 सक
            <lb />
            125/37 सभल कको एक हल खथातक मम अमां ककत करतक हह ए एक चक्र मम गणनथा
            <lb />
            कर कदनथामां क 30 जनवरल 2018 कको पतक प्रस्तपु त ककरथा गरथा । इस
            <lb />
            प्रकथार पटवथारल एवम उप पमां जलरक कको प्रथम गणनथा मम इसक एक खथातथा
            <lb />
            मथानकर सभल खसरको मक गणनथा एक सथाथ कक गई । उप पमां जलरक ककौशल
            <lb />
            ठथाकपु र दथारथा अगलक हल कदन 31 जनवरल 2018 कको प्रत्रक क खसरक कथा
            <lb />
            पपृ थक-पपृ थक खथातथा मथानकर पपृ थक गणनथा पतक प्रस्तपु त ककरथा गरथा ।
            <lb />
            सथाथ हल सथाथ पटवथारल दथारथा 01 फरवरल 2018 कको आनलथाईन बल-01
            <lb />
            उपलब्धि करथारक गरक , जजसमक हर खसरक कको अलग खथातथा बनथाकर दशथार्या रथा
            <lb />
            गरथा । इसमक स्पष्ट हकोतथा हदै कक पटवथारल धिमर्या नथारथारणस सथाहह व प्रभथारल उप
            <lb />
            पमां जलरक ककौशल ठथाकपु र नक दस्तथावक जको मक कभ टरचनथा ककरक हदै । जजससक रह
            <lb />
            स्पष्ट हकोतथा हदै कक कनजलमथा पकत टल.व्हल. रकव एवम बलल नथागवमां शल कको
            <lb />
            अनपु कचत लथाभ पहह मां चथानक कक जलए रह कथारर्या वथाहल कक गई । रह आपरथाजधिक
            <lb />
            षडरमां त एवमां आपरथाजधिक दपु ष्प्रक रणथा कक शक णल मम आतथा हदै । जजलथा बस्तर मम
            <lb />
            जजलथा पमां जलरक पदस्थ हदै , इसकक बथावजभ द जजलथा पमां जलरक कको सम्बकोजधित
            <lb />
            पतथाचथार कको जजलथा कक स्थथान पर व्हथाइटनर लगथातक हह ए उप पमां जलरक कको
            <lb />
            कक वल पलल ग्रथाम कक गणनथा हक तपु अनपु कवभथागलर अजधिकथारल (रथाजस्व) कक
            <lb />
            दथारथा अवदै धि रूप सक पतथाचथार ककरथा गरथा, जबकक इन्हम सभल ग्रथामको कथा जजलथा
            <lb />
            पमां जलरक सक गणनथा करथानथा थथा । इस पत मम जजलथा पमां जलरक शब्द मक सक
            <lb />
            जजलथा शब्द मक व्हथाईटनर कको लगथारथा जजसमक अनपु कवभथागलर अजधिकथारल एवमां
            <lb />
            प्रभथारल उप पमां जलरक ककौशल ठथाकपु र कक भभ कमकथा आपरथाजधिक हदै । बलल
            <lb />
            नथागवमां शल कपतथा बपु टक र नथागवमां शल दथारथा ग्रथाम पलल मम धिथाररत भभ कम व्रपवकतर्या त
            <lb />
            क्रमथामां क 123/1, 123/2, कपु ल रकबथा 2.69 हक ० कको शहरल मथानकर
            <lb />
            मपु आवजथा रथाकश 70.62 करकोड रूपरक अवथाडर्या ककरथा गरथा हदै , जबकक
            <lb />
            ग्रथामलण क्षक त हकोनक कक आधिथार पर कपु ल मपु आवजथा 7.79 करकोड रूपरक
            <lb />
            पररगकणत हकोतथा हदै । अतत इस खथातक दथार कको 62.82 करकोड रूपरक
            <lb />
            अजधिक मपु आवजथा प्रदथान ककरथा गरथा हदै । उक भभ कम कथा बथाजथार मभ ल्र कक
            <lb />
            गणनथा ग्रथामलण क्षक त कक अनपु रूप हल हकोनल थल । कनजलमथा पकत टल.व्हल. रकव
            <lb />
            दथारथा ग्रथाम पलल मम धिथाररत भभ कम व्रपवकतर्या त खसरथा क्रमथामां क 125/1 सक
            <lb />
            125/29, 125/31, 125/33 सक 125/37 तक कपु ल खसरथा
            <lb />
            नम्बर 35 कपु ल रकबथा 1.040 हक ० कक मपु आवजथा रथाकश 25.19 करकोड
            <lb />
            रूपरक अवथाडर्या ककरथा गरथा हदै । जबकक ग्रथामलण क्षक त हकोनक कक आधिथार पर कपु ल
            <lb />
            मपु आवजथा 4.38 करकोड रूपरक पररगकणत हकोतथा हदै । कनजलमथा पकत टल.व्हल.
            <lb />
            रकव कको 20.80 करकोड रूपरक अजधिक मपु आवजथा प्रदथान ककरथा गरथा ।
            <lb />
            पथाकलल बक वथा मनलरथाम एवमां तथथा नथागवमां शल कबल्डसर्या एवमां डक वलपसर्या भथागलदथार
            <lb />
            बलल नथागवमां शल कपतथा बपु टक र नथागवमां शल दथारथा ग्रथाम पलल मक धिथाररत कपृ कष भभ कम
            <lb />
            खसरथा क्रमथामां क 123/3 रकबथा 0.12 हक ० कक मपु आवजथा रथाकश 2.28
            <lb />
            करकोड रूपरक अवथाडर्या ककरथा गरथा । जबकक ग्रथामलण क्षक त हकोनक कक कथारण कपु ल
            <lb />
            मपु आवजथा 0.27 करकोड रूपरक आकलन हकोतथा हदै । पथाकलल बक वथा मनलरथाम
            <lb />
            एवमां खथातक दथारको कको 2.01 करकोड रूपरक अजधिक मपु आवजथा प्रदथान ककरथा गरथा
            <lb />
            हदै । ग्रथाम पलल सस्थत जजन 02 खथातक दथारको कको अनपु कचत लथाभ पहह मां चथारथा
            <lb />
            गरथा उन मक सक एक खथातक दथार बलल नथागवमां शल कक अन्र भभ कम जजसमक वह सह
            <lb />
            खथातक दथार हदै , पथाकलल बक वथा मनलरथाम एवमां अन्र तथथा नथागवमां शल कबल्डसर्या
            <lb />
            डक व्हलपसर्या भथागलदथार दथारथा ग्रथाम पलल मक धिथाररत कपृ कष भभ कम खसरथा क्रमथामां क
            <lb />
            123/3 रकबथा 0.12 हक क्टक रर कक गणनथा ग्रथामलण क्षक त कक आधिथार पर
            <lb />
            नहह कर नगरलर क्षक त मथानकर कक गई । उसमक भल नगरलर क्षक त हक तपु
            <lb />
            कवद्यमथान स्लदै ब कक कनरमथानपु सथार गणनथा नहह कक गई हदै एदै सल गणनथा करतक
            <lb />
            हह रक बलल नथागवमां शल पथाकलल बक वथा मनलरथाम एवम अन्र तथथा नथागवमां शल
            <lb />
            कबल्डसर्या एवमां डक व्लपसर्या कको अनपु कचत लथाभ पहह मां चथारथा गरथा जको आपरथाजधिक
            <lb />
            षड़रमां त एवमां आपरथाजधिक दपु ष्प्रक रणथा कक शक णल मम आतथा हदै । खसरथा क्रमथामां क
            <lb />
            123 एवम 125 इन खथातको कको शहरल क्षक त मथानतक हह ए गण कक गई,
            <lb />
            जबकक लगक हह ए खसरथा क्रमथामां क 124/27 एवम घथाटपदमभ र कक खसरथा
            <lb />
            क्रमथामां क-980/2, 981/2 कको ग्रथामलण क्षक त मथानतक हह ए गणनथा कक गई ।
            <lb />
            गणनथा हक तपु गकठत दल कक पटवथारल धिमर्या नथारथारण सथाहह दथारथा ग्रथाम पलल कको
            <lb />
            कपु छ खथातको कको नगरलर क्षक त कक भभ कम तथथा कपु छ कको ग्रथामलण एवम ग्रथाम
            <lb />
            घथाटपदमभ र कक सभल खथातको कको ग्रथामलणल क्षक त मथानकर गणनथा कक गई हदै ।
            <lb />
            पटवथारल कको मथालभ म हकोतक हह ए भल कक रह ग्रथामलण क्षक त कक भभ कम हदै , कनजलमथा
            <lb />
            बक लसरररथा तथथा बजल नथागवमां शल कको अवदै धि लथाभ पहह मां चथानक हक तपु नगरलर भभ कम
            <lb />
            कक कहसथाब सक गणनथा कक गई हदै । एक खथातथा कक एक सक अजधिक खसरको कको
            <lb />
            पपृ थक-पपृ थक खथातथा मथानकर गणनथा कर क्षक तफल आधिथाररत स्लदै ब
            <lb />
            पररवकतर्या त कर अजधिक मपु आवजथा बनथारथा गरथा जको आपरथाजधिक षड़रमां त हदै ।
            <lb />
            इसकक अकतररक बथाजथार मभ ल्र मथागर्या दशर्या क जसदथामां त वषर्या 2017-18 सक
            <lb />
            समां बमां जधित उपबमां धि कक प्रथारूप 01 क उपबमां धि कक कमां कडकथा 10 कक अनपु सथार
            <lb />
            नगरलर आवथासलर क्षक त मम एदै सल सम्पजत जको रकोड सक अमां दर सस्थत हदै परमां तपु
            <lb />
            जजसकथा उपरकोग व्रथावसथाकरक/औद्यकोकगक प्ररकोजन कक जलए ककरथा जथा रहथा
            <lb />
            हको, उस क्षक त कक जलए कनधिथार्या ररत दर मम 25% वपृ कद कर बथाजथार मभ ल्र कक
            <lb />
            गणनथा कक जथारक गल । पलल ग्रथाम कक बलल नथागवमां शल कपतथा बपु टक र नथागवमां शल कक
            <lb />
            खसरथा क्रमथामां क 123/1 उपमां 123/2 कक गणनथा मपु ख्र मथागर्या पर स्थथाकपत
            <lb />
            तथथा पररवकतर्या त भभ कम कक रूप मम बथाजथार मभ ल्र कक अजधिकतम रथाकश कक सथाथ
            <lb />
            गणनथा कक गई हदै , ककन्तपु अनपु कचत लथाभ दक नक हक तपु मपु ख्रमथागर्या कक दर कक सथाथ
            <lb />
            मपु ख्रमथागर्या सक अमां दर सस्थत भभ कम मथानतक हह ए 25% अकतररक मपु आवजथा कक
            <lb />
            गणनथा कक गई जको अवदै धि हदै । इससक स्पष्ट हकोतथा हदै कक गणनथाकतथार्या एवमां
            <lb />
            सक्षम प्रथाजधिकथारल दथारथा उक खथातक दथार कको कनरम कथा उलमां घन करतक हह ए
            <lb />
            लथाभ पहह मां चथारथा गरथा । ग्रथाम पलल सस्थत भभ कम खसरथा नमां बर 27 रकबथा
            <lb />
            0.11 हक ० सलमथा रथाठल पकत अजर रथाकठ कक नथाम पर धिथाररत हदै । इस भभ कम
            <lb />
            कथा मपु आवजथा रथाकश कक गणनथा ग्रथामलण आधिथार पर कक गई हदै । रह भभ कम
            <lb />
            ग्रथाम पलल कक बजल नथागवमां शल कक भभ कम कक दभ सरल ओर मपु ख्र सड़क मथागर्या
            <lb />
            जगदलपपु र कचतककोट पर सस्थत हदै तथथा सड़क सक हल लगल हह ई तथथा सम
            <lb />
            मभ ल्र कक भभ कम हदै । दभ सरक प्रकरण मम ग्रथाम पलल सस्थत भभ कम खसरथा नमां बर-
            <lb />
            124 रकबथा 0.66 हक ० कनत्र गकोपथाल कपतथा कशकतज एवमां अन्र कक नथाम पर
            <lb />
            धिथाररत कपृ कष भभ कम हदै तथथा भभ कम खसरथा नमां बर 125 एवमां 123 सक दकक्षणल
            <lb />
            सलमथा सक लगल हह ई हदै एवमां रह भभ कम भल सममभ ल्र हदै । इस भभ कम कक भल
            <lb />
            बथाजथार मभ ल्र कक गणनथा ग्रथाम पलल कको ग्रथामलण क्षक त मथानकर कक गई तलसरक
            <lb />
            प्रकरण मक ग्रथाम घथाटपदमभ र सस्थत भभ कम खसरथा नमां बर 980/2, 981/2,
            <lb />
            रकबथा क्रमशत 0.200 सक 0.200 हक ० मक सक रकबथा क्रमशत 0.600,
            <lb />
            0.110 हक ० अजजर्या त कक गई हदै । रक दकोनको भभ कमरथा हररशमां कर झथा कपतथा
            <lb />
            रमथाकथामां त झथा कक नथाम पर धिथाररत हदै । रह भभ कम ग्रथाम पलल सस्थत बलल
            <lb />
            नथागवमां शल कक नथाम पर धिथाररत खसरथा नमां बर 123/01 कक पभ वर सरहद पर
            <lb />
            जगदलपपु र कक ओर मपु ख्र मथागर्या सक हल लगल हह ई हदै । तथथा सममभ ल्र कक
            <lb />
            भभ कम हदै । जजसकक भल गणनथा ग्रथामलण क्षक त कक आधिथार पर कक गई हदै ।
            <lb />
            उपरकोक तथ्रम सक स्पष्ट हकोतथा हदै कक बलल नथागवमां शल व कनजलमथा बक लसरररथा
            <lb />
            पकत टल.व्हल. रकव कको अनपु कचत लथाभ दक नक कक उदक श्र सक एक क्षक त मक आनक
            <lb />
            वथालल भभ कम कक मपु आवजथा रथाकश कक गणनथा पक्षपथात पभ णर्या ढमां ग सक षड़रमां तपभ वर्या क
            <lb />
            पपृ थक-पपृ थक मथापदण्ड सक एवम बथाजथार मभ ल्र मथागर्या दकशर्या क जसदथामां त सक परक
            <lb />
            जथाकर ककरथा गरथा हदै । खसरथा नमां बर 123 पभ वर्या मक बलल नथागवमां शल, मपु .
            <lb />
            पथाकलल बक वथा मनलरथाम एवम अन्र कक समां रपु क खथातक कक भभ कम थल, जजसक
            <lb />
            बलल नथागवमां शल नक खसरथा नमां बर 123/1 एवम 123/2 कको क्रमशत
            <lb />
            कदनथामां क 23/01/2015 एवम 12/10/2010 कको अपनक सह
            <lb />
            खथातक दथारको सक हल क्रर ककरथा। चभ मां कक रक ल लथाईन कथा प्रथारमां कभक सवर 2007-
            <lb />
            08 हको चपु कथा थथा । भभ -अजर्या न कक सस्थकत मम प्रथाप मपु आवजथा कथा उपभकोग
            <lb />
            स्वरमां करनक कक कनरत सक उपरकोक दकोनको भभ कम कको क्रर ककरथा गरथा और
            <lb />
            खरलदल कक पश्चथात 07 मथाह कक भलतर हल भभ कम कथा डथारवसर्या न कदनथामां क
            <lb />
            13/09/2015 कको वथाकणसजरक एवमां आवथासलर मद मम करथारथा गरथा हदै ।
            <lb />
            जको आपरथाजधिक षडरमां त एवमां आपरथाजधिक दपु ष्प्रक रणथा कक शक णल मम आतथा हदै ।
            <lb />
            कनजलमथा, स्पमां दनथा नथामक आवथासलर पररसर कथा कनमथार्या ण ग्रथाम पलल क
            <lb />
            खसरथा 125 मक ककरथा गरथा थथा इस हक तपु ग्रथाम पमां चथारत पलल एवमां तत्कथाललन
            <lb />
            अनपु ० अजधिकथारल (रथाजस्व) सक भभ -कवकथास हक तपु अनपु जथा प्रथाप थल । उक
            <lb />
            समरथावजधि मम खथातक दथार कनजलमथा स्वरमां ग्रथाम सरपमां च रहल हदै । ककन्तपु
            <lb />
            आवथासलर प्लथाट कक कबक्रक कक जलरक नगर क्षक त अजधिक फथारदक कक हकोगल
            <lb />
            इसजलए इनकक दथारथा नगर कनगम कको आशर शपु ल्क जमथा करतक हह ए नगर
            <lb />
            कनगम मम ससम्मजलत हकोनक कथा षड़रमां त ककरथा । बस्तर जजलक मम भभ -अजर्या न
            <lb />
            प्रकरणको मक पररसम्पजतरको पर भल पक्षपथातपभ णर्या गणनथा कर बलल नथागवमां शल
            <lb />
            एवम कनजलमथा वक लसरररथा कको अवदै धि लथाभ षडरमां त पभ वर्या क कदरथा गरथा हदै ।
            <lb />
            ग्रथाम अघनपपु र घथाटपदभभ र एवम कमां गकोलल मक कम मभ ल्र कक भभ कम उपलब्धि
            <lb />
            हकोनक कक बथावजभ द इस रक ल लथाईन कको षडरमां त पभ वर्या क पलल कक ओर कनजलमथा
            <lb />
            एवम बजल नथागवमां शल कको अवदै धि लथाभ पहह मां चथानक हक तपु बदलथा गरथा एवम रक तलन
            <lb />
            गथामां व मम मपु आवजथा कथा आकलन भल गलत ककरथा गरथा । जगदलपपु र रथावघथाट
            <lb />
            रक ल परररकोजनथा हक तपु भभ कम कथा अजर्या न रक ल्वक अजधिकनरम 1989 रथथा
            <lb />
            समां शकोजधित 2008 कक अनपु सथार ककरथा गरथा हदै । उलक खनलर हदै कक रक ल्वक
            <lb />
            अजधिकनरम 1989 भभ कम अजर्या न पपु नवथार्या सन एवमां पपु नव्रर्या स्थथापन मक उकचत
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            8. Thereafter, on 05.08.2019 without application of mind or
            <lb />
            conducting any kind of preliminary investigation whatsoever, the
            <lb />
            Station House Officer issued two letters to the Bank of Baroda,
            <lb />
            Jagdalpur Branch, seeking that the bank account owned by the
            <lb />
            petitioner be frozen with immediate effect. The petitioner has
            <lb />
            filed this petition assailing the legality and propriety of the report,
            <lb />
            FIR bearing Crime No. 409/2019 and subsequent letters dated
            <lb />
            05.08.2019 issued by the respondent No. 3 freezing the bank
            <lb />
            account maintained by the petitioner. It has been further
            <lb />
            contended that the proceeding has been initiated without
            <lb />
            jurisdiction, FIR has been registered mechanically without any
            <lb />
            application of mind and thereafter, the bank account has been
            <lb />
            breezed in illegal manner and this resulted in violation of the
            <lb />
            petitioner&apos;s rights guaranteed under Sections 14, 19(1)(g), 21
            <lb />
            and 300-A of the Constitution of India.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            9.
            <lb />
            It has been further contended that since the land acquisition
            <lb />
            proceeding has been completed under the Railways Act which is
            <lb />
            a parliamentary legislation and all the authorities involved in the
            <lb />
            process of acquisition for railway projects are involved to act
            <lb />
            under the Central Government, the State Government has no
            <lb />
            jurisdiction to play in the process of acquisition of land under the
            <lb />
            Railways Act. It has been further contended that the only role
            <lb />
            assigned to the Collector of a district under the Railways Act is
            <lb />
            provided under Section 20-I which states in clause (b) of sub
            <lb />
            section (2) that in case any person refuses or fails to comply with
            <lb />
            any direction made under Section 20-I(1) to the owner of the
            <lb />
            land to surrender or deliver possession of the land, the
            <lb />
            competent authority shall apply to the Collector of the District to
            <lb />
            seek enforcement of such surrender or delivery of the land to the
            <lb />
            competent authority. Therefore, the whole proceeding is without
            <lb />
            jurisdiction and authority under Section 20D(3) of the Railways
            <lb />
            Act.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            10. It has been further contended that the scheme of the Railway Act
            <lb />
            makes it clear that no authority other than one which has a role
            <lb />
            under the statute, can interfere with the process of acquiring
            <lb />
            land under the Railways Act. It has been further contended that
            <lb />
            the conclusions drawn in the report of the Collector are without
            <lb />
            any merit as the principles on which the compensation has been
            <lb />
            determined and the process followed are both correct in
            <lb />
            accordance with law, therefore, the findings recorded by the
            <lb />
            learned Collector in its report is illegal and same deserves to be
            <lb />
            quashed by this court. It has been further contended that as per
            <lb />
            Section 20G of the Railways Act read with Section 26 along with
            <lb />
            the First Schedule to the Right to Fair Compensation Act,
            <lb />
            proceeding for determination of market value of land which has
            <lb />
            been strictly followed while determining the compensation,
            <lb />
            therefore, there is no illegality in determining the compensation
            <lb />
            and same is in accordance with law, therefore, registration of
            <lb />
            FIR and the report is illegal. The compensation awarded to the
            <lb />
            petitioner was challenged by respondent No. 6 before the
            <lb />
            Commissioner, Bastar, who has appointed as Arbitrator under
            <lb />
            the Railways Act on the ground of miscalculation of the
            <lb />
            applicable rates, therefore, prima facie, no case is made out
            <lb />
            against the petitioner for committing any fraud upon the
            <lb />
            authorities or upon the Railway. On the above factual matrix, the
            <lb />
            petitioner has prayed that the Collector has not vested any
            <lb />
            power or authority under the Railways Act to enquire about
            <lb />
            legality and propriety of quantum of compensation awarded by
            <lb />
            the competent authority, therefore, reopening of the entire
            <lb />
            acquisition proceedings which is attained its finality is illegal and
            <lb />
            deserves to be quashed and prayed for grant of following reliefs;
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;10.1. That, the Hon&apos;ble Court may kindly be
            <lb />
            pleased to issue appropriate writs), order(s), or
            <lb />
            direction9s) to set aside and quash the report of
            <lb />
            the respondent No.2 Collector dated 30-7-2019
            <lb />
            and the FIR dated 4-8-2019 in Crime No 409 of
            <lb />
            2019, registered at Police Station, Kotwali,
            <lb />
            Jagdalpur, District Bastar under Sections 109,
            <lb />
            120-B, 467, 468, 471, 406, 408, 409 of IPC and
            <lb />
            letter No. 1274 and 1283 dated 5-8-2019 issued
            <lb />
            by the respondent No.3-SHO to respondent No.4
            <lb />
            Bank seeking to freeze the Bank Account Nos.
            <lb />
            10122000007188,
            <lb />
            10120400000117
            <lb />
            and
            <lb />
            10120100010115;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            10.2. That, the Honorable Court may kindly be
            <lb />
            pleased to declare that the respondent No.2
            <lb />
            collector is not vested with any kind of authority
            <lb />
            under the Railway Act to order on enquiry into the
            <lb />
            quantum of compensation awarded by the
            <lb />
            competent authority under the Railways Act and,
            <lb />
            thereby, reopen the land acquisition proceeding
            <lb />
            which has attained finality by virtue of award dated
            <lb />
            12-02-2018.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            10.3. That, cost of the petition.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            10.4. That, any other relief which this Honorable
            <lb />
            Court may deem fit in the facts and circumstances
            <lb />
            of the case.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            11. This Court vide its order dated 04.10.2019 had directed that no
            <lb />
            coercive steps shall be taken against the petitioner till the next
            <lb />
            date of hearing as same question was raised in another petition
            <lb />
            bearing WPCR No. 674 of 2019 wherein this Court has passed
            <lb />
            an order granting interim relief of &apos;no coercive steps&apos; be taken
            <lb />
            against the petitioner.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            12. State has filed its return on behalf of respondents No. 1 to 3
            <lb />
            mainly contending that the instant petition is not maintainable in
            <lb />
            its present form as Writ Petition (Cr.) as the petitioner has sought
            <lb />
            quashing of the Collector&apos;s enquiry report dated 30.07.2019 and
            <lb />
            also sought quashing of subsequent FIR , but from the bare
            <lb />
            perusal of the pleadings of the Writ Petition (Cr.), it is ample
            <lb />
            clear that the petition is basically against the enquiry report of
            <lb />
            the Collector, It has been contended by the State in its return
            <lb />
            that from the news report published regarding large scale
            <lb />
            irregularities and illegalities committed in land acquisition
            <lb />
            proceedings pertaining to Bastar Rail Project, the matter came to
            <lb />
            the notice of the administration of District Bastar. The
            <lb />
            Commissioner, Revenue Bastar Division, Jagdalpur, District-
            <lb />
            Bastar who is also an arbitrator appointed by the Government of
            <lb />
            India in respect of the above-mentioned land acquisition, vide its
            <lb />
            letter dated 22.07.2019 directed the Collector, District-Bastar,
            <lb />
            Jagdalpur to examine the matter and to enquire into allegations
            <lb />
            leveled against the land acquisition process and the calculation
            <lb />
            and payment made therein. In pursuance of the aforesaid
            <lb />
            direction of the Commissioner, Revenue, Bastar Division, District
            <lb />
            Bastar, respondent No.2 Collector, District Bastar initiated a
            <lb />
            detailed inquiry into the entire acquisition and it was revealed
            <lb />
            that the land acquisition officer had completely failed to follow
            <lb />
            the provisions of the Act, 2013 and relevant rules while
            <lb />
            determining the compensation. It has been further revealed that
            <lb />
            large scale illegality has been committed in acquisition of land of
            <lb />
            village Palli which comes under the Gram Panchayat
            <lb />
            Kumravand. It has been further submitted that five out of seven
            <lb />
            Khatas of village Palli have been considered to be part of
            <lb />
            Municipal Council Jagdalpur whereas the remaining two Khatas
            <lb />
            have been considered to be rural areas. It is submitted that the
            <lb />
            village Palli is completely rural area and none of the Khatas of
            <lb />
            the said village has been included in the urban area as per the
            <lb />
            notification dated 4-9-2002 (Annexure R/2). The relevant
            <lb />
            portion of the said notification is extracted below :-
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            परथार्या वरण एवमां नगरलर कवकथास कवभथाग
            <lb />
            ममां तथालर, दथाऊ कल्रथाण जसमां ह भवन, रथारपपु र
            <lb />
            रथारपपु र, कदनथामां क 3 जसतम्बर 2002
            <lb />
            अजधिसभ चनथा
            <lb />
            क्रमथामां क 4719/18/2002.-रथाजर शथासन दथारथा, छतलसगढ नगरपथाजलकथा
            <lb />
            अजधिकनरम, 1961 कक धिथारथा-5(क) कक उपधिथारथा (1) मम प्रदत शककरम कथा प्ररकोग करतक
            <lb />
            हह ए नगरपथाजलकथा पररषदद जगदलपपु र जजलथा-बस्तर कक वतर्या मथान सलमथा मम अनपु सभ चल-1 मम
            <lb />
            दशथार्या ई गई अनपु सथार कनम्नजलजखत क्षक तम कको ससम्मजलत ककरथा जथातथा हदै त-
            <lb />
            अनपु सभ चल-1
            <lb />
            जजलथा बस्तर कक नगरपथाजलकथा पररषदद जगदलपपु र कक सलमथा मम ससम्मजलत ककरक
            <lb />
            जथानक वथालक ग्रथामम कथा कववरण रथाजस्व क्रमथामां क तथथा सवर क्रमथामां क व क्षक तफल कनम्नथानपु सथार हदै त-
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (1) ग्रथाम सरगलपथाल
            <lb />
            तहसलल जगदलपपु र
            <lb />
            : ग्रथाम सरगलपथाल कथा सवर नमां बर 5, 6, 7, 8, 9,
            <lb />
            10 एवमां 3/1 ग कथा टपु कड़था, क्षक तफल
            <lb />
            33.600/13598 हक क्टर.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (2) ग्रथाम कमां गकोलल
            <lb />
            5/1, 34/2, 32/1, 36 तथथा दलपत सथागर तथालथाब कथा पथार हकोतक हह ए
            <lb />
            ग्रथाम धिरमपपु रथा कथा सवर क्रमथामां क कथा पथार हकोतक हह ए ग्रथाम धिरमपपु रथा कथा सवर क्रमथामां क
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            117, 122, 123, 124, 141, 29, 1/1, 1/3, 1/2 एवमां 1/21.
            <lb />
            पसश्चम मम ग्रथाम कमां गकोलल कथा सवर क्रमथामां क 1, 2, 3, 4, 121/11, 7, 99/1 कथा
            <lb />
            टपु कड़था 88, 95/2, 95/1, 96, 89/1, 83, 80, 76 ग्रथाम अघनपपु र
            <lb />
            कथा सवर क्रमथामां क 139/1 कथा टपु कड़था.
            <lb />
            दकक्षण मम ग्रथाम अघनपपु र कथा सवर क्रमथामां क 147, 149/1 ग्रथाम सरगलपथाल कथा सवर
            <lb />
            क्रमथामां क 1, 2 एवमां 3 कथा टपु कड़था ग्रथाम फक जरपपु र कथा सवर क्रमथामां क 1/2 ररजवर्या
            <lb />
            फथारक स्ट सक रक ल्वक लथाइन ककनथारक तक ग्रथाम ककोहकथापथाल कथा सवर क्रमथामां क
            <lb />
            134/1, 1/1, 133/1, 133/8, 4/2, 8/1, 47/1, 11/2,
            <lb />
            11/1, 20/1, 29/1, 24/1, 25/1, एवमां 26/1.
            <lb />
            पभ वर्या मम
            <lb />
            ग्रथाम ककोहकथापथाल कथा सवर क्रमथामां क 20, 19, ग्रथाम हथाटकचकोरथा कथा सवर क्रमथामां क
            <lb />
            230, 229, 203, 202, 201, 190/3, 191, 192, 198, 197,
            <lb />
            196, 195, 194, 193, 174, 172, 162, 169/1, 164, 163,
            <lb />
            193, 165, 166, 146/1, एवमां 145, ग्रथाम पखनथागपु ड़था कथा सवर क्रमथामां क
            <lb />
            97/2, 90, 80, 82, 65/2, 64, 63, 62, 61.49/2. 47,
            <lb />
            37/1, 30, 29, 23/1 ग्रथाम आसनथा कथा सवर क्रमथामां क 626, 625,
            <lb />
            469/2, 465, 464, 457, ग्रथाम करकथापथाल कथा सवर क्रमथामां क 26/1 सक
            <lb />
            ग्रथाम पखनथागपु ड़था कथा सवर क्रमथामां क 30 तक तथथा गकोरररथाबहथार कक ककनथारक तक.
            <lb />
            नकोटत-
            <lb />
            इन्दथावतल नदल कक नरथा पभ ल सक ग्रथाम आसनथा तक उतरलर कदशथा मम नक शनल हथाईवक मथागर्या नमां .
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            43 कक नरक और पपु रथानक मथागर्या कक समां गम तक एवमां नवकनकमर्या त मथागर्या कक समां गम सक इन्दथावतल नदल मम
            <lb />
            कनकमर्या त पपु रथानथा पपु जलरथा सक ग्रथाम ककोहकथापथाल कथा समस्त आबथादल क्षक त व इन्दथावतल नदल कक
            <lb />
            ककनथारक -ककनथारक ककोहकथापथाल कक सरहद सक दलपत सथागर तथालथाब कक पथार (बथामां धि) तक तथथा
            <lb />
            वहथामां सक ग्रथाम धिरमपपु रथा कक कशव ममां कदर सक हकोतक हह ए ककोसमपु मां डथा तथालथाब तक, वहथामां सक ग्रथाम
            <lb />
            धिरमपपु रथा कक सरहद सक हकोतक हह ए पसश्चमल कदशथा मम कचतककोट रकोड तक तथथा कचतककोट रकोड कक
            <lb />
            पलल मथागर्या एवमां गलदम रकोड सक आनक वथालक दकोनम मथागर मां कक समां गम सक हकोतक हह ए रक ल्वक लथाइन कक
            <lb />
            ककनथारक तक तथथा दकक्षण मम रक ल्वक लथाइन कक ककनथारक सक हकोतक हह ए गकोरररथा बहथार नथालथा मम बनक
            <lb />
            रक ल्वक पपु जलरथा तक तथथा पभ वर्या गकोरररथा बहथार नथालथा मम बनक रक ल्वक पपु जलरथा सक गकोरररथा बहथार नथालथा
            <lb />
            कक ककनथारक -ककनथारक हकोतक हह ए पभ वर्या कदशथा मम जरपपु र रकोड मथागर्या पर बनक पक्कथा पपु जलरथा तथथा वहथामां
            <lb />
            सक उतरल कदशथा मम नक शनल हथाइवक मथागर्या नमां . 43 कक नरक और पपु रथानक मथागर्या रथारपपु र समां गम तक.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            13. It has been further stated that as per the above mentioned
            <lb />
            notification, only villages Sargipal, Kangoli,
            <lb />
            Dharampura,
            <lb />
            Aghanpur, Pakhnaguda, Frezarpur, Haatkachara, Kohakapal,
            <lb />
            Asna and Jagdalpur have been included within the limits of
            <lb />
            Municipal Corporation, Jagdalpur. It has been further contended
            <lb />
            by the State that the village Palli is not included within the limits
            <lb />
            of Jagdalpur Municipal Corporation. As per notification No. F-1-
            <lb />
            71/18/2004 of 2004 issued by the Department of Housing and
            <lb />
            Environment, Government of Chattisgarh, the Jagdalpur
            <lb />
            Municipal Corporation was framed by dividing the area in 40
            <lb />
            wards and the limits of the wards were determined. The ward
            <lb />
            No.37 has been notified as Lok Manya Tilak Ward and the
            <lb />
            western limits of the said ward has been determined till the
            <lb />
            eastern limits of the village Palli. After the said notification, till
            <lb />
            date, no modification has been made to the geographical limits
            <lb />
            of the Municipal Corporation Jagdalpur. It has been further
            <lb />
            contended that vide notification dated 12.07.2004, the Gram
            <lb />
            Panchayats have been formed under Section 129(B)(1) of the
            <lb />
            Chhattigarh Panchayat Raj Adhiniyam, 1993 and at serial No.21
            <lb />
            of the said notification the Gram Panchayat has been formed by
            <lb />
            including the village Kumravand and the Village-Palli. The
            <lb />
            relevant portion of the said notification is extracted below for
            <lb />
            ready reference:-
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            कथारथार्या लर कलक क्टर (पमां चथारत शथाखथा), जजलथा बस्तर (छतलसगढ)
            <lb />
            जगदलपपु र, कदनथामां क 12 जपु लथाई 2004
            <lb />
            अजधिसभ चनथा
            <lb />
            क्रमथामां क/1595/पमां चथारत/पमां चथा. कनवथार्या ./2004-छतलसगढ शथासन, पमां चथारत
            <lb />
            एवमां ग्रथामलण कवकथास कवभथाग कक अजधिसभ चनथा क्रमथामां क एफ 1/11/95/22/पमां .-2, कदनथामां क
            <lb />
            23 फरवरल, 1999 दथारथा प्रदत शककरम कको प्ररकोग मम लथातक हह ए, छतलसगढ पमां चथारत रथाज
            <lb />
            अजधिकनरम, 1993 कक धिथारथा 129 (ख)(1) कक प्रथावधिथानम कक अधिलन मम कदनक श कपु मथार
            <lb />
            शलवथास्तव, कलक क्टर, जजलथा बस्तर, एतद्दथारथा नलचक दल गई सथारणल कक स्तमां भ (3) मम दशथार्या रक
            <lb />
            गरक गथामां व/गथामां वम कक समभ ह कक जलरक जजसकक जनसमां ख्रथा सथारणल कक स्तमां भ (4) मम दशथार्या रल गई
            <lb />
            हदै , सथारणल कक स्तमां भ (2) मम उकलजखत नथाम सक अजधिकनरम कक प्ररकोजनम कक जलरक &quot;ग्रथाम&quot; कक
            <lb />
            रूप मम कवकनकदर्या ष्ट करतथा हह मां , तथथा सथावर्या जकनक जथानकथारल कक जलए प्रकथाकशत करतथा हह मां .
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            14. Again, vide notification dated 22.07.2014, Gram Panchayat
            <lb />
            Kumravand has been shown to be included in village
            <lb />
            Kumravand and Village-Palli. The relevant portion of the said
            <lb />
            notification (Annexure R/5) is extracted below for ready
            <lb />
            reference:-
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            कथारथार्या लर, कलक क्टर, जजलथा बस्तर (छतलसगढ)
            <lb />
            बस्तर, कदनथामां क 21 जपु लथाई 2014
            <lb />
            अजधिसभ चनथा
            <lb />
            क्रमथामां क/482/पमां चथारत/2014-15.-छतलसगढ शथासन, पमां चथारत एवमां ग्रथामलण कवकथास
            <lb />
            कवभथाग कक अजधिसभ चनथा क्रमथामां क एफ-1-11-95-22 पमां .-02, कदनथामां क 23 फरवरल
            <lb />
            1999 दथारथा प्रदत शककरम कको प्ररकोग मम लथातक हह ए, छतलसगढ पमां चथारत रथाज अजधिकनरम
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            1993 (क्रमथामां क 1 सनद 1994) (जजसक इसकक पश्चथातद उक अजधिकनरम कहथा गरथा हदै ) कक
            <lb />
            धिथारथा 129 ख (1) कक प्रथावधिथानम कक अधिलन मम अमां ककत आनमां द, कलक क्टर, जजलथा बस्तर
            <lb />
            समां लग सथारणल (जजसक , इसकक पश्चथातद &quot;सथारणल&quot; कहथा गरथा हदै ) कक स्तमां भ (4) मम दशथार्या रक गरक
            <lb />
            गथामां व रथा गथामां धिल कक समभ ह कक जलए जजसकक जनसमां ख्रथा सथारणल कक स्तमां भ (5) मम दशथार्या रल गई हदै ,
            <lb />
            सथारणल कक स्तमां भ (3) मम उलक जखत नथाम सक उक अजधिकनरम कक प्ररकोजनको कक जलए &quot;ग्रथाम&quot; कक
            <lb />
            रूप मम कवकनकदर्या ष्ट करतथा हह मां तथथा सथावर्या जकनक जथानकथारल कक जलए एतद्दथारथा प्रकथाकशत ककरथा
            <lb />
            जथातथा हदै .
            <lb />
            इस स्थथाकपत ग्रथाम मम अजधिकनरम कक धिथारथा 8 (क) कक अनपु सथार ग्रथाम पमां चथारत कथा
            <lb />
            गठन ककरथा जथारक गथा इस प्रकथार गकठत ग्रथाम पमां चथारतम कको अजधिकनरम कक धिथारथा 11 कक अमां तगर्या त
            <lb />
            वकणर्या त अजधिकनरम कक प्ररकोजन कक जलए आवश्रक अन्र समस्त शककरथामां प्रथाप हमगल.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            15. From perusal of the aforesaid notifications, it is clear that the
            <lb />
            village Palli is rural area and does not come within the limit of
            <lb />
            Municipal Corporation of Jagdalpur. However, with the sheer
            <lb />
            motive to provide unlawful benefit to the beneficiaries of land
            <lb />
            acquisition, five Khatas of village Palli has been shown as urban
            <lb />
            area and huge compensation has been illegally paid to the
            <lb />
            beneficiaries. It has been further revealed that the maximum
            <lb />
            numbers of complaints were pertaining to the land acquisition
            <lb />
            relating to the four villages under the Jagdalpur block, specially
            <lb />
            the acquisition in village Palli and further contended that from
            <lb />
            perusal of the report it is clear that maximum areas of land has
            <lb />
            been acquired in village Kangoli and comparatively very less
            <lb />
            area has been acquired in village Palli. However, out of the
            <lb />
            compensation of Rs.152 Crores distributed in Jagdalpur block,
            <lb />
            Rs.99.07 Crores have been distributed towards seven Khatas of
            <lb />
            village Palli. Moreover, out of 7 beneficiaries just two
            <lb />
            beneficiaries have been awarded Rs.95.82 Crores out of
            <lb />
            Rs.99.07 Crores whereas the remaining 101 land owners have
            <lb />
            been jointly awarded only Rs.53.51 Crores of compensation. It
            <lb />
            has been further contended that the total compensation which
            <lb />
            has been awarded to the land acquisition proceeding, 64.90% of
            <lb />
            compensation is for the land belonging to village Palli. Thus, for
            <lb />
            the aforesaid reasons, the bank accounts of the petitioner
            <lb />
            Neelima Belsaria and Bali Nagwanshi have been freezed, the
            <lb />
            commissioner, Bastar Division , Jagdalpur, District Bastar has
            <lb />
            been appointed as the Arbitrator by the Government of India in
            <lb />
            respect of the above-mentioned land acquisition proceedings
            <lb />
            and being the arbitrator, the commissioner had all the authority
            <lb />
            and power to direct the Collector, District Bastar to conduct an
            <lb />
            enquiry into the allegations regarding large scale illegality,
            <lb />
            therefore, proceeding initiated by the Collector is proper and just
            <lb />
            and same is not liable to be interfered with and the respondent
            <lb />
            No.2 Collector is competent authority to enquire into illegality
            <lb />
            committed by its subordinate officers. It has been contended by
            <lb />
            the State that as per the provisions of the Act, 2013, the
            <lb />
            Collector has been authorized to determine the market value of
            <lb />
            the land to be acquired for determining the amount of
            <lb />
            compensation and for awarding the solatium amount. As such,
            <lb />
            the Collector was well within his power for conducting enquiry
            <lb />
            into the allegations of illegality committed in land acquisition
            <lb />
            proceeding. It has been further contended that from bare perusal
            <lb />
            of enquiry, it would reveal that the findings arrived at by the
            <lb />
            District Collector and material collected during investigating
            <lb />
            enquiry are legal and justified and it has been contended hat
            <lb />
            various steps have been taken by the officers for unlawful gain
            <lb />
            to the petitioner and Neelima Belsaria, for the aforesaid purpose,
            <lb />
            fraudulently their lands have been shown to be of much higher
            <lb />
            value than its actual value, thereby causing huge financial loss
            <lb />
            to the Government. The acts of the officers involved in the
            <lb />
            acquisition amounts to fraud and misappropriation. It has been
            <lb />
            further contended that IRCON Limited had been given the
            <lb />
            responsibility to conduct the survey, determination of rail route
            <lb />
            and its construction and earlier, the survey for the railway line
            <lb />
            had been conducted in the year 2007, however, after the work
            <lb />
            was allotted to the IRCON limited, a fresh survey was
            <lb />
            conducted, wherein major modification was done in the Railway
            <lb />
            route which considerably increased the compensation amount
            <lb />
            for the land acquisition. The station could have been built at
            <lb />
            village Kangoli or Ghatpadmour, but without considering the
            <lb />
            available option, the land of village Palli was selected. The
            <lb />
            entrance to the railway station has been proposed through a
            <lb />
            very narrow plot near Graveyard which is situated at Khasra
            <lb />
            No.122 which is a government land. The land belonging to the
            <lb />
            petitioners Neelima Belsaria and Bali Nagwanshi is next to the
            <lb />
            Graveyard and its size value is extremely low. In connivance
            <lb />
            with the petitioner Neelima Belsaria and Bali Nagwanshi, the
            <lb />
            then Sub Divisional Officer (Revenue) Jagdalpur and other
            <lb />
            officers proposed for acquisition of land. It has been further
            <lb />
            revealed that large scale illegality has been committed in
            <lb />
            acquisition of land of village Palli which comes under the Gram
            <lb />
            Panchayat Kumravand. It has been further submitted that five
            <lb />
            out of seven Khatas of Village-Palli have been considered to be
            <lb />
            part of Municipal Council Jagdalpur whereas the remaining two
            <lb />
            Khatas have been considered to be rural areas.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            16. It has been further stated that as per the above mentioned
            <lb />
            notification, only villages Sargipal, Kangoli, Dharampura,
            <lb />
            Aghanpur, Pakhnaguda, Frezarpur, Haatkachara, Krkapal,
            <lb />
            Kohakapal, Asna and Jagdalpur have been included within the
            <lb />
            limits of Municipal Council, Jagdalpur. It has been further
            <lb />
            contended by the State that the village Palli is not included
            <lb />
            within the limits of Jagdalpur Municipal Corporation. As per
            <lb />
            notification No. F-1-71/18/2004 of 2004 issued by the
            <lb />
            Department of Housing and Environment, Government of
            <lb />
            Chhattisgarh, Jagdalpur Municipal Corporation was framed by
            <lb />
            dividing the area in 40 wards and the limits of the wards were
            <lb />
            determined. The Ward No. 37 has been notified as Lok Manya
            <lb />
            Tilak Ward and the western limits of the said ward have been
            <lb />
            determined till the eastern limits of the Village-Palli. After the
            <lb />
            said notification, till date, no modification has been made to the
            <lb />
            geographical limits of the Municipal Corporation Jagdalpur.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            17. Learned State counsel would further submit that the petitioner is
            <lb />
            not entitled to get compensation as awarded by the Competent
            <lb />
            Authority in its award as per sub rule (3) of the Rules, market
            <lb />
            price determination of immovable property if the land is more
            <lb />
            than 0.50 hectare then calculation has to be made as per the
            <lb />
            relevant sub rule (3) of Praroop Teen which are extracted below
            <lb />
            for convenience:-
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            प्रथारूप &quot;तलन&quot; कक समां बमां धि मम उपबमां धि कनरम-3,
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            3.
            <lb />
            कपृ कष भभ कम कक जलरक उपबमां धि रकद ग्रथामलण क्षक त मम ककसल एक
            <lb />
            दस्तथावक ज कक दथारथा एक सक अजधिक खसरथा नम्बरम कक कपृ कष भभ कमरम कथा
            <lb />
            कवक्रर ककरथा जथातथा हदै , तको कपु ल रकबथा 0.050 हक क्टक रर सक अजधिक हकोनक
            <lb />
            पर भभ कम कक ककस्म कक अनपु सथार, समस्त रकबक कथा मभ ल्रथामां कन हक क्टक रर दर
            <lb />
            सक ककरथा जथावक गथा ।&quot;
            <lb />
            And
            <lb />
            प्रथारूप &quot;एक&quot; कक समां बमां धि मम उपबमां धि कनरम-9,
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            9.
            <lb />
            ग्रथामलण क्षक त मम पररवकतर्या त भभ कम कवक्रर ककरक जथानक पर, जहथामां उस
            <lb />
            क्षक त मम मपु ख्रमथागर्या /जसमां कचत/अजसमां कचत कक दरम कनधिथार्या ररत हम , उस क्षक त कक
            <lb />
            जसमां कचत भभ कम कक दर कथा ढथाई गपु नथा कर बथाजथार मभ ल्र कक गणनथा कक जथारक गल।
            <lb />
            भभ कम मपु ख्र मथागर्या पर सस्थत हकोनक पर उस क्षक त कक मपु ख्र मथागर्या कक उस कथा
            <lb />
            ढथाई गपु नथा कर बथाजथार मभ ल्र कक गणनथा कक जथारक गल, परन्तपु रह भल कक
            <lb />
            मपु ख्रमथागर्या कक दर सक रकद जसमां कचत भभ कम कक दर अजधिक हको तको अजधिकतम
            <lb />
            मभ ल्र मथान्र ककरथा जथारक गथा ।&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            18. It has been further contended that from bare perusal of the
            <lb />
            aforesaid rule, it is clear that calculation of compensation of any
            <lb />
            rural area having area more than 500 square meters should be
            <lb />
            calculated at hectare rate prescribed in market price
            <lb />
            determination of immovable property guidelines. Rs. 50,61,000/-
            <lb />
            per hectare is prescribed for the village Palli as per the
            <lb />
            guidelines of 2017-18. If the land is diverted according to Rule 9
            <lb />
            as mentioned above hectare rate is multiplied by a factor 2.5 for
            <lb />
            calculation of compensation of diverted land situated in rural
            <lb />
            area. According to Rule 10 of Market Price Determination of
            <lb />
            Immovable Property guidelines, rate has to be calculated in the
            <lb />
            following manner.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;प्रथारूप &quot;एक&quot; कक समां बमां धि मम उपबमां धि कनरम-10,
            <lb />
            नगरलर आवथासलर क्षक त मम ऐसल समां पजत जको मपु ख्र रकोड सक अन्दर सस्थत हको परन्तपु
            <lb />
            जजसकथा उपरकोग व्रथावसथाकरक/औद्यकोकगक प्ररकोजन कक जलरक ककरथा जथा
            <lb />
            रहथा हको, उसक क्षक त कक जलरक कनधिथार्या ररत दर मम 25 प्रकतशत वपृ कद कर बथाजथार
            <lb />
            मभ ल्र कक गणनथा कक जथारक गल।&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            19. It is further contended by the State that by reading the
            <lb />
            aforementioned provision, it is clear that additional 25%
            <lb />
            compensation for commercial land is for Urban, off road,
            <lb />
            residential areas but petitioner&apos;s land is adjacent to Jagdalpur-
            <lb />
            Chitrakot main road and is in rural non-residential area. It is
            <lb />
            further contended that the petitioner purchased the land bearing
            <lb />
            Khasra No. 123/1 admeasuring 1.99 hectare by registered sale
            <lb />
            deed dated 23.01.2015. Market value was calculated by taking
            <lb />
            hectare rate for village Palli and the petitioner has paid stamp
            <lb />
            duty on market value calculated as above. In 2014-15 guidelines
            <lb />
            hectare rate for village Palli for land situated in all main roads
            <lb />
            was Rs. 40,16,500/-and total market price comes to Rs.
            <lb />
            79,93,000/-. It clearly shows that when the petitioner purchased
            <lb />
            the land and he paid stamp duty on market price calculated on
            <lb />
            the basis of hectare rate but demanding compensation in square
            <lb />
            meter rate is clearly in violation of principle laid down in market
            <lb />
            price determination of immovable property guidelines. It has
            <lb />
            been further contended that the petitioner along with other
            <lb />
            petitioner are the only persons whose lands are situated in rural
            <lb />
            area but compensation awarded to them considering their land
            <lb />
            as situated in urban area clearly shows revenue officials&apos;
            <lb />
            favoritism in favour of the petitioner and other petitioner. It is
            <lb />
            further submitted that total 4.184 hectares were acquired from
            <lb />
            village Palli and amount awarded of Rs.99.07 crores which is
            <lb />
            64.9% of the total compensation has been paid. It is submitted
            <lb />
            that the Additional Collector in collusion with other officials has
            <lb />
            marked the land of 05 account holders including the petitioner as
            <lb />
            urban land and granted them compensation on urban rates
            <lb />
            whereas other 2 account holders adjacent to them have been
            <lb />
            granted on rural rates. Similarly, in neighbouring village
            <lb />
            Ghatpadmur lands acquired which are adjacent to petitioner&apos;s
            <lb />
            land are granted compensation on rural rates. This act shows
            <lb />
            malafide
            <lb />
            exercise
            <lb />
            of
            <lb />
            power,
            <lb />
            fraud,
            <lb />
            arbitrariness,
            <lb />
            unreasonableness and causing huge financial loss to the public
            <lb />
            exchequer which is against market price determination of
            <lb />
            immovable property guidelines 2017-18.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            20. It has been further contended by the State counsel that the
            <lb />
            enquiry report of the Collector, District-Bastar is based on ample
            <lb />
            documentary evidence through which the large scale illegalities
            <lb />
            are proved. As the above-mentioned enquiry was initial and fact
            <lb />
            finding one, and not a departmental enquiry, therefore, no notice
            <lb />
            was required to be given to the delinquent officials. Various land
            <lb />
            owners have raised objections to the land acquisition
            <lb />
            proceedings and disputes have been referred to the arbitrator
            <lb />
            i.e. Commissioner, Revenue, Bastar Division. It is further
            <lb />
            submitted that the plea of land acquisition proceedings being
            <lb />
            under the Railways Act cannot be taken by the petitioner for
            <lb />
            challenging the FIR in connection with Crime No. 409/2019 for
            <lb />
            the reason that the direction for registration of FIR for
            <lb />
            commission of cognizable offence does not rest on the
            <lb />
            competence of an authority to enquire into the acquisition
            <lb />
            procedure. If there is prima facie material to show the
            <lb />
            commission of cognizable offence is available, the FIR can
            <lb />
            always be registered by the Police and the Collector being the
            <lb />
            head of District Administration has jurisdiction and power for
            <lb />
            directing the Police to register the FIR.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            21. It is further contended that the petitioner has accepted that his
            <lb />
            land is adjacent to Municipal boundary which does not mean
            <lb />
            within municipal boundary. The land acquisition for Rowghat -
            <lb />
            Jagdalpur special railway project has been carried out in
            <lb />
            accordance with Railways Act, 1989 as amended in 2008. The
            <lb />
            necessary provisions were enacted in 2013, therefore,
            <lb />
            compensation has to be determined as per Schedule 1, 2 and 3
            <lb />
            of the Land Inquisition Act. It has been further contended that as
            <lb />
            per guidelines of 2017-2018 different rates for land which are
            <lb />
            adjacent to road and far from road have been prescribed. The
            <lb />
            petitioner has selectively produced principle which deals with
            <lb />
            only what lands have to be considered as land situated on road.
            <lb />
            According to the guidelines for year 2017-18 in urban area,
            <lb />
            lands which are situated upto a distance 20 meters from the
            <lb />
            main road are considered as lands situated on road likewise in
            <lb />
            rural areas which are situated up to a distance of 46 meters from
            <lb />
            the main road are considered as lands situated on road. The
            <lb />
            relevant rules are extracted below for convenience:-
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            प्रथारूप &quot;एक&quot; कक समां बमां धि मम उपबमां धि कनरम-7,
            <lb />
            मपु ख्र सड़क सक 20 मलटर कक गहरथाई/दभ रल तक सस्थत भभ खण्डम कको मपु ख्र
            <lb />
            सड़क सक लगल मथानकर मपु ख्र सड़क कक जलए कनधिथार्या ररत दर अनपु सथार प्रकत
            <lb />
            वगर्या मलटर मम बथाजथारमभ ल्र कक गणनथा कक जथावक गल परन्तपु रह भल कक ककोई
            <lb />
            पक्षकथार 20 मलटर दभ रल सक अजधिक गहरथाई तक कक भभ कम क्रर करतथा हदै तब
            <lb />
            सम्पभ णर्या भभ खण्ड कको मपु ख्र सड़क सक लगथा हह आ मथानकर बथाजथारमभ ल्र कक
            <lb />
            गणनथा कक जथावक गल&quot;
            <lb />
            प्रथारूप &quot;तलन&quot; कक समां बमां धि मम उपबमां धि कनरम-10,
            <lb />
            सड़क सक दकोनम ओर 46 मलटर कक दभ रल तक सस्थत कपृ कशभभ कमरम कको
            <lb />
            सड़क सक लगल मथान कर उसकक जलए कनधिथार्या ररत दर कक अनपु सथार मभ ल्रथामां कन
            <lb />
            ककरथा जथावक गथा, परमां तपु रह भल कक रकद ककोई पक्षकथार 46 मलटर कक
            <lb />
            गहरथाई/दभ रल सक अजधिक गहरथाई तक कक भभ कमक्रर करतथा हदै तब सम्पभ णर्या
            <lb />
            रकबथा कको मभ ख्र सड़क सक लगथा हह आ मथानकर बथाजथारमभ ल्र कक गणनथा कक
            <lb />
            जथावक गल।
            <lb />
            प्रथारूप &quot;तलन&quot; कक समां बमां धि मम उपबमां धि कनरम-3,
            <lb />
            कपृ कष भभ कम कक जलरक उपबमां धि रकद ग्रथामलण क्षक त मम ककसल एक दस्तथावक ज कक
            <lb />
            दथारथा एक सक अजधिक खसरथा नम्बरम कक कपृ कष भभ कमरम कथा कवक्रर ककरथा
            <lb />
            जथातथा हदै , तको कपु ल रकबथा 0.050 हक क्टक रर सक अजधिक हकोनक पर भभ कम कक
            <lb />
            ककस्म कक अनपु सथार, समस्त रकबक कथा मभ ल्रथामां कन हक क्टक रर दर सक ककरथा
            <lb />
            जथावक गथा ।&quot;
            <lb />
            And
            <lb />
            प्रथारूप &quot;एक&quot; कक समां बमां धि मम उपबमां धि कनरम-9,
            <lb />
            ग्रथामलण क्षक त मम पररवकतर्या त भभ कम कवक्रर ककरक जथानक पर, जहथामां उस क्षक त मम
            <lb />
            मपु ख्रमथागर्या /जसमां कचत/अजसमां कचत कक दरम कनधिथार्या ररत हम , उस क्षक त कक जसमां कचत
            <lb />
            भभ कम कक दर कथा ढथाई गपु नथा कर बथाजथार मभ ल्र कक गणनथा कक जथारक गल । भभ कम
            <lb />
            मपु ख्र मथागर्या पर सस्थत हकोनक पर उस क्षक त कक मपु ख्र मथागर्या कक उस कथा
            <lb />
            ढथाईगपु नथा कर बथाजथार मभ ल्र कक गणनथा कक जथारक गल, परन्तपु रह भल कक
            <lb />
            मपु ख्रमथागर्या कक दर सक रकद जसमां कचत भभ कम कक दर अजधिक हको तको अजधिकतम
            <lb />
            मभ ल्र मथान्र ककरथा जथारक गथा ।&quot;
            <lb />
            प्रथारूप &quot;एक&quot; कक समां बमां धि मम उपबमां धि कनरम-1,
            <lb />
            टलप-1 नगर कनगम कक नगरलर क्षक तम मम .202 हक क्टक रर सक अजधिक कपृ कश
            <lb />
            भभ कम कवक्रर हकोनक पर सम्पभ णर्या रकबक कक जलए उस क्षक त हक तपु कनधिथार्या ररत प्रकत
            <lb />
            हक क्टक रर दर सक बथाजथार मभ ल्र कक समां गण्नथा कक जथावक गल ।&quot;
            <lb />
            टलप-2 नगर कनगम क्षक तम मम ककसल एक दस्तथावक ज कक दथारथा एक सक अजधिक
            <lb />
            खसरथा नमां . कक कपृ कशभभ कमरम कथा कवक्रर ककरक जथानक पर रकद कपु ल रकबथा .
            <lb />
            202 हक क्ट. सक अजधिक हको तको भभ कम कक ककस्म कक अनपु सथार समस्त रकबक
            <lb />
            कथा मभ ल्रथामां कन हक क्टक रर दर सक ककरथा जथावक गथा ।
            <lb />
            प्रथारूप &quot;तलन&quot; कक समां बमां धि मम उपबमां धि कनरम-3,
            <lb />
            कपृ कशभभ कम कक जलरक उपबमां धि रकद ग्रथामलण क्षक त मम ककसल एक दस्तथावक ज कक
            <lb />
            दथारथा एक सक अजधिक खसरथा नम्बरम कक कपृ कशभभ कमरम कथा कवक्रर ककरथा
            <lb />
            जथातथा हदै , तको कपु ल रकबथा 0.050 हक क्टक रर सक अजधिक हकोनक पर भभ कम कक
            <lb />
            ककस्म कक अनपु सथार, समस्त रकबक कको मभ ल्रथामां कन हक क्टक रर दर सक ककरथा
            <lb />
            जथावक गथा ।&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            22. It has been further contended that the petitioner has challenged
            <lb />
            the compensation awarded by the Additional Collector before the
            <lb />
            Commissioner Revenue Bastar Division whereas the Arbitrator
            <lb />
            has enhanced compensation only on reports of Additional
            <lb />
            Collector, Railway authorities but after came to know about the
            <lb />
            collector&apos;s report dated 30.07.2019 have kept the order dated
            <lb />
            11.07.2019 in abeyance the order vide its order dated
            <lb />
            02.08.2019 and directed not to pay enhanced compensation to
            <lb />
            the petitioner. The report of the Collector clearly shows, prima
            <lb />
            facie that cognizable offence is made out against the petitioner.
            <lb />
            The Collector being head of the District Administration has
            <lb />
            jurisdiction and power to register the FIR, therefore, the writ
            <lb />
            petition deserves to be dismissed.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            23. Learned counsel for respondent No.4 has filed return contending
            <lb />
            that no relief has been claimed by the petitioner against the
            <lb />
            respondent No. 4 and respondent No.4 was discharging its duty
            <lb />
            by following the instruction of the letters dated 05.08.2019
            <lb />
            issued by respondent No. 3/Station House Officer, Police Kotwali
            <lb />
            to freeze the bank account of the petitioners maintained at
            <lb />
            branch of respondent No.4 in view of reregistration of Crime No.
            <lb />
            409 of 2019 registered against the petitioner at Police Kotwali,
            <lb />
            Jagdalpur for the offences punishable under Sections 420, 467,
            <lb />
            468, 471, 406, 407, 408, 409, 120-B and 109 of IPC, they have
            <lb />
            freezed the bank account of the petitioners and would submit
            <lb />
            that no relief has been sought against them.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            24. Learned counsel for respondent No. 5 has filed its return
            <lb />
            contending that it is a joint venture project and MoU dated
            <lb />
            09.05.2015 have been executed, IRCON has been nominated
            <lb />
            as the agency for picking up equity on behalf of Ministry of
            <lb />
            Railways with no financial commitment from Ministry of
            <lb />
            Railways. The agreement has to be executed by IRCON with the
            <lb />
            State Government, SAIL and NMDC as directed by the
            <lb />
            Executive Director, Traffic Railway Board on 07-04-2015 to the
            <lb />
            Chief Secretary of the Govt. of Chattisgarh and as per policy of
            <lb />
            the Ministry pertaining to undertaking that joint venture a MoU
            <lb />
            was executed on 09.05.2015. As per the MoU, the cost of the
            <lb />
            project is Rs. 2000 Crores, therefore, this project is to be carried
            <lb />
            out through specific Joint Venture Company (JVC). The relevant
            <lb />
            clause of MoU, clause 6 &amp; 7 are extracted below:-
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;6. GoCG shall provide the land owned by State
            <lb />
            Government (Revenue land and Forest land) and
            <lb />
            value of such land shall be adjusted towards
            <lb />
            GoCG&apos;s equity share in the JVC as per Para 3
            <lb />
            above. Cost of compensatory afforestation, net
            <lb />
            present value, wildlife management plan,
            <lb />
            demarcation, felling and other charges for
            <lb />
            diversion proposal of forest plan under Forest
            <lb />
            Conservation Act shall be borne by the JVC.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            7. Acquisition of the privately owned land required
            <lb />
            for the project shall be made by the JVC as per
            <lb />
            the extant policy. JVC shall be responsible for
            <lb />
            payment of the compensation of the land and also
            <lb />
            implementation of the Rehabilitation plan asper
            <lb />
            LARR Act and Rehabilitation Policy opf the State
            <lb />
            Government. Government of CG shall extend all
            <lb />
            necessary assistance for these purposes and for
            <lb />
            expediting the land acquisition process&quot;.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            25. Respondent No. 6 has filed its return reiterating the events which
            <lb />
            have been taken place from the initial stage i.e. from
            <lb />
            establishing a JVC vide notification dated 09-05-2015 consisting
            <lb />
            of Steel Authority of India Ltd. (SAIL), Indian Railway
            <lb />
            Construction Company Ltd. (IRCON), National Mineral
            <lb />
            Development
            <lb />
            Corporation
            <lb />
            Ltd.,
            <lb />
            Chhattisgarh
            <lb />
            Minerals
            <lb />
            Development Corporation Ltd (CMDC) took part to build,
            <lb />
            construct, operate and maintain Jagdalpur Rowghat Rail
            <lb />
            Corridor Project. As per the MoU, the Government of
            <lb />
            Chhattisgarh was required to facilitate the process of land
            <lb />
            acquisition, environmental and forest clearance including the
            <lb />
            transfer of government land to the Ministry of Railways.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            26. The State Government was required to provide all the requisite
            <lb />
            statutory support whenever required to the joint venture for
            <lb />
            ensuring expeditious completion and commissioning of the
            <lb />
            project. Thereafter, notification dated 04.04.2016 was issued by
            <lb />
            the Central Government notifying the project as Special project.
            <lb />
            On 20.01.2017 the Additional Collector, District Bastar was
            <lb />
            appointed as competent authority for the purpose of land
            <lb />
            acquisition under Section 2 (7A) of the Railways Act, 1989. It has
            <lb />
            been further contended that there was large scale illegality in
            <lb />
            determining the compensation payable to the land-owners in
            <lb />
            respect of Palli village. Exorbitant and arbitrary compensation
            <lb />
            has been awarded to few land owners by treating their lands as
            <lb />
            urban lands as against rural lands. Petitioner Balil Nagwanshi
            <lb />
            has been awarded Rs.70.62 Crores for 2.69 hectares by treating
            <lb />
            his land as urban area whereas he was only entitled to Rs.7.79
            <lb />
            Crores. Petitioner Neelima has been awarded Rs.25.19 Crores
            <lb />
            for only 1.040 hectares whereas she was entitled only to Rs.4.38
            <lb />
            crores. Similarly, other land oustees of village Palli i.e., Pakali,
            <lb />
            Nagwanshi builders and developers have been paid Rs.2.28
            <lb />
            Crores for 0.12 hectares though they were entitled to receive
            <lb />
            Rs.27 lakhs. It has been further contended that as per principles
            <lb />
            of determining compensation, each account has to be treated as
            <lb />
            a single unit even though the account consists of more than one
            <lb />
            khasra plot. The land acquisition in this case involved
            <lb />
            accounts which had 15 accounts having more than one khasra
            <lb />
            plots while 13 accounts which had more than one Khasra plots
            <lb />
            were treated as single unit for awarding compensation only in
            <lb />
            accounts separate computation was done in respect of each of
            <lb />
            the khasra plots falling within those 2 accounts. Thus, the net
            <lb />
            compensation awarded increased exponentially. The lands of
            <lb />
            both petitioner and Neelima have further been treated as lands
            <lb />
            situated adjacent to main road for obtaining 25% additional
            <lb />
            compensation whereas those particular lands are not located in
            <lb />
            residential area.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            27. It has been further contended that the complicity of the IRCON
            <lb />
            officials, the initial route of the land was diverted and a new
            <lb />
            station was created at village Palli in order to ensure that the
            <lb />
            lands of the accused persons can be acquired. It is also found
            <lb />
            that the lands were first purchased with the hope of getting them
            <lb />
            acquired for the said railway project. The accused persons
            <lb />
            entered motivating transactions for the purpose of making
            <lb />
            unlawful gains at the cost of the exchequer. The lands had been
            <lb />
            purchased by paying stamp duty as rural lands, the
            <lb />
            compensation has been awarded considering them as urban
            <lb />
            lands as the same could not be done unless the land owners
            <lb />
            proved that the status of the land had changed in the meantime.
            <lb />
            Though the calculation ought to have been made in terms of
            <lb />
            hectares, the compensation has been awarded by calculating in
            <lb />
            terms of square meters. It has been further contended that the
            <lb />
            report recommended for initiating departmental enquiry against
            <lb />
            the erring officials and also called for recovering excessive
            <lb />
            compensation paid to the land owners. The detailed report
            <lb />
            submitted by the Collector makes it evident that there has been
            <lb />
            a concerted criminal conspiracy between revenue officials and
            <lb />
            the land owners in getting the compensation awarded at
            <lb />
            exorbitant rates. It is not a case of mere illegality in awarding
            <lb />
            higher compensation which could be corrected either before the
            <lb />
            arbitrator or the judicial forums but a case of large scale fraud
            <lb />
            upon the public exchequer, therefore, on the report submitted by
            <lb />
            the Collector, FIR was registered against the officials, petitioner
            <lb />
            and other accused persons. The other land oustees had
            <lb />
            received exorbitant compensation against acquisition of their
            <lb />
            lands, therefore, the findings recorded in the report are legal and
            <lb />
            just. It has been further contended that the petitioner had
            <lb />
            purchased the land bearing khasra No.123/1 admeasuring 1.99
            <lb />
            hectare in 2015 when market rate value of the land was
            <lb />
            calculated by considering unit hectare rate prescribed for village
            <lb />
            Palli. Petitioner&apos;s land market price was 79.93 lakhs in 2015 and
            <lb />
            accordingly he paid 5% stamp duty which was Rs.3.99 lakhs.
            <lb />
            Now the petitioner has been awarded compensation by
            <lb />
            considering per square meter rate whereas Neelima Belsaria
            <lb />
            who is also an accused, was awarded compensation by
            <lb />
            considering hectare rate. Similarly, the petitioner was awarded
            <lb />
            25% more compensation for 0.4 hectares of commercially
            <lb />
            diverted land which is against the provisions contained in
            <lb />
            guidelines rates for the year 2017-18. It has been further
            <lb />
            contended that in the original DPR for the Jagdalpur-Rowghat
            <lb />
            Rail Corridor Project, there was no station conceived at village
            <lb />
            Palli. The DPR has been changed without approval of BRPL
            <lb />
            Board which shows that petitioner with collusion of revenue
            <lb />
            officials and other officers of IRCON committed fraud.
            <lb />
            Respondent No. 6 has filed its return which is almost similar to
            <lb />
            the return filed by respondents No. 1 to 3/State, therefore, to
            <lb />
            avoid repeatition, brief contentions have been mentioned while
            <lb />
            mentioning the facts stated by respondent No. 6 in their return.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <head>
            WPCR No. 674 of 2019
            <lb />
        </head>

        <p>
            28. Petitioner No. 1/Siyaram Kurre, petitioner No. 2/Dindayal
            <lb />
            Mandavi, petitioner No. 3/Arjun Shrivastava &amp; petitioner No.
            <lb />
            4/Dharam Narayan Sahu, who were at the relevant time working
            <lb />
            as Additional Collector, Deputy Collector (Incharge Tahsildar),
            <lb />
            Naib Tahsildar &amp; Patwari respectively, have jointly filed the
            <lb />
            present writ petition challenging the legallity and propriety of
            <lb />
            registration of FIR dated 04.08.2019 against them and also the
            <lb />
            enquiry reported dated 30.04.2019 submitted by the Collector
            <lb />
            reiterating the same stand taken by the petitioner in WPCR No.
            <lb />
            1031 of 2019 and other writ petitions. Learned counsel for the
            <lb />
            petitioners would submit that the Collector was not competent
            <lb />
            under the Railway Act, 1982 to conduct such enquiry.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            29. He would further submit that the enquiry report is perverse and
            <lb />
            without considering the fact that the petitioners have performed
            <lb />
            their duties for carrying out the said land acquisition under the
            <lb />
            Railway&apos;s Act, therefore, the Collector cannot be enquired into
            <lb />
            the land acquisition proceedings, which has already been taken
            <lb />
            by the Railway&apos;s officers, as per provisions of the Railway Act,
            <lb />
            1989. All the officers who were government officials had acted
            <lb />
            under the Railway Act are being granted protection as per the
            <lb />
            Act, 1989. Since the petitioners have discharged their duties
            <lb />
            under the Railway Act, therefore, the Collector cannot exercise
            <lb />
            its jurisdiction to conduct the enquiry into which they have
            <lb />
            already discharged their official duties under the Railway Act, as
            <lb />
            such the report submitted by the Collected dated 30.07.2019 is
            <lb />
            contrary to the records on the basis of perverse finding recorded
            <lb />
            in the enquiry conducted by the Collector dated 30.07.2019. The
            <lb />
            subsequent registration of FIR is also illegal and deserves to be
            <lb />
            quashed by this Court.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            30. The State has filed their return reiterating the stands already
            <lb />
            taken in WPCR No. 1031 of 2019.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            31. The Union of India has also filed their return reiterating the
            <lb />
            stands already taken in WPCR No. 1031 of 2019.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            32. This Court vide order dated 17.09.2021 has directed the State to
            <lb />
            file report with regard to the land acquisition proceedings
            <lb />
            whereby some doubt was raised in the report of the Collector
            <lb />
            about the quantum of the compensation. In pursuance of the
            <lb />
            same, the State has submitted its compliance report contending
            <lb />
            that the petitioner being revenue authorities while determining
            <lb />
            the compensation deliberately overlooked the aforesaid material
            <lb />
            facts and awarded more compensation in favour of the land
            <lb />
            owners considering the lands of Village-Palli comes under the
            <lb />
            urban area. However, the aforesaid records clearly reveal that
            <lb />
            the lands of Village-Palli come under Gram Panchayat Palli. He
            <lb />
            would further submit that upon registration of offence under
            <lb />
            Crime No. 409/2019 at Police Station-Kotwali, District-Bastar
            <lb />
            for offence punishable under Sections 109, 120B, 406, 407, 420,
            <lb />
            467, 468, 471 of IPC, the relevant original records have been
            <lb />
            seized by the police of Police Station-Parpa, District-Bastar.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            33. He would further submit that the Collector &amp; District Magistrate,
            <lb />
            Jagdalpur, District-Bastar submitted enquiry reported before the
            <lb />
            State Government on 30.07.2019 which reflects irregularities
            <lb />
            committed by the petitioners by way of treating the Village-Palli
            <lb />
            comes under the territory of Municipal Corporation, Jagdalpur,
            <lb />
            District-Bastar. The petitioner being revenue authorities
            <lb />
            deliberately treated the lands of five land owners falling under
            <lb />
            the area of Municipal Corporation, Jagdalpur, District-Bastar
            <lb />
            and the land got acquired for the Rowghat-Jagdalpur Railway
            <lb />
            project. However, as per the records the lands under the Village-
            <lb />
            Palli come under the Gram Panchayat Palli. In order to describe
            <lb />
            the above facts a copy of the calculation sheet with respect to
            <lb />
            compensation towards land acquisition under the Village-Palli,
            <lb />
            Patwari Halka No. 2, Tahsil Jagdalpur, District-Bastar has been
            <lb />
            filed along with the report filed by the State.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            34. He would further submit that the market value of the agricultural
            <lb />
            land was to be determined as per the guideline for the year
            <lb />
            2017-2018, which prescribes the rate of land for the Village-
            <lb />
            Palli. As per the guidelines Rs. 50,61,000/-per hectare for the
            <lb />
            lands situated adjacent to the road, whereas Rs. 32,94,000/-for
            <lb />
            the land situated inside the village. The petitioners have
            <lb />
            calculated the compensation on the basis of Rs. 13,800/-per
            <lb />
            sq.ft. by treating the aforesaid land under the urban area. The
            <lb />
            copy of the map of Village-Panchayat Palli, Tahsil-Jagdalpur,
            <lb />
            District-Bastar has also been filed with the report.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            35. He would further submit that the Government of Chhattisgarh,
            <lb />
            Department of Urban Development has issued notification dated
            <lb />
            03.09.2002 with respect to inclusion of villages in the area of
            <lb />
            Municipal Corporation, Jagdalpur, District-Bastar where Village-
            <lb />
            Palli did not find place, hence, it is clear that Village-Palli does
            <lb />
            not come under the municipal area. The department of
            <lb />
            Panchayat &amp; Rural Development, Government of Chhattisgarh
            <lb />
            has issued notification dated 12.07.2004 with respect to villages
            <lb />
            which come under the Gram Panchayats, wherein in column 3
            <lb />
            (name of dependent village) the name of Village-Palli and
            <lb />
            Kumravand are mentioned under the Gram Panchayat
            <lb />
            Kumravand. Office of Collector, District-Bastar had issued
            <lb />
            notification dated 21.07.2014 with respect to constitution of
            <lb />
            Gram Panchayats, which reflects that at serial No. 23, Village-
            <lb />
            Palli comes under the Gram Panchayat Kumravand and would
            <lb />
            submit that the writ petition may kindly be dismissed.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <head>
            WPCR No. 979 of 2019
            <lb />
        </head>

        <p>
            36. Petitioner No. 1/ Neelima Belsaria, who was owner of the lands
            <lb />
            &amp; petitioner No. 2/ T.V. Ravi Kurup, who is husband of petitioner
            <lb />
            No. 1, have filed this writ petition reiterating the same stand
            <lb />
            taken by the petitioner in WPCR No. 1031 of 2019. The
            <lb />
            petitioners have prayed that the impugned order dated
            <lb />
            05.08.2019 (Annexure P/1) by which the bank account of the
            <lb />
            petitioner has been freezed, be kindly set aside by this Court
            <lb />
            and also prayed that the bank authority may also be directed to
            <lb />
            lift the hold on the bank accounts of the petitioners and to take
            <lb />
            appropriate action in releasing all the three bank accounts of the
            <lb />
            petitioners.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            37. The State has filed their return reiterating the stand already
            <lb />
            taken by the State in WPCR No. 1031 of 2019 and would submit
            <lb />
            that after considering the entire materials placed on records
            <lb />
            issued by the concerned Station House Officer, Police Station-
            <lb />
            City Kotwali, Jagdalpur, District-Bastar addressed to the Bank
            <lb />
            authorities to seize/freeze/seal the petitioners&apos; Bank account as
            <lb />
            Crime No. 409/2019 has been registered against them. He
            <lb />
            would further submit that there is violation of rules and quantum
            <lb />
            has been assessed on a higher side while land acquisition
            <lb />
            proceeding done by the Competent Authority, therefore, to safe
            <lb />
            guard the interest of public exchequer, the order has been
            <lb />
            issued and prayed for dismissal of the instant Writ Petition (Cr.).
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            38. Respondent No. 3/Bank of Baroda has also filed its return, in
            <lb />
            which they have stated that they have discharged their duties in
            <lb />
            compliance of the letter dated 05.08.2019 issued by Station
            <lb />
            House Officer/ respondent No. 1 and no relief has been sought
            <lb />
            against them, therefore, the instant writ petition so far as relating
            <lb />
            to them, may kindly be dismissed.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            39. Respondent No. 2/Union of India has already filed their return
            <lb />
            reiterating the stands already taken by them in WPCR No. 1013
            <lb />
            of 2019 and other writ petitions.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            40. Learned counsel for the petitioners has also filed written
            <lb />
            submissions relying upon the same factual position and would
            <lb />
            submit that as per Section 102 of the Cr.P.C. deals with power of
            <lb />
            police officer to seize certain property. Hon&apos;ble the Supreme
            <lb />
            Court in State of Maharashtra Vs. Tapas D. Neogi 1 , has held
            <lb />
            that a bank cannot be prohibited not to pay any amount out of
            <lb />
            the account of the accused to the accused nor can the accused
            <lb />
            be prohibited from taking away any property from the locker, as
            <lb />
            such an order would not be a `seizure&apos; within the meaning of
            <lb />
            Section 102 of the Criminal Procedure Code.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            41. He would further submit that Hon&apos;ble the Supreme Court in
            <lb />
            Enrica Lexie Vs. Doramma 2 , has held at paragraph 13 that the
            <lb />
            police officer in course of investigation can seize any property
            <lb />
            under Section 102 if such property is alleged to be stolen or is
            <lb />
            suspected to be stolen or is the object of the crime under
            <lb />
            investigation or has direct link with the commission of offence for
            <lb />
            which the police officer is investigating into. A property not
            <lb />
            suspected of commission of the offence which is being
            <lb />
            investigated into by the police officer cannot be seized. Under
            <lb />
            Section 102 of the Code, the police officer can seize such
            <lb />
            property which is covered by Section 102 (1) and no other. He
            <lb />
            would further submit that Hon&apos;ble the Supreme Court in Teesta
            <lb />
            Atul Setalvad Vs. State of Gujarat 3 , has also taken the same
            <lb />
            view.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            42. He would further submit that the entire action of the police
            <lb />
            authorities in freezing and seizure of the petitioners&apos; bank
            <lb />
            account is without jurisdiction, illegal and is in complete violation
            <lb />
            of the provisions of law and he would further pray that Writ
            <lb />
            Petition (Cr.) be kindly allowed.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <head>
            WPCR No. 1096 of 2019
            <lb />
        </head>

        <p>
            43. The petitioner who was working at the relevant time as Sub-
            <lb />
            Registrar, Jagdalpur, District-Bastar has filed the instant writ
            <lb />
            petition assailing the enquiry report dated 30.07.2019 (Annexure
            <lb />
            P/1) submitted by the Collector as well as the subsequent FIR
            <lb />
            No. 409/2019 dated 04.08.2019 (Annexure P/2) registered
            <lb />
            against him at Police Station-Jagdalpur, District-Bastar (C.G.).
            <lb />
            The petitioner has taken the same stand which has already been
            <lb />
            taken by the other petitioners in WPCR No. 1031 of 2019 and
            <lb />
            other writ petitions, therefore, they are not being repeated by this
            <lb />
            Court.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            44. In addition to that, learned counsel for the petitioner would
            <lb />
            submit that the petitioner was working as Sub-Registrar at the
            <lb />
            relevant point of time, regarding value of land acquired for Rail
            <lb />
            Line Special Rail Project, Rowghat-Jagdalpur regarding Village-
            <lb />
            Palli. The petitioner after perusing the relevant records, has sent
            <lb />
            information regarding market value of subject lands as per
            <lb />
            prevailing guidelines. Thereafter, vide letter dated 27.01.2018,
            <lb />
            the Joint Director has directed the petitioner to submit market
            <lb />
            value of acquired land of Village-Palli as per Khasra records.
            <lb />
            Vide letter dated 30.01.2018, the petitioner submitted the market
            <lb />
            value of acquired land of Village-Palli. On the allegation of
            <lb />
            furnishing incorrect market value of acquired land, vide order
            <lb />
            dated 30.07.2019, the petitioner was placed under suspension
            <lb />
            by the Collector, Bastar. On the same allegations, vide order
            <lb />
            dated 30.07.2019, the Collector, Bastar has directed for
            <lb />
            registration of FIR against the accused persons including
            <lb />
            present petitioner.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            45. The petitioner preferred an appeal agaist the suspension order
            <lb />
            before the Commissioner, Bastar Division and vide its letter
            <lb />
            dated 07.10.2020, the petitioner&apos;s suspension was revoked. It
            <lb />
            has been further contended that in pursuance of the same
            <lb />
            allegation, charge-sheet has been issued on 06.09.2019 and
            <lb />
            vide order dated 04.01.2021, the Collector, Bastar has closed
            <lb />
            the enquiry proceeding initiated against the petitioner. On the
            <lb />
            same facts, the FIR has been registered against the petitioner,
            <lb />
            therefore, the FIR is also liable to be quashed. It has been
            <lb />
            further submitted that as per the guidelines for the year 2017-18
            <lb />
            the market value of the land situated at Ward No. 37, Lok Manya
            <lb />
            Tilak Ward falls within area of Municipal Corporation and market
            <lb />
            value of the said area is fixed as Rs. 11,300/-sq. Mtr. as per the
            <lb />
            prevailing guidelines as such, no fraud has been committed by
            <lb />
            him.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            46. The State has filed their return reiterating the same stand taken
            <lb />
            by them in other writ petitions and would submit that the writ
            <lb />
            petition may kindly be dismissed.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            47. Respondent No. 2/Union of India has also filed their return
            <lb />
            reiterating the same stand, which they have taken in WPCR No.
            <lb />
            1031 of 2019 and other writ petitions.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <head>
            WPCR No. 751 of 2019
            <lb />
        </head>

        <p>
            48. The petitioner has reiterated the stands already taken by them in
            <lb />
            WPCR No. 1031 of 2019 and would submit that the petitioner
            <lb />
            being owner of the land has rightly been granted compensation
            <lb />
            and would also submit that the petitioner after developing the
            <lb />
            land has accorded permission from Collector, Bastar at
            <lb />
            Jagdalpur vide its order dated 19.03.2009 to sell out the plot on
            <lb />
            the basis of colonizer license and permission granted by the
            <lb />
            Municipal Corporation for development of plots. It has been
            <lb />
            further contended that the said permission was recalled vide its
            <lb />
            order dated 30.01.2012. The petitioner has challenged the said
            <lb />
            award/order before this Court in WP (227) No. 238/2012. The
            <lb />
            said writ petition was partly allowed by this Court.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            49. The petitioner has reiterated the stand taken in WPCR No. 1031
            <lb />
            of 2019 and would additionally submit that the Collector has
            <lb />
            conducted enquiry without considering the important fact that the
            <lb />
            subjected land was purchased by the petitioner vide registered
            <lb />
            sale deed dated 20.02.2008 and thereafter the Sub Divisional
            <lb />
            Officer in Revenue Case No. 119/A-2/2007-08 had granted
            <lb />
            permission for diversion of use of said land vide order dated
            <lb />
            04.08.2008,
            <lb />
            thereafter,
            <lb />
            the
            <lb />
            Commissioner,
            <lb />
            Municipal
            <lb />
            Corporation, Jagdalpur vide order dated 21.04.2011 has granted
            <lb />
            permission to develop the colony over the said plot.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            50. The petitioner after granting permission from Collector vide order
            <lb />
            dated 19.03.2009 to sell out the plot on the basis of having
            <lb />
            colonizer license and permission granted by Municipal
            <lb />
            Corporation for development of plot. However, the said
            <lb />
            permission was recalled and set aside by learned Commissioner
            <lb />
            vide order dated 30.01.2012. The petitioner had challenged the
            <lb />
            said order before this Hon&apos;ble Court in WP (227) No. 238/2012
            <lb />
            and the same was dismissed by this Hon&apos;ble Court maintaining
            <lb />
            the order of diversion of land dated 04.08.2008. The
            <lb />
            consequence of dismissal of said writ petition was that the
            <lb />
            subjected land was back to the hands of the petitioner as per the
            <lb />
            order dated 07.01.2015 passed by the Collector which was
            <lb />
            passed in Revenue Case No. 37/A-21/2011-2012. In view of
            <lb />
            these proceedings, it is apparently clear that order of diversion of
            <lb />
            use of land was maintained by the order of this Court, sold to the
            <lb />
            aboriginal tribes were found to be illegal meaning thereby the
            <lb />
            plotting over the land was maintained. All these factual aspects
            <lb />
            have been overlooked by the Collector. The competent authority
            <lb />
            is absolutely justified in considering the land to be a diverted
            <lb />
            land. Hence, the petitioner has prayed for following reliefs:-
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;(1) To quash the enquiry report dated 30.07.2019
            <lb />
            (Annexure P/1).
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (2) To quash the FIR dated 04.08.2019 (Annexure
            <lb />
            P/2) to the extent of the petitioner registered under
            <lb />
            Crime No. 409/2019 by the Police Station-
            <lb />
            Jagdalpur (C.G.)
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (3) Any other relief, which the Hon&apos;ble Court
            <lb />
            considers proper, may kindly be awarded.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            51. The State has filed its return reiterating the stand already taken
            <lb />
            in WPCR No. 1031/2019, therefore, the same is not repeated by
            <lb />
            this Court and would submit that the grounds raised in this
            <lb />
            petition challenging the impugned enquiry report and
            <lb />
            subsequent registration of FIR, is completely unsustainable,
            <lb />
            therefore, no case is made out for interference by this Court and
            <lb />
            the instant petition is liable to be dismissed by this Court.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            52. Respondent No. 2/Union of India has filed a detailed return on
            <lb />
            09.03.2020 reiterating the stand which they have already taken
            <lb />
            in WPCR No. 1031 of 2019, therefore, the same is not being
            <lb />
            repeated by this Court and would submit that contention of the
            <lb />
            petitioner that the entire enquiry report submitted by the
            <lb />
            Collector is based on perversity without opportunity of hearing in
            <lb />
            violation of principles of natural justice, is liable to be rejected by
            <lb />
            this Court. Accordingly, the instant Writ Petition (Cr.) is also liable
            <lb />
            to be rejected by this Court.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <head>
            WPCR No. 828 of 2019
            <lb />
        </head>

        <p>
            53. The petitioner No. 1/ Suresh B. Matali is Additional General
            <lb />
            Manager (Civil) &amp; petitioner No. 2/ A.V.R. Murty is Joint General
            <lb />
            Manager against whom allegation in the complaint, enquiry
            <lb />
            report as well as in the FIR has been levelled, have filed the
            <lb />
            instant writ petition reiterating the stand already taken by other
            <lb />
            petitioners in WPCR No. 1031 of 2019 and other petitioners. It
            <lb />
            has been further contended that Collector, Bastar at Jagdalpur
            <lb />
            was not competent and without hearing the parties, enquiry
            <lb />
            report has been submitted and on the basis of enquiry report,
            <lb />
            FIR has been registered. It has been further contended that on
            <lb />
            the above factual matrix, the enquiry report dated 30.07.2019
            <lb />
            and the FIR No. 409/2019 dated 04.08.2019 registered against
            <lb />
            the petitioners may kindly be quashed.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            54. The petitioner has also filed I.A. No. 02/2019 for taking additional
            <lb />
            document on record contending that the petitioners are filing
            <lb />
            copy of design submitted long back in September, 2015 with title
            <lb />
            &quot;Design of the preferred alignment within the DTM Corridor
            <lb />
            including submission of the possible alternatives for the track
            <lb />
            alignments in connection with construction of new line between
            <lb />
            Jadgalpur-Kondagaon-Rowghat on South East Central Railway
            <lb />
            in the State of Chhattisgarh, India&quot; which also rules out the
            <lb />
            allegation of any manipulation with ulterior motives by the
            <lb />
            petitioners of their own. These documents will help in better
            <lb />
            analysis of the facts and proper and judicious adjudication of the
            <lb />
            matter in the dispute. Hence, it may kindly be taken on record.
            <lb />
            The said document is taken on record while finally deciding the
            <lb />
            case and this Court will deal with this aspect of the matter at the
            <lb />
            appropriate stage while passing of the order.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            55. Learned counsel for the petitioner would submit that the
            <lb />
            document would suggest that alignment done by him is required
            <lb />
            for proper movement and for proper construction of new line, as
            <lb />
            such, they have not committed any illegality in changing the
            <lb />
            alignment and this alignment has been changed without any
            <lb />
            ulterior motive grating benefit to any accused and in fact it has
            <lb />
            been done in the interest of Railway.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            56. Respondent No. 2/Union of India has also filed their return
            <lb />
            reiterating the same stand already taken by them in WPCR No.
            <lb />
            1031 of 2019 and other writ petitions, therefore, the same are
            <lb />
            not being repeated by this Court.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            57. Learned State counsel would submit that this is defence of the
            <lb />
            petitioners, which cannot be adjudicated by this Court while
            <lb />
            considering the case under Article 226 of the Constitution of
            <lb />
            India at this stage.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <head>
            WPCR No. 1037 of 2019
            <lb />
        </head>

        <p>
            58. The petitioner is a former Indian Administrative Service (IAS)
            <lb />
            Officer and at the relevant time, he was working as Additional
            <lb />
            Collector, Bastar at Jagdalpur and also appointed as Competent
            <lb />
            Authority by Central Government as per Section 2 (7A) of
            <lb />
            Railway Act, 1989 for the purpose of land acquisition
            <lb />
            proceedings in pursuance to which the petitioner had discharged
            <lb />
            the responsibility on behalf of respondent No. 3 in the State. It is
            <lb />
            pivotal to note that the petitioner has undertaken all the land
            <lb />
            acquisition proceedings in consonance of the Railway Act, 1989
            <lb />
            and passed the award dated 12.02.2018 for 21 villages for the
            <lb />
            said project.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            59. Learned counsel for the petitioner would submit that Bali
            <lb />
            Nagwanshi was awarded compensation of Rs. 70.62 Cr. for
            <lb />
            acquisition of land admeasuring 2.69 Hectare in Khasra No.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            123/1 &amp; 123/2 and Mrs. Neelima was awarded a compensation
            <lb />
            of Rs. 20.80 Cr. for acquisition of land admeasuring 1.040
            <lb />
            Hectare in Khasra No. 125/1 to 125/29, 125/31, 125/33 to
            <lb />
            125/37. It has been further contended that the aforesaid land
            <lb />
            was diverted land for commercial and housing purpose within
            <lb />
            the urban area due to which their land valuation was higher than
            <lb />
            other lands as per the State Government land valuation
            <lb />
            guidelines.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            60. He would further submit that notification dated 02.07.2014
            <lb />
            issued as per Section 29 of the Chhattisgarh Municipal
            <lb />
            Corporation Act, 1961 had covered the lands of both the
            <lb />
            aforesaid land owners under Ward No. 37 i.e. Lok Manya Tilak
            <lb />
            Ward, wherein the lands were on the main road and the
            <lb />
            Municipal Corporation, Jadgalpur had given colonizer
            <lb />
            registration license to both the land owners and their lands have
            <lb />
            duly been diverted for the purpose of developing a housing
            <lb />
            project over their respective acquired lands earlier.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            61. He would further submit that the petitioner has passed the award
            <lb />
            considering this aspect of the matter and the Collector without
            <lb />
            considering this aspect of the matter has recorded the perverse
            <lb />
            finding and submitted his report on 30.07.2019 on the basis of
            <lb />
            which, FIR No. 409/2019 has been registered against the
            <lb />
            petitioner on 04.08.2019 at Police Station-Jagdalpur, District-
            <lb />
            Bastar for committing offence punishable under Sections 109,
            <lb />
            120B, 406, 407, 408, 409, 420, 467, 468 &amp; 471 of IPC without
            <lb />
            conducting any preliminary investigation in violation of the
            <lb />
            judgment rendered by Hon&apos;ble the Supreme Court in Lalita
            <lb />
            Kumari Vs. Government of Uttar Pradesh &amp; others 4 .
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            62. He would further submit that the respondents and any other
            <lb />
            concerned body had not taken a single objection from the
            <lb />
            inception of the land acquisition proceedings till the passing of
            <lb />
            the award dated 12.02.2018 and even thereafter till the
            <lb />
            deposition of the compensation amount and disbursement of the
            <lb />
            same, as such the respondents are estopped from raising plea
            <lb />
            with regard to assessment of compensation by him as per
            <lb />
            Doctrine of Waiver and Estoppal.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            63. The State has filed their return on behalf of respondent No. 1,
            <lb />
            &amp; 4 reiterating the same stand already taken in WPCR No.
            <lb />
            of 2019 and other writ petitions and would submit that the
            <lb />
            Collector, Bastar at Jagdalpur has rightly conducted the enquiry
            <lb />
            and on the basis of enquiry report, the FIR has rightly been
            <lb />
            registered against the petitioner. He would further submit that no
            <lb />
            case is made out by the petitioner for interference of this Court,
            <lb />
            therefore, the instant writ petition may kindly be dismissed.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            64. Respondent No. 4/Union of India has also filed their return
            <lb />
            reiterating the same stand taken by them in WPCR No. 1031 of
            <lb />
            2019 and other writ petition, therefore, the same are not being
            <lb />
            repeating by this Court.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            65. I have heard learned counsel for the parties, perused the records
            <lb />
            of the Competent Authority/ Additional Collector as well as the
            <lb />
            Commissioner/ Arbitrator with utmost satisfaction.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            66. Before adverting to the submissions made by the learned
            <lb />
            counsel for the petitioners, respondents, it is expedient for this
            <lb />
            Court to extract the relevant provisions of the Railways Act and
            <lb />
            RPL Act, 2013, which are as under:-
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;2 (7A) of the Railway Act, 1989-&quot;competent
            <lb />
            authority&quot; means any person authorised by the
            <lb />
            Central Government, by notification, to perform the
            <lb />
            functions of the competent authority for such area
            <lb />
            as may be specified in the notification;
            <lb />
            20A of the Railway Act, 1989-Power to acquire
            <lb />
            land, etc. -(1) Where the Central Government is
            <lb />
            satisfied that for a public purpose any land is
            <lb />
            required for execution of a special railway project, it
            <lb />
            may, by notification, declare its intention to acquire
            <lb />
            such land.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (2) Every notification under sub-section (1), shall
            <lb />
            give a brief description of the land and of the
            <lb />
            special railway project for which the land is
            <lb />
            intended to be acquired.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (3) The State Government or the Union territory, as
            <lb />
            the case may be, shall for the purposes of this
            <lb />
            section, provide the details of the land records to
            <lb />
            the competent authority, whenever required.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (4) The competent authority shall cause the
            <lb />
            substance of the notification to be published in two
            <lb />
            local newspapers, one of which shall be in a
            <lb />
            vernacular language.
            <lb />
            20D Hearing of objections, etc. -
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (1) Any person interested in the land may, within a
            <lb />
            period of thirty days from the date of publication of
            <lb />
            the notification under sub-section (1) of section
            <lb />
            20A, object to the acquisition of land for the
            <lb />
            purpose mentioned in that sub-section.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (2) Every objection under sub-section (1), shall be
            <lb />
            made to the competent authority in writing, and
            <lb />
            shall set out the grounds thereof and the
            <lb />
            competent authority shall give the objector an
            <lb />
            opportunity of being heard, either in person or by a
            <lb />
            legal practitioner, and may, after hearing all such
            <lb />
            objections and after making such further enquiry, if
            <lb />
            any, as the competent authority thinks necessary,
            <lb />
            by order, either allow or disallow the objections.
            <lb />
            Explanation.-For the purposes of this sub-
            <lb />
            section, &quot;legal practitioner&quot; has the same meaning
            <lb />
            as in clause (i) of sub-section (1) of section 2 of the
            <lb />
            Advocates Act, 1961 (25 of 1961). (3) Any order
            <lb />
            made by the competent authority under sub-section
            <lb />
            (2) shall be final. ]
            <lb />
            20E Declaration of acquisition. -(1) Where no
            <lb />
            objection under sub-section (1) of section 20D has
            <lb />
            been made to the competent authority within the
            <lb />
            period specified therein or where the competent
            <lb />
            authority has disallowed the objections under sub-
            <lb />
            section (2) of that section, the competent authority
            <lb />
            shall, as soon as may be, submit a report
            <lb />
            accordingly to the Central Government and on
            <lb />
            receipt of such report, the Central Government
            <lb />
            shall declare, by notification, that the land should
            <lb />
            be acquired for the purpose mentioned in sub-
            <lb />
            section (1) of section 20A.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (2) On the publication of the declaration under sub-
            <lb />
            section (1), the land shall vest absolutely in the
            <lb />
            Central Government free from all encumbrances.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (3) Where in respect of any land, a notification has
            <lb />
            been published under sub-section (1) of section
            <lb />
            20A for its acquisition, but no declaration under
            <lb />
            sub-section (1) of this section has been published
            <lb />
            within a period of one year from the date of
            <lb />
            publication of that notification, the said notification
            <lb />
            shall cease to have any effect:
            <lb />
            Provided that in computing the said period of one
            <lb />
            year, the period during which any action or
            <lb />
            proceedings to be taken in pursuance of the
            <lb />
            notification issued under sub-section (1) of section
            <lb />
            20A is stayed by an order of a court shall be
            <lb />
            excluded.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (4) A declaration made by the Central Government
            <lb />
            under sub-section (1) shall not be called in
            <lb />
            question in any court or by any other authority.
            <lb />
            20F Determination of amount payable at
            <lb />
            compensation. -(1) Where any land is acquired
            <lb />
            under this Act, there shall be paid an amount which
            <lb />
            shall be determined by an order of the competent
            <lb />
            authority.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (2) The competent authority shall make an award
            <lb />
            under this section within a period of one year from
            <lb />
            the date of the publication of the declaration and if
            <lb />
            no award is made within that period, the entire
            <lb />
            proceedings for the acquisition of the land shall
            <lb />
            lapse:
            <lb />
            Provided that the competent authority may, after
            <lb />
            the expiry of the period of limitation, if he is
            <lb />
            satisfied that the delay has been caused due to
            <lb />
            unavoidable circumstances, and for the reasons to
            <lb />
            be recorded in writing, he may make the award
            <lb />
            within an extended period of six months:
            <lb />
            Provided further that where an award is made
            <lb />
            within the extended period, the entitled person
            <lb />
            shall, in the interest of justice, be paid an additional
            <lb />
            compensation for the delay in making of the award,
            <lb />
            every month for the period so extended, at the rate
            <lb />
            of not less than five per cent. of the value of the
            <lb />
            award, for each month of such delay.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (3) Where the right of user or any right in the nature
            <lb />
            of an easement on, any land is acquired under this
            <lb />
            Act, there shall be paid an amount to the owner
            <lb />
            and any other person whose right of enjoyment in
            <lb />
            that land has been affected in any manner
            <lb />
            whatsoever by reason of such acquisition, an
            <lb />
            amount calculated at ten per cent. of the amount
            <lb />
            determined under sub-section (1), for that land.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (4) Before proceeding to determine the amount
            <lb />
            under sub-section (1) or sub-section (3), as the
            <lb />
            case may be, the competent authority shall give a
            <lb />
            public notice published in two local newspapers,
            <lb />
            one of which shall be in a vernacular language
            <lb />
            inviting claims from all persons interested in the
            <lb />
            land to be acquired.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (5) Such notice shall state the particulars of the
            <lb />
            land and shall require all persons interested in such
            <lb />
            land to appear in person or by an agent or by a
            <lb />
            legal practitioner referred to in sub-section (2) of
            <lb />
            section 20D, before the competent authority, at a
            <lb />
            time and place and to state the nature of their
            <lb />
            respective interest in such land.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (6) If the amount determined by the competent
            <lb />
            authority under sub-section (1) or as the case may
            <lb />
            be sub-section (3) is not acceptable to either of the
            <lb />
            parties, the amount shall, on an application by
            <lb />
            either of the parties, be determined by the arbitrator
            <lb />
            to be appointed by the Central Government in such
            <lb />
            manner as may be prescribed.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (7) Subject to the provisions of this Act, the
            <lb />
            provisions of the Arbitration and Conciliation Act,
            <lb />
            1996 (26 of 1996) shall apply to every arbitration
            <lb />
            under this Act.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (8) The competent authority or the arbitrator while
            <lb />
            determining the amount of compensation under
            <lb />
            sub-section (1) or sub-section (6), as the case may
            <lb />
            be, shall take into consideration-
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (a) the market value of the land on the date of
            <lb />
            publication of the notification under section 20A;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (b) the damage, if any sustained by the person
            <lb />
            interested at the time of taking possession of the
            <lb />
            land, by reason of the severing of such land from
            <lb />
            other land;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (c) the damage, if any, sustained by the person
            <lb />
            interested at the time of taking possession of the
            <lb />
            land, by reason of the acquisition injuriously
            <lb />
            affecting his other immovable property in any
            <lb />
            manner, or his earnings;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (d) if, in consequences of the acquisition of the
            <lb />
            land, the person interested is compelled to change
            <lb />
            his residence or place of business, the reasonable
            <lb />
            expenses, if any, incidental to such change.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (9) In addition to the market-value of the land as
            <lb />
            above provided, the competent authority or the
            <lb />
            arbitrator, as the case may be, shall in every case
            <lb />
            award a sum of sixty per centum on such market-
            <lb />
            value, in consideration of the compulsory nature of
            <lb />
            the acquisition.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            20-I Power to take possession. -
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (1) Where any land has vested in the Central
            <lb />
            Government under sub-section (2) of section 20E,
            <lb />
            and the amount determined by the competent
            <lb />
            authority under section 20F with respect to such
            <lb />
            land has been deposited under sub-section (1) of
            <lb />
            section 20H with the competent authority by the
            <lb />
            Central Government, the competent authority may,
            <lb />
            by notice in writing, direct the owner as well as any
            <lb />
            other person who may be in possession of such
            <lb />
            land to surrender or deliver possession thereof to
            <lb />
            the competent authority or any person duly
            <lb />
            authorised by it in this behalf within a period of sixty
            <lb />
            days of the service of the notice.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (2) If any person refuses or fails to comply with any
            <lb />
            direction made under sub-section (1), the
            <lb />
            competent authority shall apply-
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (a) in case of any land situated in any area falling
            <lb />
            within the metropolitan area, to the Commissioner
            <lb />
            of Police;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (b) in case of any land situated in any area other
            <lb />
            than the area referred to in clause (a), to the
            <lb />
            Collector of a district, and such Commissioner or
            <lb />
            Collector, as the case may be, shall enforce the
            <lb />
            surrender of the land, to the competent authority or
            <lb />
            to the person duly authorised by it.
            <lb />
            Section 26 of the Act, 2013-Determination of
            <lb />
            market value of land by Collector.-(1) The
            <lb />
            Collector shall adopt the following criteria in
            <lb />
            assessing and determining the market value of the
            <lb />
            land, namely:-
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (a) the market value, if any, specified in the Indian
            <lb />
            Stamp Act, 1899 (2 of 1899) for the registration of
            <lb />
            sale deeds or agreements to sell, as the case may
            <lb />
            be, in the area, where the land is situated; or
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (b) the average sale price for similar type of land
            <lb />
            situated in the nearest village or nearest vicinity
            <lb />
            area; or
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (c) consented amount of compensation as agreed
            <lb />
            upon under sub-section (2) of section 2 in case of
            <lb />
            acquisition of lands for private companies or for
            <lb />
            public private partnership projects, whichever is
            <lb />
            higher: Provided that the date for determination of
            <lb />
            market value shall be the date on which the
            <lb />
            notification has been issued under section 11.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            Explanation 1.-The average sale price referred to
            <lb />
            in clause (b) shall be determined taking into
            <lb />
            account the sale deeds or the agreements to sell
            <lb />
            registered for similar type of area in the near village
            <lb />
            or near vicinity area during immediately preceding
            <lb />
            three years of the year in which such acquisition of
            <lb />
            land is proposed to be made.
            <lb />
            Explanation 2.-For determining the average sale
            <lb />
            price referred to in Explanation 1, one-half of the
            <lb />
            total number of sale deeds or the agreements to
            <lb />
            sell in which the highest sale price has been
            <lb />
            mentioned shall be taken into account.
            <lb />
            Explanation 3.-While determining the market
            <lb />
            value under this section and the average sale price
            <lb />
            referred to in Explanation 1 or Explanation 2, any
            <lb />
            price paid as compensation for land acquired under
            <lb />
            the provisions of this Act on an earlier occasion in
            <lb />
            the district shall not be taken into consideration.
            <lb />
            Explanation 4.-While determining the market
            <lb />
            value under this section and the average sale price
            <lb />
            referred to in Explanation 1 or Explanation 2, any
            <lb />
            price paid, which in the opinion of the Collector is
            <lb />
            not indicative of actual prevailing market value may
            <lb />
            be discounted for the purposes of calculating
            <lb />
            market value.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (2) The market value calculated as per sub-section
            <lb />
            (1) shall be multiplied by a factor to be specified in
            <lb />
            the First Schedule.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (3) Where the market value under sub-section (1)
            <lb />
            or sub-section (2) cannot be determined for the
            <lb />
            reason that-
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (a) the land is situated in such area where the
            <lb />
            transactions in land are restricted by or under any
            <lb />
            other law for the time being in force in that area; or
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (b) the registered sale deeds or agreements to sell
            <lb />
            as mentioned in clause (a) of sub-section (1) for
            <lb />
            similar land are not available for the immediately
            <lb />
            preceding three years; or
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (c) the market value has not been specified under
            <lb />
            the Indian Stamp Act, 1899 (2 of 1899) by the
            <lb />
            appropriate authority,
        </item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            the State Government concerned shall specify the
            <lb />
            floor price or minimum price per unit area of the
            <lb />
            said land based on the price calculated in the
            <lb />
            manner specified in sub-section (1) in respect of
            <lb />
            similar types of land situated in the immediate
            <lb />
            adjoining areas:
        </item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            Provided that in a case where the Requiring Body
            <lb />
            offers its shares to the owners of the lands (whose
            <lb />
            lands have been acquired) as a part compensation,
            <lb />
            for acquisition of land, such shares in no case shall
            <lb />
            exceed twenty-five per cent, of the value so
            <lb />
            calculated under sub-section (1) or sub-section (2)
            <lb />
            or sub-section (3) as the case may be:
        </item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            Provided further that the Requiring Body shall in no
            <lb />
            case compel any owner of the land (whose land
            <lb />
            has been acquired) to take its shares, the value of
            <lb />
            which is deductible in the value of the land
            <lb />
            calculated under sub-section (1): Provided also that
            <lb />
            the Collector shall, before initiation of any land
            <lb />
            acquisition proceedings in any area, take all
            <lb />
            necessary steps to revise and update the market
            <lb />
            value of the land on the basis of the prevalent
            <lb />
            market rate in that area:
        </item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            Provided also that the appropriate Government
            <lb />
            shall ensure that the market value determined for
            <lb />
            acquisition of any land or property of an
            <lb />
            educational
            <lb />
            institution
            <lb />
            established
            <lb />
            and
            <lb />
            administered by a religious or linguistic minority
            <lb />
            shall be such as would not restrict or abrogate the
            <lb />
            right to establish and administer educational
            <lb />
            institutions of their choice.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            67. In view of the above stated factual matrix, following points
            <lb />
            required to be determined by this Court are :-
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            (1) Whether the Collector is competent to conduct
            <lb />
            enquiry with regard to the project carried out by the
            <lb />
            Central Government.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (2) Whether the facts and grounds raised by the
            <lb />
            petitioners can be examined by this Court at this
            <lb />
            stage to quash the FIR.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (3) If the charge-sheet and the suspension order
            <lb />
            has already been revoked, then what is the effect
            <lb />
            with regard to criminal proceedings initiated against
            <lb />
            the petitioner in WPCR No. 1096 of 2019.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (4) Whether the Station House Officer was justified
            <lb />
            in issuing the notice dated 05.08.2019 for freezing
            <lb />
            the bank account.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            68. The Bastar Railway Private Limited has filed Special Leave
            <lb />
            Petition (Criminal) Nos. 2712, 2713-2714, 2715-2716 &amp; 2717-
            <lb />
            2718 of 2020, wherein Hon&apos;ble the Supreme Court has stayed
            <lb />
            the disbursement of the amount awarded by the Competent
            <lb />
            Authority and the interim order of &apos;no coercive steps&apos; passed by
            <lb />
            this Court on 08.06.2020 was made continued till disposal of the
            <lb />
            writ petitions pending before this Court and Hon&apos;ble the Supreme
            <lb />
            Court has directed this Court to dispose of the writ petition within
            <lb />
            two months from the date of passing of the order.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            69. In compliance of the order passed by Hon&apos;ble the Supreme
            <lb />
            Court, the matter was listed before this Court on 17.09.2021 and
            <lb />
            thereafter, the matter was listed on 07.10.2021 and the matter
            <lb />
            was heard in part. Again, it was listed before this Court on
            <lb />
            29.10.2021 and thereafter on 16.11.2021. On 16.11.2021, the
            <lb />
            matter was finally heard and orders were reserved.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <head>
            Point No. 1 &amp; 2
            <lb />
        </head>

        <p>
            70. From the above stated facts, it is apparent that the petitioner&apos;s
            <lb />
            main limb of argument for quashing of the enquiry report
            <lb />
            submitted by the Collector is that the Collector is not competent
            <lb />
            authority to conduct the above enquiry in the project run by the
            <lb />
            Central Government.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            71. To substantiate the submission, learned counsel for the
            <lb />
            petitioner would submit that the whole acquisition proceeding in
            <lb />
            respect of the land acquired by Special Railway Project is
            <lb />
            governed by Chapter 4A of the Railway Act, 1989, which is a
            <lb />
            complete code for land acquisition projects. He would submit
            <lb />
            that Section 20A provides for declaration of intention of the
            <lb />
            Central Government to acquire land, Section 20B provides for
            <lb />
            any person authorized by the Competent Authority and inspect
            <lb />
            and survey and make measurement of the land intent to acquire
            <lb />
            the land for Railway project, Section 20C provides for evaluation
            <lb />
            of damages caused the land, Section 20D provides for hearing
            <lb />
            and disposing of objections of the person interested in the land
            <lb />
            which is to be acquired, Section 20E provides for notification of
            <lb />
            the declaration that the land should be acquired where no
            <lb />
            objections to the acquisition are filed within stipulated time or
            <lb />
            objection is disallowed by the competent authority and the land
            <lb />
            will be vested upon such notification free of all encumbrances,
            <lb />
            Section 20F provides competent authority to deliver an award
            <lb />
            determining the compensation to be paid to each of the person
            <lb />
            whose land is to be acquired. Section 20G provides for
            <lb />
            methodology to be adopted by the competent authority for
            <lb />
            determination of the market value. He would submit that the
            <lb />
            scheme of Chapter 4A of the Railways Act does not leave any
            <lb />
            room for the State Government to play any role in the process of
            <lb />
            acquisition of land under the Railways Act. He would further
            <lb />
            submit that the Railways Act is clearly referable to Entry No. 22
            <lb />
            of list 1 read with entry No. 22 acquisition and requisition of
            <lb />
            property in list 7 of the Constitution. Thus, the State has no role
            <lb />
            to play, therefore, the proceeding initiated by the Collector is
            <lb />
            without any jurisdiction. He would refer to the judgment passed
            <lb />
            by Hon&apos;ble the Supreme Court in case of Dipak Babaria &amp;
            <lb />
            another Vs. State of Gujarat &amp; others 5 , wherein it has been
            <lb />
            held as under:-
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;72. In our view, considering the scheme of the act,
            <lb />
            the process of industrialization must take place in
            <lb />
            accordance therewith. As stated earlier if the law
            <lb />
            requires a particular thing should be done in a
            <lb />
            particular manner it must be done in that way and
            <lb />
            none other. The State cannot ignore the policy
            <lb />
            intent and the procedure contemplated by the
            <lb />
            statute. In the instant case, the State could have
            <lb />
            acquired the land, and then either by auction or by
            <lb />
            considering the merit of the proposal of respondent
            <lb />
            No.5 allotted it to respondent No.5. Assuming that
            <lb />
            the application of the Respondent No 5 was for a
            <lb />
            bona-fide purpose, the same had to be examined
            <lb />
            by the industrial commissioner, to begin with, and
            <lb />
            thereafter it should have gone to the collector. After
            <lb />
            the property vests in the Government, even if there
            <lb />
            were other bidders to the property, the collector
            <lb />
            could have considered the merits and the bona-
            <lb />
            fides of the application of Respondent No. 5, and
            <lb />
            nothing would have prevented him from following
            <lb />
            the course which is permissible under the law. It is
            <lb />
            not merely the end but the means which are of
            <lb />
            5
            <lb />
            equal importance, particularly if they are enshrined
            <lb />
            in the legislative scheme. The minimum that was
            <lb />
            required was an enquiry at the level of the
            <lb />
            Collector who is the statutory authority. Dictating
            <lb />
            him to act in a particular manner on the
            <lb />
            assumption by the Minister that it is in the interest
            <lb />
            of the industrial development would lead to a
            <lb />
            breach of the mandate of the statute framed by the
            <lb />
            legislature. The Ministers are not expected to act
            <lb />
            in this manner and therefore, this particular route
            <lb />
            through the corridors of the Ministry, contrary to the
            <lb />
            statute, cannot be approved. The present case is
            <lb />
            clearly one of dereliction of his duties by the
            <lb />
            Collector and dictation by the Minister, showing
            <lb />
            nothing but arrogance of power.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            72. To meet this submission, learned Senior counsel for respondent
            <lb />
            No. 6-Bastar Railway Pvt. Ltd. would submit that as per
            <lb />
            memorandum of understanding (MoU) between Government of
            <lb />
            Chhattisgarh, represented by Secretary Commerce and
            <lb />
            Industries, M/s NMDC Limited, a &apos;Navratna&apos; Public Sector
            <lb />
            Undertaking of Govt. of India under the administrative control of
            <lb />
            Ministry of Steel, Steel Authority of India Limited, a &apos;Maharatna&apos;
            <lb />
            Public Sector Undertaking of Govt. of India under the
            <lb />
            administrative control of Ministry of Steel &amp; IRCON International
            <lb />
            Limited, the cost of the project was to be shared by MoR (57%),
            <lb />
            NMDC (10%), SAIL (21%) &amp; Govt. of Chhattisgarh (12%).
            <lb />
            Clause 12 of the MoU provides that Government of Chhattisgarh
            <lb />
            shall provide the requisite statutory support wherever required to
            <lb />
            the JVC to ensure expeditious completion and commissioning of
            <lb />
            the project. From the above stated clause, it is quite vivid that
            <lb />
            the Government of Chhattisgarh has to conclude the process of
            <lb />
            land acquisition process and there is a report regarding
            <lb />
            malafide, arbitrariness and prima facie fraudulent practice have
            <lb />
            been adopted in the land acquisition process, the Collector being
            <lb />
            nominee of the State Government is competent enough to
            <lb />
            conduct enquiry and from the enquiry report dated 30.07.2019, it
            <lb />
            is clearly prima facie established that there is fraud and collusion
            <lb />
            of the revenue authority, which has exaggerated the quantum of
            <lb />
            compensation, therefore, the enquiry conducted on the direction
            <lb />
            of the Collector cannot be said to be without jurisdiction.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            73. Learned Senior counsel for Bastar Railway Pvt. Ltd. would
            <lb />
            submit that the Collector, Bastar has proposed the Additional
            <lb />
            Collector, Bastar to be appointed as Competent Authority/ Land
            <lb />
            Acquisition Officer for conducting the land acquisition
            <lb />
            proceedings, therefore, the Government of India has notified the
            <lb />
            Additional Collector, Bastar as Competent Authority. Since the
            <lb />
            subordinate officer of the Collector has been appointed as
            <lb />
            Competent Authority on the recommendation of the Collector,
            <lb />
            the Collector will always have an inherent supervisory role over
            <lb />
            the conduct, acts and omissions of its subordinate i.e. the
            <lb />
            Additional Collector.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            74. He would further submit that the provisions of Right to Fair
            <lb />
            Compensation and Transparency in Land Acquisition,
            <lb />
            Rehabilitation and Resettlement Act, 2013 (for short &quot;the Act,
            <lb />
            2013&quot;), the Collector has been authorized to determine the
            <lb />
            market value of the land to be acquired for determining the
            <lb />
            amount of compensation and awarding of solatium. It is also
            <lb />
            submitted that under the removal of Difficulties of Order, 2015
            <lb />
            issued under the provisions of the Act, 2013 relating to
            <lb />
            determination of compensation in accordance with the First,
            <lb />
            Second and Third Schedule have been made applicable to all
            <lb />
            the land acquisition cases specified in the Fourth Schedule of
            <lb />
            the Act, 2013 and the Fourth Schedule of the Act, 2013 includes
            <lb />
            the Railways Act, 1989.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            75. He would further submit that the Collector has the jurisdiction
            <lb />
            and power to enquire into the allegations of corruption, fraud in
            <lb />
            the present land acquisition because under the MoU the State
            <lb />
            Government is to facilitate the land acquisition. Moreover, the
            <lb />
            State has 10% stake in the Joint Venture Company (JVC)/BRPL,
            <lb />
            therefore, the role, power and jurisdiction of the Collector cannot
            <lb />
            be curtailed under any circumstances. Even otherwise, the
            <lb />
            Collector upon receiving the information from any sources
            <lb />
            whatsoever about discrepancies in the land acquisition
            <lb />
            proceedings, was well within his authority to request his
            <lb />
            subordinate officer to make a complaint to the police informing
            <lb />
            them about the commission of a cognizable offence for
            <lb />
            registration of FIR against the accused persons. Hon&apos;ble the
            <lb />
            Supreme Court in Lalita Kumari (Supra) at paragraph 1, 119,
            <lb />
            120, has held that the Police was under obligation to register FIR
            <lb />
            under Section 154 of Cr.P.C. Section 154 of the Cr.P.C. is
            <lb />
            reproduced below:-
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;if the information discloses commission of a
            <lb />
            cognizable offence without a preliminary enquiry,
            <lb />
            therefore, the contention made by learned Senior
            <lb />
            counsel for the petitioner that the Collector is not
            <lb />
            competent authority to conduct the enquiry in the
            <lb />
            matter of Railway project, cannot be accepted and
            <lb />
            is accordingly rejected.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            76. Hon&apos;ble the Supreme Court in Lalita Kumari (Supra) at
            <lb />
            paragraph 1, 119, 120, has held as under:-
        </p>
        <lb />
        <item>
            1. The important issue which arises for
            <lb />
            consideration in the referred matter is whether &quot;a
            <lb />
            police officer is bound to register a First
            <lb />
            Information Report (FIR) upon receiving any
            <lb />
            information relating to commission of a cognizable
            <lb />
            offence under Section 154 of the Code of Criminal
            <lb />
            Procedure, 1973 (in short &apos;the Code&apos;) or the police
            <lb />
            officer has the power to conduct a &quot;preliminary
            <lb />
            inquiry&quot; in order to test the veracity of such
            <lb />
            information before registering the same?&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            119. Therefore, in view of various counter claims
            <lb />
            regarding registration or non-registration, what is
            <lb />
            necessary is only that the information given to the
            <lb />
            police must disclose the commission of a
            <lb />
            cognizable offence. In such a situation, registration
            <lb />
            of an FIR is mandatory. However, if no cognizable
            <lb />
            offence is made out in the information given, then
            <lb />
            the FIR need not be registered immediately and
            <lb />
            perhaps the police can conduct a sort of
            <lb />
            preliminary verification or inquiry for the limited
            <lb />
            purpose of ascertaining as to whether a cognizable
            <lb />
            offence has been committed. But, if the information
            <lb />
            given clearly mentions the commission of a
            <lb />
            cognizable offence, there is no other option but to
            <lb />
            register an FIR forthwith. Other considerations are
            <lb />
            not relevant at the stage of registration of FIR,
            <lb />
            such as, whether the information is falsely given,
            <lb />
            whether the information is genuine, whether the
            <lb />
            information is credible etc. These are the issues
            <lb />
            that have to be verified during the investigation of
            <lb />
            the FIR. At the stage of registration of FIR, what is
            <lb />
            to be seen is merely whether the information given
            <lb />
            ex facie discloses the commission of a cognizable
            <lb />
            offence. If, after investigation, the information given
            <lb />
            is found to be false, there is always an option to
            <lb />
            prosecute the complainant for filing a false FIR.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            120. In view of the aforesaid discussion, we hold:
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            120.1. Registration of FIR is mandatory under
            <lb />
            Section 154 of the Code, if the information
            <lb />
            discloses commission of a cognizable offence and
            <lb />
            no preliminary inquiry is permissible in such a
            <lb />
            situation.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            120.2. If the information received does not disclose
            <lb />
            a cognizable offence but indicates the necessity for
            <lb />
            an inquiry, a preliminary inquiry may be conducted
            <lb />
            only to ascertain whether cognizable offence is
            <lb />
            disclosed or not.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            120.3. If the inquiry discloses the commission of a
            <lb />
            cognizable offence, the FIR must be registered. In
            <lb />
            cases where preliminary inquiry ends in closing the
            <lb />
            complaint, a copy of the entry of such closure must
            <lb />
            be supplied to the first informant forthwith and not
            <lb />
            later than one week. It must disclose reasons in
            <lb />
            brief for closing the complaint and not proceeding
            <lb />
            further.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            120.4. The police officer cannot avoid his duty of
            <lb />
            registering offence if cognizable offence is
            <lb />
            disclosed. Action must be taken against erring
            <lb />
            officers who do not register the FIR if information
            <lb />
            received by him discloses a cognizable offence.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            120.5. The scope of preliminary inquiry is not to
            <lb />
            verify the veracity or otherwise of the information
            <lb />
            received but only to ascertain whether the
            <lb />
            information reveals any cognizable offence.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            120.6. As to what type and in which cases
            <lb />
            preliminary inquiry is to be conducted will depend
            <lb />
            on the facts and circumstances of each case. The
            <lb />
            category of cases in which preliminary inquiry may
            <lb />
            be made are as under:
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (a)
            <lb />
            Matrimonial disputes/ family disputes
            <lb />
            (b)
            <lb />
            Commercial offences
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (c)
            <lb />
            Medical negligence cases
            <lb />
            (d)
            <lb />
            Corruption cases
            <lb />
            (e)
            <lb />
            Cases where there is abnormal
            <lb />
            delay/laches in initiating criminal prosecution, for
            <lb />
            example, over 3 months delay in reporting the
            <lb />
            matter without satisfactorily explaining the reasons
            <lb />
            for delay.
            <lb />
            The aforesaid are only illustrations and not
            <lb />
            exhaustive of all conditions which may warrant
            <lb />
            preliminary inquiry.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            120.7. While ensuring and protecting the rights of
            <lb />
            the accused and the complainant, a preliminary
            <lb />
            inquiry should be made time bound and in any
            <lb />
            case it should not exceed 7 days. The fact of such
            <lb />
            delay and the causes of it must be reflected in the
            <lb />
            General Diary entry.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            120.8. Since the General Diary/Station Diary/Daily
            <lb />
            Diary is the record of all information received in a
            <lb />
            police station, we direct that all information relating
            <lb />
            to cognizable offences, whether resulting in
            <lb />
            registration of FIR or leading to an inquiry, must be
            <lb />
            mandatorily and meticulously reflected in the said
            <lb />
            Diary and the decision to conduct a preliminary
            <lb />
            inquiry must also be reflected, as mentioned
            <lb />
            above.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            77. Learned Senior counsel BRPL would submit that the petitioner
            <lb />
            was awarded 25% extra compensation for his commercial land,
            <lb />
            which is in contravention of Rule 9 of guidelines for the year
            <lb />
            2017-18. It has been further contended that the competent
            <lb />
            authority while determining compensation, petitioners&apos; two
            <lb />
            different Khasra Nos. 123/1 &amp; 132/2 have been treated
            <lb />
            separately and exaggerated compensation has been awarded,
            <lb />
            which is also in contravention of guidelines for the year 2017-18.
            <lb />
            No other land of owners except Smt. Neelima Belsaria were
            <lb />
            calculated separately. Out of 7 Khasra in Village-Palli, 5 were
            <lb />
            considered in Municipal Corporation area while other 2 were
            <lb />
            considered as rural in adjoining Village-Ghatpadmur. The lands
            <lb />
            adjoining to the petitioners&apos; lands were also considered as rural
            <lb />
            and awarded compensation according to the guidelines for the
            <lb />
            year 2017-18 applying prescribed per hectare rate, as such,
            <lb />
            there are anomalies in calculating the compensation.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            78. Learned Senior counsel for BRPL would further submit that vide
            <lb />
            notification dated 12.07.2004, Gram Panchayats have been
            <lb />
            formed under Section 129(B)(1) of Chhattisgarh Panchayati Raj
            <lb />
            Adhiniyam, 1993 and as per Sr. No. 21 of the said notification,
            <lb />
            Village-Kumravand and the Village-Palli have been notified in
            <lb />
            the Gram Panchayat. Later on vide notification dated
            <lb />
            22.07.2014, the said Gram Panchayat Kumravand has been
            <lb />
            formed by including Village-Kumravand and Village-Palli. From
            <lb />
            the above mentioned notifications, it is apparent that the Village-
            <lb />
            Palli has always been a rural area and does not come within the
            <lb />
            limit of Municipal Corporation, Jagdalpur. However, with sheer
            <lb />
            motive to provide unlawful benefit to the beneficiaries of land
            <lb />
            acquisition especially the petitioner Bali Nagwanshi and Smt.
            <lb />
            Neelima, 5 Khatas of Village-Palli have been shown as urban
            <lb />
            area and huge compensation has been illegally paid to the
            <lb />
            beneficiaries. On the other hand, learned Senior counsel for the
            <lb />
            petitioner would submit that the land belonging to Bali
            <lb />
            Nagwanshi and Smt. Neelima Belsaria falls within the ambit of
            <lb />
            urban area, as such, there are disputed facts and various
            <lb />
            notifications have been preferred, which notifications are
            <lb />
            applicable and which are not applicable, is a disputed facts,
            <lb />
            which can be determined during trial, therefore, this Court
            <lb />
            cannot consider these notifications at this stage.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            79. Further contention of learned Senior counsel for the petitioner
            <lb />
            that the land belonging to the petitioners is situated at urban
            <lb />
            area and the compensation has rightly been awarded to them,
            <lb />
            therefore, no case of fraud is made out against the petitioners
            <lb />
            and the FIR is liable to be quashed by this Court. So far as the
            <lb />
            contention of learned counsel for the petitioners that the
            <lb />
            Collector, Bastar report is based upon no evidence or surmises,
            <lb />
            is his defence, which cannot be adjudicated by this Court at this
            <lb />
            stage. It is the defence of the petitioners, which this Court cannot
            <lb />
            examine at the time of examining the FIR.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            80. The thread bearing analysis can be done only by trial Court
            <lb />
            where the trial is going on, therefore, the defence taken by the
            <lb />
            petitioners cannot be examined by this Court while hearing writ
            <lb />
            petition under Article 226 of Constitution of India as held Hon&apos;ble
            <lb />
            the Supreme Court in Kaptan Singh vs State of U.P. &amp; others 6
            <lb />
            wherein it has been held as under:-
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;9.1 At the outset, it is required to be noted that in
            <lb />
            the present case the High Court in exercise of
            <lb />
            powers under Section 482 Cr.P.C. has quashed the
            <lb />
            criminal proceedings for the offences under
            <lb />
            Sections 147, 148, 149, 406, 329 and 386 of IPC. It
            <lb />
            is required to be noted that when the High Court in
            <lb />
            exercise of powers under Section 482 Cr.P.C.
            <lb />
            quashed the criminal proceedings, by the time the
            <lb />
            Investigating Officer after recording the statement
            <lb />
            of the witnesses, statement of the complainant and
            <lb />
            collecting the evidence from the incident place and
            <lb />
            after taking statement of the independent
            <lb />
            witnesses and even statement of the accused
            <lb />
            persons, has filed the charge-sheet before the
            <lb />
            Learned Magistrate for the offences under Sections
            <lb />
            147, 148, 149, 406, 329 and 386 of IPC and even
            <lb />
            the learned Magistrate also took the cognizance.
            <lb />
            From the impugned judgment and order passed by
            <lb />
            the High Court, it does not appear that the High
            <lb />
            Court took into consideration the material collected
            <lb />
            during the investigation/inquiry and even the
            <lb />
            statements recorded. If the petition under Section
            <lb />
            482 Cr.P.C. was at the stage of FIR in that case the
            <lb />
            allegations in the FIR/Complaint only are required
            <lb />
            to be considered and whether a cognizable offence
            <lb />
            is disclosed or not is required to be considered.
            <lb />
            However, thereafter when the statements are
            <lb />
            recorded, evidence is collected and the charge-
            <lb />
            sheet is filed after conclusion of the
            <lb />
            investigation/inquiry the matter stands on different
            <lb />
            footing and the Court is required to consider the
            <lb />
            material/evidence
            <lb />
            collected
            <lb />
            during
            <lb />
            the
            <lb />
            investigation. Even at this stage also, as observed
            <lb />
            and held by this Court in catena of decisions, the
            <lb />
            High Court is not required to go into the merits of
            <lb />
            the allegations and/or enter into the merits of the
            <lb />
            case as if the High Court is exercising the appellate
            <lb />
            jurisdiction and/or conducting the trial. As held by
            <lb />
            this Court in the case of Dineshbhai Chandubhai
            <lb />
            Patel (Supra) in order to examine as to whether
            <lb />
            factual contents of FIR disclose any cognizable
            <lb />
            offence or not, the High Court cannot act like the
            <lb />
            Investigating agency nor can exercise the powers
            <lb />
            like an Appellate Court. It is further observed and
            <lb />
            held that question is required to be examined
            <lb />
            keeping in view, the contents of FIR and prima
            <lb />
            facie material, if any, requiring no proof. At such
            <lb />
            stage, the High Court cannot appreciate evidence
            <lb />
            nor can it draw its own inferences from contents of
            <lb />
            FIR and material relied on. It is further observed it
            <lb />
            is more so, when the material relied on is disputed.
            <lb />
            It is further observed that in such a situation, it
            <lb />
            becomes the job of the Investigating Authority at
            <lb />
            such stage to probe and then of the Court to
            <lb />
            examine questions once the charge-sheet is filed
            <lb />
            along with such material as to how far and to what
            <lb />
            extent reliance can be placed on such material.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            9.2 In the case of Dhruvaram Murlidhar Sonar
            <lb />
            (Supra) after considering the decisions of this Court
            <lb />
            in Bhajan Lal (Supra), it is held by this Court that
            <lb />
            exercise of powers under Section 482 Cr.P.C. to
            <lb />
            quash the proceedings is an exception and not a
            <lb />
            rule. It is further observed that inherent jurisdiction
            <lb />
            under Section 482 Cr.P.C. though wide is to be
            <lb />
            exercised sparingly, carefully and with caution, only
            <lb />
            when such exercise is justified by tests specifically
            <lb />
            laid down in section itself. It is further observed that
            <lb />
            appreciation of evidence is not permissible at the
            <lb />
            stage of quashing of proceedings in exercise of
            <lb />
            powers under Section 482 Cr.P.C. Similar view has
            <lb />
            been expressed by this Court in the case of Arvind
            <lb />
            Khanna (Supra), Managipet (Supra) and in the
            <lb />
            case of XYZ (Supra), referred to hereinabove.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            9.3 Applying the law laid down by this Court in the
            <lb />
            aforesaid decisions to the facts of the case on
            <lb />
            hand, we are of the opinion that the High Court has
            <lb />
            exceeded its jurisdiction in quashing the criminal
            <lb />
            proceedings in exercise of powers under Section
            <lb />
            482 Cr.P.C.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            10. The High Court has failed to appreciate and
            <lb />
            consider the fact that there are very serious triable
            <lb />
            issues/allegations which are required to be gone
            <lb />
            into and considered at the time of trial. The High
            <lb />
            Court has lost sight of crucial aspects which have
            <lb />
            emerged during the course of the investigation.
            <lb />
            The High Court has failed to appreciate and
            <lb />
            consider the fact that the document i.e. a joint
            <lb />
            notarized affidavit of Mamta Gupta -Accused No.2
            <lb />
            and Munni Devi under which according to Accused
            <lb />
            no.2 -Ms. Mamta Gupta, Rs.25 lakhs was paid and
            <lb />
            the possession was transferred to her itself is
            <lb />
            seriously disputed. It is required to be noted that in
            <lb />
            the registered agreement to sell dated 27.10.2010,
            <lb />
            the sale consideration is stated to be Rs.25 lakhs
            <lb />
            and with no reference to payment of Rs.25 lakhs to
            <lb />
            Ms. Munni Devi and no reference to handing over
            <lb />
            the possession. However, in the joint notarized
            <lb />
            affidavit of the same date i.e., 27.10.2010 sale
            <lb />
            consideration is stated to be Rs.35 lakhs out of
            <lb />
            which Rs.25 lakhs is alleged to have been paid and
            <lb />
            there is a reference to transfer of possession to
            <lb />
            Accused No.2. Whether Rs.25 lakhs has been paid
            <lb />
            or not the accused have to establish during the
            <lb />
            trial, because the accused are relying upon the
            <lb />
            said document and payment of Rs.25 lakhs as
            <lb />
            mentioned in the joint notarized affidavit dated
            <lb />
            27.10.2010. It is also required to be considered that
            <lb />
            the first agreement to sell in which Rs.25 lakhs is
            <lb />
            stated to be sale consideration and there is
            <lb />
            reference to the payment of Rs.10 lakhs by
            <lb />
            cheques. It is a registered document. The aforesaid
            <lb />
            are all triable issues/allegations which are required
            <lb />
            to be considered at the time of trial. The High Court
            <lb />
            has failed to notice and/or consider the material
            <lb />
            collected during the investigation.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            81. Hon&apos;ble the Supreme Court in very recent judgment in case of
            <lb />
            State of Odisha Vs. Pratima Mohanti 7 , has held as under:-
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;9. While quashing the criminal proceedings the
            <lb />
            High Court has not at all adverted to itself the
            <lb />
            aforesaid aspects and has embarked upon an
            <lb />
            enquiry as to the reliability and genuineness of the
            <lb />
            evidence collected during the investigation as if the
            <lb />
            High Court was conducting the mini trial. Therefore,
            <lb />
            as such the impugned judgment and order passed
            <lb />
            by the High Court quashing the criminal
            <lb />
            proceedings against the respondents herein
            <lb />
            original accused Nos. 4, 5 and 3 -Smt. Pratima
            <lb />
            Mohanty, Shri Prakash Chandra Patra and Shri
            <lb />
            Rajendra Kumar Samal is unsustainable, both, in
            <lb />
            law and/or facts and the same deserves to be
            <lb />
            quashed and set aside.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            10. In view of the above and for the reasons stated
            <lb />
            above present appeals succeed. Impugned
            <lb />
            7
            <lb />
            common judgment and order passed by the High
            <lb />
            Court dated 04.09.2019 passed in Criminal
            <lb />
            Miscellaneous Application No.3177 of 2017 and
            <lb />
            Criminal Miscellaneous Application No.4804 of
            <lb />
            2015 are hereby quashed and set aside in so far as
            <lb />
            quashing the criminal proceedings against original
            <lb />
            Accused Nos.4, 5 &amp; 3 is concerned.
            <lb />
            Respondent Nos.4, 5 &amp; 3 to face trial along with
            <lb />
            other co-accused.
            <lb />
            Present Appeals are accordingly allowed.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            82. The allegations made in the FIR regarding fraud and collusion,
            <lb />
            are to be ascertained by the trial Court at the time of recording
            <lb />
            evidence, therefore, this Court cannot look into this aspect of the
            <lb />
            matter at this stage while hearing the petition for quashing the
            <lb />
            FIR registered against the petitioners.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            83. The contention of the petitioner is that no opportunity has been
            <lb />
            granted to them before conduction of enquiry by the team
            <lb />
            constituted by the Collector. This is a fact finding enquiry and the
            <lb />
            petitioner may get the full opportunity while cross-examining the
            <lb />
            witnesses or evidence adduced by the prosecution during trial of
            <lb />
            the case, therefore, the submission that the accused should
            <lb />
            have been granted opportunity of hearing while conducting
            <lb />
            enquiry is not a ground to quash the FIR. Accordingly, the same
            <lb />
            is rejected.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            84. During course of hearing, learned Senior counsel for the
            <lb />
            petitioner has himself relied upon the guidelines and tried to
            <lb />
            make out the case that the compensation has been granted on
            <lb />
            the basis of guidelines. Again, it has to be ascertained by the
            <lb />
            trial Court at the time of trial of the case whether the guidelines
            <lb />
            and the Map are rightly followed or not, therefore, this Court
            <lb />
            while prayer for quashing of the FIR cannot look into this aspect
            <lb />
            of the matter as this Court cannot conduct roving and moving
            <lb />
            enquiry to ascertain the facts whether the offence has been
            <lb />
            committed or not. This can be very well ascertained by the trial
            <lb />
            Court while conducting thread bearing appreciation of evidence,
            <lb />
            material collected and produced for the trial.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            85. The whole facts are moving around the facts that the lands
            <lb />
            belonging to the petitioner are within the urban area, which has
            <lb />
            to be ascertained after recording of the evidence, then only it
            <lb />
            can be find out whether the accused has committed any offence
            <lb />
            or not.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            86. From bare perusal of the FIR, it is evident that certain allegations
            <lb />
            have been levelled and the same has to be ascertained during
            <lb />
            trial, therefore, contention of learned counsel for the petitioner
            <lb />
            that compensation has been determined by the Competent
            <lb />
            Authoty is in accordance with law and no case of fraud as
            <lb />
            alleged in the FIR, is made out, can be ascertained by the trial
            <lb />
            court only, which cannot be looked into by this Court at this
            <lb />
            juncture.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            87. Learned counsel for the petitioners would submit that the
            <lb />
            competent authority has determined the market value of the land
            <lb />
            as per Section 26 of the Act, 2013. As per Section 26 of the Land
            <lb />
            Acquisition Act, 2013, certain procedures have to be followed for
            <lb />
            determination of market value by the Collector, which is as
            <lb />
            under:-
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;26. Determination of market value of land by
            <lb />
            Collector.&quot; -(1) The Collector shall adopt the
            <lb />
            following criteria in assessing and determining the
            <lb />
            market value of the land, namely:-
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (a) the minimum land value, if any, specified
            <lb />
            in the Indian Stamp Act, 1899 for the
            <lb />
            registration of saledeeds or agreements to
            <lb />
            sell, as the case may be, in the area, where
            <lb />
            the land is situated; or
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (b) the average sale price for similar type of
            <lb />
            land situated in the nearest village or nearest
            <lb />
            vicinity area; or
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (c) consented amount of compensation as
            <lb />
            agreed upon under sub-section (2) of section
            <lb />
            2 in case of acquisition of lands for private
            <lb />
            companies or for public private partnership
            <lb />
            projects, whichever is higher:
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            Provided that the date for determination of market
            <lb />
            value shall be the date on which the notification
            <lb />
            has been issued under section 11.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            Explanation 1-The average sale price referred to in
            <lb />
            clause (b) shall be determined taking into account
            <lb />
            the sale deeds or the agreements to sell registered
            <lb />
            for similar type of area in the near village or near
            <lb />
            vicinity area during immediately preceding three
            <lb />
            years of the year in which such acquisition of land
            <lb />
            is proposed to be made.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            Explanation 2-For determining the average sale
            <lb />
            price referred to in Explanation 1, one-half of the
            <lb />
            total number of sale deeds or the agreements to
            <lb />
            sell in which the highest sale price has been
            <lb />
            mentioned shall be taken into account.
        </item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            Explanation 3-While determining the market value
            <lb />
            under this section and the average sale price
            <lb />
            referred to in Explanation 1 or Explanation 2, any
            <lb />
            price paid as compensation for land acquired under
            <lb />
            the provisions of this Act on an earlier occasion in
            <lb />
            the district shall not be taken into consideration.
        </item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            Explanation 4-While determining the market value
            <lb />
            under this section and the average sale price
            <lb />
            referred to in Explanation 1 or Explanation 2, any
            <lb />
            price paid, which in the opinion of the Collector is
            <lb />
            not indicative of actual prevailing market value may
            <lb />
            be discounted for the purposes of calculating
            <lb />
            market value.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            88. Section 26 provides that how the market value has to be
            <lb />
            determined and whether such procedure has been followed or
            <lb />
            not, is again the question of facts, which can be determined by
            <lb />
            the trial Court while examining the allegations levelled against
            <lb />
            the petitioners in the FIR, as such, this contention of learned
            <lb />
            counsel for the petitioners as this juncture, cannot be looked into
            <lb />
            by this Court.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            89. The Competent Authority has simply applied the market value
            <lb />
            specified in the Indian Stamp Act, 1989 for registration of sale
            <lb />
            deed without adopting other modes of the determination of
            <lb />
            market value of land as there was dispute with regard to the fact
            <lb />
            whether Village-Palli falls within urban area or rural area, which
            <lb />
            shows that the Competent Authority has not discharged its
            <lb />
            official duties in determination of the market value of the land
            <lb />
            and prima facie caused huge financial loss to public exchequer.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            90. This Court has also called for the record of the land acquisition
            <lb />
            proceeding, which nowhere reflects how the Competent
            <lb />
            Authority has reached to a conclusion for grant of such huge
            <lb />
            amount of compensation to the land owners. The record would
            <lb />
            show that the Competent Authority has only referred to the
            <lb />
            guidelines for the year 2017-18, but nowhere mentioned that
            <lb />
            which provision of the guidelines has been considered and
            <lb />
            which part of the guidelines has been considered and the
            <lb />
            competent authority has not given any finding whether Village-
            <lb />
            Palli falls within urban area or rural area.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            91. The learned Senior counsel for the petitioner has referred to
            <lb />
            various notifications which are prior to the land acquisition
            <lb />
            proceedings, therefore, it is incumbent on the part of the
            <lb />
            competent authority to examine the notifications to give specific
            <lb />
            findings whether the land belongs to urban area or not. This
            <lb />
            shows prima facie case as alleged in the FIR, is made out.
            <lb />
            Though all the facts have to be determined while recording
            <lb />
            evidence examined before the trial court, therefore, this Court at
            <lb />
            this juncture, cannot consider its authenticity and correctness
            <lb />
            and the same can very well be examined by the trial Court at the
            <lb />
            time of recording of evidence.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            92. Further contention of learned counsel for the petitioner that the
            <lb />
            Collector&apos;s report himself be set aside as the same has been
            <lb />
            prepared in violation of principal of natural justice without giving
            <lb />
            opportunity to the accused persons, therefore, the same is liable
            <lb />
            to be quashed. He would refer to the judgment rendered by
            <lb />
            Hon&apos;ble the Supreme Court in State of Bihar Vs. Lal Krishna
            <lb />
            Advani &amp; others 8 , wherein it has been held at paragraph 6 as
            <lb />
            under:-
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;
            <lb />
            6. The High Court, while referring to a decision
            <lb />
            Reported in State of Jammu and Kashmir &amp; Ors.
            <lb />
            Vs. Bakshi Gulam Mohammad &amp; Anr. AIR 1967
            <lb />
            SC p. 122, observed that an authority who takes a
            <lb />
            decision, which may have civil consequences and
            <lb />
            affects right of a person, the principle of natural
            <lb />
            justice would at once come into play. Reputation
            <lb />
            of an individual is an important part of one&apos;s life.
            <lb />
        </item>
        <item>
            The High Court then quoted a passage from a
            <lb />
            decision of this Court reported in Smt.Kiran Bedi
            <lb />
            and Jinder Singh Vs. Committee of Inquiry &amp; Anr.
            <lb />
            [AIR 1989 SC 714], which passage (SCC p. 515,
            <lb />
            para 25) contains the observations from an
            <lb />
            American decision in D.F. Marion V. Minnie Davis,
            <lb />
            [55 American LR 171], reads as follows :
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            &quot;The right to enjoyment of a private reputation,
            <lb />
            unassailed by malicious slander is of ancient
            <lb />
            origin, and is necessary to human society. A good
            <lb />
            reputation is an element of personal security and
            <lb />
            is protected by the Constitution equally with the
            <lb />
            right to the enjoyment of life, liberty and property.&quot;
            <lb />
            Some decisions, to which our attention has been
            <lb />
            drawn by Shri Harish N.Salve, learned senior
            <lb />
            counsel appearing for the respondent no.1, may
            <lb />
            be referred. [1983 (1) SCC 124], Board of
            <lb />
            Trustees of the Port of Bombay Vs. Dilipkumar
            <lb />
            Raghavendranath Nadkarni &amp; Ors., wherein it was
            <lb />
            observed that right to reputation is a facet of right
            <lb />
            to life of a citizen under Article 21 of the
            <lb />
            Constitution. He has also referred to the
            <lb />
            International Covenant on Civil and Political
            <lb />
            Rights, 1965 (ICCPR), recognizing right to have
            <lb />
            opinions and the right of freedom of expression
            <lb />
            subject to the right of reputation of others. The
            <lb />
            Covenant provides :
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            &quot;1. Everyone shall have the right to hold opinions
            <lb />
            without interference.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            2. Everyone shall have the right to freedom of
            <lb />
            expression; this right shall include freedom to
            <lb />
            seek, receive and impart information and ideas of
            <lb />
            all kinds, regardless of frontiers, either orally, in
            <lb />
            writing or in print, in the form of art, or through any
            <lb />
            other media of his choice.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            3. The exercise of the rights provided for in
            <lb />
            paragraph 2 of this article carries with it special
            <lb />
            duties and responsibilities. It may therefore be
            <lb />
            subject to certain restrictions, but these shall only
            <lb />
            be such as are provided by law and are
            <lb />
            necessary;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (a) For respect of the rights or reputations of
            <lb />
            others;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (b) For the protection of national security or of
            <lb />
            public order (ordre public), or of public health or
            <lb />
            morals.&quot;
            <lb />
            It is thus amply clear that one is entitled to have
            <lb />
            and preserve, one&apos;s reputation and one also has a
            <lb />
            right to protect it. In case any authority, in
            <lb />
            discharge of its duties fastened upon it under the
            <lb />
            law, traverses into the realm of personal
            <lb />
            reputation adversely affecting him, must provide a
            <lb />
            chance to him to have his say in the matter. In
            <lb />
            such circumstances right of an individual to have
            <lb />
            the safeguard of principles of natural justice
            <lb />
            before being adversely commented upon by a
            <lb />
            Commission of Inquiry is statutorily recognised
            <lb />
            and violation of the same will have to bear the
            <lb />
            scrutiny of judicial review. A reference may be
            <lb />
            made to [1984] A.C. 808, Peter Thomas Mahon
            <lb />
            Vs Air New Zealand Ltd.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            93. Learned counsel for the Bastar Railway Pvt. Ltd. and State
            <lb />
            would submit that report is subjected to cross-examination
            <lb />
            before the trial Court wherein, the authenticity and correctness of
            <lb />
            the report can be examined, as such, it is not required for the
            <lb />
            Collector to give an opportunity of hearing to the petitioner. From
            <lb />
            the entire facts, material placed before this Court, this Court is of
            <lb />
            the view that the allegation of fraud has been levelled against
            <lb />
            the petitioners and criminal law has set in motion by registration
            <lb />
            of FIR and the petitioners have ample opportunities during the
            <lb />
            trial to rebut the correctness and authenticity of the report
            <lb />
            prepared by the Collector, therefore, the submission that the
            <lb />
            enquiry report is liable to be quashed on the count of non-
            <lb />
            compliance of principle of natural justice, the same is liable to be
            <lb />
            rejected by this Court at this juncture. It is pertinent to mention
            <lb />
            here that the petitioners can very well cross-examine author of
            <lb />
            the report and the materials which have been taken into
            <lb />
            consideration while preparing the report, therefore, the report
            <lb />
            cannot be quashed by this Court at this juncture. So far as
            <lb />
            judgment cited by learned Senior counsel is not applicable to the
            <lb />
            present facts and circumstances of the case.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            94. The learned Senior counsel for the petitioner would submit that
            <lb />
            the Collector has no power to direct registration of an FIR after
            <lb />
            conducting an enquiry in area where he has no administrative
            <lb />
            jurisdiction and has referred to the judgment rendered by
            <lb />
            Hon&apos;ble the Supreme Court in Naman Singh alias Naman
            <lb />
            Pratap Singh &amp; another Vs. State of Uttar Pradesh &amp; others 9 ,
            <lb />
            wherein it has been held as under:-
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;7. It is therefore apparent that in the scheme of the
            <lb />
            Code, an Executive Magistrate has no role to play
            <lb />
            in directing the police to register an F.I.R. on basis
            <lb />
            of a private complaint lodged before him. If a
            <lb />
            complaint is lodged before the Executive
            <lb />
            Magistrate regarding an issue over which he has
            <lb />
            administrative jurisdiction, and the Magistrate
            <lb />
            proceeds to hold an administrative inquiry, it may
            <lb />
            be possible for him to lodge an F.I.R. himself in the
            <lb />
            matter. In such a case, entirely different
            <lb />
            considerations would arise. A reading of the F.I.R.
            <lb />
            reveals that the police has registered the F.I.R. on
            <lb />
            directions of the Sub-Divisional Magistrate which
            <lb />
            was clearly impermissible in the law. The Sub-
            <lb />
            Divisional Magistrate does not exercise powers
            <lb />
            under Section 156 (3) of the Code. The very
            <lb />
            institution of the F.I.R. in the manner done is
            <lb />
            contrary to the law and without jurisdiction.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            95. Since this Court in foregoing paragraph has already recorded
            <lb />
            finding that the Government of Chhattisgarh is at stake in this
            <lb />
            project though carried out by a Joint Venture Company,
            <lb />
            therefore, Collector being the head of District Administration has
            <lb />
            jurisdiction and power for directing the Police to register the FIR.
            <lb />
            The judgment referred to by learned Senior counsel for the
            <lb />
            petitioner is distinguishable on the facts of the present case.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            96. From the above discussion and considering the law on the
            <lb />
            subject, it is held that the petitioners have raised various defence
            <lb />
            for quashing of the FIR, which has been registered on the basis
            <lb />
            of the report submitted by the Collector on 30.07.2019.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            97. In view of the above, Point No. 1 is decided against the
            <lb />
            petitioner that the Collector is Competent to conduct the enquiry
            <lb />
            with regard to the project carried out by the Central Government
            <lb />
            and Point No. 2 is also decided against the petitioners that the
            <lb />
            facts and grounds raised by them cannot be examined by this
            <lb />
            Court at this stage to quash the FIR.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <head>
            Point No. 3
            <lb />
        </head>

        <p>
            98. Learned counsel for the petitioner in WPCR No. 1096 of 2019
            <lb />
            would submit that since charge-sheet and subsequent
            <lb />
            department enquiry has been dropped, therefore, the criminal
            <lb />
            proceedings, registration of FIR on the set of allegation is liable
            <lb />
            to be quashed by this Court. The submissions made by learned
            <lb />
            counsel for the petitioners cannot be considered as in the
            <lb />
            departmental proceedings whether the material which have been
            <lb />
            collected during the investigation have been brought to the
            <lb />
            notice of the disciplinary authority are not clear and this Court
            <lb />
            cannot lost sight of the fact that the petitioner has informed the
            <lb />
            Competent Authority with regard to the market value of the land
            <lb />
            situated at Ward No. 37, Lok Manya Tilak Ward and this ward is
            <lb />
            situated within the Municipal limit whereas, the whole dispute
            <lb />
            moves around with regard to location of the ward whether the
            <lb />
            land situated at Palli Naka falls within urban area or rural area,
            <lb />
            therefore, it is incumbent on the part of the petitioner to give the
            <lb />
            correct position. The fact whether the petitioner has given
            <lb />
            correct position or not with regard to the land is matter of the
            <lb />
            enquiry and investigation, therefore, the FIR at this stage cannot
            <lb />
            be quashed by this Court.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            99. Hon&apos;ble the Supreme Court in State Through SPE &amp; CBI,
            <lb />
            Andhra Pradesh Vs. M. Krishna Mohan &amp; another 10 , has
            <lb />
            examined similar issue raised by the petitioner if since
            <lb />
            departmental enquiry has been closed, the criminal proceedings
            <lb />
            cannot be continued or not and has held as under:-
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;31. Furthermore, the enquiry report has not been
            <lb />
            brought on record. The factum of exoneration of
            <lb />
            respondent No.2 in the departmental proceedings
            <lb />
            was raised by way of defence. It was, therefore,
            <lb />
            obligatory on his part to bring on record all the
            <lb />
            relevant documents, namely, the charge-sheet, the
            <lb />
            other materials brought on record by the
            <lb />
            department and the findings of the Enquiry Officer.
            <lb />
            If the statement of the Investigating Officer (PW-
            <lb />
            23) is to be accepted and there is absolutely no
            <lb />
            reason as to why it should not be; there was no
            <lb />
            occasion for the enquiry officer to have the benefit
            <lb />
            of the depositions of the purported loanees,
            <lb />
            namely, PW-21 and PW-22, the opinion of the
            <lb />
            fingerprint expert and other material brought on
            <lb />
            record by the prosecution which clearly
            <lb />
            established the involvement of the respondents
            <lb />
            herein.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            32. Mr. Nageshwar Rao relied upon a decision of
            <lb />
            this Court in P.S. Rajya v. State of Bihar [(1996) 9
            <lb />
            SCC 1]. The fact situation obtaining therein was
            <lb />
            absolutely different. In that case, in the vigilance
            <lb />
            report, the delinquent officer was shown to be
            <lb />
            innocent. It was at that juncture, an application for
            <lb />
            quashing of the proceedings was filed before the
            <lb />
            High Court under Section 482 of the Code of
            <lb />
            Criminal Procedure which was allowed relying on
            <lb />
            State of Haryana v. Bhajan Lal [1992 Supp.(1)
            <lb />
            SCC 335], holding :
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            &quot;23. Even though all these facts including
            <lb />
            the Report of the Central Vigilance
            <lb />
            Commission were brought to the notice of
            <lb />
            the High Court, unfortunately, the High
            <lb />
            Court took a view that the issues raised had
            <lb />
            to be gone into in the final proceedings and
            <lb />
            the Report of the Central Vigilance
            <lb />
            Commission, exonerating the appellant of
            <lb />
            the
            <lb />
            same
            <lb />
            charge
            <lb />
            in
            <lb />
            departmental
            <lb />
            proceedings would not conclude the
            <lb />
            criminal case against the appellant. We
            <lb />
            have already held that for the reasons
            <lb />
            given, on the peculiar facts of this case, the
            <lb />
            criminal proceedings initiated against the
            <lb />
            appellant cannot be pursued.&quot; (Underlining
            <lb />
            is ours for emphasis)
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            33. The said decision was, therefore, rendered on
            <lb />
            the facts obtaining therein and cannot be said to
            <lb />
            be an authority for the proposition that exoneration
            <lb />
            in departmental proceeding ipso facto would lead
            <lb />
            to a judgment of acquittal in a criminal trial.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            34. In Superintendent of Police (CBI) v. Deepak
            <lb />
            Chowdhary &amp; Ors. [(1995) 6 SCC 225], this Court
            <lb />
            while considering a matter of sanction, vis-a-vis,
            <lb />
            exoneration in a departmental proceedings, held :
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            &quot;5. We find force in the contention. The
            <lb />
            grant of sanction is only an administrative
            <lb />
            function, though it is true that the accused
            <lb />
            may be saddled with the liability to be
            <lb />
            prosecuted in a court of law. What is
            <lb />
            material at that time is that the necessary
            <lb />
            facts
            <lb />
            collected
            <lb />
            during
            <lb />
            investigation
            <lb />
            constituting the offence have to be placed
            <lb />
            before the sanctioning authority and it has
            <lb />
            to consider the material. Prima facie, the
            <lb />
            authority is required to reach the
            <lb />
            satisfaction that the relevant facts would
            <lb />
            constitute the offence and then either grant
            <lb />
            or refuse to grant sanction. The grant of
            <lb />
            sanction, therefore, being administrative act
            <lb />
            the need to provide an opportunity of
            <lb />
            hearing to the accused before according
            <lb />
            sanction does not arise. The High Court,
            <lb />
            therefore, was clearly in error in holding that
            <lb />
            the order of sanction is vitiated by violation
            <lb />
            of the principles of natural justice.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            35. In a case of this nature where departmental
            <lb />
            proceeding was initiated only as against
            <lb />
            respondent No.2, the enquiry officer did not have
            <lb />
            the benefit to consider all the materials which
            <lb />
            could be brought on record by the Department in
            <lb />
            the light of the investigation made by a specialized
            <lb />
            investigating agency, the evidence of experts and
            <lb />
            deposition of witnesses to show that forgery of
            <lb />
            document has been committed by forging thumb
            <lb />
            impression and handwriting, we are of the opinion
            <lb />
            that exoneration of respondent No.2 in the
            <lb />
            departmental proceedings cannot lead to the
            <lb />
            conclusion that he was not guilty of commission of
            <lb />
            the offences wherefor he was charged.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            100. From the above stated legal position and considering the factual
            <lb />
            matrix of the case, this Court is of the view that even though the
            <lb />
            departmental enquiry has been closed, the FIR cannot be closed
            <lb />
            on this count alone, as such, Point No. 3 decided against the
            <lb />
            petitioner.
        </p>
        <lb />
        <head>Point No. 4</head>
        <lb />
        <p>
            101. The learned counsel for the petitioner in WPCR No. 979 of 2019
            <lb />
            would submit that the police officer cannot seize the bank
            <lb />
            account exercising its power under Section 102 of the Cr.P.C.
            <lb />
            and has referred the judgment rendered by Hon&apos;ble the Supreme
            <lb />
            Court in Teesta Atul Setalvad (Supra). The judgment cited by
            <lb />
            the learned counsel for the petitioner itself decided that the bank
            <lb />
            account is a property within the ambit of Section 102 of the
            <lb />
            Cr.P.C. and the police officer can very well seize the bank
            <lb />
            account if the bank account found to be suspicion of commission
            <lb />
            of any offence then a police officer can very well seize the bank
            <lb />
            account. In the case on hand, the amount of compensation
            <lb />
            which according to the prosecution, has been illegally and
            <lb />
            exorbitant amount has been awarded by committing fraud and
            <lb />
            this amount is kept in the bank account of the petitioner which
            <lb />
            has been mentioned in the present writ petition. Hon&apos;ble the
            <lb />
            Supreme Court in Teesta Atul Setalvad (Supra) has held as
            <lb />
            under:-
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;17. The sweep and applicability of Section 102 of
            <lb />
            the Code is no more res integra. That question has
            <lb />
            been directly considered and answered in the case
            <lb />
            of State of Maharashtra v. Tapas D. Neogy [(1997)
            <lb />
            7 SCC 685]. The Court examined the question
            <lb />
            whether the police officer investigating any offence
            <lb />
            can issue prohibitory orders in respect of bank
            <lb />
            accounts in exercise of power under Section 102
            <lb />
            of the Code. The High Court, in that case, after
            <lb />
            analysing the provisions of Section 102 of the
            <lb />
            Code had opined that bank account of the accused
            <lb />
            or of any relation of the accused cannot be held to
            <lb />
            be 4 (1999) 7 SCC 685 &quot;property&quot; within the
            <lb />
            meaning of Section 102 of the Code. Therefore,
            <lb />
            the Investigating Officer will have no power to
            <lb />
            seize bank accounts or to issue any prohibitory
            <lb />
            order prohibiting the operation of the bank
            <lb />
            account. This Court noted that there were
            <lb />
            conflicting decisions of different High Courts on
            <lb />
            this aspect and as the question was seminal, it
            <lb />
            chose to answer the same. In para 6, this Court
            <lb />
            noted thus: (SCC p. 691)
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            &quot;6. A plain reading of sub-section (1) of
            <lb />
            Section 102 indicates that the Police Officer
            <lb />
            has the power to seize any property which
            <lb />
            may be found under circumstances creating
            <lb />
            suspicion of the commission of any offence.
            <lb />
            The legislature having used the expression
            <lb />
            &quot;any property&quot; and &quot;any offence&quot; have made
            <lb />
            the applicability of the provisions wide
            <lb />
            enough to cover offences created under any
            <lb />
            Act. But the two preconditions for
            <lb />
            applicability of Section 102(1) are that it
            <lb />
            must be &quot;property and secondly, in respect
            <lb />
            &quot;
            <lb />
            of the said property there must have been
            <lb />
            suspicion of commission of any offence. In
            <lb />
            this view of the matter the two further
            <lb />
            questions that arise for consideration are
            <lb />
            whether the bank account of an accused or
            <lb />
            of his relation can be said to be &quot;property&quot;
            <lb />
            within the meaning of sub-section (1) of
            <lb />
            Section 102 of the Cr.P.C. and secondly,
            <lb />
            whether circumstances exist, creating
            <lb />
            suspicion of commission of any offence in
            <lb />
            relation to the same.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            18. After analysing the decisions of different High
            <lb />
            Courts, this Court in paragraph 12, expounded the
            <lb />
            legal position thus:
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            &quot;12. Having considered the divergent views
            <lb />
            taken by different High Courts with regard to
            <lb />
            the power of seizure under Section 102 of
            <lb />
            the Code of Criminal Procedure, and
            <lb />
            whether the bank account can be held to be
            <lb />
            &quot;property within the meaning of the said
            <lb />
            &quot;
            <lb />
            Section 102(1), we see no justification to
            <lb />
            give any narrow interpretation to the
            <lb />
            provisions of the Criminal Procedure Code.
            <lb />
            It is well known that corruption in public
            <lb />
            offices has become so rampant that it has
            <lb />
            become difficult to cope up with the same.
            <lb />
            Then again the time consumed by the
            <lb />
            Courts in concluding the trials is another
            <lb />
            factor which should be borne in mind in
            <lb />
            interpreting the provisions of Section 102 of
            <lb />
            the Criminal Procedure Code and the
            <lb />
            underlying
            <lb />
            object
            <lb />
            engrafted
            <lb />
            therein,
            <lb />
            inasmuch as if there can be no order of
            <lb />
            seizure of the bank account of the accused
            <lb />
            then the entire money deposited in a bank
            <lb />
            which is ultimately held in the trial to be the
            <lb />
            outcome of the illegal gratification, could be
            <lb />
            withdrawn by the accused and the Courts
            <lb />
            would be powerless to get the said money
            <lb />
            which has any direct link with the
            <lb />
            commission of the offence committed by the
            <lb />
            accused as a public officer. We are,
            <lb />
            therefore, persuaded to take the view that
            <lb />
            the bank account of the accused or any of
            <lb />
            his relations is &quot;property&quot; within the meaning
            <lb />
            of Section 102 of the Criminal Procedure
            <lb />
            Code and a police officer in course of
            <lb />
            investigation can seize or prohibit the
            <lb />
            operation of the said account if such assets
            <lb />
            have direct links with the commission of the
            <lb />
            offence for which the police officer is
            <lb />
            investigating into……….. In the aforesaid
            <lb />
            premises, we have no hesitation to come to
            <lb />
            the conclusion that the High Court of
            <lb />
            Bombay committed error in holding that the
            <lb />
            police officer could not have seized the bank
            <lb />
            account or could not have issued any
            <lb />
            direction to the bank officer, prohibiting the
            <lb />
            account of the accused from being operated
            <lb />
            upon.&quot;
            <lb />
            After this decision, there is no room to
            <lb />
            countenance the challenge to the action of seizure
            <lb />
            of bank account of any person which may be found
            <lb />
            under circumstances creating suspicion of the
            <lb />
            commission of any offence.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            102. From the above stated facts and circumstances of the case, it is
            <lb />
            crystal clear that in such circumstances, the police officer can
            <lb />
            very well seize the bank account which is a property as per
            <lb />
            Section 102 of the Cr.P.C. Thus, the Point No. 4 decides
            <lb />
            against the petitioner.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            103. This defence cannot be considered by this Court while quashing
            <lb />
            of the FIR, therefore, the present WPCR No. 674 of 2019, 979
            <lb />
            of 2019, 1037 of 2019, 751 of 2019, 828 of 2019, 1031 of 2019
            <lb />
            &amp; 1096 of 2019 are liable to be and are hereby disposed of with
            <lb />
            direction mentioned in subsequent paragraph of this order.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <head>
            WPC No. 3355 of 2019
            <lb />
        </head>

        <p>
            104. The petitioner/ Bastar Railway Private Limited (BRPL) has filed
            <lb />
            the present Writ Petition (C) assailing the award dated
            <lb />
            12.02.2018 (Annexure P/1) passed by the Competent Authority/
            <lb />
            Additional Collector, Bastar and also prayed for issuance of
            <lb />
            direction for seizure of the accounts of the beneficiaries
            <lb />
            respondents No. 6 to 10 as they have been illegally paid excess
            <lb />
            compensation and also prayed for issuance of direction for
            <lb />
            recovery of the excess amount paid from respondents No. 6 to
            <lb />
            10 as well as from erring officers in accordance with law. During
            <lb />
            pendency of the writ petition the application for amendment in
            <lb />
            the prayer clause was made by which the petitioner has prayed
            <lb />
            for setting aside the award dated 11.07.2019 passed by the
            <lb />
            Commissioner (Annexure P/24), the same amendment was
            <lb />
            allowed.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            105. The facts in brief as projected by the petitioner are that the
            <lb />
            petitioner is a Joint Venture Company (JVC) by name and style
            <lb />
            of Bastar Railway Pvt. Ltd. (BRPL) which was brought in
            <lb />
            existence vide MoU dated 09.05.2015 between NMDC, Sail,
            <lb />
            IRCON and Government of Chhattisgarh as per the provisions of
            <lb />
            Companies Act, 2013. The company was incorporated for
            <lb />
            construction of 140 Km. Rowghat-Jagdalpur Broad Gauge
            <lb />
            Single Railway Line as a special railway project vide Gazette
            <lb />
            notification dated 04.04.2016 with an estimated cost of the
            <lb />
            project to the tune of Rs. 2538.3 Crores. For execution of the
            <lb />
            project 863 Hectare of land was to be acquired and as per the
            <lb />
            MoU the acquisition work was to be carried out by the
            <lb />
            Chhattisgarh Government along with IRCON. For acquisition of
            <lb />
            the said land Gazette notification was issued on 20.01.2017 by
            <lb />
            the Ministry of Railways. Subsequently, the Competent Authority,
            <lb />
            Bastar District issued a notification under 20A of the Railway Act
            <lb />
            on 21.08.2017 and also called for objection if any required to be
            <lb />
            raised by the land oustees within 30 days under Section 20D of
            <lb />
            the Railways Act. Thereafter, on 12.02.2018, the Additional
            <lb />
            Collector, District-Bastar passed compensation to the tune of
            <lb />
            Rs. 188.83 Crores for the land oustees.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            106. The other petitioner namely Smt. Neelima Belsaria has
            <lb />
            submitted her application under Section 20F of the Railway Act
            <lb />
            before the Commissioner, Bastar for enhancement of
            <lb />
            compensation. The learned Commissioner vide its order dated
            <lb />
            11.07.2019 has passed the award and thereafter vide its order
            <lb />
            dated 02.08.2019 has stayed the effect and operation of the
            <lb />
            award and thereafter called the report from the Collector, Bastar.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            107. Learned Senior Counsel for the petitioner would submit that in
            <lb />
            total there were seven land holders in village Palli, out of which
            <lb />
            two have been paid compensation based on rural rates whereas
            <lb />
            five land holders have been paid compensation on urban rates
            <lb />
            i.e. respondents No. 6 to 10, as such, Rs. 86 crores have been
            <lb />
            wrongly transferred in the accounts of private respondents. The
            <lb />
            petitioner has also mentioned the compensation as paid to the
            <lb />
            seven account holders of Palli village in tabulation form as
            <lb />
            below:-
            <lb />
        </p>

        <table>
            S
            <lb />
            N
            <lb />
            Name of the land
            <lb />
            holder
            <lb />
            Area in
            <lb />
            Hec.
            <lb />
            Compensation
            <lb />
            paid
            <lb />
            Compensation
            <lb />
            payable
            <lb />
            Difference
            <lb />
            1 Bali Nagwanshi
            <lb />
            2.69
            <lb />
            70,62,28,954
            <lb />
            7,79,72,110 62,82,56,844
            <lb />
            2 Nilima w/o T.V. Ravi
            <lb />
            1.04
            <lb />
            25,19,76,110
            <lb />
            4,38,93,116 20,80,82,994
            <lb />
            3 Pakli w/o Late
            <lb />
            Maniram
            <lb />
            0.12
            <lb />
            2,28,91,076
            <lb />
            27,43,978 2,01,47,098
            <lb />
            4 Nitya Gopal
            <lb />
            0.249
            <lb />
            16,89,624
            <lb />
            16,40,412
            <lb />
            49,212
            <lb />
            5 Seema Rathi
            <lb />
            0.055
            <lb />
            9,33,026
            <lb />
            13,91,776
            <lb />
            -4,58,750
            <lb />
            6 Omprakash Ukey
            <lb />
            0.01
            <lb />
            23,27,800
            <lb />
            14,45,500
            <lb />
            8,82,300
            <lb />
            7 Suresh Kashyap
            <lb />
            0.02
            <lb />
            46,55,600
            <lb />
            28,91,000
            <lb />
            17,64,600
            <lb />
        </table>

        <p>
            108. The said illegality is reflected in the newspaper report dated
            <lb />
            19.07.2019 and thereafter on the basis of that report the
            <lb />
            Collector, Bastar constituted committee who has enquired the
            <lb />
            matter and submitted its report on 30.07.2019. On the basis of
            <lb />
            that report FIR bearing Crime No. 408/2019 has been registered
            <lb />
            and the matter is pending consideration before the police
            <lb />
            authorities. In the meantime, respondents No. 6 to 10 have filed
            <lb />
            Writ Petitions (criminal) assailing the submission of report by the
            <lb />
            collector and subsequent registration of the FIR before this
            <lb />
            Court. Learned Senior Counsel for the petitioner would further
            <lb />
            submit that in compliance of the award dated 12.02.2018 the
            <lb />
            petitioner has deposited the amount before the concerning
            <lb />
            authority to avoid their liability to pay further interest on the huge
            <lb />
            amount. The Collector in its report has given findings with regard
            <lb />
            to involvement of each of the government officers and thereafter
            <lb />
            in his report has prima facie held that the government officers
            <lb />
            along with other private respondents land oustees have
            <lb />
            committed offence of fraud and cheating, as such, directed for
            <lb />
            registration of offence and in turn the police have registered
            <lb />
            offence under Sections 109, 120-B, 420, 467, 468, 471, 406,
            <lb />
            407, 408 and 409 IPC. He would further submit that since the
            <lb />
            award passed by the competent authority has been issued with
            <lb />
            malafide and arbitrariness, therefore, it is liable to be quashed by
            <lb />
            this Court. It has been further contended that while awarding the
            <lb />
            compensation the competent authority has committed gross
            <lb />
            illegality by willfully awarding compensation and interest under
            <lb />
            the Right to Fair Compensation and Transparency in Land
            <lb />
            Acquisition, Rehabilitation and Resettlement Act, 2013 which is
            <lb />
            not applicable in the present case. It has been further contended
            <lb />
            that the learned authority has granted compensation treating the
            <lb />
            land of respondents No. 6 to 10 as diverted land whereas the
            <lb />
            said land is agriculture land and not fit for the purposes of
            <lb />
            acquisition and would pray that the award dated 12.02.2018
            <lb />
            passed by the competent authority be kindly set aside and grant
            <lb />
            of other reliefs as seizure of the accounts of the beneficiaries i.e.
            <lb />
            respondents No. 6 to 10 who have been paid excess
            <lb />
            compensation and also prayd for direction for recovery of the
            <lb />
            excess amount paid to them and action to be initiated against
            <lb />
            the erring officers as per the Revenue Recovery Act, 1890.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            109. Respondent No. 6 has filed a detailed return reiterating the
            <lb />
            grounds which have been taken by them in writ petition
            <lb />
            (criminal) assailing the authority of the collector to conduct
            <lb />
            inquiry and subsequent registration of the FIR on the basis of the
            <lb />
            report submitted by the Collector and also highlighted that said
            <lb />
            land belongs to urban area and village Palli falls within the ambit
            <lb />
            of Municipal Corporation, therefore, the award passed by the
            <lb />
            competent authority and affirmed by the Arbitrator, is legal and
            <lb />
            just and therefore, the writ petition is liable to be dismissed. It
            <lb />
            has been also contended that the Collector has conducted
            <lb />
            fishing and roving enquiry in to the award and into the events
            <lb />
            preceding the award. The said three member inquiry committee
            <lb />
            without giving any opportunity of hearing to the answering
            <lb />
            respondents and other stakeholders and the revenue officers
            <lb />
            associated with the acquisition proceedings reached to the
            <lb />
            conclusion that there was fowl play on large scale. Further it has
            <lb />
            been contended that three members inquiry committee also
            <lb />
            concluded that the revenue officers and Railway Officers were
            <lb />
            also involved in the fowl play. It is beyond competency for the
            <lb />
            State Government officers i.e. the Sub Divisional Officer to
            <lb />
            conduct investigation into the acquisition proceeding by the
            <lb />
            Central Government for the purpose of Indian Railway and to
            <lb />
            conclude without hearing any affected parties. Further three
            <lb />
            members inquiry committee recommended for strict action and
            <lb />
            recovery of the excess compensation amount allegedly paid to
            <lb />
            the answering respondents, which is without jurisdiction.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            110. The petitioner has filed rejoinder to the return in which he has
            <lb />
            reiterated the same stand which he has taken while defending in
            <lb />
            the writ petition (criminal) and have referred to the guidelines
            <lb />
            issued for the year 2017-18 as per the Stamp Act issued by the
            <lb />
            Government of Chhattisgarh and they have also referred to the
            <lb />
            notifications to substantiate that the village Palli does not fall
            <lb />
            within the jurisdiction of Nagar Palika and it is panchayat,
            <lb />
            therefore, this Court is not repeating the facts which have
            <lb />
            already been taken and dealt with by this Court in Writ Petitions
            <lb />
            (Criminal) at length.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            111. From the above stated factual matrix the point required to be
            <lb />
            determined by this Court is whether the award dated 12.02.2018
            <lb />
            passed by the Competent Authority and arbitration award
            <lb />
            passed by the Arbitrator/Commissioner, Jagdalpur on
            <lb />
            11.07.2019, can be interfered by this Court while exercising
            <lb />
            powers under Article 226/227 of the Constitution of India?
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            112. Learned Senior Counsel for the petitioner would submit that
            <lb />
            Article 226 of the Constitution of India confers wide powers to
            <lb />
            High Courts to issue directions, orders or writs other than the
            <lb />
            prerogative pleads. It also enables the High Courts to mold
            <lb />
            reliefs to meet the peculiar and complicated requirements of this
            <lb />
            Country and would refer to judgment passed by Hon&apos;ble the
            <lb />
            Supreme Court in case of Andi Mukta Sadguru Shree
            <lb />
            Muktajee Vandas Swami Suvarna Jayanti Mahotsav Smarak
            <lb />
            Trust and Others Vs. V.R. Rudani and Others 11 and would
            <lb />
            refer to para 19 which reads as under :-
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;19.The scope of this article has been ex-plained
            <lb />
            by Subba Rao., in Dwarkanath v. Income Tax
            <lb />
            Officer, [1965] 3 SCR 536 at (540-41):
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            &quot;This article is couched in compre-hensive
            <lb />
            phraseology and it ex-facie confers a wide power
            <lb />
            on the High Courts to reach injus-tice wherever it
            <lb />
            is found. The Constitution designedly used a wide
            <lb />
            language in describing the nature of the power, the
            <lb />
            purpose for which and the person or authority
            <lb />
            against whom it can be exercised. It can issue
            <lb />
            writs in the nature of prerogative writs as
            <lb />
            understood in England; but the use of the
            <lb />
            expression &quot;na-ture&quot;, for the said expression does
            <lb />
            not equate the writs that can be issued in India
            <lb />
            with those in England, but only draws an analogy
            <lb />
            from them. That apart, High Courts can also issue
            <lb />
            directions, orders or writs other than the
            <lb />
            prerogative writs. It enables the High Courts to
            <lb />
            mould the reliefs to meet the pecul-iar and
            <lb />
            complicated requirements of this country. Any
            <lb />
            attempt to equate the scope of the power of the
            <lb />
            High Court under Article 226 of the Constitution
            <lb />
            with that of the English Courts to issue prerogative
            <lb />
            writs is to intro-duce the unnecessary procedural
            <lb />
            restrictions grown over the years in a
            <lb />
            comparatively small country like England with a
            <lb />
            unitary form of Government into a vast country like
            <lb />
            India functioning under a federal structure. Such a
            <lb />
            construction defeats the purpose of the article
            <lb />
            itself.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            113. He would further submit that this Court can always look into the
            <lb />
            subsequent events and developments that have been taken
            <lb />
            place after filing of the writ petition or filing of the Special Leave
            <lb />
            Petition and it is also within jurisdiction to pass subsequent order
            <lb />
            to give effect to the remedies available to the parties and would
            <lb />
            refer to the judgment of Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court in case of PRP
            <lb />
            Exports &amp; others Vs. Chief Secretary, Government of Tamil
            <lb />
            Nadu &amp; others, has held at paragraph 8 as under:-
        </p>
        <lb />
        <item>
            &quot;8. Shri Harish Salve, learned senior counsel
            <lb />
            appearing for the Petitioner, submitted that he is
            <lb />
            more concerned with the first question and
            <lb />
            arguments were advanced by him as well as Shri
            <lb />
            C. Sundaram, learned senior counsel appearing for
            <lb />
            the State, on that point. In our view, the Division
            <lb />
            Bench of the High Court is right in examining the
            <lb />
            subsequent events as well in a case where larger
            <lb />
            public interest is involved. This Court in All India
            <lb />
            Railway Recruitment Board v. K. Shyam Kumar
            <lb />
            [(2010) 6 SCC 614] distinguished Mohinder Singh
            <lb />
            Gill&apos;s case (supra), stating when a larger public
            <lb />
            interest is involved, the Court can always look into
            <lb />
            the subsequent events. Relevant paragraph of the
            <lb />
            judgment is extracted hereinbelow :-
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            &quot;45. We are of the view that the decision-
            <lb />
            maker can always rely upon subsequent
            <lb />
            materials to support the decision already
            <lb />
            taken when larger public interest is involved.
            <lb />
            This Court in Madhyamic Shiksha Mandal,
            <lb />
            M.P. v. Abhilash Shiksha Prasar Samiti found
            <lb />
            no irregularity in placing reliance on a
            <lb />
            subsequent report to sustain the cancellation
            <lb />
            of the examination conducted where there
            <lb />
            were serious allegations of mass copying.
            <lb />
            The principle laid down in Mohinder Singh Gill
            <lb />
            case is not applicable where larger public
            <lb />
            interest is involved and in such situations,
            <lb />
            additional grounds can be looked into to
            <lb />
            examine the validity of an order. The finding
            <lb />
            recorded by the High Court that the report of
            <lb />
            CBI cannot be looked into to examine the
            <lb />
            validity of the order dated 4-6-2004, cannot
            <lb />
            be sustained&quot;.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            114. He would submit that this Court while exercising powers under
            <lb />
            Article 226/227 of the Constitution of India can definitely interfere
            <lb />
            with the arbitration matters if there is perversity in the order that
            <lb />
            must stare one in the face. It has been further contended by the
            <lb />
            learned Senior Counsel for the petitioner that in any case the
            <lb />
            hierarchy in our legal frame work mandates that a legislative
            <lb />
            enactment cannot curtail a constitutional right and he would refer
            <lb />
            to the judgment rendered by Hon&apos;ble the Supreme Court in case
            <lb />
            of Nivedita Sharma Vs. Cellular Operators Association of
            <lb />
            India and Others 12 wherein it has been held at paragraph No.
            <lb />
            11, which is extracted below:-
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;11. We have considered the respective
            <lb />
            arguments/submissions. There cannot be any
            <lb />
            dispute that the power of the High Courts to issue
            <lb />
            directions, orders or writs including writs in the
            <lb />
            nature of habeas corpus, certiorari, mandamus,
            <lb />
            quo warranto and prohibition under Article 226 of
            <lb />
            the Constitution is a basic feature of the
            <lb />
            Constitution and cannot be curtailed by
            <lb />
            parliamentary legislation L. Chandra Kumar v.
            <lb />
            Union of India (1997) 3 SCC 261. However, it is
            <lb />
            one thing to say that in exercise of the power
            <lb />
            vested in it under Article 226 of the Constitution,
            <lb />
            the High Court can entertain a writ petition against
            <lb />
            any order passed by or action taken by the State
            <lb />
            and/or its agency/instrumentality or any public
            <lb />
            authority or order passed by a quasi-judicial
            <lb />
            body/authority, and it is an altogether different thing
            <lb />
            to say that each and every petition filed under
            <lb />
            Article 226 of the Constitution must be entertained
            <lb />
            by the High Court as a matter of course ignoring
            <lb />
            the fact that the aggrieved person has an effective
            <lb />
            alternative remedy. Rather, it is settled law that
            <lb />
            when a statutory forum is created by law for
            <lb />
            redressal of grievances, a writ petition should not
            <lb />
            be entertained ignoring the statutory dispensation.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            115. The learned Senior Counsel for the respondents would submit
            <lb />
            that the case as projected by the petitioner is not a case where
            <lb />
            petition under Article 226 of the Constitution of India must be
            <lb />
            entertained by this Court. He would further submit that it is
            <lb />
            settled legal position that when a statutory forum is created by
            <lb />
            law for redressal of grievances writ petition should not be
            <lb />
            entertained ignoring the statutory dispensation.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            116. The learned Senior counsel for the petitioner would submit that it
            <lb />
            is exceptionable circumstances where this Court should exercise
            <lb />
            its power under Article 226/227 of the Constitution of India. To
            <lb />
            substantiate his submission he would submit that by making
            <lb />
            fraud, compensation has been enhanced to more than 100 times
            <lb />
            which has caused huge financial burden to the public Exchequer
            <lb />
            and the whole projects have been hampered because of the
            <lb />
            arbitration award passed by the learned Competent Authority.
            <lb />
            There is clear cut case of fraud which vitiates entire things,
            <lb />
            therefore, this is a case where this Court should not restrain
            <lb />
            themselves from deciding the matter on merits of the case in
            <lb />
            view of the judgment of the Supreme Court in case of Bhaven
            <lb />
            Constitution Vs. Executive Engineer Sardar Sarovar
            <lb />
            Narmada Nigam Ltd. 13 , wherein it has been held at paragraph
            <lb />
            16 which is extracted as under:-
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;16.Thereafter, Respondent No. 1 chose to
            <lb />
            impugn the order passed by the arbitrator
            <lb />
            under Section 16(2) of the Arbitration Act through
            <lb />
            a petition under Article 226/227 of the Indian
            <lb />
            Constitution. In the usual course, the Arbitration
            <lb />
            Act provides for a mechanism of challenge
            <lb />
            under Section 34. The opening phase of Section
            <lb />
            34 reads as &apos;Recourse to a Court against an
            <lb />
            arbitral award may be made only by an application
            <lb />
            for setting aside such award in accordance with
            <lb />
            sub-section (2) and sub-section (3)&apos;. The use of
            <lb />
            term &apos;only&apos; as occurring under the provision serves
            <lb />
            two purposes of making the enactment a complete
            <lb />
            code and lay down the procedure.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            117. Since no one has raised objection about the maintainability of
            <lb />
            the writ petition at the initial stage and thereafter, various orders
            <lb />
            have been passed, even otherwise, as held by Hon&apos;ble the
            <lb />
            Supreme Court in Deep Industries Limited Vs. Oil and Natural
            <lb />
            Gas Corporation Limited &amp; another 14 that if exceptional
            <lb />
            circumstances or patently lacking in jurisdiction are passed, this
            <lb />
            Court can hear the matter under Article 226/227 of the
            <lb />
            Constitution of India. This Court cannot lose sight of the facts
            <lb />
            that the land losers or the Government officials against whom,
            <lb />
            the FIR has been registered have also assailed that registration
            <lb />
            of FIR and subsequent criminal proceeding before this Court by
            <lb />
            filing writ petition contending that the proceedings initiated by the
            <lb />
            Competent Authority while determining the compensation or
            <lb />
            award passed by the Commissioner has submitted that award
            <lb />
            has been passed in accordance with law, therefore, the
            <lb />
            registration of FIR is illegal. On the other hand, the petitioner in
            <lb />
            Writ Petition (C) is assailing the award as well as determination
            <lb />
            of compensation by the Competent Authority, therefore, to avoid
            <lb />
            difference of opinion by different forum, this is a peculiar
            <lb />
            situation where this Court should not restrain in deciding validity
            <lb />
            of the arbitration award and determination of compensation by
            <lb />
            the authority, therefore, the matter is finally decided by this Court
            <lb />
            on its merits.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            118. This Court has called upon the records of Competent Authority,
            <lb />
            as well as Arbitrator, who has passed the arbitration award to
            <lb />
            ascertain what are the materials have been considered by them
            <lb />
            while passing the award or determining the compensation and to
            <lb />
            examine whether there is any perversity while determining
            <lb />
            compensation by the Competent Authority. The record of the
            <lb />
            Competent Authority will reflect that the objection raised by Bali
            <lb />
            Nagwanshi has been allowed and it has been held that his land
            <lb />
            belongs to urban area, without considering any notification
            <lb />
            issued by the Government of Chhattisgarh while recording such
            <lb />
            finding. It has also been reflected from the record that the
            <lb />
            Competent Authority while assessing the compensation has only
            <lb />
            mentioned about the guidelines for the year 2017-18, it has not
            <lb />
            spoken which provisions have been made applicable while
            <lb />
            determining th compensation. There was no material
            <lb />
            consideration with regard to the guidelines and only reference
            <lb />
            was made whereas it was necessary for the Competent
            <lb />
            Authority while assessing the compensation should have atleast
            <lb />
            mentioned which provisions are made applicable and how the
            <lb />
            land of the land owners falls within the such category of the
            <lb />
            guideline. There is no such exercise done by the Competent
            <lb />
            Authority and while affirming the award, the Commissioner/
            <lb />
            Arbitrator has also not done any such exercise, which shows
            <lb />
            non-application of mind and clearly speaks about the perversity
            <lb />
            while passing of the award.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            119. Similarly, while recording the finding the land belonging to Bali
            <lb />
            Nagwanshi is diverted land and award has been passed treating
            <lb />
            the land to be diverted land and situated at urban area. The
            <lb />
            Competent Authority in its award has only referred to the
            <lb />
            guidelines of 2017-18 but has not taken into consideration which
            <lb />
            provisions of the guidelines have been applied for determining
            <lb />
            the compensation. The record also contains some Gadna Patrak
            <lb />
            (Calculation-Sheet). That calculation-sheet is also silent with
            <lb />
            regard to how the calculation has been done. The record simply
            <lb />
            said &quot;Bhumi ka Muawaja Patrak Guidlines ke Anusar&quot;. Learned
            <lb />
            counsel for respondents No. 6 and 7 would submit that
            <lb />
            calculation sheet has been done strictly as per the guidelines
            <lb />
            therefore, the award passed by the learned Competent Authority
            <lb />
            is justified and should not be interfered by this Court. In their
            <lb />
            support they have referred to various provisions and guidelines.
            <lb />
            But the record is silent and does not reflect which provisions of
            <lb />
            the guidelines have been made effective while calculating the
            <lb />
            compensation, even no reasons have been assigned how this
            <lb />
            particular provisions of guidelines have been made effective.
            <lb />
            This shows non-application of mind by the Competent Authority.
            <lb />
            Thus, the award suffers from non-application of mind and
            <lb />
            without consideration of the guidelines, as such suffers from
            <lb />
            perversity and patent illegality which can be interfered by this
            <lb />
            Court.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            120. Learned Senior Counsel for the petitioner would submit that
            <lb />
            village Palli does not fall within urban area whereas the learned
            <lb />
            counsel for Respondents No. 6 and 7 while referring to the
            <lb />
            guidelines would submit that it falls within the urban area. This is
            <lb />
            a disputed fact and various notifications have also been
            <lb />
            submitted either by the petitioner that village Palli is still in the
            <lb />
            Gram Panchayat and does not fall within the ambit of Nagar
            <lb />
            Palika whereas learned counsel for the respondent has referred
            <lb />
            to guidelines wherein village Palli has been declared as
            <lb />
            Lokmanya Tilak Ward No. 37. These are disputed facts. The
            <lb />
            award has been passed by the Competent Authority without
            <lb />
            considering the circular and guidelines and excess amount of
            <lb />
            compensation has been granted. Thus, the award suffers from
            <lb />
            non application of mind and deserves to be set aside and
            <lb />
            accordingly the writ petition (civil) is allowed in part.
        </p>
        <lb />
        <p>
            121. Learned Senior Counsel for the petitioner would submit that the
            <lb />
            arbitration award dated 11.07.2019 passed by the
            <lb />
            Commissioner, Jagdalpur is also illegal and same is liable to be
            <lb />
            quashed as the petitioner/Bastar Railway Private Limited (BRPL)
            <lb />
            has not been arrayed as party. He would further submit that the
            <lb />
            respondent No. 7/Smt. Neelima Belsaria has filed an application
            <lb />
            on 26.02.2019 for re-calculation of the compensation and grant
            <lb />
            of interest before the Arbitrator/Commissioner, Jagdalpur
            <lb />
            wherein the Additional Collector/Competent Authority as well as
            <lb />
            Chief Executive Officer (Construction), South Eastern Central
            <lb />
            Railway have been made party, but the petitioner has not been
            <lb />
            made party. The Commissioner vide its award dated 11.07.2019
            <lb />
            has allowed the application without any notice to the petitioner,
            <lb />
            which is in violation of the principle of natural justice and he
            <lb />
            would refer to judgment of Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court in case of
            <lb />
            Delhi Development Authority Vs. Bhola Nath Sharma (Dead)
            <lb />
            by Lrs. &amp; others 15 wherein it has been held at paragraph 42,
            <lb />
            which is extracted below:-
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;42. In view of the above discussion, we hold that :
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (i) the DDA falls within the definition of the
            <lb />
            expressions &quot;local authority&quot; [Section 3(aa)] and
            <lb />
            &quot;person interested&quot; [Section 3(b)] of the Act;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (ii) the DDA was entitled to participate in the
            <lb />
            proceedings held before the Land Acquisition
            <lb />
            Collector;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (iii) the failure of the Land Acquisition Collector to
            <lb />
            issue notice to the DDA and give an opportunity to
            <lb />
            it to adduce evidence for the purpose of
            <lb />
            determining the amount of compensation payable
            <lb />
            to the land owners was fatal to the award passed
            <lb />
            by him;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (iv) the DDA was entitled to notice and opportunity
            <lb />
            to adduce evidence before the Reference Court
            <lb />
            could enhance market value of the acquired land
            <lb />
            entitling the respondents to claim higher
            <lb />
            compensation and, as no notice or opportunity was
            <lb />
            given to the DDA by the Reference Court, the
            <lb />
            judgments rendered by it are liable to be treated as
            <lb />
            nullity;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (v) the Division Bench of the High Court also
            <lb />
            committed serious error by further enhancing the
            <lb />
            amount of compensation payable to the contesting
            <lb />
            respondents without requiring them to implead the
            <lb />
            DDA as party respondent so as to enable it to
            <lb />
            contest their prayer for grant of higher
            <lb />
            compensation.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            122. The learned Senior counsel for respondent No. 7 would submit
            <lb />
            that the petitioner&apos;s contention that Competent Authority (instead
            <lb />
            of Arbitrator) while determining the compensation have not been
            <lb />
            made party to the case and on this count alone the award is
            <lb />
            liable to be set aside, cannot be accepted and the judgment
            <lb />
            cited by learned counsel for the petitioner in case of Bholanath
            <lb />
            Sharma (Supra) is distinguishable on its own facts. He would
            <lb />
            further submit that the said judgment is not applicable as it was
            <lb />
            delivered because of the specific provisions contained in Section
            <lb />
            15 of the Land Acquisition Act, 1984 as amended by permitting
            <lb />
            any local authority or company to appear and adduce evidence
            <lb />
            where cost of the land acquisition is borne out of fund controlled
            <lb />
            by which company or authority. This is not the situation in the
            <lb />
            present case. As per the provisions of the Railways Act, 1989, it
            <lb />
            is crystal clear that it is only the person whose land is being
            <lb />
            acquired and the Central Government i.e. Ministry of Railway
            <lb />
            who must be heard for determining the compensation and on
            <lb />
            other party is entitled to hearing. He would also refer to Section
            <lb />
            2 (29A) of the Railways Act, which is extracted below:-
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            1. Person claiming interested, compensation for
            <lb />
            acquisition of land
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            2. The tribal and other forest dwellers
            <lb />
            3. Persons interested in easement affecting the land
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            4. Persons having tenancy right under the relevant
            <lb />
            stated law.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            123. Therefore, the learned counsel for respondent No. 7 would
            <lb />
            submit that the petitioner does not fall in any of the category,
            <lb />
            therefore, it is not necessary party to be heard at the time of
            <lb />
            passing of the award by the Competent Authority at the time of
            <lb />
            determining compensation or by the Arbitrator.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            124. The submission of the learned counsel for the respondents No. 7
            <lb />
            that the petitioner does not fall within any of the category to be
            <lb />
            heard can not be accepted as amount of compensation was
            <lb />
            deposited by the petitioner and they are adversely affected by
            <lb />
            the compensation granted by the competent authority and also
            <lb />
            by the arbitration award passed by the learned Commissioner,
            <lb />
            Jagdalpur, therefore, they are necessary party and without they
            <lb />
            are being heard, the award is in violation of principle of natural
            <lb />
            justice, on this Court alone the award is liable to be set aside.
            <lb />
            Even otherwise, if we see the MoU dated 09.05.2015, the
            <lb />
            petitioner is a Joint Venture Company (JVC), which consists
            <lb />
            Steel Authority of India Ltd. (SAIL), Indian Railway Construction
            <lb />
            Company Ltd. (IRCON), National Mineral Development
            <lb />
            Corporation
            <lb />
            Ltd.,
            <lb />
            Chhattisgarh
            <lb />
            Minerals
            <lb />
            Development
            <lb />
            Corporation Ltd (CMDC) took part to build, construct, operate
            <lb />
            and maintain Jagdalpur Rowghat Rail Corridor Project. As per
            <lb />
            clause 7 of the MoU, the JVC shall be responsible for payment
            <lb />
            of compensation of land and also implementation of
            <lb />
            rehabilitation plan as per LAPR Act and rehabilitation policy of
            <lb />
            the State Government, therefore, the petitioner falls within the
            <lb />
            ambit of person interested and as such, he was necessary party
            <lb />
            before the proceedings. It is pertinent to mention here that as
            <lb />
            per Section 20D of the Railways Act, 1989, the competent
            <lb />
            authority is bound to hear and dispose of the objection of person
            <lb />
            interested in the land which is to be acquired under the Railways
            <lb />
            Act. The word &apos;interested person&apos; has been defined in Black&apos;s
            <lb />
            Law Dictionary, which is as under:-
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;A person having a property right in or claims
            <lb />
            against a thing, such as a trust or decendent&apos;s
            <lb />
            state. The meaning may be extent to include an
            <lb />
            entity, such as a business i.e. a creditor of a
            <lb />
            decedent.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            125. Hon&apos;ble the Supreme Court has also examined the word &apos;person
            <lb />
            interested&apos; in case of Himalaya Tiles and Marble (P) Ltd. Vs.
            <lb />
            Francis Victor Coutinho (Dead) by LR&apos;s 16 , and has held at
            <lb />
            paragraph 14, which is extracted as under:-
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;14. Thus, the preponderance of judicial opinion
            <lb />
            seems to favour the view that the definition of
            <lb />
            &apos;person interested&apos; must be liberally construed so
            <lb />
            as to&apos; include a body, local authority, or a company
            <lb />
            for whose benefit the land is acquired and who is
            <lb />
            bound under an agreement to pay the
            <lb />
            compensation. In our opinion, this view accords
            <lb />
            with the principles of equity, justice and good
            <lb />
            conscience. How can it be said that a person for
            <lb />
            whose benefit the land is acquired and who is to
            <lb />
            pay the compensation is not a person interested
            <lb />
            even though its stake may be extremely vital ? For
            <lb />
            instance, the land acquisition proceedings may be
            <lb />
            held to be invalid and thus a person concerned is
            <lb />
            completely deprived of the benefit which is
            <lb />
            proposed to be given to him. Similarly if such a
            <lb />
            person is not heard by the Collector or a court, he
            <lb />
            may have to pay a very heavy compensation
            <lb />
            which, in case he is allowed to appear before a
            <lb />
            court, he could have satisfied it that the
            <lb />
            compensation was far too heavy having regard to
            <lb />
            the nature and extent of the land. We are,
            <lb />
            therefore, unable to agree with the view taken by
            <lb />
            the Orissa High Court or even by the Calcutta High
            <lb />
            Court that a company, local authority or a person or
            <lb />
            whose benefit the land is acquired is not an
            <lb />
            interested person. We are satisfied that such a
            <lb />
            person is vitally interested both in the title to the
            <lb />
            property as also in the compensation to be paid
            <lb />
            therefor because both these factors concern its
            <lb />
            future course of action and if decided against him,
            <lb />
            seriously prejudice his rights. Moreover, in view of
            <lb />
            the decision of this Court referred to above, we
            <lb />
            hold that the appellant was undoubtedly a person
            <lb />
            interested as contemplated by s. 18(1) of the Act.
            <lb />
            The High Court, therefore, committed an error in
            <lb />
            throwing out the appeal of the appellant on the
            <lb />
            ground that it had no locus to file an appeal before
            <lb />
            the Bench.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            126. Hon&apos;ble the Supreme Court in Union of India (UOI) &amp; others
            <lb />
            Vs. District Judge, Udhampur &amp; others 17 , and has held at
            <lb />
            paragraph 8 which is extracted as under:-
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;8. This view was reiterated in Neelagangabai v.
            <lb />
            State of Karnataka MANU/SC/0254/1990: [1990] 3
            <lb />
            SCR 20; Krishi Upaj Mandi Samiti v. Ashok Singhal
            <lb />
            and Ors. (1991) Suppl. 2 SCC 419; Union of India
            <lb />
            v. Sher Singh and Ors. MANU/SC/0451/1993:
            <lb />
            [1993] 1 SCR 326 and Bihar State Electricity Board
            <lb />
            v. State of Bihar and Ors. Civil Appeal Nos. 157/-
            <lb />
            1600/94 dated February 21, 1994. Thus it is settled
            <lb />
            law that the requisitioning authority is a person
            <lb />
            interested since it is interested in the fixation of the
            <lb />
            proper and just market value or compensation of
            <lb />
            the land acquired on its behalf as well as to see
            <lb />
            that the true extent of the land is acquired and is
            <lb />
            free from encumbrances. The participation in the
            <lb />
            proceedings by the local officers is to enable not
            <lb />
            only the determination of the proper and just
            <lb />
            market value or compensation in their presence
            <lb />
            after laying necessary and relevant evidence but
            <lb />
            also to secure valid title to the land acquired so that
            <lb />
            land acquisition officer and the court determines
            <lb />
            just and proper market value of the lands. It is,
            <lb />
            therefore, clear that the appellant is a proper and
            <lb />
            necessary party under Order 1 Rule 10 CPC. It is
            <lb />
            also the person interested under Section 2(d) of the
            <lb />
            Act. Accordingly the view of the High Court that the
            <lb />
            appellants are not interested person is clearly
            <lb />
            illegal. It is accordingly set aside.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            127. In view of the above stated legal position, it is quite clear that the
            <lb />
            petitioner/BRPL is interested person, as such, he should have
            <lb />
            been noticed by the learned Arbitrator where the award was
            <lb />
            challenged by respondent No. 7. Thus, the arbitration award
            <lb />
            passed by the Commissioner is in violation of principle of natural
            <lb />
            justice and is liable to be set aside by this Court also.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            128. Accordingly, the award dated 12.02.2018 passed by the
            <lb />
            Competent Authority and the award passed by the
            <lb />
            Commissioner, Jagdalpur dated 11.07.2019 are set aside.
            <lb />
            Resultantly WPC No. 3355 of 2019 is allowed. In consequence,
            <lb />
            the learned Competent Authority is directed to re-calculate the
            <lb />
            award after considering the circular, guidelines and if required to
            <lb />
            ascertain the factual matrix, he may direct for recording of the
            <lb />
            evidence also while passing the award. The exercise should be
            <lb />
            carried out within six months from the date of receipt of copy of
            <lb />
            this order. Considering the fact that this Court has granted
            <lb />
            interim protection of no coercive steps in WPCR No. 1031 of
            <lb />
            2019 shall be continued till the award is passed by the
            <lb />
            Competent Authority afresh subject to condition that the
            <lb />
            petitioner/land losers whose lands have been acquired or
            <lb />
            purported to be acquired shall file an affidavit before the
            <lb />
            concerned Bank within a period of one month from the date of
            <lb />
            receipt of copy of this order for transfer of amount, which they
            <lb />
            have received towards compensation within one month from the
            <lb />
            date of receipt of copy of this order. Thereafter, the Bank shall
            <lb />
            immediately transfer the amount in account of the land
            <lb />
            acquisition officer, who shall not disburse the amount till the
            <lb />
            award is finally decided by the Competent Authority.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            129. The petitioners/land losers are also directed to refund the
            <lb />
            amount of compensation, which has been received by them in
            <lb />
            pursuance of award dated 12.02.2018 passed by the Competent
            <lb />
            Authority. Their entitlement of compensation and quantum will be
            <lb />
            decided by the Competent Authority afresh, in accordance with
            <lb />
            law giving opportunity of hearing to Bastar Railway Private
            <lb />
            Limited and others.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            130. So far as the Government Officers are concerned, they are also
            <lb />
            granted protection of no coercive steps with a condition that they
            <lb />
            will mark their presence before the Station House Officer,
            <lb />
            Jagdalpur every month till the award is finally decided by the
            <lb />
            Competent Authority and subsequent presence will be
            <lb />
            dependable on final outcome of the award.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            131. With these observations and directions, WPCR No. 674 of 2019,
            <lb />
            979 of 2019, 1037 of 2019, 751 of 2019, 828 of 2019, 1031 of
            <lb />
            2019 &amp; 1096 of 2019 are disposed of and WPC No. 3355 of
            <lb />
            2019 is allowed.
        </p>
        <lb />
        <p>
            Sd/-
            <lb />
            (Narendra Kumar Vyas)
            <lb />
            Judge
            <lb />
        </p>

    </text>
</tei>