<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc xml:id="0" />
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <p>
            1.
            <lb />
            This appeal is directed against the judgment dated 21.12.1998
            <lb />
            passed in Sessions Trial No.269 of 1997 by the Sessions Judge,
            <lb />
            Raipur convicting and sentencing each of the Appellants as under:
        </p>
        <lb />
        <table>
            Conviction
            <lb />
            Sentence
            <lb />
            Under Section 306 of the
            <lb />
            Indian Penal Code
            <lb />
            Rigorous Imprisonment for 5 years
            <lb />
        </table>

        <p>
            2.
            <lb />
            Facts of the case, in brief, are that Rajkumari (deceased) was
            <lb />
            married with Appellant No.1, Homan 4-5 years prior to her death. It
            <lb />
            is alleged that after the marriage, she lived happily for about 1
            <lb />
            year, but thereafter the Appellants began to abuse her due to non-
            <lb />
            birth of any child from her. It is also alleged that Appellant No.2,
            <lb />
            Hirmat Bai, mother-in-law of the deceased and Appellant No.1,
            <lb />
            Homan, husband of the deceased used to beat and harass her and
            <lb />
            ask her to leave their house and go out. On account of this, on
            <lb />
            14.5.1997 at about 3:00 p.m., she consumed some pesticide and
            <lb />
            died. Morgue Intimation (Ex.P7) was lodged by Deonath (PW9) on
            <lb />
            the date of death itself at about 8:20 p.m. Inquest (ExP5) was
            <lb />
            prepared by Additional Tahsildar Radhey Shyam Sonpipare
            <lb />
            (PW6). Post mortem was conducted by Dr. Krishna Kumar Sen
            <lb />
            (PW12). His report is Ex.P11 in which it has been opined that the
            <lb />
            cause of death was suspected poisoning. No opinion has been
            <lb />
            stated regarding nature of the death revealing that it was an
            <lb />
            accidental or a homicidal or a suicidal death. Viscera of the dead
            <lb />
            body was preserved and sent to the Forensic Science Laboratory
            <lb />
            for chemical examination. FSL Report of examination of the
            <lb />
            viscera is Ex.P13 in which it has been reported that Aluminium
            <lb />
            Phosphide Pesticide (Sulfas) was found in the viscera. After
            <lb />
            morgue inquiry, First Information Report (Ex.P8) was registered on
            <lb />
            15.5.1997. Offences under Sections 306 and 498A read with
            <lb />
            Section 34 of the IPC was registered against the Appellants. On
            <lb />
            completion of the investigation, a charge-sheet was filed against
            <lb />
            them for offences punishable under Sections 306 and 498A read
            <lb />
            with Section 34 of the IPC. Charges were framed against them
            <lb />
            under Section 306 of the IPC.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            3.
            <lb />
            To rope in the Appellants, the prosecution examined as many as 12
            <lb />
            witnesses. Statements of the Appellants were also recorded under
            <lb />
            Section 313 of the Cr.P.C. in which they denied the circumstances
            <lb />
            appearing against them, pleaded innocence and false implication.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            3 witnesses have been examined in their defence.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            4.
            <lb />
            After Trial, the Trial Court convicted and sentenced the Appellants
            <lb />
            as mentioned in the first paragraph of this judgment. Hence, this
            <lb />
            appeal.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            5.
            <lb />
            Learned Counsel appearing for the Appellants argued that on the
            <lb />
            basis of testimony of Shivkumar (PW2), brother of the deceased
            <lb />
            and Pratap (PW3), father of the deceased, the offence alleged
            <lb />
            against the Appellants under Section 306 of the IPC is not at all
            <lb />
            made out. It was further argued that as per the statement of
            <lb />
            Shivkumar (PW2), the deceased had never told him about the
            <lb />
            alleged harassment and the relationship between the Appellants
            <lb />
            and the deceased was good. Shivkumar (PW2) has given the
            <lb />
            statement on the basis of statement of Raju, but statement of Raju
            <lb />
            has not been recorded by the prosecution. The prosecution has
            <lb />
            totally failed to prove the alleged harassment or cruelty by the
            <lb />
            Appellants. Therefore, the Appellants cannot be convicted for the
            <lb />
            alleged offence. There are material contradictions and omissions
            <lb />
            in the testimony of the prosecution witnesses which create doubt
            <lb />
            on the prosecution case. Reliance was placed on (2013) 12 SCC
            <lb />
            286 (Atmaram v. State of Maharashtra) and (2007) 11 SCC 205
            <lb />
            (Bhagwan Das v. Kartar Singh).
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            6.
            <lb />
            On the contrary, Learned Counsel appearing for the State
            <lb />
            supported the impugned judgment.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            7.
            <lb />
            I have heard Learned Counsel appearing for the parties and
            <lb />
            perused the material available on record minutely.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            8.
            <lb />
            Sections 107 and 498-A of the Indian Penal Code run thus:
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;107. Abetment of a thing.-A person abets the doing
            <lb />
            of a thing, who-
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            First.-Instigates any person to do that thing; or
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            Secondly.-Engages with one or more other person or
            <lb />
            persons in any conspiracy for the doing of that thing, if
            <lb />
            an act or illegal omission takes place in pursuance of
            <lb />
            that conspiracy, and in order to the doing of that thing;
            <lb />
            or
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            Thirdly.-Intentionally aids, by any act or illegal
            <lb />
            omission, the doing of that thing.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            Explanation
            <lb />
            1.-A
            <lb />
            person
            <lb />
            who,
            <lb />
            by
            <lb />
            wilful
            <lb />
            misrepresentation, or by wilful concealment of a
            <lb />
            material fact which he is bound to disclose, voluntarily
            <lb />
            causes or procures, or attempts to cause or procure, a
            <lb />
            thing to be done, is said to instigate the doing of that
            <lb />
            thing.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            Explanation 2.-Whoever, either prior to or at the time
            <lb />
            of the commission of an act, does anything in order to
            <lb />
            facilitate the commission of that act, and thereby
            <lb />
            facilitates the commission thereof, is said to aid the
            <lb />
            doing of that act.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            498A. Husband or relative of husband of a
            <lb />
            woman subjecting her to cruelty.-Whoever, being
            <lb />
            the husband or the relative of the husband of a woman,
            <lb />
            subjects such woman to cruelty shall be punished with
            <lb />
            imprisonment for a term which may extend to three
            <lb />
            years and shall also be liable to fine.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            Explanation.-For the purposes of this section, &quot;cruelty&quot;
            <lb />
            means-
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (a) any wilful conduct which is of such a nature as is
            <lb />
            likely to drive the woman to commit suicide or to cause
            <lb />
            grave injury or danger to life, limb or health (whether
            <lb />
            mental or physical) of the woman; or
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (b) harassment of the woman where such harassment
            <lb />
            is with a view to coercing her or any person related to
            <lb />
            her to meet any unlawful demand for any property or
            <lb />
            valuable security or is on account of failure by her or
            <lb />
            any person related to her to meet such demand.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            9.
            <lb />
            In Bhagwan Das case (supra), it has been observed by the
            <lb />
            Supreme Court as under:
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;15. In our opinion the view taken by the High
            <lb />
            Court is correct. It often happens that there are
            <lb />
            disputes and discords in the matrimonial home and a
            <lb />
            wife is often harassed by the husband or her inlaws.
            <lb />
            This, however, in our opinion would not by itself and
            <lb />
            without something more attract Section 306 IPC read
            <lb />
            with Section 107 IPC.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            16.
            <lb />
            However, in our opinion mere harassment of
            <lb />
            wife by husband due to differences per se does not
            <lb />
            attract Section 306 read with Section 107 IPC, if the
            <lb />
            wife commits suicide. Hence, we agree with the view
            <lb />
            taken by the High Court. We, however, make it clear
            <lb />
            that if the suicide was due to demand of dowry soon
            <lb />
            before her death then Section 304B IPC may be
            <lb />
            attracted, whether it is a case of homicide or suicide.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            (Vide Kans Raj v. State of Punjab, (2000) 5 SCC 207,
            <lb />
            Satvir Singh v. State of Punjab, (2001) 8 SCC 633 and
            <lb />
            Shanti v. State of Haryana, (1991) 1 SCC 371.)&quot;
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            10.
            <lb />
            In Atmaram case (supra), the Supreme Court has observed thus:
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;19. From the discussion of the aforesaid
            <lb />
            evidence on record, we find that the prosecution has
            <lb />
            not been able to prove beyond reasonable doubt that
            <lb />
            the appellant was guilty of any wilful conduct which
            <lb />
            was of such a nature as was likely to drive Purnabai to
            <lb />
            commit suicide. Rather, there appears to be some
            <lb />
            evidence in the depositions of PW 1 and PW 4 (father
            <lb />
            and sister of Purnabai) that Purnabai was sad due to a
            <lb />
            daughter being born to her and a son being born to the
            <lb />
            first wife of the appellant. These circumstances may
            <lb />
            have driven Purnabai to commit suicide by jumping
            <lb />
            into the well along with her daughter.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            Such a
            <lb />
            consequence from the mental state of Purnabai cannot
            <lb />
            be a ground for holding that the appellant was guilty
            <lb />
            of cruelty within the meaning of clause (a) of the
            <lb />
            Explanation to Section 498A IPC. We, therefore, hold
            <lb />
            that the presumption under Section 113A is not
            <lb />
            attracted and the appellant cannot also be held guilty
            <lb />
            of abetting the suicide of Purnabai. We have to bear in
            <lb />
            mind this note of caution in State of W.B. v. Orilal
            <lb />
            Jaiswal, (1994) 1 SCC 73: (SCC p. 90, para 17)
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            &quot;17. ….... the Court should be
            <lb />
            extremely careful in assessing the facts
            <lb />
            and circumstances of each case and the
            <lb />
            evidence adduced in the trial for the
            <lb />
            purpose of finding whether the cruelty
            <lb />
            meted out to the victim had in fact
            <lb />
            induced her to end the life by committing
            <lb />
            suicide. If it transpires to the Court that
            <lb />
            a victim committing suicide was
            <lb />
            hypersensitive to ordinary petulance,
            <lb />
            discord and differences in domestic life
            <lb />
            quite common to the society to which the
            <lb />
            victim belonged and such petulance,
            <lb />
            discord and differences were not expected
            <lb />
            to induce a similarly circumstanced
            <lb />
            individual in a given society to commit
            <lb />
            suicide, the conscience of the Court should
            <lb />
            not be satisfied for basing a finding that
            <lb />
            the accused charged of abetting the
            <lb />
            offence of suicide should be found guilty.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            20.
            <lb />
            For the aforesaid reasons, we allow this
            <lb />
            appeal and set aside the impugned judgment of the
            <lb />
            High Court and the judgment of the trial court holding
            <lb />
            the appellant guilty of the offences under Sections 306
            <lb />
            and 498A IPC and direct that the bail bonds executed
            <lb />
            by the appellant be discharged.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            11.
            <lb />
            From the above, it is clear that for the guilt under Section 306 of
            <lb />
            the IPC the prosecution is bound to establish that the deceased
            <lb />
            was subjected to cruelty as defined in Explanation (a) to Section
            <lb />
            498-A of the IPC.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            12.
            <lb />
            In the light of above, I shall now examine the evidence adduced by
            <lb />
            the prosecution minutely.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            13.
            <lb />
            Admittedly, the marriage between the deceased and Appellant
            <lb />
            Homan was solemnised 4-5 years prior to her death. From the
            <lb />
            evidence adduced by the prosecution, it is also clear that the
            <lb />
            Appellant Homan had married the deceased by wearing her churi.
            <lb />
            From the evidence, it is also clear that earlier the deceased had
            <lb />
            married one Ballu and from Ballu she had two children.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            14.
            <lb />
            Deonath (PW9), who is brother-in-law (Devar) of the deceased is
            <lb />
            the witness who lodged morgue intimation (Ex.P7). He has stated
            <lb />
            that the deceased came to his house in the afternoon and fell down
            <lb />
            becoming unconscious after feeling giddiness. Her body had
            <lb />
            turned into bluish colour. He has stated that how did the deceased
            <lb />
            die is not known to him. Additional Tahsildar Radhey Shyam
            <lb />
            Sonpipare (PW6) prepared the inquest (ExP5). Dr. Krishna Kumar
            <lb />
            Sen (PW12) conducted post mortem examination on the dead
            <lb />
            body. His report is Ex.P11 in which it has been opined that the
            <lb />
            cause of death was suspected poisoning. No opinion has been
            <lb />
            stated regarding nature of the death revealing that it was an
            <lb />
            accidental or a homicidal or a suicidal death. Viscera of the dead
            <lb />
            body was preserved and sent to the Forensic Science Laboratory
            <lb />
            for chemical examination. FSL Report of examination of the
            <lb />
            viscera is Ex.P13 in which it has been reported that Aluminium
            <lb />
            Phosphide Pesticide (Sulfas) was found in the viscera. Station
            <lb />
            House Officer Narendra Singh (PW5) has done the morgue inquiry,
            <lb />
            registered the FIR (Ex.P8) and investigated into the offence in
            <lb />
            question. Some part of the investigation was done by Prem
            <lb />
            Narayan Shukla (PW10). PW10 also recorded statements of some
            <lb />
            witnesses under Section 161 of the Cr.P.C.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            15.
            <lb />
            From the above, it is clear that the deceased had consumed
            <lb />
            poisonous substance sulfas and she died unnatural death within 7
            <lb />
            years of her marriage. It is not the case of the prosecution that the
            <lb />
            deceased was being harassed for dowry, but, as per the case of
            <lb />
            the prosecution, she was harassed by both the Appellants for non-
            <lb />
            birth of a child by her. For this, the prosecution has examined
            <lb />
            Shivkumar (PW2), brother of the deceased and Pratap (PW3),
            <lb />
            father of the deceased.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            16.
            <lb />
            Shivkumar (PW2) has stated that after the marriage, the Appellants
            <lb />
            kept the deceased happily for about 2 years. Thereafter, they
            <lb />
            started beating and harassing her alleging that she was unable to
            <lb />
            give birth to a child. He has further stated that during festivals,
            <lb />
            when the deceased was visiting their house, she had been telling
            <lb />
            him these things. He has further stated that his younger brother
            <lb />
            Raju had told him that the Appellants also used to tell the
            <lb />
            deceased if she would not leave their house they will kill her by
            <lb />
            giving her poison. In his cross-examination in paragraph 5, he has
            <lb />
            admitted that during 4-5 years after the marriage, he visited the
            <lb />
            house of her sister (the deceased) 1-2 times, but on those
            <lb />
            occasions, his sister had not made him any complaint. In
            <lb />
            paragraph 8, he has further stated that his sister, when she was
            <lb />
            visiting their house, she had been telling about the harassment.
            <lb />
            But, they did not make any report nor did they tell the same to any
            <lb />
            of the neighbours. He has categorically stated that normally these
            <lb />
            small things happen, therefore, they did not tell or report. He has
            <lb />
            further admitted that the deceased was living happily at the house
            <lb />
            of the Appellants.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            17.
            <lb />
            Pratap (PW3) has stated that he had visited the matrimonial house
            <lb />
            of his daughter (the deceased). On that occasion, the deceased
            <lb />
            had told him that the Appellants were asking her to go out of their
            <lb />
            house saying that she was unable to give birth to a child. He has
            <lb />
            further stated that Hirmat Bai, mother-in-law of the deceased used
            <lb />
            to abuse the deceased and on the husband of the deceased
            <lb />
            returning home, Hirmat Bai used to make him complaints. When
            <lb />
            the deceased had visited his house (paternal house of the
            <lb />
            deceased), she had told him these facts. On this, he had called a
            <lb />
            panchayat meeting of their community and the panchayat meeting
            <lb />
            was convened. This witness has also admitted that on being
            <lb />
            complained by the deceased, he did not make any report in the
            <lb />
            police station nor did he tell this fact to any neighbour or person of
            <lb />
            their community. He has further admitted that normally these small
            <lb />
            things happen, therefore, he did not tell or report. In paragraph 9
            <lb />
            of his cross-examination, he has admitted that daughters of his
            <lb />
            brothers-in-law have also been married in Village Kesla where the
            <lb />
            Appellants reside and the deceased used to visit the matrimonial
            <lb />
            houses of those daughters of his brothers-in-law.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            18.
            <lb />
            The testimony of Shivkumar (PW2) and Pratap (PW3) reveals that
            <lb />
            after the marriage the deceased lived happily at her matrimonial
            <lb />
            house for about 2 years. Though these witnesses alleging that the
            <lb />
            Appellants were harassing and beating her alleging that she was
            <lb />
            unable to give birth to a child yet they have admitted that normally
            <lb />
            these small things happen in every house and having thought so,
            <lb />
            they did not make any complaint.
            <lb />
            Shivkumar (PW2) has
            <lb />
            categorically stated that he had visited the matrimonial house of
            <lb />
            the deceased and on that occasion, the deceased had not made
            <lb />
            him any compliant. From the statement of Pratap (PW3) also, it is
            <lb />
            clear that marriage of daughters of his brothers-in-law were also
            <lb />
            solemnised in Village Kesla where the Appellants were residing
            <lb />
            and the deceased used to visit the matrimonial houses of those
            <lb />
            daughters of his brothers-in-law in Village Kesla. But, there is
            <lb />
            nothing on record to show that the deceased ever made any
            <lb />
            complaint to those ladies [daughters of the brothers-in-law of
            <lb />
            Pratap (PW3)].
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            19.
            <lb />
            In Bhagwan Das case (supra), it has been observed by the
            <lb />
            Supreme Court that it often happens that there are disputes and
            <lb />
            discords in the matrimonial home and a wife is often harassed by
            <lb />
            the husband or her in-laws. This, however, would not by itself and
            <lb />
            without something more attract Section 306 IPC read with Section
            <lb />
            107 IPC. It has been further observed by Their Lordships that
            <lb />
            mere harassment of wife by husband due to differences per se
            <lb />
            does not attract Section 306 read with Section 107 IPC, if the wife
            <lb />
            commits suicide.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            20.
            <lb />
            In the light of above, in the present case also, there is no clinching
            <lb />
            evidence available on record regarding harassment to the
            <lb />
            deceased. There is nothing on record on the basis of which the
            <lb />
            Appellants could be held guilty under Section 306 of the IPC.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            21.
            <lb />
            Consequently, the appeal deserves to be and is hereby allowed.
            <lb />
            The impugned judgment of conviction and sentence is set aside.
            <lb />
            The Appellants are acquitted of the charge framed against them.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            22.
            <lb />
            Record of the Court below be sent back along with a copy of this
            <lb />
            judgment forthwith for information and necessary compliance.
            <lb />
            Sd/-
            <lb />
            (Arvind Singh Chandel)
            <lb />
            JUDGE
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>Gopal</p>


    </text>
</tei>