<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">

			<p>This writ petition has been filed to direct the respondents to grant<lb/> permission for Sendamelam on 18-02-2020 at about 10.00 a.m to 01.00<lb/> p.m in connection with the palkudam Eduthu Radhaveethi Ula Varuthal,<lb/> again 05.00 p.m. to 09.00 p.m. Theesatti Eduthu Radhaveethi Ula Varuthal<lb/> and midnight 01.00 hours Karagattam, Sapparam Radhaveethi Ula Varuthal<lb/> in Arulmigu sri Muppidathi Amman Kovil &quot;Masi Festival&quot; situated at<lb/> Vadakarai, Tenkasi District.<lb/></p>

			<p>2. Heard the learned Counsel appearing for the petitioner and the<lb/> learned Additional Public Prosecutor appearing for the respondents.<lb/></p>

			<p>3.The learned Additional Public Prosecutor<lb/> appearing for the<lb/> respondents would submit that they have no objection in granting<lb/> permission, but, in the guise of conducting Radhaveethi Ula, the petitioner<lb/> shall not disturb persons belonging to the other community and other<lb/> religions and that the respondents shall take in to consideration the ground<lb/> situation, will restrict the time period for conducting Radhaveethi Ula. He<lb/> would further submit that the Director General of Police, in his proceedings<lb/> 2/6<lb/> in Rc.No.007301/Genl.I(1)/2019 dated 09.04.2019 has issued circular to<lb/> Commissioner of Police, Superintendent of Police and all the Station Housing<lb/> Officer and directed them to follow the procedure and instruct the petitioner<lb/> seeking permission to conduct cultural programs viz., Sendamelam, to<lb/> comply with the conditions and permission may be granted subject to the<lb/> petitioner agreeing to comply with the said conditions by filing necessary<lb/> undertaking before the respondent police.<lb/></p>

			<p>4. The respondents police are directed to grant permission for<lb/> conducting the cultural programme (ie.,) Sendamelam on 18.02.2020 at<lb/> about 10.00 a.m to 01.00 p.m in connection with the Palkudam Eduthu<lb/> Radhaveethi Ula Varuthal, again 05.00 p.m. to 09.00 p.m. Theesatti Eduthu<lb/> Radhaveethi Ula Varuthal and midnight 01.00 hours Karagattam, Sapparam<lb/> Radhaveethi Ula Varuthal in Arulmigu Sri Muppidathi Amman Kovil &quot;Masi<lb/> Festival&quot; situated at Vadakarai, Tenkasi District, by enclosing the following<lb/> conditions:<lb/></p>

            <list>

			<item>(a) The Sendamelam in connection with the Palkudam<lb/> Eduthu Radhaveethi Ula Varuthal, Theesatti Eduthu Radhaveethi<lb/> Ula Varuthal, Karagattam, Sapparam Radhaveethi Ula Varuthal<lb/> festival or any cultural programme should be completed within<lb/> the time specified by the SHO.<lb/></item>

			<item>(b) The noise level during beating of Sendamelam should<lb/> not be above the prescribed noise levels and it should not create<lb/> noise pollution;<lb/></item>

			<item>(c) no songs, touching upon any political party or religion,<lb/> community or caste be played;<lb/></item>

			<item>(d) Organizers shall not erect any digital banners/pla cards<lb/> on either side of the arterial roads, platforms, walkways/major<lb/> roads and any other roads<lb/></item>

			<item>(e) the function should not affect caste, religious or<lb/> communal harmony and shall be conducted without any<lb/> discrimination<lb/></item>

			<item>(f) if there is any violation of any one of the conditions<lb/> imposed, the concerned Police Officer is at liberty to take<lb/> necessary action, as per law and stop such performance;<lb/></item>

			<item>(g) similarly, the Police is empowered to stop the<lb/> programme, if it exceeds beyond the permitted time;<lb/></item>

			<item>(h) if any untoward incident takes place, the organizers of<lb/> the programme be made responsible for the same<lb/></item>

			<item>(i) the authority concerned shall videograph the entire<lb/> programme at the cost of the applicant and submit the CD to the<lb/> S.P concerned.<lb/></item>

			<item>(j)Organizers shall have to obtain all other required<lb/> permission from the authorities concerned<lb/></item>

			<item>(k)Any other conditions as the authority concerned consider<lb/> to impose according to the ground reality&quot;.<lb/></item>

            </list>

			<p>5. The petitioner is also directed to ensure that the conditions are<lb/> strictly complied with and they will not create any noise pollution disturbing<lb/> the persons belonging to other community and religions and also to ensure<lb/> that no law and order problem is created in the course of conducting the<lb/> festival.<lb/></p>

			<p>6. The writ petition stands disposed of with the above directions.<lb/> However, there shall be no order as to costs.<lb/></p>

			<p>14.02.2020<lb/></p>
            
            <p> Index : Yes / No<lb/> Internet : Yes / No<lb/> vsg<lb/></p>
            
            <p> Note : Issue order copy on 17.02.2020.<lb/> </p>
            
            <p> To<lb/></p>
            
            <p> 1.The Superintendent of Police<lb/> Tenkasi District, Tenkasi.<lb/></p>

			<p>2.The Inspector of Police<lb/> Atchanpudur Police Station,<lb/> Tenkasi District.<lb/></p>

		


	</text>
</tei>
