<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc xml:id="0" />
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <p>
            1.
            <lb />
            These two writ petitions under Article 226 of the Constitution
            <lb />
            of India read with Section 482 of the Code of Criminal Procedure
            <lb />
            1973, have been instituted on behalf of Zakir Khan (hereinafter
            <lb />
            &quot;Detenu No. 1&quot;), the Petitioner in W.P.(CRL.) 72/2022 and Sanjeev
            <lb />
            Kumar @ Sanjeev Kumar Yadav (&quot;Detenu No. 2&quot;), the Petitioner in
            <lb />
            W.P.(CRL.) 73/2022 (hereinafter collectively referred to as the
            <lb />
            &quot;Detenus&quot;), praying for quashing of detention orders, both dated
            <lb />
            26.11.2021, bearing No. PD-PD-12001/17/2021-COFEPOSA and PD-
            <lb />
            12001/18/2021-COFEPOSA, issued under Section 3(1) of the
            <lb />
            Conservation of Foreign Exchange and Prevention of Smuggling
            <lb />
            Activities Act, 1974 (hereinafter &quot;COFEPOSA&quot;) against the
            <lb />
            Petitioners/Detenus No. 1 and 2 respectively; and for further directions
            <lb />
            that the detenus be set at liberty forthwith. As these Petitions raise
            <lb />
            common questions of law and are premised on similar facts, they are
            <lb />
            being disposed off by this common order.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <head>
            FACTS OF THE CASE: -
            <lb />
        </head>

        <p>
            2.
            <lb />
            The relevant facts qua the detenus, as are necessary for the
            <lb />
            adjudication of the subject writ petitions are briefly encapsulated as
            <lb />
            follows: -
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            i)
            <lb />
            The Income Tax Department conducted a search and seizure
            <lb />
            operation on 10.10.2021 at 23 premises allegedly belonging
            <lb />
            to the Detenu No. 1 and persons allegedly associated with
            <lb />
            him. Thereupon, a Statement (Annexure P-4) of the Detenu
            <lb />
            No.1 was recorded u/s 132(4) of the Income Tax Act, 1961,
            <lb />
            on the 11.10.2021, wherein the Detenu No. 1 admittedly
            <lb />
            stated that he had studied only till the VIII standard and
            <lb />
            therefore, expressed his volition to record his statement in
            <lb />
            Hindi.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            ii)
            <lb />
            That, further on 13.10.2021, a Container No. PCIU8689880
            <lb />
            (40 Feet) imported by one M/s Indo Fab, at Kolkata Port,
            <lb />
            with a declaration stated to contain HDMI cables, was
            <lb />
            subjected to examination by the Income Tax Authorities in
            <lb />
            the presence of port custom officers wherein it was found
            <lb />
            that it contained several prohibited items namely, old and
            <lb />
            used/refurbished laptops, mobile phones etc. Accordingly,
            <lb />
            the same was detained by the Customs officers at Kolkata. It
            <lb />
            was alleged that the said firm M/s Indo Fab was
            <lb />
            owned/controlled by the Detenu No.1.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            iii) That on the basis of information received from the Income
            <lb />
            Tax Department, New Delhi; the Directorate of Revenue
            <lb />
            Intelligence, Delhi Zonal Unit (hereinafter DRI/Respondent
            <lb />
            No.3) initiated search proceedings at the purported
            <lb />
            residential premises of the Detenu No. 1 i.e., at S-80 Greater
            <lb />
            Kailash-I, New Delhi, on the 18.10.2021. During the search,
            <lb />
            certain documents allegedly found stored in the said
            <lb />
            premises in the form of files, loose documents, writing pads,
            <lb />
            diaries, Certificate of Incorporation/Articles of Association
            <lb />
            pertaining to three Hong Kong based supplier firms on
            <lb />
            which the name of the Detenu No.1 was mentioned as
            <lb />
            nominated person were recovered. All documents relevant to
            <lb />
            the investigation were resumed for further investigations in
            <lb />
            relation to the suspected undervaluation of imported goods
            <lb />
            by the firms allegedly controlled/owned by the Detenu No.1
            <lb />
            and the Panchnama was drawn.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            iv) On 18.10.2021, upon further search conducted at the office
            <lb />
            premises of Mr. Anurag Tiwari, Custom Broker-proprietor
            <lb />
            of M/s Anurag Tiwari situated at L-509, Gali No. 15,
            <lb />
            Mahipalpur Extension, New Delhi, when it was allegedly
            <lb />
            noticed that the clearance work of imports made in relation
            <lb />
            to the firms purportedly controlled/owned by the Detenu No.
            <lb />
            1 was handled by one Sanjeev Kumar Yadav (Detenu No.2),
            <lb />
            having Custom Broker firm namely, M/s Sanjeev Kumar
            <lb />
            situated at Khasra No. 808, Gali No. 6B, K Block,
            <lb />
            Mahipalpur, New Delhi. Accordingly, search proceedings
            <lb />
            under the Customs Act, 1962 were carried out at the said
            <lb />
            office of Sanjeev Kumar whereupon certain documents were
            <lb />
            allegedly found stored in the said premises, in the form of
            <lb />
            files, loose documents etc. in respect of the said firms
            <lb />
            purportedly controlled/owned by the Detenu No.1. The
            <lb />
            officers of the DRI resumed the said documents for further
            <lb />
            investigations.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            v)
            <lb />
            On or about the 18/19.10.2021, the Detenus were arrested by
            <lb />
            officers of the DRI and produced before the Court of CMM
            <lb />
            (Duty Magistrate), Patiala House Courts through Virtual
            <lb />
            Conference at around 08:30 PM (as it was a holiday) and
            <lb />
            were remanded to 3 days Judicial Custody.
        </p>
        <lb />
        <p>
            vi) On 22.10.2021, Detenus were produced before the Learned
            <lb />
            Court of CMM, Patiala House Courts, New Delhi and
            <lb />
            remanded to 14 days judicial custody till the 04.11.2021.
        </p>
        <lb />
        <p>
            vii) The Detenus admittedly filed retraction applications on the
            <lb />
            28.10.2021, before the learned CMM Court thereby,
            <lb />
            retracting their statements recorded on 18/19.10.2021 before
            <lb />
            the DRI.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            viii) The DRI then caused to be filed an application before the
            <lb />
            learned CMM, Patiala House Courts, New Delhi seeking
            <lb />
            permission to record statements of the Detenus u/s 108 of the
            <lb />
            Customs Act, 1962, which was allowed vide order dated
            <lb />
            01.11.2021.
        </p>
        <lb />
        <p>
            ix) On 02.11.2021, another container No. PCIU8010617 (40&quot;)
            <lb />
            imported by M/s Viha International at Kolkata Port, with a
            <lb />
            declaration to contain HDMI cables, was subjected to
            <lb />
            examination by the officers of DRI, Kolkata wherein it was
            <lb />
            allegedly found that it contained several prohibited items
            <lb />
            namely, old and used laptops, CPUs. Accordingly, the same
            <lb />
            was detained by the officers of DRI, Kolkata. It is alleged
            <lb />
            that the said firm M/s Viha International was also
            <lb />
            owned/controlled by the Detenu No. 1.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            x)
            <lb />
            On 05.11.2021, the DRI caused to be filed an application
            <lb />
            before the learned CMM Court seeking extension of the
            <lb />
            Detenus remand for a further period of 14 days. Vide Order
            <lb />
            dated 05.11.2021, the judicial remand was extended till
            <lb />
            18.11.2021
        </p>
        <lb />
        <p>
            xi) On 08.11.2021, Bail applications were filed by the Detenus
            <lb />
            before the learned CMM, Patiala House Courts, New Delhi,
            <lb />
            both of which were summarily declined vide an order dated
            <lb />
            15.11.2021.
        </p>
        <lb />
        <p>
            xii) Judicial remand of the Detenus was further extended for a
            <lb />
            period of 14 days till 02.12.2021 by the Ld, CMM, vide
            <lb />
            order dated 18.11.2021.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            xiii) On the 26.11.2021, the subject impugned detention orders
            <lb />
            (Annexure P-1) were passed by the Detaining Authority
            <lb />
            (Ministry of Finance, Department of Revenue, Central
            <lb />
            Economic Intelligence Bureau, COFEPOSA Wing,
            <lb />
            hereinafter the Detaining Authority/Respondent No.2),
            <lb />
            which were served upon the Detenus on 27.11.2022 while
            <lb />
            they were still in judicial custody in Tihar Jail, New Delhi,
            <lb />
            pursuant to their arrest by the DRI for the purported
            <lb />
            commission of alleged offences, punishable u/s
            <lb />
            132/135(1)(a)(b) of the Customs Act, 1962.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            i)
            <lb />
            Since no criminal prosecution was filed against the Detenus
            <lb />
            in the customs case, the Detenus were granted statutory bail
            <lb />
            in terms of the mandate of the provision of Section 167(2) of
            <lb />
            the Code of Criminal Procedure vide Order dated 20.12.2021
            <lb />
            passed by the Learned CMM.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            ii)
            <lb />
            On 21.12.2021 the Detenus made a representation to the
            <lb />
            Detaining Authority, submitting that a large number of
            <lb />
            documents furnished to them were illegible and many other
            <lb />
            documents that had been relied upon and referred to were
            <lb />
            not furnished, communicated and/or supplied at all; and
            <lb />
            therefore, demanding legible copies of all of the above, so as
            <lb />
            to enable them to make an effective representation. This
            <lb />
            detailed representation was rejected by the Detaining
            <lb />
            Authority vide order dated 28.12.2021 (received by the
            <lb />
            Detenus in the jail on 29.12.2021).
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            iii) On the 04.01.2022, a constitutionally provided
            <lb />
            representation was filed by the Detenus before the
            <lb />
            COFEPOSA Advisory Board (hereinafter &quot;Advisory
            <lb />
            Board&quot;).
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            3.
            <lb />
            A further perusal of the grounds of detention, impugned in these
            <lb />
            proceedings reveal that the role assigned therein to the Detenu No.1
            <lb />
            pursuant to the investigation carried out is that: -
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            (a) Detenu was the founding member/owner of three Hong Kong
            <lb />
            based supplier firms viz. M/s Trackon Logistics Limited,
            <lb />
            Yottabyte International Co. Limited and M/s SFS Import &amp;
            <lb />
            Export Co. Limited, and from these supplier firms, goods were
            <lb />
            imported in the name of shell entities/dummy firms owned by
            <lb />
            the Detenu No.1 and that he used to decide the prices at which
            <lb />
            such goods are to be invoiced and declared before the Indian
            <lb />
            Customs. The value of the imported goods declared by these
            <lb />
            shell entities before Customs was allegedly roughly 5% (1/20 th )
            <lb />
            of the actual purchase value of these goods;
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            (b) That the Detenu No.1 was the mastermind behind perpetrating
            <lb />
            the entire modus operandi of mis-declaration /undervaluation of
            <lb />
            imports through several dummy firms owned/controlled by him
            <lb />
            and differential remittances for the imported goods were
            <lb />
            remitted through hawala channels in order to evade custom
            <lb />
            duties, thereby causing huge loss to public exchequer. It is
            <lb />
            alleged that, during the period of 2017-2021, the Detenu No.1
            <lb />
            had imported goods amounting to an estimated value of Rs.2730
            <lb />
            crores, on which differential duty liability was estimated to be
            <lb />
            the sum of Rs 500 crores, whereas the actual declared value of
            <lb />
            the subject imported goods before the customs was statedly
            <lb />
            Rs.136 crores and the duty paid thereon was approximately
            <lb />
            Rs.42 crores.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            4.
            <lb />
            Also, a perusal of the grounds of detention, impugned in these
            <lb />
            proceedings, reveal that the role assigned therein to Detenu No.2,
            <lb />
            pursuant to the investigation carried out is that:-
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            (a) Detenu No.2 was the proprietor of the Customs Broker firm
            <lb />
            namely M/s Sanjeev Kumar, and rendered Customs Clearing
            <lb />
            Services for past 6 years to Detenu No. 1 in importing the
            <lb />
            consignment of electronic goods and computer peripherals,
            <lb />
            through his Custom Broker License as well as the borrowed
            <lb />
            Custom broker licenses of M/s Expert Cargo Movers of Shri
            <lb />
            Manoj Nagar and M/s Anurag Tiwari of Shri Anurag Tiwari,
            <lb />
            respectively; and paid monthly amount to the above-stated
            <lb />
            firms ranging from Rs.20,000/-to Rs.40,000/-, depending upon
            <lb />
            the volume of import in a given month.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            (b) Detenu No. 2 also used the Custom broker licenses of M/s
            <lb />
            Phenomenal Logistics, M/s Anubhav Cargo, M/s Shyam Singh
            <lb />
            and M/s Satish Panjwani for the custom clearance of the goods
            <lb />
            allegedly imported by the various entities controlled by Detenu
            <lb />
            No.1.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            (c) Detenu No. 2 used to charge Rs.10,000/-from Detenu No. 1 as
            <lb />
            agency charges through banking channel and, since the goods
            <lb />
            imported by Detenu No.1 were highly undervalued, Detenu
            <lb />
            No.2 used to charge Rs. One lakh per consignment in cash over
            <lb />
            and above the agency charges, for smooth clearance of the
            <lb />
            under-invoiced and under-valued imported goods.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            (d) Detenu No.2 is stated to have orchestrated a plan to facilitate
            <lb />
            customs clearance of imported goods that were mis-declared
            <lb />
            and undervalued using licenses of other Customs Brokers
            <lb />
            despite the fact that the Detenu No.2 himself has a Customs
            <lb />
            Broker License in his name.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <head>
            ARGUMENTS ON BEHALF OF THE PETITIONERS: -
            <lb />
        </head>

        <p>
            5.
            <lb />
            Mr. Vikram Chaudari, learned Senior Counsel appearing on
            <lb />
            behalf of the Detenus vehemently assails the impugned orders of
            <lb />
            detention; Firstly, by submitting that, the now admitted position
            <lb />
            regarding the supply of illegible copies of Relied Upon Documents
            <lb />
            (&quot;RUDs&quot;) including but not limited to those supplied to the Detenus,
            <lb />
            but also those on the record with the Detaining Authority; and the
            <lb />
            axiomatic consequential non-consideration thereof by the Detaining
            <lb />
            Authority has rendered of the impugned detention order invalid.
            <lb />
            Counsel also submitted that the supply of illegible copies of RUDs to
            <lb />
            the Detenus, has further severely prejudiced the detenus from filing an
            <lb />
            effective representation before the Detaining Authority as well as the
            <lb />
            Advisory Board.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            6.
            <lb />
            It is submitted in this behalf by the Ld. Senior Counsel that, the
            <lb />
            proposal for preventive detention was received by the Detaining
            <lb />
            Authority from the Advisory Board only on 24.11.2021 and with
            <lb />
            surprising alacrity less than 2 days thereafter on the 26.11.2021, the
            <lb />
            impugned detention order was passed after considering and relying
            <lb />
            upon 977 pages of RUDs including the admittedly illegible
            <lb />
            documents. It is further submitted that it would be humanly impossible
            <lb />
            for the Detaining Authority to sift through such voluminous
            <lb />
            documents diligently in the said short span of a day and half; and for
            <lb />
            the Detaining Authority to arrive at the subjective satisfaction; and as
            <lb />
            a result the impugned Detention Order is evidently passed in a rushed,
            <lb />
            casual and cavalier manner, which is in gross violation of the
            <lb />
            Constitutional right guaranteed under Article 22(5) of the Constitution
            <lb />
            of India and the same is consequently liable to be quashed, on this
            <lb />
            ground alone.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            7.
            <lb />
            It is further submitted that, a plethora of referred to and/or
            <lb />
            RUDs have not been supplied to the Detenus at all, despite the specific
            <lb />
            demand made by them vide Representation dated 21.12.2021
            <lb />
            (Annexure P-26) which inter alia include:-
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;i.
            <lb />
            Search authorisation issued by Deputy Director, DRI, DZU,
            <lb />
            vide DIN No. 202110DDZ4000000C568 dated 18.10.2021;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            ii.
            <lb />
            Order for extension of Judicial Remand of Zakir Khan and
            <lb />
            Sanjeev Kumar for further 14 days till 02.12.2021;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            iii.
            <lb />
            Documents/loose papers found at the Petitioner&quot;s residence
            <lb />
            and mentioned in Panchnama dated 18.10.2021;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            iv.
            <lb />
            Documents/loose papers found at Sanjeev Kumar&quot;s residence
            <lb />
            and mentioned in Panchnama dated 18.10.2021;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            v.
            <lb />
            Grounds of arrest mentioned in Arrest Memo dated
            <lb />
            19.10.2021;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            vi.
            <lb />
            E-mails downloaded at the office of Custom Broker M/s Sai
            <lb />
            Dutta Clearing Agency Pvt. Limited, situated at Mumbai, and
            <lb />
            mentioned in the Panchnama dated 18.10.2021;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            vii.
            <lb />
            Documents pertaining to M/s Vijay Overseas, M/s Meena
            <lb />
            Prints and M/s Z.K. Overseas which have been seized and
            <lb />
            mentioned in panchnama dated 18.10.2021 drawn at the office
            <lb />
            of Custom Broker M/s Sai Dutta Clearing Agency Pvt.
            <lb />
            Limited;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            viii.
            <lb />
            Pages seized and mentioned in Panchnama dated 22.10.2021
            <lb />
            drawn at the office of M/s Jyoti Enterprises Custom Broker
            <lb />
            situated at Kolkata;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            ix.
            <lb />
            Application for extension of Judicial Remand and the
            <lb />
            subsequent order extending Judicial Remand till 04.11.2021;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            x.
            <lb />
            Application for extension of Judicial Remand and the
            <lb />
            subsequent order extending Judicial Remand till 18.11.2021;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            xi.
            <lb />
            Application for extension of Judicial Remand and the
            <lb />
            subsequent order extending Judicial Remand till 02.12.2021;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            xii.
            <lb />
            RUDs to the 3 Show Cause Notices (at serial number 37, 38 &amp;
            <lb />
            40 of the list of RUDs respectively);
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            xiii.
            <lb />
            Final proceedings in the aforementioned SCNs Notices (at
            <lb />
            serial number 37, 38 &amp; 40 of the list of RUDs respectively) or
            <lb />
            the final orders passed thereof in adjudication or appeal;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            xiv.
            <lb />
            Application has been moved by the Petitioner and Sanjeev
            <lb />
            Kumar informing the Court that they do not want to move any
            <lb />
            bail application;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            xv.
            <lb />
            Preliminary investigation report enclosed in letter dated
            <lb />
            18.10.2021 received from DRI HQ;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            xvi.
            <lb />
            Statement of Sh. Ravichandra Mishra registered by Income
            <lb />
            Tax department referred to in the Detention Order;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            xvii. Signed pages of Sh. Javed Khan&quot;s statement dated
            <lb />
            22.10.2021;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            xviii. Summons issued to persons who have allegedly not joined
            <lb />
            investigation (mentioned in Ground [xxvi] of the impugned
            <lb />
            detention order)&quot;
            <lb />
            At this stage it is observed that in the RUDs, that were supplied, the
            <lb />
            following documents were found to be completely illegible: -
            <lb />
        </item>

        <table>
            Sr. No.
            <lb />
            of list of
            <lb />
            RUDs
            <lb />
            Description
            <lb />
            Page No.
            <lb />
            3.
            <lb />
            Statement of Zakir before I/Tax Deptt
            <lb />
            61 to 68, 75 to 89, 93 to
            <lb />
            100 &amp; 105 to 110
            <lb />
            3.
            <lb />
            Statement of Priyanka Razdan before
            <lb />
            I/Tax Deptt
            <lb />
            135, 137 to 139, 141 to
            <lb />
            150, 155, 156, 166,
            <lb />
            167, 170 to 172
            <lb />
            9.
            <lb />
            Statement of Sanjeev Kumar u/s 108
            <lb />
            Customs Act
            <lb />
            217, 220 &amp; 223
            <lb />
            15.
            <lb />
            Panchnama dated 18.10.2021 drawn at
            <lb />
            the office of Custom Broker M/s Sai
            <lb />
            Dutta Clearing Agency Pvt. Ltd
            <lb />
            244 &amp; 245
            <lb />
            18.
            <lb />
            Letter dated 19.10.2021 from I/Tax
            <lb />
            pertaining to forensic image of PR
            <lb />
            iphone and Zakir Khan iphone.
            <lb />
            248
            <lb />
            19.
            <lb />
            Panchnama dated 21.10.2021 in
            <lb />
            respect of goods stuffed in Container
            <lb />
            consigned in the name of M/s R.K.
            <lb />
            Overseas imported at Kolkata.
            <lb />
            251 &amp; 252
            <lb />
            24.
            <lb />
            Panchnama dated 22.10.2021 at the
            <lb />
            office premises of Custom Broker M/s
            <lb />
            Jyoti Enterprises
            <lb />
            270
            <lb />
            25.
            <lb />
            Statement under 108 of the Customs
            <lb />
            Act dated 22.10.2021 -Ravichandra
            <lb />
            Mishra, Custom Broker.
            <lb />
            275
            <lb />
            26.
            <lb />
            Statement under 108 of the Customs
            <lb />
            Act dated 22.10.2021 -Javed Khan
            <lb />
            280
            <lb />
            30.
            <lb />
            Panchnama dated 02.11.2021 in
            <lb />
            respect of goods contained in
            <lb />
            Container
            <lb />
            293 to 295
            <lb />
            66.
            <lb />
            Excerpt of extraction report wrt to
            <lb />
            mobile phone of Zakir Khan …….
            <lb />
            574, 575, 590, 593,
            <lb />
            596, 599, 605 &amp; 608
            <lb />
            67.
            <lb />
            Excerpt of extraction report retrieved
            <lb />
            forensically wrt. to mobile phone of
            <lb />
            Zakir Khan ……..
            <lb />
            612, 635, 649, 653,
            <lb />
            747, 748, 757 to 759,
            <lb />
            766 to 768, 936 &amp; 937
        </table>
        <lb />
        <p>
            It is further averred that, even if for the sake of argument, it is
            <lb />
            assumed that the said documents were placed before the Detaining
            <lb />
            Authority, the non-consideration thereof in its entirety and not making
            <lb />
            them a part of RUDs, has vitiated the detention order. It is urged that,
            <lb />
            either the Sponsoring Authority has withheld the material and vital
            <lb />
            documents from the gaze of scrutiny of the Detaining Authority or in
            <lb />
            any event, these vital materials have been ignored by the Detaining
            <lb />
            Authority, which is a clear non-application of mind. It is trite to state
            <lb />
            that, if a vital piece of evidence which is likely to influence the
            <lb />
            subjective satisfaction of the Detaining Authority is not placed before
            <lb />
            it, then the detention order would be vitiated in law and fact on the
            <lb />
            ground of suffering from the vice of non-application of mind. In
            <lb />
            support of this argument, the learned Senior Counsel placed reliance
            <lb />
            on the following decisions of the Hon&quot;ble Supreme Court: -
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;(i)
            <lb />
            Taramati Chandulal Sejpal v. State of
            <lb />
            Maharashtra; (1981) 2 SCC 17;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (ii)
            <lb />
            Icchudevi Choraria v. Union of India, (1980) 4
            <lb />
            SCC 531;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (iii)
            <lb />
            Kamla Kanyalal Khushalani v. State of
            <lb />
            Maharashtra, (1981) 1 SCC 748;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (iv)
            <lb />
            Shalini Soni v. Union of India, (1980) 4 SCC 544;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (v)
            <lb />
            Ibrahim Ahamad Batti v. State of Gujarat, (1982)
            <lb />
            3 SCC 440;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (vi)
            <lb />
            Ahmed Nasar v. State of Tamil Nadu, (1999) 8
            <lb />
            SCC 473;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (vii)
            <lb />
            Kamlesh Kumar Ishwardas Patel v. Union of
            <lb />
            India, (1995) 4 SCC 51;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (viii)
            <lb />
            State of Rajasthan v. Talib Khan, (1996) 11 SCC
            <lb />
            393; and
        </item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            (ix)
            <lb />
            Chandra Prakash v. State of U.P., (2002) 4 SCC
            <lb />
            234.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            8.
            <lb />
            It is furthermore submitted that, the Detenus representation
            <lb />
            dated 21.12.2021 seeking legible copies of RUDs was summarily
            <lb />
            rejected by Detaining Authority vide communication dated 28.12.2021
            <lb />
            in the most casual, cavalier and mechanical manner. It is reiterated
            <lb />
            that, not furnishing, or supplying the relevant material(s) or
            <lb />
            document(s) despite demand, is grossly violative of the fundamental
            <lb />
            rights of the detenus as enshrined and guaranteed under Article(s) 14,
            <lb />
            21 &amp; 22 of the Constitution.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            9.
            <lb />
            The learned Senior Counsel appearing on behalf of the Detenus
            <lb />
            submits that, the Detaining Authority has merely acted as a rubber
            <lb />
            stamp by issuing the Detention Order, based solely upon the specious
            <lb />
            allegations made by the Sponsoring Authority. There was no
            <lb />
            subjective satisfaction and considered formulation of grounds on the
            <lb />
            part of the Detaining Authority, which could warrant the passing of
            <lb />
            the detention order under Section 3(1) of the COFEPOSA. The
            <lb />
            Detaining Authority has relied upon certain documents, copies
            <lb />
            whereof were not made a part of the RUDS, as for example, in Para
            <lb />
            xiv of Grounds of Detention, wherein the statement of one
            <lb />
            Ravichandra Mishra before the Income Tax Department has been
            <lb />
            extensively relied upon by the Detaining Authority, however the same
            <lb />
            statement has not been made a part of the RUDs. It is therefore
            <lb />
            submitted that, owing to glaring instances of non-application of mind
            <lb />
            by the Detaining Authority, the same have entirely and unequivocally
            <lb />
            vitiated the said order; since they have rendered nugatory and illusory
            <lb />
            the fundamental right of the Detenu to make an effective
            <lb />
            representation.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            10. It is also contended that, the impugned Detention Orders have
            <lb />
            been passed in the most hurried and casual manner. In other words, in
            <lb />
            the Detention Order against Detenu No.1, it is averred that it is
            <lb />
            necessary to make the Order of Preventive Detention against the
            <lb />
            Detenu;
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;with a view to preventing him from smuggling of goods,
            <lb />
            abetting the smuggling of goods, and engaging in transporting
            <lb />
            or concealing or keeping smuggled goods in future.&quot;
            <lb />
            Even in the grounds of detention, the Detaining Authority has
            <lb />
            recorded its subjective satisfaction by stating that,
            <lb />
            &quot;….you i.e., Zakir Khan has shown a general habit and
            <lb />
            propensity to indulge in fraudulent activities by way of
            <lb />
            smuggling goods, abetting the smuggling of goods, and
            <lb />
            engaging in transporting or concealing or keeping smuggled
            <lb />
            goods at the cost of government revenue and national
            <lb />
            security……&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            In this behalf it is stated that it is no more res integra that where
            <lb />
            various grounds could be joined by the conjunctive &quot;and&quot; the use of
            <lb />
            the disjunctive &quot;or&quot; in such a case is impermissible. It is further
            <lb />
            submitted that, the Grounds of Detention served to Detenu No.1 are
            <lb />
            exactly the same as those served on the co-accused Detenu No.2; and
            <lb />
            all that the Detaining Authority has done is substitute the name of
            <lb />
            Detenu with the expression &quot;you&quot;. That apart, both the Detentions
            <lb />
            Orders are exfacie verbatim copies of each other. The Impugned
            <lb />
            Detention Order is thus, passed in the most cavalier manner, thereby
            <lb />
            resultantly invalidating the same.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            11. In order to buttress his exhaustive oral submissions, Mr. Vikram
            <lb />
            Chaudari, learned Senior Counsel appearing on behalf of the Detenus,
            <lb />
            has pressed into reliance the following decisions: -
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            i.
            <lb />
            Rajesh Vashdev Adnani v. State of Maharashtra
            <lb />
            reported as (2005) 8 SCC 390.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            ii.
            <lb />
            Rakesh Sherpal Singh Rana v. State of Maharashtra,
            <lb />
            reported as 2000 SCC OnLine Bom 684.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            iii.
            <lb />
            Narendra Bahadur Lama v. Union of India, reported as
            <lb />
            2001 SCC OnLine Del 521.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            iv.
            <lb />
            Dimple Prakash Shah vs. UOI-reported as 2010 SCC
            <lb />
            Online Del 1605.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            v.
            <lb />
            Anwar Abdulla v. UOI, reported as 1991 SCC Online Kar
            <lb />
            470.
        </item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            vi.
            <lb />
            Mohinder Singh Gill v. Chief Election Commr., reported
            <lb />
            as (1978) 1 SCC 405.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            vii.
            <lb />
            Gautam Jain v. Union of India, reported as (2017) 3 SCC
            <lb />
            133.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            viii.
            <lb />
            Mohd. Nashruddin v. Union of India, reported as 2021
            <lb />
            SCC OnLine Del 4017.
        </item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            ix.
            <lb />
            Manjit Singh Grewal v. UOI, reported as 1990 (Supp)
            <lb />
            SCC 59.
        </item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            x.
            <lb />
            Dharmista Bhagat v. State, reported as 1989 Supp (2)
            <lb />
            SCC 155.
        </item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            xi.
            <lb />
            Bhupinder Singh v. UOI, reported as (1987) 2 SCC 234.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            xii.
            <lb />
            A. Geetha vs. State of T.N., reported as (2006) 7 SCC
            <lb />
            603.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <head>
            ARGUMENTS ON BEHALF OF THE RESPONDENT
            <lb />
        </head>

        <p>
            12. Per Contra, Mr. Chetan Sharma, the learned Additional Solicitor
            <lb />
            General of India appearing on behalf of the Respondents would submit
            <lb />
            that the impugned detention orders dated 26.11.2021 passed by the
            <lb />
            Competent Authority under Section 3 (1) of the COFEPOSA are legal,
            <lb />
            valid and constitutional and the same have been passed by the
            <lb />
            Competent Authority with due application of mind and after arriving
            <lb />
            at the requisite subjective satisfaction; based on the sufficient material
            <lb />
            facts and circumstances of the case. It is further submitted that the
            <lb />
            subjective satisfaction of the Detaining Authority is elaborated in the
            <lb />
            grounds of detention communicated to the Detenus vide letter dated
            <lb />
            26.11.2021 (Annexure P-3). Therefore, sensing the magnitude of
            <lb />
            offences being committed by the detenus with utter disregard to the
            <lb />
            law of land, the Detaining Authority was convinced and issued the
            <lb />
            Detention Order after carefully and exhaustively examining all the
            <lb />
            documents / information submitted before it. It is further urged that all
            <lb />
            requirements of the COFEPOSA Act, 1974 as well as the relevant
            <lb />
            Constitutional provisions have been scrupulously complied with.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            13. It is submitted that, all the documents relied upon by the
            <lb />
            Detaining Authority had already been supplied to the Detenus. It is
            <lb />
            further submitted that it is a well-settled law that each and every
            <lb />
            document is not required to be furnished to the Detenu. It is further
            <lb />
            submitted that only copies of documents on which the Impugned
            <lb />
            Detention Order is primarily based are required to be supplied to the
            <lb />
            Detenus. It is furthermore submitted that mere reference of certain
            <lb />
            instances in the order of Detention for the purposes of completion of
            <lb />
            narration, would not entitle the detenu for copies of such documents.
            <lb />
            In the present case, all the relied upon documents have been duly
            <lb />
            supplied to the Detenu under his dated acknowledgement within the
            <lb />
            stipulated statutory time period of 5 days, from the date of detention.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            14. It is also submitted that that the language used in the Detention
            <lb />
            Order as well as in the Ground of Detention is in consonance with the
            <lb />
            Section 3 (1) of the COFEPOSA Act, 1974 and the same are not based
            <lb />
            on any inference drawn by the Detaining Authority. The Detention
            <lb />
            Order has been passed and issued following the due process of law
            <lb />
            and after due application of mind and deliberations after taking into
            <lb />
            consideration the facts of the case. It is consequently denied that the
            <lb />
            order of detention has been passed a in casual manner.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            15. It is urged that the Detaining Authority has not relied on
            <lb />
            illegible documents. It is asserted that the Hon&quot;ble Court must sift and
            <lb />
            weigh, between vital and essential documents, and not be swayed by
            <lb />
            the purported illegible documents which have not influenced the
            <lb />
            decision making of the Detaining Authority in any manner.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            16. It is submitted that all evidences relied upon in this case and
            <lb />
            served on the Detenus were invariably produced before the Detaining
            <lb />
            Authority for the latter&quot;s subjective satisfaction. It is further submitted
            <lb />
            that any proposal for preventive detention under COFEPOSA must
            <lb />
            pass through an elaborated procedure of screening and approval
            <lb />
            from officers of the Department as well as from a Screening
            <lb />
            Committee comprising of senior officers of Customs, CBI and the
            <lb />
            Law Department. Only thereafter does the detaining authority
            <lb />
            consider the proposal along with all the relevant materials and
            <lb />
            arrive at the subjective satisfaction that preventive detention of the
            <lb />
            detenu(s) is necessary. The Detention Order is then issued along
            <lb />
            with the detailed grounds of detention. It is further submitted that,
            <lb />
            every document / material which was relied upon for the purpose of
            <lb />
            arriving at the subjective satisfaction in the issuance of the detention
            <lb />
            order, has been supplied to the Detenus under proper
            <lb />
            acknowledgement. It is further submitted that therefore, the subjective
            <lb />
            satisfaction of the detaining authority cannot be argued to stand
            <lb />
            vitiated.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            17. It is submitted that; the present Detenus are involved in duty
            <lb />
            evasion to the tune of more than Rs. 500 crores. It is emphasized that
            <lb />
            the present case is not a &quot;run of the mill&quot; case but an instance of an
            <lb />
            organized syndicate of smuggling and evasion of duties and
            <lb />
            prohibitions wherein the mastermind, along with his associates have a
            <lb />
            remarkable proclivity towards indulging in gross misdeclaration with
            <lb />
            impunity and absolute disregard for law. It is further submitted that the
            <lb />
            booking of previous offences against the Detenus, the plethora of
            <lb />
            evidence available in relation to past misdeclarations, the period for
            <lb />
            which the contraventions have happened in the past, and the sheer
            <lb />
            value of Government revenue involved are clear indications towards
            <lb />
            the need to curtail the liberty of the Detenus with the intent to prevent
            <lb />
            them from indulging in such contraventions again.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            18. Upon a specific query from the bench, it has been fairly
            <lb />
            admitted on behalf of the Detaining Authority -though not on
            <lb />
            affidavit -that various documents sent for consideration to the
            <lb />
            detaining authority, were admittedly wholly illegible and therefore the
            <lb />
            said RUDs supplied to the Detenus were also consequently illegible;
            <lb />
            which factual position was accepted on behalf of the DRI, as is clearly
            <lb />
            recorded in the order dated 03.03.2022 passed by this Court, in the
            <lb />
            present petitions.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            19. In this behalf, it is submitted that, it is incumbent upon the
            <lb />
            Detenus to show that prejudice was caused owing to the illegible
            <lb />
            RUDs.
            <lb />
            It is further submitted that the Detenu must show that the failure to
            <lb />
            supply the RUDs or the supply of illegible RUDs had impaired or
            <lb />
            prejudiced his right, however, slight or insignificant it may be.
            <lb />
            Reliance is place on Kamarunnissa Ec. versus Union of India and
            <lb />
            Ors. reported as (1991) 1 Supreme Court Cases 128.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            20. The learned ASG asserted vehemently on behalf of the
            <lb />
            detaining authority in his oral arguments that, the illegible documents
            <lb />
            are irrelevant and ought to be eschewed from consideration; in view of
            <lb />
            the provision of Section 5A of the COFEPOSA, which stipulates that
            <lb />
            the grounds of detention may be severable, particularly in cases where
            <lb />
            the order of detention has been passed on the basis of two or more
            <lb />
            grounds. It is submitted that, the grounds which indicate reliance upon
            <lb />
            the illegible RUDS may therefore, in law, be severed from the
            <lb />
            remaining grounds that have led to the subjective satisfaction of the
            <lb />
            Detaining Authority. It is further submitted that, the Detenu instead of
            <lb />
            seeking legible copies, should have ignored the illegible document and
            <lb />
            should have filed his representation by excluding the illegible
            <lb />
            documents. The summary of the argument was that in view of section
            <lb />
            5A issues relating to illegible documents having been placed before
            <lb />
            the Detaining Authority, and consequent supply of illegible documents
            <lb />
            as relied upon document must be ignored. Reliance in this regard has
            <lb />
            been placed on the judgement of the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court in
            <lb />
            Gautam Jain v. Union of India reported as (2017) 3 SCC 133.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            21. It is lastly submitted that, the case laws on which the Detenus
            <lb />
            have placed reliance in support of their case are distinguishable from
            <lb />
            the present case as in those cases, the alleged illegible documents were
            <lb />
            vital documents and had a bearing on the mind of the detaining
            <lb />
            authority. However, in the present case the alleged illegible documents
            <lb />
            are not vital and material or have a bearing on the formulation of the
            <lb />
            grounds of detention. The alleged illegible documents are the
            <lb />
            additional and supporting documents in the form of annexures of the
            <lb />
            statements/panchnamas wherein all such documents were duly
            <lb />
            explained. Further, such documents are fully comprehensible and
            <lb />
            understandable when seen with the statements/panchnamas to which
            <lb />
            they are made part of as acknowledged by the Detenus in their own
            <lb />
            handwriting. This amounts to due communication of the grounds of
            <lb />
            detention, in terms of the requirements of Article 22(5) of the
            <lb />
            Constitution of India.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            22. In support of his arguments, Mr. Chetan Sharma, learned ASG
            <lb />
            appearing on behalf of the respondents relied upon the following
            <lb />
            decisions: -
        </p>
        <lb />
        <item>
            i.
            <lb />
            Naresh Kumar Goyal v. Union of India and
            <lb />
            Others, reported as (2005) 8 SCC 276
        </item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            ii.
            <lb />
            State of Maharashtra and others v. Bhaurao
            <lb />
            Punjabrao Gawande, reported as (2008) 3 SCC 613
        </item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            iii.
            <lb />
            Haradhan Saha versus State of West Bengal and
            <lb />
            Others, reported as (1975) 3 SCC 198
        </item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            iv.
            <lb />
            Romesh Chandra Mehta vs State of West Bengal,
            <lb />
            before the Hon&quot;ble Supreme Court in Criminal
            <lb />
            Appeal No. 27 of 1967
        </item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            v.
            <lb />
            Kamarunnissa Etc. vs Union of India and Ors,
            <lb />
            reported as 1991 AIR SC 1640
        </item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            vi.
            <lb />
            Gautam Jain v. Union of India, reported as (2017) 3
            <lb />
            SCC 133.
        </item>
        <lb />
        <head>DISCUSSSION</head>
        <lb />

        <p>
            23. Having heard learned counsel appearing on behalf of the parties
            <lb />
            and after due consideration of the rival submissions in the context of
            <lb />
            the facts and circumstances on record, as well as the relevant
            <lb />
            provisions of law and the decisions relied upon by the parties and
            <lb />
            having perused the material on record, including the pleadings and the
            <lb />
            original file, the following issues arise for the consideration of this
            <lb />
            Court in these proceedings: -
        </p>
        <lb />
        <p>
            A) Whether the non-supply of certain RUDs and the supply of
            <lb />
            illegible RUDs, vitiates the subjective satisfaction arrived at
            <lb />
            by the Detaining Authority; and whether the detention
            <lb />
            orders passed are resultantly vitiated on the ground of non-
            <lb />
            application of mind; thereby rendering them invalid and bad
            <lb />
            in law.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            B) Whether in the event that issue A (Supra) is answered in the
            <lb />
            affirmative, the argument premised on S.5A of the
            <lb />
            COFEPOSA Act, in the facts and circumstances of the
            <lb />
            present case will have the effect of saving the detention
            <lb />
            order from invalidation.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            24. At the outset we consider it relevant to observe that on a
            <lb />
            specific query from the Court as to why no criminal prosecution has
            <lb />
            been filed as yet against the Detenus resulting in their release on
            <lb />
            statutory bail under the mandate of Section 167(2) of the CrPC, no
            <lb />
            cogent or satisfactory explanation was offered or forthcoming.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            25. We find it apposite at this stage to extract the observations
            <lb />
            made by the Hon&quot;ble Supreme Court in a recent decision in Mallada
            <lb />
            K. Sri Ram vs. The State of Telangana &amp; Ors. in Criminal Appeal
            <lb />
            No. 561 of 2022
            <lb />
            (Arising out of SLP (Crl) No. 1788
            <lb />
            of 2022, reported as LQ/SC/2022/476, specifically paragraph 15 as is
            <lb />
            reproduced hereunder: -
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;15. A mere apprehension of a breach of law and order is not
            <lb />
            sufficient to meet the standard of adversely affecting the
            <lb />
            maintenance of public order. In this case, the apprehension of a
            <lb />
            disturbance to public order owing to a crime that was reported over
            <lb />
            seven months prior to the detention order has no basis in fact. The
            <lb />
            apprehension of an adverse impact to public order is a mere surmise
            <lb />
            of the detaining authority, especially when there have been no
            <lb />
            reports of unrest since the detenu was released on bail on 8 January
            <lb />
            2021 and detained with effect from 26 June 2021. The nature of the
            <lb />
            allegations against the detenu are grave. However, the personal
            <lb />
            liberty of an accused cannot be sacrificed on the altar of
            <lb />
            preventive detention merely because a person is implicated in a
            <lb />
            criminal proceeding. The powers of preventive detention are
            <lb />
            exceptional and even draconian. Tracing their origin to the
            <lb />
            colonial era, they have been continued with strict constitutional
            <lb />
            safeguards against abuse. Article 22 of the Constitution was
            <lb />
            specifically inserted and extensively debated in the Constituent
            <lb />
            Assembly to ensure that the exceptional powers of preventive
            <lb />
            detention do not devolve into a draconian and arbitrary exercise
            <lb />
            of state authority. The case at hand is a clear example of non-
            <lb />
            application of mind to material circumstances having a bearing
            <lb />
            on the subjective satisfaction of the detaining authority. The two
            <lb />
            FIRs which were registered against the detenu are capable of being
            <lb />
            dealt by the ordinary course of criminal law.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            26. Insofar as the first issue, as to whether the non-supply of certain
            <lb />
            RUDs and the supply of illegible RUDs, vitiates the subjective
            <lb />
            satisfaction arrived at by the Detaining Authority; and whether the
            <lb />
            detention orders passed are resultantly vitiated on the ground of non-
            <lb />
            application of mind is concerned; we have considered the rival
            <lb />
            submissions made before us in the backdrop of the perusal of the
            <lb />
            original record as well as the material placed before us in the present
            <lb />
            proceedings.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            27. It is imperative at this juncture to observe, that vide order dated
            <lb />
            03.03.2022 passed by this Court in the present petitions, it was noted
            <lb />
            as follows: -
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;Mr. Vikram Chaudhri, learned senior counsel appearing on behalf
            <lb />
            of the petitioners in these writ petitions has handed over in Court
            <lb />
            today the original set of relied documents RUDs furnished to
            <lb />
            the detenues at the time of their detention.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            The Court has perused the said documents. The Court has further
            <lb />
            asked Mr. Sumit Kumar, Senior Intelligence Officer, Directorate of
            <lb />
            Revenue Intelligence to examine the said original documents and
            <lb />
            inform this court as to whether they are the set of documents that
            <lb />
            were served upon the detenues.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            The said official appearing on behalf of DRI confirms that the set of
            <lb />
            documents produced in court on behalf of the detenues are the
            <lb />
            originals, which were served upon them at the time of their
            <lb />
            detention.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            28. It is observed that it was fairly admitted before this Court that
            <lb />
            several RUDs including not only those supplied to the Detenus, but
            <lb />
            also those on the record with the Detaining Authority are illegible i.e.,
            <lb />
            not readable. In this regard, this Court&quot;s decision in Mohd.
            <lb />
            Nashruddin v. Union of India &amp; Ors., reported as 2021 SCC OnLine
            <lb />
            Del 4017 and the relevant paragraphs thereof are reproduced
            <lb />
            hereunder:-
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;47. It is trite to say that a person detained in pursuance of an order
            <lb />
            for preventive detention, has a constitutional right to make an
            <lb />
            effective representation against the same. The authorities are
            <lb />
            constitutionally charged with the responsibility to ensure that the
            <lb />
            grounds of detention, including all relevant documents that are
            <lb />
            considered whilst forming the subjective satisfaction, W.P.(CRL.)
            <lb />
            1924/2020 Page 52 of 86 are provided to the detenu by the Detaining
            <lb />
            Authority, so as to enable the detenu to make an effective
            <lb />
            representation to the Advisory Board, as well as to the Detaining
            <lb />
            Authority. Therefore, the non-supply of legible copies of all
            <lb />
            relevant documents inspite of a request and representation made
            <lb />
            by the detenu for the supply of the same, renders the order of
            <lb />
            detention illegal and bad; and vitiates the subjective satisfaction
            <lb />
            arrived at by the Detaining Authority.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            48. In our considered view, therefore, the supply of the following
            <lb />
            documents namely, a) Passport, b) Identity Cards of codetenu&quot;s, c)
            <lb />
            WhatsApp chats, d) bill of entry, e) invoice, f) the statement of Mr.
            <lb />
            Rohit Sharma who is alleged to have defaced the gold bars imported
            <lb />
            illegally etc. was critical, in order to enable the detenu to make a
            <lb />
            comprehensive, holistic and effective representation against the
            <lb />
            impugned detention order, both before the Advisory Board, as
            <lb />
            well as before the Detaining Authority.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            49. In the present case, the denial by the official respondent to
            <lb />
            supply legible copies of the relevant documents to the detenu,
            <lb />
            despite his express request to do so, tantamount to denial of his
            <lb />
            constitutional right, thereby vitiating the detention order,
            <lb />
            founded on the said relevant material.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            50. In this regard the Hon&quot;ble Supreme Court has, in Dharmistha
            <lb />
            Bhagat V State of Karnataka &amp; Ors reported as 1989 Supp (2) SCC
            <lb />
            155 and in particular paragraph 5 thereof, observed that non-supply
            <lb />
            of legible copies of vital documents would render the order of
            <lb />
            detention illegal and bad. The relevant portion has been extracted
            <lb />
            hereinbelow:
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            5. The learned counsel appearing on behalf of Respondent 1,
            <lb />
            Union of India has contended that even though legible copy of
            <lb />
            panchnama referred to in the list of documents mentioned in
            <lb />
            the grounds of detention has not been supplied to the detenu
            <lb />
            yet the fact that five gold biscuits of foreign marking were
            <lb />
            recovered from the possession of the detenu was sufficient for
            <lb />
            subjective satisfaction of the detaining authority in making the
            <lb />
            said order of detention. So the detention order cannot be
            <lb />
            termed as illegal and bad for non-supply of legible/typed copy
            <lb />
            of the said document i.e. panchnama dated 12-2-1988. The
            <lb />
            panchnama dated 12-2-1988 which had been referred to in the
            <lb />
            list of documents referred to in the grounds of detention and a
            <lb />
            copy of which had been given to the detenu along with the
            <lb />
            grounds of detention, is not at all legible as is evident from
            <lb />
            the copy served on the detenu. It is also not in dispute that
            <lb />
            on receiving the documents along with the grounds of
            <lb />
            detention the detenu had made a representation to
            <lb />
            Respondent 1 stating that some of the documents
            <lb />
            including the panchnama which had been supplied to him
            <lb />
            are illegible and as such a request was made for giving
            <lb />
            typed copies of those documents to enable the detenu to
            <lb />
            make an effective representation against the same. The
            <lb />
            detaining authority on receipt of the said representation
            <lb />
            sent a reply denying that the copies of those documents
            <lb />
            were illegible and refusing to supply typed copies of the
            <lb />
            same. It is clearly provided in sub-article (5) of Article 22
            <lb />
            of the Constitution of India that:
        </item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            &quot;(5) When any person is detained in pursuance of
            <lb />
            an order made under any law providing for
            <lb />
            preventive detention, the authority making the
            <lb />
            order shall, as soon as may be, communicate to such
            <lb />
            person the grounds on which the order has been
            <lb />
            made and shall afford him the earliest opportunity
            <lb />
            of making a representation against the order.&quot;
        </item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            Therefore, it is imperative that the detaining authority has
            <lb />
            to serve the grounds of detention which include also all the
            <lb />
            relevant documents which had been considered in forming
            <lb />
            the subjective satisfaction by the detaining authority
            <lb />
            before making the order of detention and referred to in
            <lb />
            the list of documents accompanying the grounds of
            <lb />
            detention in order to enable the detenu to make an
            <lb />
            effective representation to the Advisory Board as well as
            <lb />
            to the detaining authority. Therefore, the non-supply of
            <lb />
            legible copy of this vital document i.e. panchnama dated
            <lb />
            12-2-1988 in spite of the request made by the detenu to
            <lb />
            supply the same renders the order of detention illegal and
            <lb />
            bad. This Court in Mehrunissa v. State of Maharashtra
            <lb />
            [(1981) 2 SCC 709 : 1981 SCC (Cri) 592 : AIR 1981 SC
            <lb />
            1861] has observed that: (SCC p. 710)
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            &quot;The detenu was entitled to be supplied with copies of
            <lb />
            all material documents instead of having to rely upon
            <lb />
            his memory in regard to the contents of the documents.
            <lb />
            The failure of the detaining authority to supply copies
            <lb />
            of such documents vitiated the detention, as has been
            <lb />
            held by this Court in the two cases cited by counsel.
            <lb />
            The detenu is, therefore, entitled to be released. He is
            <lb />
            accordingly directed to be released forthwith.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            51. To the similar effect are the observations recorded in the
            <lb />
            judgment of the Apex Court in Manjeet Singh Grewal vs. UOI &amp;
            <lb />
            Ors. reported as 1990 Supp SCC 59.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            29. Upon a plain reading of the said order dated 03.03.2022 and the
            <lb />
            above extracted decision of this court, we are of the view that, as the
            <lb />
            RUDs; supplied to the Detenus as well as relied upon by the Detaining
            <lb />
            Authority, in arriving at its subjective satisfaction were admittedly
            <lb />
            illegible; it has the unnerving consequence of violating the
            <lb />
            constitutional rights guaranteed to the Detenus.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            30. In this behalf, the contention made on behalf of the official
            <lb />
            respondents is to the effect that, it is incumbent upon the Detenus to
            <lb />
            show that prejudice was caused to them owing to the supply of
            <lb />
            illegible RUDs; the specific contention being that, the Detenu must
            <lb />
            establish that the failure to supply the RUDs or the supply of illegible
            <lb />
            RUDs had impaired or prejudiced his right.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            31. In our opinion, the aforementioned contention raised on behalf
            <lb />
            on the official respondents is untenable in light of the Hon&quot;ble
            <lb />
            Supreme Court&quot;s decision in Mrs. Tsering Dolkar vs. Administrator,
            <lb />
            Union Territory Of Delhi &amp; Others reported as (1987) 2 SCC 69 and
            <lb />
            in particular paragraph 12, wherein it was observed as under: -
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;12. The learned Additional Solicitor General relied upon the feature
            <lb />
            that the petitioner-wife knew both English and Tibetan languages
            <lb />
            and an effective representation as a fact had been made. There can be
            <lb />
            no two opinions that the requirement of law within the provisions of
            <lb />
            Article 22(5) of the Constitution is that the detenu has to be informed
            <lb />
            about the grounds of detention in a language which he understands.
            <lb />
            The fact that the detenus wife knew the language in which the
            <lb />
            grounds were flamed does not satisfy the legal requirement. Reliance
            <lb />
            was placed by the learned Additional Solicitor General on a decision
            <lb />
            of this Court in Prakash Chandra Mehta v. Commissioner and
            <lb />
            Secretary, Government of Kerala &amp;Ors., [1985] 3 SCR 679 in
            <lb />
            support of his contention that unless the detenu was able to establish
            <lb />
            prejudice on account of the fact that the grounds of detention and the
            <lb />
            documents accompanying the grounds were not in a language known
            <lb />
            to the detenu the order would not be vitiated. There is no clear
            <lb />
            indication of the test of prejudice being applied in that case. On the
            <lb />
            facts relevant before the Court, a conclusion was reached that the
            <lb />
            detenu was merely reigning ignorance of English and on the footing
            <lb />
            that he knew English, the matter was disposed of. We must make it
            <lb />
            clear that the law as laid down by this Court clearly indicates
            <lb />
            that in the matter of preventive detention, the test is not one of
            <lb />
            prejudice but one of strict compliance with the provisions of the
            <lb />
            Act and when there is a failure to comply with those
            <lb />
            requirements it becomes difficult to sustain the order. (See AIR
            <lb />
            1975 SC 1513, [1975] 2 SCR 832 , AIR 1975 SC 245 ).&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            32. Further, we are constrained to observe that in the grounds of
            <lb />
            detention, strong reliance has been placed upon the statements of the
            <lb />
            detenus and co-detenus, recorded under the provisions of Customs
            <lb />
            Act, 1962. A plain reading of the said grounds of detention clearly
            <lb />
            reflects the extensive reliance placed upon the said statements by the
            <lb />
            Detaining Authority, for arriving at its subjective satisfaction. In this
            <lb />
            behalf, it is observed that the impugned orders of detention only a
            <lb />
            passing reference has been made to the circumstance that the
            <lb />
            Department of Revenue had issued rebuttals to the subject retractions
            <lb />
            of the Detenus and that too only on 24.11.2021, merely two days
            <lb />
            before the passing of the impugned orders. For abundant clarity the
            <lb />
            relevant portions of the impugned order of detention passed against
            <lb />
            Detenu No.2 are reproduced below: -
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;xxxvi.
            <lb />
            Zakir Khan filed an application dated 28.10.2021
            <lb />
            before the Ld. CMM, Patiala House, New Delhi stating
            <lb />
            that the statements dated 18/19.10.2021 before the DRI
            <lb />
            officers have been obtained under coercion and torture
            <lb />
            and he was forced to write a statement which is totally
            <lb />
            false. He accordingly prayed the Ld. CMM, Patiala
            <lb />
            House, New Delhi that he may be permitted to retract
            <lb />
            his statement dated 18/19.10.2021 and same may be
            <lb />
            treated as false and inadmissible. The DRI filed a
            <lb />
            rebuttal dated 24.11.2021 before the Ld. CMM, Patiala
            <lb />
            House, New Delhi stating inter alia that retraction
            <lb />
            application contained untrue averments and are without
            <lb />
            any substance, afterthought, and farce. In reply, DRI
            <lb />
            stated that the applicant tendered his voluntary
            <lb />
            statement under his signature and the said statement
            <lb />
            has also been confirmed in his handwriting towards the
            <lb />
            end. Further, the retraction has been made 10 days of
            <lb />
            the statement; the long gap between the recording of
            <lb />
            the statement and the retraction application makes it
            <lb />
            clear that the retraction application filed by him is an
            <lb />
            afterthought and based on legal tutoring. It was further
            <lb />
            stated by DRI that the applicant was medically
            <lb />
            examined at Ram Manohar Lohia Hospital Delhi and
            <lb />
            thereafter produced before the Ld. Duty Magistrate. As
            <lb />
            per the reply of the DRI filed before the Ld. CMM
            <lb />
            Patiala House, New Delhi no injury marks (fresh or
            <lb />
            otherwise) or bruises was reported by the duty doctors
            <lb />
            during the medical examination.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            xxxvii.
            <lb />
            You i.e. Sanjeev Kumar Yadav filed an application
            <lb />
            dated 28.10.2021 before the Ld. CMM, Patiala House,
            <lb />
            New Delhi stating that the statements dated
            <lb />
            18/19.10.2021 before the DRI officers have been
            <lb />
            obtained under coercion and torture. You accordingly
            <lb />
            prayed the Hon&quot;ble Court that your statement dated
            <lb />
            18/19.10.2021 may be ignored and you mat be allowed
            <lb />
            to retract the same. The DRI filed a rebuttal dated
            <lb />
            24.11.2021 before the Hon&quot;ble Court stating inter alia
            <lb />
            that retraction application contained untrue averments
            <lb />
            and are without any substance, afterthought, and farce.
            <lb />
            In reply, DRI stated that the applicant i.e. you tendered
            <lb />
            your voluntary statement under his signature and the
            <lb />
            said statement has also been confirmed in your
            <lb />
            handwriting towards the end. Further, the retraction has
            <lb />
            been made 10 days of the statement; the long gap
            <lb />
            between the recording of the statement and the
            <lb />
            retraction application makes it clear that the retraction
            <lb />
            application filed by you is an afterthought and based on
            <lb />
            legal tutoring. It was further stated by DRI that the
            <lb />
            applicant i.e. you was medically examined at Ram
            <lb />
            Manohar Lohia Hospital Delhi and thereafter produced
            <lb />
            before the Ld. Duty Magistrate. As per the reply of the
            <lb />
            DRI filed before the Ld. CMM Patiala House, New
            <lb />
            Delhi no injury marks (fresh or otherwise) or bruises
            <lb />
            was reported by the duty doctors during the medical
            <lb />
            examination.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            This above extracted grounds highlight the considerable gap of time
            <lb />
            between the retraction of their statements by the detenus and co-
            <lb />
            detenus, and the rebuttal thereof by the DRI. This belated rebuttal on
            <lb />
            the part of the official respondents was relevant and germane and
            <lb />
            therefore, merited consideration by the Detaining Authority,
            <lb />
            particularly when extensive reliance was evidently placed upon those
            <lb />
            statements. The Detaining Authority would also have been well-
            <lb />
            advised to consider the aspect of admissibility of the statements,
            <lb />
            which stood retracted; and were only belatedly rebutted by the
            <lb />
            Sponsoring Authority, two days before the passing of the impugned
            <lb />
            orders of detention. Further, we find from the record of the Detaining
            <lb />
            Authority that strong reliance has been placed upon the statement of
            <lb />
            not just the detenus but also the statements allegedly recorded of
            <lb />
            Sanjeev Kumar Yadav (Detenu No. 2), statedly the co-accused. In this
            <lb />
            behalf, the record reflects that Detenu No. 2 retracted his statement on
            <lb />
            the very same day as Detenu No. 1 on 28.10.2021, which retraction
            <lb />
            has evidently not been placed before the Detaining Authority by the
            <lb />
            Sponsoring Authority. In our view, once the Detaining Authority
            <lb />
            has relied upon the inculpative statements of the co-accused their
            <lb />
            retractions assumed great relevance in the factual backdrop of the
            <lb />
            present case. Consequently, the admissibility of the said
            <lb />
            statements becomes dubious once there is a retraction, which issue
            <lb />
            merited consideration, was evidently not afforded to it by the
            <lb />
            Detaining Authority. In this behalf, reliance is placed on this Courts
            <lb />
            decision in Gopal Gupta vs. Union of India &amp; Ors. reported as 2021
            <lb />
            SCC OnLine Del 3926.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            33. In this behalf, it is also trite to state that the Sponsoring
            <lb />
            Authority was under a legal obligation to have placed the said
            <lb />
            retractions before the Detaining Authority for the latter&quot;s subjective
            <lb />
            satisfaction. In this regard, it would be beneficial first to consider the
            <lb />
            observations of the Hon&quot;ble Supreme Court in A Sowkath Ali vs.
            <lb />
            Union of India &amp; Others, reported as (2000) 7 SCC 148 and
            <lb />
            particularly in paragraph thereof. The said paragraph is extracted
            <lb />
            hereinbelow for the sake of facility: -
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;20. There can be no doubt, it was not necessary, while considering
            <lb />
            the case of the petitioner detenu, to place all or any of the documents
            <lb />
            which are relevant and are relied on in the proceedings of a co-
            <lb />
            accused, but where the sponsoring authority opts out of its own
            <lb />
            volition to place any document of the other co-detenu, not merely
            <lb />
            as a narration of fact but reiterating in details the confession
            <lb />
            made by him, then it cannot be said it would not prejudice the
            <lb />
            case of the detenu. If this has been done it was incumbent for the
            <lb />
            sponsoring authority to have placed their retraction also. As held
            <lb />
            in Rajappa Neelakantan case [(2000) 7 SCC 144 : (2000) 2 Scale
            <lb />
            642] the placement of document of other co-accused may
            <lb />
            prejudice the case of the petitioner. In the first place the same
            <lb />
            should not have been placed, but if placed, the confessional
            <lb />
            statement and the retraction, both constituting a composite
            <lb />
            relevant fact both should have been placed. If any one of the two
            <lb />
            documents alone is placed, without the other, it would affect the
            <lb />
            subjective satisfaction of the detaining authority. What was the
            <lb />
            necessity of reproducing the details of the confessional statement
            <lb />
            of another co-accused in the present case? If the sponsoring
            <lb />
            authority would not have placed this then possibly no legal
            <lb />
            grievance could have been made by the detenu. But once the
            <lb />
            sponsoring authority having chosen to place the confessional
            <lb />
            statement, then it was incumbent on it to place the retraction
            <lb />
            also made by them. In our considered opinion, its non-placement
            <lb />
            affects the subjective satisfaction of the detaining authority. This
            <lb />
            Court has time and again laid down that the sponsoring
            <lb />
            authority should place all the relevant documents before the
            <lb />
            detaining authority. It should not withhold any such document
            <lb />
            based on its own opinion. All documents, which are relevant,
            <lb />
            which have bearing on the issue, which are likely to affect the
            <lb />
            mind of the detaining authority should be placed before him. Of
            <lb />
            course a document which has no link with the issue cannot be
            <lb />
            construed as relevant.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            34. In a similar vein are the observations of the Hon&quot;ble Supreme
            <lb />
            Court in P. Sarvanan vs. State of T.N. and Others, reported as (2001)
            <lb />
            10 SCC 212 and in particular paragraphs 7, 8 and 9 thereof. The said
            <lb />
            paragraphs as extracted hereinbelow: -
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;7. When we went through the grounds of detention enumerated by
            <lb />
            the detaining authority we noticed that there is no escape from the
            <lb />
            conclusion that the subjective satisfaction arrived at by the detaining
            <lb />
            authority was the cumulative result of all the grounds mentioned
            <lb />
            therein. It is difficult for us to say that the detaining authority would
            <lb />
            have come to the subjective satisfaction solely on the strength of the
            <lb />
            confession attributed to the petitioner dated 7-11-1999, particularly
            <lb />
            because it was retracted by him. It is possible to presume that the
            <lb />
            confession made by the co-accused Sowkath Ali would also have
            <lb />
            contributed to the final opinion that the confession made by the
            <lb />
            petitioner on 7-11-1999 can safely be relied on. What would have
            <lb />
            been the position if the detaining authority was apprised of the fact
            <lb />
            that Sowkath Ali had retracted his confession, is not for us to make a
            <lb />
            retrospective judgment at this distance of time.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            8. The second contention that non-placement of the retraction made
            <lb />
            by Sowkath Ali would not have affected the conclusion as the
            <lb />
            petitioner&apos;s confession stood unsullied, cannot be accepted by us.
            <lb />
            The detaining authority had relied on different materials and it was a
            <lb />
            cumulative effect from those materials which led him to his
            <lb />
            subjective satisfaction. What is enumerated in Section 5-A of the
            <lb />
            COFEPOSA Act cannot, therefore, be applied on the fact situation in
            <lb />
            this case.
        </item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            9. In this context, it is to be mentioned that the detention order
            <lb />
            passed against Sowkath Ali was quashed by this Court when he
            <lb />
            challenged that detention order under Article 32 of the Constitution
            <lb />
            (vide A. Sowkath Ali v. Union of India [(2000) 7 SCC 148 : 2000
            <lb />
            SCC (Cri) 1304 : (2000) 5 Scale 372].&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            35. Further, in Union of India vs. Ranu Bhandari, reported as
            <lb />
            (2008) 17 SCC 348, the Hon&quot;ble Supreme Court has observed so in
            <lb />
            Paragraphs 33, 34 and 35, which are reproduced hereunder: -
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;33. In the instant case, as some of the vital documents which have a
            <lb />
            direct bearing on the detention order, had not been placed before the
            <lb />
            detaining authority, there was sufficient ground for the detenu to
            <lb />
            question such omission. We are also of the view that on account of
            <lb />
            the non-supply of the documents mentioned hereinbefore, the detenu
            <lb />
            was prevented from making an effective representation against his
            <lb />
            detention.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            34. In the said circumstances, we do not see any reason to interfere
            <lb />
            with the judgment and order of the High Court and the appeal is
            <lb />
            accordingly dismissed.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            35. In parting, we may reiterate what we have indicated hereinbefore,
            <lb />
            that since the personal liberty and individual freedom of a citizen is
            <lb />
            curtailed by an order of preventive detention, the detaining
            <lb />
            authorities must apply their minds carefully and exercise great
            <lb />
            caution in passing such an order upon being fully satisfied from
            <lb />
            materials which are both for and against the detenu that such an
            <lb />
            order is required to be passed in the interest of the State and for the
            <lb />
            public good.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            36.
            <lb />
            As regards, the emphasis placed by the respondents on the
            <lb />
            decision of the Hon&quot;ble Supreme Court in Madan Lal Anand vs. UOI,
            <lb />
            reported as (1990) 1 SCC 81, to the effect that it has been held therein
            <lb />
            that only copies of documents, on which the impugned detention
            <lb />
            orders are primarily based should be supplied to the detenus and not
            <lb />
            any and every document; we only observe that it was also clearly held
            <lb />
            therein in paragraph 24 thereof as under: -
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;We must not, however, be understood to say that the detaining
            <lb />
            authority will not consider any other document.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            37. In view of the aforementioned decisions, the legal position that
            <lb />
            emerges on this aspect is that, if the documents are relevant and have a
            <lb />
            direct bearing on the case, they must be placed before the Detaining
            <lb />
            Authority for its &quot;subjective satisfaction&quot;.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            38. The reliance placed by the respondent upon the decision of
            <lb />
            Kamarunnisa vs. Union of India, reported as (1991) 1 SCC 128, does
            <lb />
            not come to their aid, since in the present case we agree with the
            <lb />
            submissions made on behalf of the Detenus, that the present is a case
            <lb />
            of non-placement of vital facts and documents before the Detaining
            <lb />
            Authority owing to their illegibility and that the &quot;subjective
            <lb />
            satisfaction&quot; is vitiated since the latter was not in possession of vital
            <lb />
            RUDs. The ratio in Kamarunnisa (supra) is, therefore, distinguishable
            <lb />
            on the facts thereof. Therefore, we have no hesitation in holding that,
            <lb />
            the Detaining Authority fell into error in relying upon illegible
            <lb />
            documents which is the equivalent of non-placement of RUDs, by the
            <lb />
            act of omitting them from consideration, thereby vitiating its
            <lb />
            subjective satisfaction, for suffering from the vice of non-application
            <lb />
            of mind.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            39. It is trite to say that when a person is detained in pursuance to
            <lb />
            an order of preventive detention, the statutory authorities are
            <lb />
            constitutionally charged with the responsibility of ensuring that the
            <lb />
            grounds of detention, including legible copies of all RUDs and other
            <lb />
            relevant documents that are considered whilst forming the subjective
            <lb />
            satisfaction, are provided to the detenu by the Detaining Authority; so
            <lb />
            as to enable the detenu to make an effective representation to the
            <lb />
            Advisory Board, as well as to the Detaining Authority. Therefore, the
            <lb />
            failure and non-supply of legible copies of all RUDs despite of a
            <lb />
            request and representation made by the Detenus for the supply of the
            <lb />
            same, renders the order of detention illegal and bad in law; and vitiates
            <lb />
            the subjective satisfaction arrived at by the Detaining Authority.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            40. We, therefore, answer the first issue by observing that, the
            <lb />
            Detaining Authority gravely erred in relying upon illegible documents
            <lb />
            which is equivalent to non-placement of RUDs by the act of omitting
            <lb />
            them from due consideration which consequently vitiates the
            <lb />
            subjective satisfaction arrived at by the detaining authority.
            <lb />
            Resultantly, in our considered view, the impugned detention order
            <lb />
            stands invalidated.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            41. It therefore becomes incumbent upon us to determine the
            <lb />
            alternative issue framed hereinabove. Insofar as the second issue, as to
            <lb />
            whether the argument premised on S.5A of the COFEPOSA Act by
            <lb />
            the official Respondents has the effect of saving the detention order; in
            <lb />
            the facts and circumstances of the present case is concerned; we have
            <lb />
            accorded our careful consideration to the rival submissions made
            <lb />
            before us in this regard, in the backdrop of the original records and
            <lb />
            material placed before us in the present proceedings.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            42. The issues as canvassed before this Court on behalf of the
            <lb />
            Detenus is not of mere non supply of legible copies of illegible
            <lb />
            documents despite demand. It is the contention of the Ld. Senior
            <lb />
            Advocate on behalf of the Detenus that had the Detaining Authority
            <lb />
            himself considered the documents for arriving at subjective
            <lb />
            satisfaction, rather than adopting any draft grounds of detention, the
            <lb />
            Detaining Authority would have been alive to the fact that several
            <lb />
            RUDs placed before it were wholly illegible. The specific contention
            <lb />
            canvassed is that the subjective satisfaction of the Detaining
            <lb />
            Authority, which is condition precedent for issuance of the Detention
            <lb />
            Order, is in the circumstance vitiated for non-application of mind. If
            <lb />
            the condition precedent for issuance of a detention order is not
            <lb />
            satisfied, then such an order cannot be saved even by Section 5A of
            <lb />
            the COFEPOSA.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            43. The contention made on behalf of the Detenus needs to be
            <lb />
            examined in light of the aforesaid specific claim on affidavit filed on
            <lb />
            behalf of the Detaining Authority that, &quot;all the documents supplied to
            <lb />
            the detenues were relied upon by it for arriving at subjective
            <lb />
            satisfaction.&quot;
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            44. It is settled law and not in dispute that under section 3 of
            <lb />
            COFEPOSA it is only the detaining authority, which can ultimately
            <lb />
            decide to pass or not, a detention order against any person, and that
            <lb />
            too, after himself perusing each and every document and material
            <lb />
            placed before it. It is also not in dispute that the subjective satisfaction
            <lb />
            of the detaining authority itself is to be arrived at after perusing all the
            <lb />
            relevant documents and material. This is a constitutionally provided
            <lb />
            condition precedent for passing a valid order of Detention. We find
            <lb />
            considerable force in the contention that had the Detaining Authority
            <lb />
            himself perused the RUDs for arriving at its subjective satisfaction and
            <lb />
            formulation of grounds, it would have been alive to the fact that
            <lb />
            various RUDs placed before it were illegible.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            45. It is pertinent to observe the Detenus submission that the order
            <lb />
            of detention was passed in a tearing hurry without due application of
            <lb />
            mind. A timeline of the passing of the detention order is as follows;
            <lb />
            the last document furnished to Detenu is dated 24.11.2017 (RUD-60 to
            <lb />
            64). Since one of the last document is prepared only on 24.11.2017 by
            <lb />
            the counsel for the detenu and filed in the lower Court on the same
            <lb />
            day, copy of which was supplied to the sponsoring authority on
            <lb />
            24.11.2017 itself, which was presumably forwarded by the sponsoring
            <lb />
            authority to the Detaining Authority only on or about 25.11.2021, it is
            <lb />
            axiomatic that it would be humanly impossible for the Detaining
            <lb />
            Authority to scrutinize 977 pages of documents and formulate the
            <lb />
            grounds of detention and thereafter pass the detention order on
            <lb />
            26.11.2017 within a day and a half that too against two detenus. The
            <lb />
            Detaining Authority while arriving at its conclusions, inter alia, in
            <lb />
            Para 11 of the Grounds of Detention has clearly and categorically
            <lb />
            averred as under:
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;11. While passing the Detention Order under the provisions of the
            <lb />
            Conservation of Foreign Exchange and Prevention of
            <lb />
            Smuggling Activities Act; 1974, I have referred to and relief
            <lb />
            upon the documents mentioned in the enclosed list, which are
            <lb />
            also being served to you along with the grounds of detention&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            The paucity of time for the Detaining Authority to himself consider
            <lb />
            the voluminous documents to form its subjective satisfaction, and
            <lb />
            thereafter to formulate lengthy grounds of detention, rather than
            <lb />
            merely approving draft grounds of detention, also tilts the scale in
            <lb />
            favour of the Detenus.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            46. It is pertinent at this juncture to observe that, the official
            <lb />
            Respondents have pleaded the ground of severability under Section
            <lb />
            5A of the COFEPOSA only by way of oral submissions before this
            <lb />
            Court, the same is not reflected in the counter affidavit, barring a
            <lb />
            passing reference to Gautam Jain (Supra) in the written submissions
            <lb />
            filed on behalf of the official Respondents. The omission is found to
            <lb />
            be conspicuous by its absence in the affidavits filed on behalf of the
            <lb />
            official Respondents.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            47. The reliance placed by the respondent upon the decision of
            <lb />
            Gautam Jain vs. Union of India, reported as (2017) 3 SCC 133, does
            <lb />
            not come to their assistance, since in the present case we agree with
            <lb />
            the submissions made on behalf of the Detenus. The Hon&apos;ble Supreme
            <lb />
            Court enunciated therein, the undisputed legal position that, if the
            <lb />
            detention order is based on more than one grounds, independent of
            <lb />
            each other, then the detention order will still survive even if one of the
            <lb />
            grounds is found to be is non-existing or legally unsustainable.
            <lb />
            However, it must be observed that, on the other hand, if the detention
            <lb />
            order is founded substantially on one composite ground, though
            <lb />
            containing various species or sub-heads, the detention order would be
            <lb />
            vitiated if such ground is found fault with.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            48. The instant case, does not attract the dictum enunciated in
            <lb />
            Gautam Jain (Supra), since the grounds of detention in the present
            <lb />
            petition are not severable, in view of the patent and palpable vice of
            <lb />
            non-application of mind by the Detaining Authority antecedent and
            <lb />
            attendant in the passing of the detention order. Premised on averments
            <lb />
            made of behalf of the Respondents, it is found that illegible documents
            <lb />
            supplied to the detenu were clearly and categorically admitted to have
            <lb />
            been relied upon by the Detaining Authority. Therefore, the instant
            <lb />
            case is distinguishable from the aforementioned case; as the very
            <lb />
            grounds of detention in these impugned orders are not severable in the
            <lb />
            peculiar facts and circumstances of the present petition.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            49. In the case of Praduman Singh v. Union of India &amp; Ors.,
            <lb />
            2004 SCC Online Del 446, this Court had held that-
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;15. There seems to be force in this argument because according to
            <lb />
            this reply, the file was submitted to the detaining authority on
            <lb />
            6th May, 2003 along with the document at Sl. No. 37 of the
            <lb />
            relied upon documents together with the draft Grounds of
            <lb />
            detention by the Deputy Secretary (COFEPOSA) so that in
            <lb />
            case the detaining authority ultimately decided to pass the
            <lb />
            detention order against the accused person, it may also like to
            <lb />
            go through the Grounds of detention placed on the file and vet
            <lb />
            the same with whatever changes or additions it may deem fit.
            <lb />
            Whether such a procedure/practice as has been adopted in the
            <lb />
            case can be said to be in accordance with law or established
            <lb />
            procedure and practice which is followed in such like matters?
            <lb />
            We must remember that Section 3 of the Act provides for
            <lb />
            power to make detention order. Sub-Section (1) of Section 3
            <lb />
            of the Act speaks of the authorities who are competent to
            <lb />
            make detention orders. In the case of Central Government, an
            <lb />
            officer not below the rank of a Joint Secretary and in the case
            <lb />
            of State Government, not below the rank of a Secretary to that
            <lb />
            Government, who have been specially empowered for the
            <lb />
            purposes of Section 3, can only make detention orders. This
            <lb />
            clearly depicts the legislative intent that the task of passing a
            <lb />
            detention order can only be entrusted to high/senior
            <lb />
            functionaries of the State. Only such functionaries who are
            <lb />
            specially empowered in this behalf are entitled to pass the
            <lb />
            detention order if they are satisfied that the detention of any
            <lb />
            person is required with a view to preventing him from acting
            <lb />
            in any manner prejudicial to the conservation or augmentation
            <lb />
            of foreign exchange or with a view to preventing him from
            <lb />
            smuggling of goods, etc. Therefore, the satisfaction envisaged
            <lb />
            in Section 3 has necessarily to be of the officer specially
            <lb />
            empowered in that behalf and of nobody else. We do not
            <lb />
            mean to stretch this proposition to the extent that only the
            <lb />
            specially empowered officer himself has to do each and every
            <lb />
            thing in connection with the passing of the detention order. He
            <lb />
            is certainly entitled to take the assistance, from his lower
            <lb />
            functionaries for accomplishing this task but their input will
            <lb />
            be limited only to place the entire material before the
            <lb />
            detaining authority and they should not involve themselves in
            <lb />
            decision making process about the recording of satisfaction.
            <lb />
            That is entirely within the domain of the detaining authority.
            <lb />
            What has been done in the case in hand is somewhat
            <lb />
            disturbing because even before the detaining authority
            <lb />
            considered the matter and applied its mind to the material
            <lb />
            placed before him and recorded his satisfaction about making
            <lb />
            the detention order, the lower functionaries had actually put
            <lb />
            up a draft of detention order for the approval/vetting by the
            <lb />
            detaining authority which implies that the lower functionaries
            <lb />
            presumed that the detaining authority is going to pass the
            <lb />
            detention order in all eventualities/probabilities. Such a
            <lb />
            procedure or practice of putting up draft orders for
            <lb />
            approval/vetting by the competent authorities/senior
            <lb />
            functionaries can perhaps be justified in the routine
            <lb />
            discharge of administrative functions and duties in various
            <lb />
            Ministries and Departments of the Governments while
            <lb />
            dealing with purely administrative matters. The Rules of
            <lb />
            business allocation of the Government permits such a
            <lb />
            procedure but when it comes to the passing of quasi-
            <lb />
            judicial orders or a detention order under various
            <lb />
            preventive detention laws, it has to be different. Adoption
            <lb />
            of such a practice or procedure would vitiate the order as
            <lb />
            the detaining authority is likely to be influenced by such
            <lb />
            an assistance rendered by the lower functionaries, with
            <lb />
            whatever bona fide or sincerity it may be. It would have
            <lb />
            been a different thing if the entire material had been placed
            <lb />
            before the detaining authority and he had applied his mind
            <lb />
            and reached a satisfaction about the need to detain the
            <lb />
            petitioner on certain grounds and then the lower functionaries
            <lb />
            had assisted him in formalising the task of preparation and
            <lb />
            issuance of the detention order. We have, therefore, no
            <lb />
            hesitation in holding that the impugned detention order
            <lb />
            can again be termed as without application of mind by the
            <lb />
            detaining authority himself and the satisfaction recorded
            <lb />
            in the case in hand was not solely of the detaining
            <lb />
            authority. The impugned order is vitiated on this count as
            <lb />
            well.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            50. Significantly, the aforementioned judgement also held,
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;.......Therefore, it is not possible to hold that the impugned
            <lb />
            order which is vitiated on account of non-application of mind by
            <lb />
            the detaining authority, can be saved on the strength of Section
            <lb />
            5A of the Act. We, therefore, hold that the impugned order is
            <lb />
            vitiated and is liable to be quashed on this ground alone.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            51. We are therefore of the considered view that, in cases where
            <lb />
            orders of detention fail on the ground that the subjective satisfaction of
            <lb />
            the Detaining Authority is vitiated owing to non-application of mind;
            <lb />
            the protection afforded qua severability of grounds stipulated under
            <lb />
            the provision of 5A of the COFEPOSA Act, are neither attracted nor
            <lb />
            available, in law.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            52. In view of the foregoing discussion and having accorded our
            <lb />
            thoughtful consideration to the facts and material on record, the issues
            <lb />
            struck hereinabove for consideration; are decided in favour of the
            <lb />
            detenus and against the respondents.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            53. The writ petitions are accordingly allowed. As a result, the
            <lb />
            detention orders bearing No. PD-PD-12001/17/2021-COFEPOSA and
            <lb />
            PD-12001/18/2021-COFEPOSA, both dated 26.11.2021 passed
            <lb />
            against the Detenu No. 1 and No.2 respectively are hereby set-aside
            <lb />
            and quashed. The detenus are directed to be set at liberty forthwith
            <lb />
            unless their custody is required in connection with any other case.
            <lb />
            Pending applications stand disposed of.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            54. The Court Master is directed to return the original file, retained
            <lb />
            for the perusal of this Court, to Mr. Anurag Ahluwalia, learned CGSC
            <lb />
            forthwith.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            55. Copies of this Judgment be provided to the learned counsel
            <lb />
            appearing on behalf of the parties electronically and be also uploaded
            <lb />
            on the website of this Court forthwith.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            SIDDHARTH MRIDUL
            <lb />
            JUDGE
            <lb />
            RAJNISH BHATNAGAR
            <lb />
            JUDGE
            <lb />
            MAY 02, 2022
            <lb />
            dn/ak
        </p>


    </text>
</tei>