<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<figure type="table">
			INDEX
			<lb />
			S. No.
			<lb />
			Particular
			<lb />
			Page
			<lb />
			1.
			<lb />
			The Beginning
			<lb />
			2 to 4
			<lb />
			2.
			<lb />
			Legal Landscape
			<lb />
			4 to 9
			<lb />
			2.
			<lb />
			Stand of Government of India
			<lb />
			(GOI)
			<lb />
			9 to 16
			<lb />
			3.
			<lb />
			Petitioner‟s Arguments
			<lb />
			16 to 17
			<lb />
			4.
			<lb />
			Contention on behalf of R-2 and
			<lb />
			R-3 viz Hockey India and its
			<lb />
			18 to 24
			<lb />
			&quot;Life Member&quot;
			<lb />
			5
			<lb />
			Conclusions and Directions:
			<lb />
			24 to 27
			<lb />
			6
			<lb />
			Accountability
			<lb />
			27 to 30
			<lb />
		</figure>
		<head>
			W.P.(C) 5703/2020 &amp; CM APPLs. 20604/2020, 6417/2021, 36762/2021
			<lb />
		</head>
		<head>
			The Beginning
			<lb />
		</head>
		<p>
			1.
			<lb />
			The petitioner is a former Olympian. He excelled in the game of
			<lb />
			hockey as a member of Indian Hockey Team in the 1976 Summer Olympics.
			<lb />
			He was also a prominent member of the Indian Hockey Team which won the
			<lb />
			gold medal at the 1975 Hockey World Cup. For many years thereafter, he is
			<lb />
			stated to have contributed to the advancement of the cause of hockey in India.
			<lb />
			As a senior player and as a concerned citizen, he desires that the management
			<lb />
			of the hockey in the country, be run according to the rules and the guidelines
			<lb />
			laid-down by the Government of India (GOI) through: i) Circular dated 20 th
			<lb />
			September 1975 (hereinafter referred to as the 1975 Circular) ii) modified by
			<lb />
			letter of 14.8.2001 (the 2001 Guidelines) and iii) the National Sports
			<lb />
			Development Code of India, 2011 (&quot;Sports Code&quot;). He contends that there
			<lb />
			should be transparency in the affairs of the National Sports Federation (NSF)
			<lb />
			for hockey viz. Hockey India -R-2.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			2.
			<lb />
			He is also concerned that the continued presence of certain persons as
			<lb />
			office bearers or otherwise in supernumerary posts or under not so innovative
			<lb />
			nomenclatures, such as Life President, Life Member and CEO is unwarranted
			<lb />
			and illegal, therefore, the same be struck down as not being in consonance
			<lb />
			with the Sports Code, as has already been held by this court in Mahipal Singh
			<lb />
			vs. UOI, 2018 SCC Del 10284.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			3.
			<lb />
			The petition seeks the following specific reliefs:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot;…a) Issue an appropriate Writ in the nature of Certiorari
				<lb />
				quashing Articles 2.1.3, 3.0, 4.1, 5.13, 5.14, 6.6.1 of the
				<lb />
				Respondent No. 2, MOA whereby the posts of &quot;Life Member&quot;,
				<lb />
				&quot;CEO&quot; and &quot;Life President&quot; have been created, being in blatant
				<lb />
				contravention of the NSCI, Circular 1975 and 2001 Guidelines,
				<lb />
				as illegal and unsustainable; and
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				b) Issue an appropriate Writ in the nature of Certiorari quashing
				<lb />
				Articles 1.11, 4.1, 5.3, 6.6.1, insofar as they giving voting rights
				<lb />
				and recognize the posts of &quot;Life Member&quot;, &quot;CEO&quot; and &quot;Life
				<lb />
				President&quot; created in the Respondent No. 2, federation being in
				<lb />
				blatant contravention of the NSCI, Circular 1975 and 2001
				<lb />
				Guidelines as illegal and unsustainable; and
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				c) Issue an appropriate Writ in the nature of Certiorari quashing
				<lb />
				the appointments of the Respondent No. 3 and 4 as &quot;Life
				<lb />
				Member&quot; as &quot;CEO&quot; respectively in the Respondent No. 2
				<lb />
				Federation; and
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				d) Issue an appropriate Writ in the nature of Certiorari quashing
				<lb />
				consequential appointments of the Respondent No. 3 and 4 based
				<lb />
				on their being an office bearers/ life member in the Respondent
				<lb />
				No. 2 federation; and
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				e) Issue an appropriate Writ in the nature of Mandamus
				<lb />
				directing the Respondent No. 3 and 4 to render accounts of all
				<lb />
				gratification and financial benefits received by them from the
				<lb />
				Respondent No. 2 for holding the posts of &quot;Life Member&quot; and
				<lb />
				&quot;CEO&quot; respectively from the time of their appointments until
				<lb />
				date, and refund the same to the accounts of the Respondent
				<lb />
				No.2; and
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				f) Issue an appropriate Writ in the nature of Mandamus
				<lb />
				appointing an impartial Administrator or ad-hoc committee of
				<lb />
				eminent sport persons to administer the affairs and oversee the
				<lb />
				day to day functioning and working of the Respondent No. 2 until
				<lb />
				the MOA of the Respondent No. 2 is amended and fresh elections
				<lb />
				in accordance with the Model Election Guidelines under the
				<lb />
				NSCI are undertaken; and
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				g)Issue an appropriate Writ in the nature of Mandamus
				<lb />
				appointing a Returning officer or directing such Administrator to
				<lb />
				conduct fresh elections of the Respondent No. 2 in accordance
				<lb />
				with the Model Election Guidelines under the NSCI; and
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				h) Issue an appropriate Writ in the nature of Mandamus
				<lb />
				directing the Respondent No. 1 to cancel the affiliation of the
				<lb />
				Respondent No. 2 until the MOA of the Respondent No. 2 is
				<lb />
				amended, appointments of Respondent No. 3 and 4 are
				<lb />
				terminated and fresh elections in accordance with the Model
				<lb />
				Election Guidelines under the NSCI are undertaken…&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<head>
			Legal Landscape:
			<lb />
		</head>
		<p>
			4.
			<lb />
			Mahipal Singh (supra) held, inter alia, as under:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot;62. The Model Election Guidelines annexed to the NSCI and
				<lb />
				constituting a part thereof clearly set out the officers who would
				<lb />
				constitute Office Bearers of the NSF, and the post of &quot;Life
				<lb />
				President&quot; is not among them. Indeed, neither does the NSCI, nor
				<lb />
				do any of the Circulars issued prior thereto, contemplate a post of
				<lb />
				&quot;Life President&quot; in an NSF. While Clause 19 of its pre-amended
				<lb />
				MOA included, in the Office Bearers of the AKFI, only the
				<lb />
				President, Vice Presidents, Honorary General Secretary,
				<lb />
				Honorary Joint Secretaries and Honorary Treasurer, Clause 8.9
				<lb />
				of the amended MOA of the AKFI included, among the Office
				<lb />
				Bearers, the &quot;Life President&quot;. This was, on the face of it, illegal,
				<lb />
				as the NSCI did not visualize any post of Life President at all, in
				<lb />
				an NSF, either as an Office Bearer, or otherwise.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				63. In our opinion, as a beneficiary of the recognition conferred
				<lb />
				by the Government, the AKFI was bound by the stipulations
				<lb />
				contained in the NSCI, and other Cognate Guidelines issued by
				<lb />
				the Government, and had no authority to create posts de hors,
				<lb />
				and in excess of, those contemplated by the NSCI.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				64. Apart from the fact that the AKFI, in its capacity as a NSF
				<lb />
				availing recognition from the Government, did not have any
				<lb />
				authority to create a post of &quot;Life President&quot;, where the NSCI did
				<lb />
				not contemplate the existence of any such post, Clause 15.8
				<lb />
				compounded the illegality by providing that the Life President
				<lb />
				would hold office during his entire life time. This stipulation,
				<lb />
				again, directly infracted the tenure limits, specified in the NSCI
				<lb />
				which, as already noted hereinabove, were binding on all
				<lb />
				recognised NSFs, including the AKFI. The creation of such an
				<lb />
				immortal entity, blessed with the gift of &quot;ichhamrityu&quot; (death at
				<lb />
				will) was, we are certain, not even remotely within the
				<lb />
				imagination, not to say contemplation, of the framers of the NSCI.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				65. Equally, the post of Life President itself being an illegally
				<lb />
				created post, there could be no question of the holder of the said
				<lb />
				post having any right to represent the AKFI at any international
				<lb />
				forum. The NSCI, as well as the Guidelines issued prior thereto,
				<lb />
				clearly permitted representation, by any NSF, in continental or
				<lb />
				international sports events in which India was a participant, only
				<lb />
				if the NSF complied with the stipulations prescribed therein,
				<lb />
				which included adherence to the age specifications and tenure
				<lb />
				limits specified, as well as conducting of elections in accordance
				<lb />
				with the Model Election Guidelines.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				66. In any event, the very creation of the post of Life President
				<lb />
				being vitiated by law, there could be no question of granting any
				<lb />
				benefits to the holder of such an illegally created post. Though
				<lb />
				Mr. Dubey asserted that no salary, or emoluments, were paid to
				<lb />
				Respondent No. 4, in his capacity as Life President, expenses
				<lb />
				would, no doubt, be incurred in allowing Respondent No. 4 to
				<lb />
				travel nationally and internationally, purportedly representing
				<lb />
				the country in sporting events. These expenses are defrayed out of
				<lb />
				public monies, and amount to thievery of the ordinary citizen by
				<lb />
				executive dispensation, which is completely unthinkable in law.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				67. Clauses 8.9, 15.8 and 17.2 of the amended MOA of the AKFI
				<lb />
				are, therefore, declared to be completely illegal, and liable to be
				<lb />
				struck down…&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			5.
			<lb />
			The SLP against the said judgment was dismissed on 31.08.2018.
			<lb />
			Therefore, the said order has attained finality. Its effect is that there can be no
			<lb />
			addition of posts by innovative nomenclatures or creation of new posts in the
			<lb />
			Managing/Executive Committee (MC) of a NSF. In particular, there can be
			<lb />
			no Life President or Life Member in the NSF nor can there be a CEO on the
			<lb />
			Managing Committee, as it perpetuates the presence of some individuals and
			<lb />
			is against the very ethos of a democratically constituted body, be it a Society,
			<lb />
			Association of individuals or a Federation, which the entity must be, to be
			<lb />
			granted recognition by the GOI. The petitioner contends that such illegal posts
			<lb />
			be struck down as being in gross breach of the Sports Code and against the
			<lb />
			dicta of Mahipal Singh. He also contends that there be at least financial
			<lb />
			accountability of those who have deliberately breached the law and illegally
			<lb />
			enjoyed the perks of such illegal positions.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			6.
			<lb />
			Under the Sports Code the &quot;Model Elections Guidelines to be followed
			<lb />
			by all Sports Federations&quot; reads, inter-alia, as under:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot;1. Short Title &amp; Definitions
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(1) These Bye-laws shall be called the &quot;Election Bye-laws&quot; and
				<lb />
				shall govern the conduct of Election of Office Bearers and
				<lb />
				Members of Managing Committee of ________
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(2) In these Bye-laws, unless the context otherwise requires, -
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(a) &quot;clause&quot; ad &quot;sub-clause&quot; mean the clause and sub-clause of
				<lb />
				these Bye-laws;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(b) &quot;Managing members&quot; means Member of Managing Committee
				<lb />
				of _______
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(c) &quot;Form&quot; means the Form appended to these Bye-laws;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(d) _____ means Name of the Federation;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(e) &quot;Post&quot; includes the office of President, Secretary General,
				<lb />
				Treasurer, Vice President, Joint Secretary and Member of
				<lb />
				Managing Committee of _____.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(f) &quot;Rule&quot; means the rule of Rules and Regulations of _______.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				2. Managing Committee:
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(1) The 7 (Seven) Officer Bearers (in addition to 5 executive
				<lb />
				members) shall be as follows:-
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				1. President 1 (one)
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				2. Vice-Presidents 2 (two)
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				3. General Secretary
				<lb />
				1 (One)
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				4. Treasurer
				<lb />
				1 (One)
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				5. Joint Secretaries 2 (Two)
				<lb />
				(Note the above number may be changed according to the
				<lb />
				Constitution of the concerned Federation)
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				3. Manner of Election:
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(1) Office bearers and members of Managing Committee of _____
				<lb />
				shall be elected by secret ballot.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(2) Election shall be held at the Annual General Council Meeting
				<lb />
				(AGM) in accordance with the procedure prescribed hereinafter,
				<lb />
				from amongst the representatives of the Permanent Member
				<lb />
				States/ Union Territories/ Boards/ Institutions.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				4. Electoral College:
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(1) Each Permanent Member State/ Union Territory duly
				<lb />
				affiliated by _____ (abbreviation of Federation) as its Permanent
				<lb />
				Member shall have two votes at the elections of the Office Bearers
				<lb />
				and Managing Committee Members.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(2) For the purposes of sub-clause(1), each Permanent Member
				<lb />
				State/ Union Territory shall be represented by two members
				<lb />
				authorized by the President or Secretary General/ Secretary of the
				<lb />
				affiliated Permanent Member State/ Union Territory; however, in
				<lb />
				case President/ Secretary General/ Secretary nominates different
				<lb />
				person(s) authorized by the President shall be deemed to be the
				<lb />
				duly authorized person(s). Irrespective of the date.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				7. The model nomination paper for election to a &quot;Post&quot; is prescribed as
				<lb />
				under:
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				NOMINATION PAPER FOR
				<lb />
				ELECTION
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				AS____________________________(NAME OF THE POST)
				<lb />
				TO
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(Name and address of returning officer)
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				The Returning Officer for above Election
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				_______________________________
				<lb />
				_______________________________
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				We nominate
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				Shri/Smt./Ms.__________________________________________
				<lb />
				_____________________________________________________
				<lb />
				_____________________(name and address), whose name is
				<lb />
				entered at SI.No.______ in the Electoral College list for the above
				<lb />
				mentioned post.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				2.
				<lb />
				Our particulars are given below:-
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<figure type="table">
			Name of
			<lb />
			candidate
			<lb />
			Name
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			Member
			<lb />
			State/Union
			<lb />
			Territory/Board/Institute
			<lb />
			SI. No. in the
			<lb />
			electoral
			<lb />
			college list
			<lb />
			Sign.
			<lb />
			Proposer
			<lb />
			Seconder
			<lb />
		</figure>
		<list>
			<item>
				I, the candidate above named, do hereby give my assent to my
				<lb />
				nomination for the above post.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				Name of the Candidate______________________
				<lb />
				Name of Member State/Union Territory/ Board/ Institution
				<lb />
				Sl. No. In the electoral College list_______________________
				<lb />
				Signature
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				Place:
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				Date:‖&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				….&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			8.
			<lb />
			Clause 2 of the Model Election Guidelines stipulates that there would
			<lb />
			be seven posts/office bearers and five Executive Members in the Managing
			<lb />
			Committee; elections to the same are to be held at the NSF&quot;s Annual General
			<lb />
			Meeting (AGM) [clause 3(2)].
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			9.
			<lb />
			It is evident from the Model Nomination Paper that for the post of
			<lb />
			office bearers candidates are required to be from one or the other Member
			<lb />
			State, Union Territory, Board or Institution, figuring in the Electoral College
			<lb />
			list.
			<lb />
			Stand of Government of India (GOI):
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			10. Mr. Sachin Datta, the learned Senior Advocate for the Union of India,
			<lb />
			upon instructions, agrees with the said contentions. However, he says that the
			<lb />
			GOI&quot;s letter dated 24.11.2020 should not be construed to mean that the
			<lb />
			Government has permitted the position of Life Member, Life President and
			<lb />
			CEO. The said letter addressed to the President of Hockey India reads inter-
			<lb />
			alia as under:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot;
				<lb />
				No. 32-02/2020-SP-III
				<lb />
				Government of India
				<lb />
				Ministry of Youth Affairs &amp; Sports
				<lb />
				Department of Sports
				<lb />
				…..
				<lb />
				Shastri Bhawan, New Delhi
				<lb />
				24 th November 2020
				<lb />
				To,
				<lb />
				President,
				<lb />
				Hockey India,
				<lb />
				B1/E4, Ground Floor,
				<lb />
				Mohan Cooperative Industrial Estate Mathura Road, New Delhi -
				<lb />
				110044
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				Subject: Holding of Honorary Posts in Hockey India to enable
				<lb />
				members to contest for posts in the International Federation
				<lb />
				Sir,
				<lb />
				I am directed to refer to Hockey India&quot;s letter No.
				<lb />
				HI/MYAS/2020/11/04 dated 17.11.2020 on the above subject and to
				<lb />
				acknowledge the receipt of proposed amendments in Hockey India&quot;s
				<lb />
				constitution. Comments of the Ministry on the said proposed
				<lb />
				amendments in Hockey India&quot;s constitution will be conveyed in due
				<lb />
				course of time.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				2. As regards the honorary post of Life Member, it is informed that
				<lb />
				as there is no specific mention in the National Sports Development
				<lb />
				Code 2011 for the post of honorary life member, it is for the
				<lb />
				respective National Sports Federation to take a view for having life
				<lb />
				members without voting rights in their Executive Body as well as
				<lb />
				General Body.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				3. This issues with the approval of the competent authority.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				Yours faithfully.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				Sd/-
				<lb />
				(S.P.S. Tomar)
				<lb />
				Deputy Secretary to the Government of India&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			11. Comments, if any, of the Government of India to the proposed
			<lb />
			amendments to the Hockey India&apos;s Articles of Association/constitution are not
			<lb />
			on record. However, the suggestions of the Government have been
			<lb />
			implemented, inasmuch as voting rights of the Life President, Life Member
			<lb />
			and CEO have been taken away. Nevertheless, the supernumerary and illegal
			<lb />
			posts of Life President, Life Members and CEO do exist in the constitution of
			<lb />
			R-2, which is not envisaged under the Sports Code as held in Mahipal Singh
			<lb />
			(supra).
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			12. A NSF is envisaged as a dynamic body, its management vests in
			<lb />
			members of a Managing Committee elected through a valid election process.
			<lb />
			The objective of such election is to provide due representation to the best
			<lb />
			talent, resource and skill available. In each Managing Committee, sports-
			<lb />
			persons need to have a representation of at least 25% as mandated in the
			<lb />
			Sports Code. Therefore, conceptually there is no scope for a permanent
			<lb />
			position for any individual in a NSF. Hockey is an Olympic sport. It is also
			<lb />
			categorized as a &quot;priority sport&quot; in India. The spirit of Olympism needs to be
			<lb />
			respected. Olympism promotes space for growth and recognition of the best
			<lb />
			talent in each human generation, so that the individual and the society
			<lb />
			progresses from strength to strength, as aspired in the Olympic motto &apos;Citius -
			<lb />
			Altius -Fortius&apos;: Faster -Higher -Stronger. It is, therefore, vital that the
			<lb />
			meritorious and experienced players in the sport concerned and familiar with
			<lb />
			its needs, be accorded an opportunity to contribute their time, skill and
			<lb />
			expertise in the management of the NSF for advancement of the sport in
			<lb />
			India.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			13. The court is informed that apropos similar innovative and illegal posts
			<lb />
			having been created by Indian Amateur Boxing Federation (&quot;IABF&quot;), the
			<lb />
			Government had unambiguously conveyed to IABF that there could be no
			<lb />
			breach of the Sports Code. Indeed, by order dated 07.12.2012 recognition of
			<lb />
			IABF was suspended. It was put on notice for de-recognition. A copy of the
			<lb />
			said order has been shared between the counsel. It reads as under:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				BY SPEED POST
				<lb />
				No. 19-10/2010-SP.III
				<lb />
				Government of India
				<lb />
				Ministry of Youth Affairs &amp; Sports (Department of Sports)
				<lb />
				(Department of Sports)
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				New Delhi, the 7th December, 2012
				<lb />
				The Secretary General,
				<lb />
				Indian Amateur Boxing Federation,
				<lb />
				Room No. 2 &amp;#, 2nd Floor,
				<lb />
				NDMC Building
				<lb />
				Palika Place, Punchkuian Road,
				<lb />
				New Delhi -110001
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				Subject: Annual General Meeting of Indian Amateur Boxing
				<lb />
				Federation held at Patiala on 23rd September, 2012 and
				<lb />
				holding of election of Office Bearers therein -reg.
				<lb />
				Sir,
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				I am directed to refer to your letter No. IABF/AGM/2012-
				<lb />
				13/0520 dated 19th November, 2012 on the subject mentioned
				<lb />
				above. While examining the reply of the IABF, the following have
				<lb />
				been noticed:
				<lb />
				that the time period between the finalization of the electoral roll
				<lb />
				and the filing of nomination was very short. Since the candidates
				<lb />
				had to file their nominations in person, it was discriminatory
				<lb />
				particularly against the candidates from far flung areas.
				<lb />
				the proposal to amend the constitution in order to create a post
				<lb />
				of Chairman and to permit office bearers of the IABF to be office
				<lb />
				bearers of other NSFs were against the principles of good
				<lb />
				governance and the National Sports Development Code of India,
				<lb />
				2011;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				The decision of the Returning Officer to call for nominations
				<lb />
				from the floor of the House was completely illegal for the
				<lb />
				following reasons:
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(a) No evidence has been produced that indicates that the
				<lb />
				officials list (Electoral College) was widely publicized. In any
				<lb />
				case the time between the publication of the Electoral College
				<lb />
				and the date of nomination is so short, that general publicity,
				<lb />
				except through the website of the IABF would be impossible. This
				<lb />
				also means that persons in the electoral list, without access to the
				<lb />
				internet, would have had no knowledge about the Electoral
				<lb />
				College.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(b) There is no provision in any rule which allows nominations
				<lb />
				from the floor of the House. The Returning Officer completely
				<lb />
				erred in accepting the nominations after the last date of filing of
				<lb />
				nominations and even after the last date for withdrawal.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				2.
				<lb />
				It is, therefore, clear that the elections violated the Sports
				<lb />
				Code Guidelines, the Constitution of the IABF itself and the
				<lb />
				manner in which they were held violated the basic principles of
				<lb />
				Natural justice.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				3. The IABF is therefore, advised to annul the election held at
				<lb />
				Patiala on 23rd September, 2012 with immediate effect and to
				<lb />
				hold fresh elections for all the elective posts under an
				<lb />
				independent Returning Officer in compliance with the National
				<lb />
				Sports Development Code of India, 2011 and declare the results
				<lb />
				of the same afresh. While issuing the Notice, it may be ensured
				<lb />
				that there is sufficient time between finalization and circulation
				<lb />
				of the Electoral College and last date of filing of nominations so
				<lb />
				that all eligible and willing persons could file their nominations.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				4. The recognition granted earlier to the IABF is hereby
				<lb />
				suspended. The IABF is requested to communicate its decision
				<lb />
				regarding holding of fresh elections within 15 days of receipt of
				<lb />
				this letter, failing which the Government may derecognize the
				<lb />
				IABF without any further notice.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				5. A copy of the Notice to be issued for holding the fresh election
				<lb />
				alongwith the name of Returning Officer be also sent to the
				<lb />
				Ministry well in advance.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				6. The Federation is also requested to specify tenure and terms
				<lb />
				and conditions for the post of Chairman created by the
				<lb />
				federation during the AGM held on 23 rd September, 2012. It
				<lb />
				should also be specified in their Constitution that the person
				<lb />
				holding the post of Chairman will not form a part of the
				<lb />
				Electoral College in any future election.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				Yours faithfully,
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(Onkar Kedia)
				<lb />
				Joint Secretary to the Government of India.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(Emphasis Supplied).
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			14.
			<lb />
			Also by its letter dated 16.03.2020, the Government had cautioned the
			<lb />
			All India Tennis Association that the position of Life President and Life Vice-
			<lb />
			President is unnecessary and is contrary to the dicta of this court in Mahipal
			<lb />
			Singh (supra) and is against the Sports Code. Therefore, the said NSF was
			<lb />
			directed to amend its bye-laws within six weeks from the said date. There was
			<lb />
			compliance. The letter to the AITA was regarding creation of post of Life
			<lb />
			President and such similar posts in contravention to the Sports Code. What is
			<lb />
			to be seen from the above is that Mahipal Singh (supra) prohibits creation of
			<lb />
			posts or additional nomenclature being given to any executive body or in the
			<lb />
			General Body of NSF, which is beyond the Model Elections Guidelines.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			15. Apropos the Archery Association of India (NSF for Archery), the
			<lb />
			Supreme Court has by order dated 01.05.2019 in Maharashtra Archery
			<lb />
			Association vs. Rahul Mehra and Ors. (2019) 18 SCC 287 held, inter alia, as
			<lb />
			under:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot; 21. We make it clear that the High Court may also consider the
				<lb />
				stand taken by the appellant(s) and Union of India that the
				<lb />
				decision of this Court in Board of Control for Cricket (supra) will
				<lb />
				be of no avail to the present case, because the National Sports
				<lb />
				Code takes within its fold fifty-two disciplines of sports and
				<lb />
				Cricket is not one of the scheduled sports. In other words, the
				<lb />
				dispensation to be followed must be in conformity with the
				<lb />
				National Sports Code in so far as AAI is concerned. We keep this
				<lb />
				issue open to be considered at the appropriate stage.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(emphasis supplied)
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			16. In effect, till such time that a sports body structures itself according to
			<lb />
			the Sports Code and adheres to its stipulates, it will not be granted recognition
			<lb />
			by the Central Government. In the circumstances, it would be in the fitness of
			<lb />
			things that Hockey India put its house in order lest the Central Government
			<lb />
			shall suspend its recognition and not grant any benefits to it, as has been
			<lb />
			directed in W.P. (C) 2310/2012 titled Indian Olympic Association vs. Union
			<lb />
			of India (2012 DLT 389) which is reproduced hereunder: -
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot;….86. For the foregoing reasons, it is held that the petitioners&quot;
				<lb />
				contentions are rejected. The Court reiterates its conclusions that
				<lb />
				international sports and regulation of NSFs, and IOA, in respect
				<lb />
				of the matters which are the subject of these proceedings, falls
				<lb />
				within Entry 97 of the First List to the Seventh Schedule to the
				<lb />
				Constitution of India. The Central Government can insist upon
				<lb />
				adherence to these provisions, without the aid of legislation. It is
				<lb />
				also held that the Sports Code does not violate the freedom under
				<lb />
				Article 19(1)(c) of the Constitution. Neither are its provisions
				<lb />
				arbitrary. The tenure restrictions impugned in this case can and
				<lb />
				are insisted upon as a part of the public interest in efficient and
				<lb />
				fair administration of such NSFs. This Court also specifically
				<lb />
				notes the letter/notice dated 20.09.1975, which forms part of the
				<lb />
				Sports Code, as modified by the later letter of 01.05.2010, to the
				<lb />
				following extent:
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				&quot;i. The President of any recognized National Sports Federation,
				<lb />
				including the Indian Olympic Association can hold the office for a
				<lb />
				maximum period of twelve years with or without break:
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				ii. The Secretary (or by whatever other designation such as
				<lb />
				Secretary General or General Secretary by which he is referred
				<lb />
				to) and the Treasurer of any recognized National Sports
				<lb />
				Federation, including the Indian Olympic Association, may serve
				<lb />
				a maximum of two successive terms of four years each after which
				<lb />
				a minimum &apos;Cooling off period of four years will apply to seek
				<lb />
				fresh election to either post.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				iii. The President, the Secretary and the Treasurer of any
				<lb />
				recognized National Sports Federation, including the Indian
				<lb />
				Olympic Association, shall cease to hold that post on attaining the
				<lb />
				age of 70 years.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				iv. The other provisions in respect of the tenure limit as contained
				<lb />
				in the letter of 1975 mentioned above shall remain as it is.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				v. The above dispensation will come into operation with
				<lb />
				immediate effect.&quot;
				<lb />
				This regulation (subject to any subsequent amendments) should,
				<lb />
				till appropriate legislation is framed by Parliament, bind the
				<lb />
				parties and all NSFs as a condition for recognition, aid and
				<lb />
				crucially, for the use of the term &quot;India&quot; by any team in
				<lb />
				International Olympic sporting event.&quot; ...
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			Petitioner&quot;s Arguments
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			17. Mr. Vanshdeep Dalmia, the learned counsel for the petitioner submits
			<lb />
			that all NSFs will have to be treated alike. He contends that, that which is not
			<lb />
			permitted directly, cannot be introduced indirectly and illegally, yet this is
			<lb />
			what has been done by Hockey India. It is a brazen endeavour to make
			<lb />
			permanent positions for persons, who may have political, administrative or
			<lb />
			social influence over other members of the NSF, thereby, leading to the lop-
			<lb />
			sided and monopolistic administration of the sports body. He further submits
			<lb />
			that the mere presence of such individuals even in non-voting capacity, asserts
			<lb />
			influence in the subsequent management of the NSF and in the fair and
			<lb />
			independent decision-making process and is undaunted voting process during
			<lb />
			its General Body Meetings, etc.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			18. Insofar as the Sports Code does not provide for any Life Member, Life
			<lb />
			President or CEO in the MC of NSF, vesting authority in such &quot;Posts&quot; to run
			<lb />
			the affairs and/or to have any sway in the management of a NSF is
			<lb />
			impermissible. If such supernumerary positions are created or such persons
			<lb />
			are granted the powers of the MC, the Government of India will be bound not
			<lb />
			to recognize the said NSF. It is desirable that there be consistency and
			<lb />
			predictability in the management and administrative structure of a NSF, as it
			<lb />
			will aid in good governance by bringing about uniformity, discipline and
			<lb />
			transparency in the administration of the sports bodies.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			19. Insofar as the Government has taken a view with respect to IABF, the
			<lb />
			same view would be applicable to all NSFs, including Hockey India. It could
			<lb />
			have been clearly conveyed to R-2 in the letter dated 24.11.2020 that the
			<lb />
			position of Life Member, Life President and CEO, with the voting rights on
			<lb />
			the Managing/Executive Body of Hockey India, was impermissible, and that
			<lb />
			the same should have been discontinued promptly. R-2 should have been put
			<lb />
			to notice of suspension due to non-adherence to the Sports Code. Instead, of
			<lb />
			leaving it to the NSF to take a call in the matter, strict implementation of the
			<lb />
			rules and mandate of the Sports Code was warranted, lest it lend to a
			<lb />
			perception of indulgence or cause confusion.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			20. However, for legitimate management of R-2, some immediate remedial
			<lb />
			measures need to be set in motion without the loss of recognition by GOI.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			Contention on behalf of R-2 and R-3 viz Hockey India and its &quot;Life Member&quot;
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			21. The contention of Hockey India is that the Sports Code itself
			<lb />
			contemplates professionalization of management of sports bodies under the
			<lb />
			following clause:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot; 1.4.9 Professionalisation of management
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				One of the acute problems being faced by many national
				<lb />
				federations is the lack of professional skills to plan and implement
				<lb />
				detailed programmes for the long term development of sports.
				<lb />
				Most office bearers worldwide are in honorary capacity and find
				<lb />
				it difficult to manage the complex workings of large Federations
				<lb />
				without taking outside professional skill. Appointment of
				<lb />
				professionals in such a scenario does not in any way diminish the
				<lb />
				status or responsibility of federation executives.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				Planning in this area should address issues such as
				<lb />
				appointments of staff to handle administration and finance. It
				<lb />
				should also include professional development programmes setting
				<lb />
				up of administrative procedures, improved communication and
				<lb />
				meeting procedures and committee structures.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			22. Ms. Shyel Trehan, the learned counsel for R-3 submits, that it is in
			<lb />
			furtherance of professionalization and good governance of sports
			<lb />
			management, that a CEO was appointed by Hockey India. The court is of the
			<lb />
			view that, there can be no dispute that professional management of NSFs
			<lb />
			could only be for the benefit of the sport and sports-persons. Therefore,
			<lb />
			appointment of CEOs and such other managers cannot be questioned.
			<lb />
			However, an illegality manifests when such CEOs or managers form a part of
			<lb />
			the Executive Body and/or are given a voting right in a NSF. A CEO or other
			<lb />
			manager is at best an employee or a consultant and would have to follow the
			<lb />
			directions and the targets set by the sports body. It is of some comfort though
			<lb />
			that with passage of time, Hockey India has reconsidered its position and
			<lb />
			ensured that no voting rights vest in the Life President, Life Members or
			<lb />
			CEO. Hockey India Federation defines the role of CEO as under:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot; 5.13 CEO
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				The CEO will have all the powers of the Secretary General, will
				<lb />
				be Member of the Executive Board with voting rights and will
				<lb />
				exercise these powers under the guidance and control of
				<lb />
				Secretary General. The CEO in case of unavailability of the
				<lb />
				President will also have the powers given to President under
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				5.4.5. Any such orders made by the CEO must subsequently be
				<lb />
				confirmed by the Working Board/Executive Board or Congress
				<lb />
				as the case may be.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			23. There cannot be two posts with the same executive/management
			<lb />
			powers. The Secretary General is a prescribed /permitted &quot;Post&quot; whereas the
			<lb />
			CEO with voting powers in the Managing Committee, is not. The CEO cannot
			<lb />
			have the powers of the President or the Secretary General of the NSF.
			<lb />
			Therefore, the lavishly but erringly vested powers in the CEO, will have to
			<lb />
			go. It is so ordered. The CEO can at best be an employee or consultant on
			<lb />
			contractual basis.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			24. Mr. Rajiv Nayar, the learned Senior Advocate for R-2 refers to the
			<lb />
			provision for CEO in the management body of International Hockey
			<lb />
			Federation (FIH), the relevant FIH provision reads, inter alia, as under:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot; 8.2. The CEO
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(a) The Executive Board may appoint a CEO on such terms and
				<lb />
				conditions as to remuneration, period of employment (and
				<lb />
				termination thereof) and duties as the Executive Board deems fit.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(b) The CEO shall be a member of the Executive Board. He shall
				<lb />
				be responsible for managing the staff and the day-to-day
				<lb />
				operations of the FIH, for administering its affairs, and for
				<lb />
				implementing the decisions and policies of Congress and the
				<lb />
				Executive Board.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(emphasis supplied)
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			25. It is to be noted that the said structure is specific to the Federation of
			<lb />
			International Hockey. It need not necessarily be adopted by Hockey India.
			<lb />
			The only rules a NSF needs to follow are contained in the Sports Code and as
			<lb />
			interpreted by the courts. A NSF is not answerable to an international body.
			<lb />
			Its legitimacy emanates from the recognition it receives from the Government
			<lb />
			of India. The rules set in India for such recognition have to be followed. As
			<lb />
			noted hereinabove, the GOI has already stated that the addition of posts
			<lb />
			beyond what has been laid down in the Sports Code (Model Election
			<lb />
			Guidelines) is an impermissible innovation, which will render the NSFs&quot;
			<lb />
			recognition liable to suspension and in the case of adamant recalcitrance lead
			<lb />
			to its de-recognition. That being the position, a CEO cannot be a Member of
			<lb />
			the Executive Body nor can the powers of Secretary General or President be
			<lb />
			vested in such Post. It will be open to a NSF to employ specialists and
			<lb />
			managers for the augmentation of the objectives of the NSF but without the
			<lb />
			said individual being a part of the Executive Body or having any voting right
			<lb />
			in the management of the said NSF.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			26. The court is informed that, on an average, the Government spends
			<lb />
			approximately Rs.30-35 crores annually on hockey sporting activities under
			<lb />
			the aegis of Hockey India. However, the unaccounted benefits with respect to
			<lb />
			Government stadia and other infrastructure as well as concessions given
			<lb />
			towards Railways, air travel and sports equipment, which if computed, would
			<lb />
			run into a much larger financial figure. Should a NSF fall foul of the Sports
			<lb />
			Code, it would have no right to retain its recognition with the Government of
			<lb />
			India and the Government is bound to either suspend the recognition for non-
			<lb />
			adherence with the Sports Code or to de-recognize the said NSF. The learned
			<lb />
			counsel for the petitioner says that it may well be considered that NSFs have
			<lb />
			an officer in the scheme of their managements, from the office of the
			<lb />
			Comptroller and Auditor General (&quot;CAG&quot;), to oversee the accounts of the
			<lb />
			NSF at all levels. Let this be considered by the GOI.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			27. The Court is informed that Government of India has unambiguously
			<lb />
			stated its position in its affidavit dated 03.10.2012 in W.P. (Civil) No.
			<lb />
			195/2010, viz Rahul Mehra vs. UOI, that new positions or designations, such
			<lb />
			as Chairmen, Advisors, Consultants, etc. created to accommodate persons
			<lb />
			who have become ineligible for re-elections is impermissible under the Sports
			<lb />
			Code. The said paragraph reads, inter alia, as under:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot;14. That contentions raised by the Petitioner in Para 9 require
				<lb />
				no comments from the answering Respondent as the same are
				<lb />
				matters of record. However, going by the press reports, there
				<lb />
				appears to be some cases in which new positions/offices such as
				<lb />
				Chairman, Advisors, Consultants, etc, have been created in order
				<lb />
				to accommodate officials who have become ineligible for re-
				<lb />
				election as they have completed their maximum tenure and/or age
				<lb />
				as mandated under the Sports Code. When such posts are created
				<lb />
				with an intention to bypass or circumvent the provisions of the
				<lb />
				Sports Code, it amounts to defeating the very purpose of the said
				<lb />
				Sports Code and also violates principles of good governance and
				<lb />
				international best practices. In such cases, it would also entail
				<lb />
				action to derecognize such NSFs for such default.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			28. In the same writ petition the Government has also asserted, by an earlier
			<lb />
			affidavit of 27.05.2012, inter alia as under:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot;10. It is pertinent to mention here that the Government vide its
				<lb />
				communication dated 1st May 2010 issued tenure restrictions for
				<lb />
				the office bearers of the NSF&apos;s which is incorporated in the Sports
				<lb />
				Code. The salient features of the 1st May 2010 communication
				<lb />
				are:
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				a. The President of any recognized NSF, including the IOA can
				<lb />
				hold the office for a maximum period of 12 years, with or without
				<lb />
				break.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				b. The Secretary/Secretary General/General Secretary and the
				<lb />
				Treasurer of any recognized NSF and the IOA, may serve a
				<lb />
				maximum of two successive terms of four years each, after which a
				<lb />
				minimum cooling off period of four years would apply to seek
				<lb />
				fresh election to either post.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				c. The President, Secretary and the Treasurer of any recognized
				<lb />
				NSF and the 1OA, would cease to hold the post on attaining the
				<lb />
				age of 70 years.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				d. The other provisions in respect of the tenure limit as contained
				<lb />
				in the 1975 Guidelines were to remain unaffected.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				e. It would not disturb the current tenure of any member, provided
				<lb />
				he/she has been properly elected to the post and would be
				<lb />
				operative for all future elections to be conducted as per the
				<lb />
				normal course in the IOA as well as NSFs.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				f. Compliance with the aforesaid directions would be a mandatory
				<lb />
				precondition for receiving any form of assistance, financial or
				<lb />
				otherwise from the Government of India as well as to derive the
				<lb />
				authority to perform public functions of selection, deputation of
				<lb />
				national teams for participation in recognized continental and
				<lb />
				world level international sports competitions which involve
				<lb />
				representation of member countries, and to represent the country
				<lb />
				in international associations, events, meets, conferences etc.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			29. Copies of the said affidavits have been handed-over by the learned
			<lb />
			counsel for the petitioner to the learned counsel for the parties. There is no
			<lb />
			dispute apropos Government of India&quot;s clear stand as noted above. A NSF, in
			<lb />
			particular its Managing/Executive Committee (MC), has to ensure that each
			<lb />
			member on the MC is eligible for, elected to and serves in that capacity, in
			<lb />
			strict adherence with the Sports Code. No deviation from the Guidelines,
			<lb />
			Circulars and the dicta of courts is permissible. Should any NSF do so, it will
			<lb />
			render itself out of the game. The GOI will promptly suspend its recognition,
			<lb />
			till the NSF conforms to the law, as discussed above. Indeed, the GOI has
			<lb />
			already ensured so, in the case of NSF&quot;s representing tennis, boxing,
			<lb />
			wrestling, and some other sport disciplines. Such nature of prompt and
			<lb />
			equivalent action by the Government for strict adherence to the Sports Code
			<lb />
			apropos all NSF would be expected.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			30. In Narinder Batra vs UOI [ILR (2009) 4 Del 280] this court has
			<lb />
			emphasized the primary obligation of NSFs towards players in
			<lb />
			contradistinction to the perks enjoyed by the Office Bearers of the NSFs. It
			<lb />
			has observed as under:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot;…Today sports is no more something that can be dealt with in a
				<lb />
				meeting over a five star meal. It requires technical knowledge of both
				<lb />
				the game, the equipment and the training. Every aspect from the
				<lb />
				aerodynamics in equipment, even of the clothes worn by an athlete to
				<lb />
				shoes of a hockey/football/basket player; hair cut of the swimmer to
				<lb />
				&apos;weight and material of the equipment used is governed by scientific
				<lb />
				details and principles. In times of expertise, sports management
				<lb />
				experts are as important to a good sports programme just as
				<lb />
				experienced competent players or ex-players in decision and policy
				<lb />
				making areas who would ensure that the sports persons got the same,
				<lb />
				if not better residential/hotel and other facilities as the office bearers
				<lb />
				at national and international competition venues; who understood
				<lb />
				how important good treatment is for the self esteem and confidence of
				<lb />
				the teams and sports persons, especially when their opponents get the
				<lb />
				best; where real expenditure is incurred on and energy is devoted to
				<lb />
				sports persons rather than on maintenance of the office bearers or
				<lb />
				squabbles over elections. Only then could it be said that the sporting
				<lb />
				credentials or the tenure of the controlling board is immaterial for the
				<lb />
				interest of the sport….&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			31. It is hoped that monies shall be expended largely on sports persons,
			<lb />
			their training, equipment, healthy diet and the best of travel facilities and
			<lb />
			accommodation. The expenses incurred on the NSF&quot;s MC or its officials
			<lb />
			should not be extravagant, disproportionate or unnecessary.
			<lb />
			Conclusions and Directions:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			32. The 1975 Circular, the 2001 Guidelines, the Sports Code and the
			<lb />
			judgement of the Courts, govern sports administration in India. They
			<lb />
			collectively constitute the law on the subject. They have held sway over 57
			<lb />
			years. They are here to stay. No variation of the same, to the detriment of
			<lb />
			sports-persons or to sports administration, is permissible.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			33. Sports does not merely infuse a spirit of healthy competition among
			<lb />
			players, spectators and enthusiasts, it also gives people a unifying cause to
			<lb />
			rally behind, of course, with much passion and fun. Often the heart-beat of a
			<lb />
			nation is hinged on that subtle nick to the ball into the goal-post, in the last
			<lb />
			moments of a game. But, above all, it teaches discipline and respect for rules
			<lb />
			and to acknowledge the legitimate winner. It is a sublimation of physical
			<lb />
			energies and mental alacrity in a fair competition, to acknowledge a clear
			<lb />
			winner. It is a celebration of fair play. There can be no clandestine ways to
			<lb />
			win, as that would not be sport. Fairness on the play-field, admirable skills of
			<lb />
			players, unity of purpose, team-work and coordination, etc. are qualities and
			<lb />
			values which any sport, played fairly, imparts and instills in society.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			34. Indeed, it is this spirit which is manifested in the Objective of the
			<lb />
			Sports Code. It reads inter alia:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot;.....1.1 Sports development is a national priority, as it promotes
				<lb />
				active lifestyle, child and youth development, social
				<lb />
				inclusiveness, employment opportunities, peace and development,
				<lb />
				and above all a sense of belongingness and national pride...&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			35. In view of the above, the administrative setup of R-2, is, erroneously or
			<lb />
			illegally constituted because of the Life President and Life Members. The
			<lb />
			Government of India cannot grant recognition to a NSF whose constitution is
			<lb />
			not in consonance with the Sports Code. The posts of Life President, Life
			<lb />
			Member in the NSF are illegal so is the post of CEO in the Managing
			<lb />
			Committee. These posts are struck-down. All such references in the
			<lb />
			Constitution/Memorandum of Association of R-2 will have to be removed. As
			<lb />
			noted hereinabove, the mere presence of some persons in a Society as a
			<lb />
			Member or in a meeting, albeit without voting rights can influence
			<lb />
			independent decision-making and election process. Till such time it is
			<lb />
			brought in consonance with the Sports Code and as interpreted by this court,
			<lb />
			its affairs cannot be left in the hands of persons who have no legitimacy. In
			<lb />
			the absence of a Managing Committee, elected under a constitution strictly in
			<lb />
			consonance with the Sports Code and the court judgments, the interests of
			<lb />
			hockey, its development and the sentiments of the hockey-players, aspirants
			<lb />
			and enthusiasts should not suffer. Therefore, it would be in the public interest
			<lb />
			that its affairs be put in the hands of a Committee of Administrators (&quot;CoA&quot;)
			<lb />
			as has been directed by the Supreme Court on 18 th May 2022, in the case of
			<lb />
			another NSF in All India Football Federation vs. Rahul Mehra &amp; Ors (SLP
			<lb />
			(Civil) Nos. 30748-30749/2017). Accordingly, following three persons of
			<lb />
			eminence from the fields of law, public administration and elections, and
			<lb />
			from the sport of hockey at national and international levels, are appointed as
			<lb />
			members of the CoA:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				(i) Mr Justice Anil R Dave, former Judge of the Supreme Court;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(ii) Dr S.Y Qureshi, IAS, former Chief Election Commissioner; and
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(iii) Mr Zafar Iqbal, former Olympian and captain of the Indian
				<lb />
				Hockey team, Padmashri awardee.
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			32. Concurrence of the members of the CoA would be sought, for their
			<lb />
			assistance. Their functions shall largely be the same as outlined by the
			<lb />
			Supreme Court in All India Football Federation vs. Rahul Mehra (supra)
			<lb />
			which are that the CoA shall:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				(i) assist in the preparation and adoption of the Constitution of R2 as per
				<lb />
				the Sports Code and court rulings;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(ii) prepare the electoral roll/college for the purpose of conducting the
				<lb />
				elections to the Executive Committee in accordance with the provisions
				<lb />
				of the Constitution, as proposed;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(iii) carry out the day-to-day governance of R-2;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(iv) In discharging its task in terms of (iii) above, the CoA would be at
				<lb />
				liberty to take the assistance of the erstwhile EC/MC of R-2 which has
				<lb />
				continued thus far in order to facilitate decisions being taken, inter alia,
				<lb />
				on the holding of tournaments, selection of players and all other matters
				<lb />
				necessary for the proper governance of R-2;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(v) The erstwhile Committee shall forthwith hand over the charge to the
				<lb />
				CoA;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(vi) The CoA would be at liberty to make all appropriate arrangements,
				<lb />
				for the governance of Hockey India until fresh elections are held in terms
				<lb />
				of the Sports Code conforming constitution;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(vii) facilitate the holding of elections and the handing over of the affairs
				<lb />
				to a democratically elected body in terms of its constitution which will
				<lb />
				be adopted, preferably within a period of 20 weeks from the date the
				<lb />
				learned CoA members give their assent.
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			33. The honorarium payable to the CoA members and facilities to be
			<lb />
			extended to them will be akin to what may be fixed in All India Football
			<lb />
			Federation vs. Rahul Mehra (supra). For the moment, a deposit of Rs. 3 lacs
			<lb />
			per month shall be made with each CoA member to meet expenses, etc.
			<lb />
			Accountability
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			34. Individuals who have exhausted their age and/or tenure in terms of the
			<lb />
			Sports Code automatically disqualify themselves from contesting for any
			<lb />
			Executive Posts. The mere fact that the constitution of the NSF is not aligned
			<lb />
			with the Sports Code of 2011 and the law, it will not be to the advantage of
			<lb />
			either the NSF or its office-bearers. The age and tenure restrictions came into
			<lb />
			effect from 1 st May 2010. The Sports Code only reiterates it in 2011. Persons
			<lb />
			who have been in posts such as Life President, Life Member and &quot;CEO on the
			<lb />
			Management Committee&quot; (with voting rights), which is clearly in breach of
			<lb />
			the Sports Code, and have enjoyed benefits of such office and expenses have
			<lb />
			been incurred on them by a NSF in breach of the law must be asked to return
			<lb />
			the expended amounts. Revenues generated by a NSF is largely on account of
			<lb />
			recognition granted to it by the Government of India. In the absence of such
			<lb />
			recognition, the Society/Association would have no legitimacy or occasion to
			<lb />
			seek or attract sponsorship for any tournament, sporting event, travel,
			<lb />
			accommodation, training and/or other administrative measures. The monies
			<lb />
			which are so generated by a NSF, are more in the nature of public trust and
			<lb />
			the same is to be utilized in the public interest i.e. promotion of the sport and
			<lb />
			representation of India in international tournaments. The CoA shall ascertain
			<lb />
			the amount spent on such individuals and initiate process for recovery of the
			<lb />
			same, so shall the GOI. Expenses incurred on such supernumerary,
			<lb />
			innovative and illegal posts need to be recovered and there has to be
			<lb />
			accountability. Details of the amounts expended on such persons will be
			<lb />
			furnished by Hockey India before the CoA. The latter too shall examine the
			<lb />
			records and seek refund of monies from the current Life President and the
			<lb />
			Life Members, as may be.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			35. The court is informed that the CEO, in the present case, is a person
			<lb />
			experienced in the game of hockey and has assisted the Indian team, in the
			<lb />
			capacity of an administrator; the CEO has no voting rights in the management
			<lb />
			of R-2; the CEO&quot;s assistance has been rendered on the basis of a contract, and
			<lb />
			not as an Office Bearer; her assistance was clearly on day-to-day basis for the
			<lb />
			Indian Hockey team. In the circumstances, the Court is of the view that
			<lb />
			recovery against the current CEO would not be warranted. Regarding
			<lb />
			retention of the services of the CEO as a consultant, the CoA may decide.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			36. Logically then, the non-refund of such monies, as may be quantified,
			<lb />
			would render the individuals &quot;ineligible&quot; for holding any &quot;Post&quot; in the
			<lb />
			Managing Committee of a NSF. No premium can accrue to a person or entity
			<lb />
			for non-compliance with the law. It is a matter of record that R-3, the current
			<lb />
			&quot;Life-President&quot; of Hockey-India, had successfully pursued the removal and
			<lb />
			derecognition of the erstwhile Indian Hockey Federation (&quot;IHF&quot;) because its
			<lb />
			then President was entrenched as its President for 11 years. In R-3&quot;s said writ
			<lb />
			petition 1 this court had directed Government of India to investigate and
			<lb />
			enquire, if deemed necessary, apropos expenses made and to examine all
			<lb />
			complaints regarding breach of guidelines and grant of financial and other
			<lb />
			assistance to IHF.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			37. In Mahipal Singh the Court had directed the GOI to take steps
			<lb />
			regarding recovery of monies expended on persons who had occupied illegal
			<lb />
			positions in the Amateur Kabaddi Federation of India.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			38. It was directed as under:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot; 78. Given the totally clandestine and surreptitious manner in
				<lb />
				which the provisions of the MOA were illegally amended, in
				<lb />
				order to enable Respondent No. 5 to contest for the post of
				<lb />
				President, we further direct that Respondent No. 5 render
				<lb />
				accounts of all financial benefits, which have enured to
				<lb />
				Respondent No. 5, as and in her capacity as President of the
				<lb />
				AKFI since the time of her appointment to the said post on 19 th
				<lb />
				May, 2013 until date, and the same be recovered from her,
				<lb />
				forthwith.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			39. It is not known what was the follow-up, if any ensued. The age and
			<lb />
			tenure restrictions of the Sports Code as well as the cooling-off period
			<lb />
			between successive terms in the Managing Committee of a NSF, coupled with
			<lb />
			the necessary 2/3 rd votes for the second term, are clear safeguards against
			<lb />
			permanent positions in a NSF. What cannot be done &quot;per directum&quot; is not
			<lb />
			permitted &quot;per obliquum&quot; meaning thereby, that, whatever is prohibited by
			<lb />
			law cannot be effected by an indirect or circuitous contrivance.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			40. R-3 knew fully well that the post of Life President and Life Member in
			<lb />
			a NSF is illegal. He had been specifically intimated so by the Government of
			<lb />
			India. Yet when Hockey India was registered as a Society under the Societies
			<lb />
			Registration Act 1860, on 28.05.2009 and was granted prompt recognition by
			<lb />
			the Government of India within a couple of days thereof, R-3 went ahead and
			<lb />
			had himself appointed as Life Member of Hockey India. This smacks of
			<lb />
			brazen impertinence to the clear mandate of law. It was a less than honest
			<lb />
			but futile endeavour to institutionalize oneself in a body whose legitimacy
			<lb />
			itself is contingent upon conformity with the Sport Code and the law. What a
			<lb />
			paradox, to make oneself permanent in an entity whose tenure itself is
			<lb />
			impermanent. The illegal Post of Life President or Life Member cannot be
			<lb />
			the stepping-stone for any other position or benefit elsewhere, be it nationally
			<lb />
			(including in the Indian Olympic Association) or in international bodies. If
			<lb />
			R-3 has so benefitted, then such benefit or position shall end right away. Let
			<lb />
			the CoA look into the matter, so would the Government of India.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			41. It will be open to the petitioner and the CoA to approach the Court in
			<lb />
			case of any difficulty.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			42. The petition is allowed and disposed off in terms of the above.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			NAJMI WAZIRI, J.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			SWARANA KANTA SHARMA, J.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			MAY 25, 2022
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			RW/ZP/SK
		</p>
	</text>
</tei>
