<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot;यद्यदाचरति श्रे ष्ठस्ित्तदे वे िरो जनः। स यत्प् रमाण ं कु रुिे लोकस्िदनु वित िे ।।&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			1.
			<lb />
			The shloka from Bhagwad Gita succinctly states -whatever action
			<lb />
			is performed by a leader, common men follow in his footsteps; and
			<lb />
			whatever standards he sets by his acts, are pursued by his subjects. &quot;With
			<lb />
			great power comes great responsibilities&quot; -goes another popular quote.
			<lb />
			Digitally Signed By:DAMINI
			<lb />
			The persons who are mass leaders and occupy high offices must conduct
			<lb />
			themselves with utmost integrity and responsibility. Leaders elected in a
			<lb />
			democracy like that of India, owe their responsibility not only towards the
			<lb />
			electorate in their own constituency, but also towards the society/nation
			<lb />
			as a whole and ultimately to the Constitution. It is they who are the role
			<lb />
			models for the ordinary masses. Thus, it does not befit or behove the
			<lb />
			leaders to indulge in acts or speeches that cause rifts amongst
			<lb />
			communities, create tensions, and disrupt the social fabric in the society.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			2.
			<lb />
			Hate speeches especially delivered by elected representatives,
			<lb />
			political and religious leaders based on religion, caste, region or ethnicity
			<lb />
			militate against the concept of fraternity, bulldoze the constitutional
			<lb />
			ethos, and violates Articles 14, 15, 19, 21 read with Article 38 of the
			<lb />
			Constitution and is in blatant derogation of the fundamental duties
			<lb />
			prescribed under Article 51-A (a), (b), (c), (e), (f), (i), (j) of the
			<lb />
			Constitution and therefore warrant stringent peremptory action on the part
			<lb />
			of Central and State Governments.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			3.
			<lb />
			The instant petition arises out of the impugned order of dismissal
			<lb />
			of Application of Petitioners under Section 156 (3) of Code of Criminal
			<lb />
			Procedure, 1973 (hereinafter referred to as the &quot;Code&quot;) dated 26.08.2020
			<lb />
			passed in Ct. Case No. 04/2020 titled Brinda Karat &amp; Anr. v. State, by the
			<lb />
			Court of the Ld. Additional Chief Metropolitan Magistrate (I), Rouse
			<lb />
			Avenue Courts, Delhi (hereinafter referred to as the &quot;ACMM&quot;). By way
			<lb />
			of the instant petition, the petitioners have prayed as under:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				a. Pass a Writ of Certiorari setting aside/quashing Order
				<lb />
				dated 26.08.2020 passed in Brinda Karat &amp; Anr. v. State,
				<lb />
				Ct. Cas. No. 04/2020, by the Ld. Additional Chief
				<lb />
				Metropolitan Magistrate (I), Rouse Avenue Courts,
				<lb />
				Delhi; and
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				b. Without prejudice to Prayer (i), exercise jurisdiction
				<lb />
				under Article 227 read with S.483 CrPC directing
				<lb />
				expeditious disposal of Applications under Section 156(3)
				<lb />
				CrPC and direct that technical objections and
				<lb />
				maintainability be decided at the threshold to avoid
				<lb />
				prejudice to the Complainant and wastage of judicial
				<lb />
				time; and
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				c. Issue directions in the nature of a writ of mandamus
				<lb />
				under Article 226 of the Constitution to the Respondent
				<lb />
				State to widely publicize the manner in which such prior
				<lb />
				sanction can be obtained by a complainant / applicant
				<lb />
				preferring a Complaint under Section 200 CrPC, for the
				<lb />
				offences mentioned in Ss. 195 and 196 CrPC, to facilitate
				<lb />
				access to justice.
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<head>
			FACTUAL MATRIX
			<lb />
		</head>
		<p>
			4.
			<lb />
			The matter has arisen out of the facts as detailed hereunder:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				a. Both the petitioners are politicians of the Communist
				<lb />
				Party of India (Marxist) (hereinafter &quot;CPI(M)&quot;). As per
				<lb />
				the contents of the petition, Petitioner No. 1 is a member
				<lb />
				of the Polit Bureau of the CPI(M) and a former Member
				<lb />
				of Parliament. Petitioner No. 2 is a member of the Central
				<lb />
				Committee of the CPI(M), in addition to being the
				<lb />
				Secretary of Delhi State Committee of CPI(M).
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				b. It is the petitioners&apos; case that on 27 th January 2020, Mr.
				<lb />
				Anurag Thakur, a Union Minister and Member of
				<lb />
				Parliament, allegedly made a hate speech at a rally in
				<lb />
				Rithala shouting the slogan &quot;desh ke gaddaron ko&apos;&apos; and
				<lb />
				exhorting the crowd to respond with &quot;goli maaron saalon
				<lb />
				ko&quot;.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				c. It is further alleged that on 28 th January 2020, Mr.
				<lb />
				Parvesh Verma, Member of Parliament from West Delhi
				<lb />
				Lok Sabha Constituency, made inflammatory hate
				<lb />
				speeches while campaigning for the Bharatiya Janata
				<lb />
				Party (hereinafter &quot;BJP&quot;). Allegations are also levelled
				<lb />
				against him qua his interview to ANI, wherein he is
				<lb />
				stated to have threatened use of force to remove
				<lb />
				protestors at Shaheen Bagh and promoting hatred and
				<lb />
				enmity by portraying them as invaders.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				d. As per the petition, the petitioners on 29 th January 2020
				<lb />
				made a complaint against Mr. Anurag Thakur and Mr.
				<lb />
				Parvesh Verma to the Commissioner of Police, Delhi
				<lb />
				asking for registration of FIR against the two alleging
				<lb />
				them of having committed serious cognizable offences of
				<lb />
				inciting communal enmity, extending threats and making
				<lb />
				statements prejudicial to national integration.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				e. In furtherance of the said complaint, on 31 st January
				<lb />
				2020, another letter was addressed to the Commissioner
				<lb />
				stating therein that because of inaction of police over
				<lb />
				their complaint has led to an incident wherein, according
				<lb />
				to the letter, an armed man shot at protesting students. In
				<lb />
				this second letter the petitioners again urged the
				<lb />
				Commissioner to take immediate action, file FIRs and
				<lb />
				take preventive steps against Hindu Sena.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				f. On 2 nd February 2020, the petitioners, by way of a letter
				<lb />
				addressed to the SHO, Parliament Street Police Station,
				<lb />
				New Delhi, made a request to immediately file FIRs
				<lb />
				against Mr. Anurag Thakur and Mr. Parvesh Verma,
				<lb />
				enclosing therein the two aforementioned representations
				<lb />
				made earlier to the Commissioner.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				g. Subsequently, on 5 th February 2020, the Petitioners filed
				<lb />
				an Application under Section 156(3) of Code seeking
				<lb />
				registration of FIR before the Additional Chief
				<lb />
				Metropolitan Magistrate (I), Rouse Avenue Courts,
				<lb />
				Delhi, which was registered as Ct. Case No.04/2020. The
				<lb />
				Application, inter alia, sought for registration of FIR
				<lb />
				against the accused persons for offences under Sections
				<lb />
				153A/153B/295A/298/504/505/506 of the Indian Penal
				<lb />
				Code, 1860.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				h. ATR was called from the DCP District New Delhi.
				<lb />
				Subsequently, as per the record of the proceedings of the
				<lb />
				Court below, on 11 th February 2020, ATR was filed by
				<lb />
				the Special Investigation Unit of Crime Branch and was
				<lb />
				taken on record. On the said date, the Crime Branch was
				<lb />
				directed to expedite the preliminary inquiry and file the
				<lb />
				detailed ATR in next 15 days.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				i. In the proceedings dated 26 th February 2020, the status
				<lb />
				report was filed by the investigating agency, wherein it
				<lb />
				was recorded that on the basis of allegations levelled in
				<lb />
				the complaint, prima facie no cognizable offence was
				<lb />
				found to be committed. The Copy of the Status Report
				<lb />
				was supplied to the other side and arguments were heard.
				<lb />
				The matter was posted for orders on 2nd March 2020.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				j. On 2 nd March 2020, the Court of ACMM-I was informed
				<lb />
				that a WP (CRL) 565/2020 titled as &quot;Harsh Mander and
				<lb />
				Another v. GNCTD and Others&quot; was pending before this
				<lb />
				High Court containing the same averments and seeking
				<lb />
				the same relief as was being made in the petitioners&apos;
				<lb />
				application. In view of the fact that the High Court was
				<lb />
				already seized of the matter and had listed the matter for
				<lb />
				13 th April 2020 giving the opportunity to the Union of
				<lb />
				India for filing its response, the ACMM chose not to pass
				<lb />
				any order in the application till the outcome of the said
				<lb />
				writ petition.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				k. On 26 th August 2020, the ACMM dismissed the
				<lb />
				Petitioners&apos; Application under Section 156(3) of the
				<lb />
				Code, recording the finding that the application was not
				<lb />
				tenable in the eyes of law on the ground that there was no
				<lb />
				previous
				<lb />
				sanction
				<lb />
				obtained
				<lb />
				by
				<lb />
				the
				<lb />
				complainants/petitioners from the competent authority to
				<lb />
				prosecute the named individuals for the offences alleged
				<lb />
				in the complaint.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				l. Aggrieved by the said Order, the petitioners have
				<lb />
				approached this Court under Articles 226/227 of the
				<lb />
				Constitution of India read with Sections 482/483 of the
				<lb />
				Code praying inter alia for setting aside of the impugned
				<lb />
				Order.
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<head>
			SUBMISSIONS
			<lb />
		</head>
		<p>
			5.
			<lb />
			Learned counsel appearing on behalf of the petitioners submitted
			<lb />
			that the communal, incendiary, and hateful speeches made by Mr. Verma
			<lb />
			and Mr. Thakur directly contributed towards fostering an atmosphere of
			<lb />
			hatred and division targeting a particular religious community. It is
			<lb />
			submitted that the speeches further served to embolden persons and
			<lb />
			contributed significantly to a rise in hostility and enmity against the anti-
			<lb />
			CAA protestors, resulting in multiple incidents of threats and violence.
			<lb />
			Some such incidents were enumerated in the Petitioner&apos;s Application
			<lb />
			under Section 156(3) CrPC and are also enumerated in the present
			<lb />
			Petition.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			6.
			<lb />
			Additionally, it is submitted that the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court in
			<lb />
			Amish Devgan v. Union of India and Ors. (2021) 1 SCC 1, has held that
			<lb />
			the impact of hate speech depends on the person who has uttered the
			<lb />
			words and a speech by a person of influence, such as a top government
			<lb />
			functionary or political leader of following, therefore carries far more
			<lb />
			credibility and impact than a common person. The Supreme Court further
			<lb />
			held that malicious intent can be derived from the context of the speech
			<lb />
			itself, the identity of the speaker, the targeted and non-targeted group, the
			<lb />
			context and circumstances when such speech was made and proximate
			<lb />
			nexus with the harm.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			7.
			<lb />
			It is submitted that in the present case, the speeches were made by
			<lb />
			influential political leaders to large groups of people during elections with
			<lb />
			the clear intent to promote hatred and enmity against persons from a
			<lb />
			particular community. It is stated that the tacit endorsement of such
			<lb />
			communal sentiment resulted in multiple escalating incidents of threats
			<lb />
			and violence.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			8.
			<lb />
			Further, it is submitted that the hate speeches made by Mr. Thakur
			<lb />
			and Mr. Verma evidently sought to refer to an identifiable set of persons,
			<lb />
			fomenting inimical sentiments against them, and such persons clearly fall
			<lb />
			within a &quot;religion&quot; or &quot;community&quot; of persons as envisaged in Section
			<lb />
			153A of IPC.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			9.
			<lb />
			It is submitted that the context in which the utterance was made by
			<lb />
			the accused makes it amply clear that the same constitutes hate speech. It
			<lb />
			is stated that the speeches were also prima facie intended to promote
			<lb />
			hatred, enmity and ill-will against such a community. Even without such
			<lb />
			escalation, the content of the speeches is divisive and communal in
			<lb />
			nature.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			10. It is also submitted that the ingredients of the offences of hate
			<lb />
			speech under Sections 153A/ 153B/ 295A/ 298/ 504/ 505/ 506 of IPC
			<lb />
			have clearly been made out in the facts and circumstances of this case.
			<lb />
			The police have not only a legal obligation but also a duty of care and
			<lb />
			protection towards the public and ought to have registered an FIR on the
			<lb />
			Complaint of the Applicant at the first instance.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			11. It is submitted that it is a settled law that no sanction is required in
			<lb />
			order to register an FIR by the police; failing which, it is well-within the
			<lb />
			powers of the Magistrate to direct investigation under Section 156(3) of
			<lb />
			Code. It is submitted that if the said judicial power is ousted, there will be
			<lb />
			no recourse for genuine complainants against the inaction of the police in
			<lb />
			a case such as the present one.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			12. It is submitted that even otherwise, there is no procedure prescribed
			<lb />
			for an individual to approach the competent authorities to obtain sanction
			<lb />
			under Section 196 of the Code, prior to filing an Application under
			<lb />
			Section 156(3) of the Code. If an individual were to approach authorities
			<lb />
			for grant of sanction, such individual would necessarily need to collect all
			<lb />
			evidence that is required, along with a request, as the police/ CBI does in
			<lb />
			the case of obtaining prior sanction under Section 19 PC Act/ Section 197
			<lb />
			of the Code, in terms of the judgment of the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court in
			<lb />
			CBI v. Ashok Kumar Aggarwal (2014) 14 SCC 295. The following
			<lb />
			extract is indicative of the burden that would be placed on a member of
			<lb />
			the general public prior to sending a request for sanction:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot;8. In view of the above, the legal propositions can be
				<lb />
				summarised as under:
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(a) The prosecution must send the entire relevant record to the
				<lb />
				sanctioning authority including the FIR, disclosure statements,
				<lb />
				statements of witnesses, recovery memos, draft charge sheet
				<lb />
				and all other relevant material. The record so sent should also
				<lb />
				contain the material/document, if any, which may tilt the
				<lb />
				balance in favour of the accused and on the basis of which, the
				<lb />
				competent authority may refuse sanction.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(b) The authority itself has to do complete and conscious
				<lb />
				scrutiny of the whole record so produced by the prosecution
				<lb />
				independently applying its mind and taking into consideration
				<lb />
				all the relevant facts before grant of sanction while discharging
				<lb />
				its duty to give or withhold the sanction.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(c) The power to grant sanction is to be exercised strictly
				<lb />
				keeping in mind the public interest and the protection available
				<lb />
				to the accused against whom the sanction is sought. The order
				<lb />
				of sanction should make it evident that the authority had been
				<lb />
				aware of all relevant facts/materials and had applied its mind to
				<lb />
				all the relevant material.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(d) In every individual case, the prosecution has to establish
				<lb />
				and satisfy the court by leading evidence that the entire relevant
				<lb />
				facts had been placed before the sanctioning authority and the
				<lb />
				authority had applied its mind on the same and that the
				<lb />
				sanction had been granted in accordance with law.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			13. It is stated that Section 196 of the Code is different from Section 19
			<lb />
			of the Prevention of Corruption Act and Section 197 of Code. A bare
			<lb />
			reading of Anil Kumar &amp; Ors. v. M.K. Aiyappa &amp; Anr. (2013) 10 SCC
			<lb />
			705, and of Manju Surana v. Sunil Arora, (2018) 5 SCC 557, would
			<lb />
			indicate that the requirement of prior sanction even at the stage of
			<lb />
			adjudication of  an Application under Section 156 (3) of the Code, was in
			<lb />
			order to prevent vexing public servants. The following extracts indicate
			<lb />
			the same:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				a. Anil Kumar (supra):
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				&quot;13. …We find it difficult to accept that contention. Subsection
				<lb />
				(3) of Section 19 has an object to achieve, which applies in
				<lb />
				circumstances where a Special Judge has already rendered a
				<lb />
				finding, sentence or order. In such an event, it shall not be
				<lb />
				reversed or altered by a court in appeal, confirmation or
				<lb />
				revision on the ground of absence of sanction. That does not
				<lb />
				mean that the requirement to obtain sanction is not a
				<lb />
				mandatory requirement. Once it is noticed that there was no
				<lb />
				previous sanction, as already indicated in various judgments
				<lb />
				referred to hereinabove, the Magistrate cannot order
				<lb />
				investigation against a public servant while invoking powers
				<lb />
				under Section 156(3) Cr.P.C.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				b. Manju Surana (supra):
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				&quot;… Mr. Tushar Mehta, learned Additional Solicitor General
				<lb />
				sought to canvas the view taken in the last two judgments
				<lb />
				referred to aforesaid to submit that application of mind was
				<lb />
				necessary to exercise power under Section 156(3) of the Cr.P.C.
				<lb />
				and that credibility of information was to be weighed before
				<lb />
				ordering investigation (Ramdev Food Products (P) Ltd. v. State
				<lb />
				of Gujarat). It was, thus, submitted that allegation against a
				<lb />
				public servant under the P.C. Act offences are technical in
				<lb />
				nature and would require a higher evaluation standard and
				<lb />
				thus the Magistrates ought to apply their mind before ordering
				<lb />
				investigation against public servant. The consequences of
				<lb />
				starting investigation under Section 156(3) of the Cr.P.C., it
				<lb />
				was submitted, would result in the police registering an FIR
				<lb />
				(Suresh Chand Jain v. State of Madhya Pradesh and Mohd.
				<lb />
				Yousuf v. Afaq Jahan). Thus, a situation may arise where a
				<lb />
				Magistrate may exercise his power under Section 156(3) of the
				<lb />
				Cr.P.C. in a routine manner resulting in an FIR being
				<lb />
				registered against a public servant, who may have no role in the
				<lb />
				allegation made.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			14. It is submitted that reliance placed upon Anil Kumar (supra) to
			<lb />
			submit that prior sanction is required for directions under Section 156(3)
			<lb />
			of the Code is erroneous since, the findings therein pertained specifically
			<lb />
			to sanction under Section 19 of the Prevention of Corruption Act, 1988
			<lb />
			(PC Act) and not with respect to the provisions of the Code. Further, the
			<lb />
			said findings are contrary to settled law establishing that proceedings
			<lb />
			under Section 156(3) of the Code would not amount to taking cognizance
			<lb />
			and has been doubted in Manju Surana (supra). The judgment of the
			<lb />
			Supreme Court in Manju Surana (supra) interprets Anil Kumar (supra)
			<lb />
			as applicable to cases under the PC Act and further refers to the question
			<lb />
			of whether sanction under the PC Act is necessary to maintain an
			<lb />
			application under Section 156(3) of the Code to a larger bench. This
			<lb />
			interpretation is a binding precedent as on date and has not been doubted
			<lb />
			or challenged as yet. It is therefore submitted that the judgment of the
			<lb />
			Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court in Anil Kumar (supra) must be read as limited to
			<lb />
			the PC Act, and even that ratio is not good law as on date, as argued in
			<lb />
			the following paragraphs.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			15. It is further submitted that Anil Kumar (supra) is per incuriam
			<lb />
			several decisions of the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court, including RR Chari v.
			<lb />
			State of UP (AIR 1951 SC 207), and Gopal Das Sindhi v. State of Assam
			<lb />
			(AIR 1961 SC 986). Section 196 of the Code categorically bars a court
			<lb />
			from taking cognizance for the offences prescribed therein without a prior
			<lb />
			sanction. It is settled law in a plethora of cases including, Manju Surana
			<lb />
			(supra), Gopal Das Sindhi (supra), Tula Ram v. Kishore Singh (1977) 4
			<lb />
			SCC 459, State of Karnataka v. Pastor P. Raju (2006) 6 SCC 728 that
			<lb />
			application of mind for ordering an investigation under Section 156(3)
			<lb />
			would not amount to taking cognizance. The judgment in Pastor P. Raju
			<lb />
			(supra) in fact holds as under:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot;A plain reading of this provision will show that no Court can
				<lb />
				take cognizance of an offence punishable under Section 153-B
				<lb />
				or sub-section (2) or sub-section (3) of Section 505 of Indian
				<lb />
				Penal Code or a criminal conspiracy to commit such offence
				<lb />
				except with the previous sanction of the Central Government or
				<lb />
				of the State Government or of the District Magistrate. The
				<lb />
				opening words of the Section are &quot;No Court shall take
				<lb />
				cognizance&quot; and consequently the bar created by the provision
				<lb />
				is against taking of cognizance by the Court. There is no bar
				<lb />
				against registration of a criminal case or investigation by the
				<lb />
				police agency or submission of a report by the police on
				<lb />
				completion of investigation, as contemplated by Section 173
				<lb />
				Cr.P.C. If a criminal case is registered, investigation of the
				<lb />
				offence is done and the police submits a report as a result of
				<lb />
				such investigation before a Magistrate without the previous
				<lb />
				sanction of the Central Government or of the State Government
				<lb />
				or of the District Magistrate, there will be no violation of
				<lb />
				Section 196(1-A) Cr.P.C. and no illegality of any kind would be
				<lb />
				committed.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			16. It is submitted that this Court in Bhagwati Devi Gupta v. Star
			<lb />
			Infratech, 2021 SCC OnLine Del 3995, observed that once a bench of
			<lb />
			the Supreme Court has doubted the correctness of an earlier bench of co-
			<lb />
			equal strength and referred the issue to a larger bench, it would be
			<lb />
			debatable whether courts lower in hierarchy should continue to follow the
			<lb />
			earlier decision.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			17. It is further submitted that the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court in Jayant
			<lb />
			and Ors. v. State of Madhya Pradesh, (2021) 2 SCC 670 dealt with
			<lb />
			Section 22 of the Mines and Minerals (Development and Regulation) Act,
			<lb />
			1957 (&quot;MMDR Act&quot;), which bars a court from taking cognizance of an
			<lb />
			offence punishable under the MMDR Act except upon complaint made in
			<lb />
			writing by a person authorized in this behalf by the Central or State
			<lb />
			Government. In this case, the Supreme Court upheld the order of the Ld.
			<lb />
			Magistrate who in exercise of suo moto powers conferred under Section
			<lb />
			156(3) CrPC had directed the police to register an FIR, conduct
			<lb />
			investigation and submit a report under the MMDR Act. Relying on
			<lb />
			settled law, the Supreme Court held that at this stage, it cannot be said
			<lb />
			that the Ld. Magistrate had taken any cognizance of the alleged offences
			<lb />
			attracting the bar under Section 22 MMDR Act, and that there is no bar
			<lb />
			against registration or investigation of a criminal case or submission of a
			<lb />
			report by the police under Section 173(8) of Code.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			18. It is also stated that while the contents of the aforesaid speeches
			<lb />
			prima facie demonstrate the commission of cognizable offences, the
			<lb />
			inaction on the part of state agencies, and non-registration of FIR,
			<lb />
			provides implicit sanction for such utterances to be repeated, as it did in
			<lb />
			the present case. As a matter of public policy, and in furtherance of the
			<lb />
			fundamental precepts of criminal law, the power of the Ld. Judicial
			<lb />
			Magistrate under Section 156(3) of the Code to ensure the discharge of
			<lb />
			the duty of the state agencies to register the FIR in a timely manner must
			<lb />
			not and cannot be abrogated from.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			19. In light of the aforesaid, it is therefore prayed that there is no bar to
			<lb />
			the exercise of power under Section 156(3) of the Code and that the
			<lb />
			Order dated 26th August 2020 passed by the Ld. ACMM (I), Rouse
			<lb />
			Avenue Courts, Delhi in Ct. Cas. No. 04/2020 be set aside by this Court.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			20. Per Contra, Mr. Amit Mahajan, learned CGSC appearing for the
			<lb />
			Respondents submitted that the issue which arises for consideration of
			<lb />
			this Hon&apos;ble Court is whether a sanction under Section 196 of the Code is
			<lb />
			necessary prior for any direction being issued by Ld. ACMM for
			<lb />
			registration of FIR under Section 156(3) of CrPC.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			21. It is submitted that a bare perusal of Section 196 of the Code would
			<lb />
			show that no court can take cognizance of any offence punishable under
			<lb />
			Chapter VI or under Section 153A, 295A or sub-section (1) of Section
			<lb />
			505 of IPC without previous sanction of the Central Government or the
			<lb />
			State Government as the case may be. Similarly, Section 197 provides
			<lb />
			that when any person who is or was a public servant not removable from
			<lb />
			his office save by or with the sanction of the Government is accused of
			<lb />
			any offence alleged to have been committed by him while acting or
			<lb />
			purporting to act in discharge of his official duty, no court shall take
			<lb />
			cognizance of such offence except with the previous sanction. In the
			<lb />
			present case also, the allegations have been levelled under various
			<lb />
			Sections including Section 295-A, 153-A and Section 505 of the IPC.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			22. It is further submitted that the petitioner has argued that the
			<lb />
			sanction is only required when the court takes cognizance after filing of a
			<lb />
			chargesheet and for the purpose of giving directions for investigation
			<lb />
			under Section 156(3) of CrPC, no such sanction is required. This issue is
			<lb />
			no longer res integra.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			23. The Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court in the case of Anil Kumar (supra) and
			<lb />
			L. Narayana Swamy v. State of Karnataka &amp; Ors (2016) 9 SCC 598
			<lb />
			have specifically held that the court cannot direct registration of FIR or
			<lb />
			investigation into an offence while exercising power under Section
			<lb />
			156(3) of CrPC in relation to offence where the sanction is required to be
			<lb />
			taken before a court can take cognizance.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			24. It is further submitted that a perusal of the status report of the
			<lb />
			respondent would reveal that on the basis of the allegations levelled by
			<lb />
			the Petitioners, the respondents came to the conclusion that prima-facie
			<lb />
			no cognizable offence was found to be committed. It is submitted that
			<lb />
			once the investigation agency comes to the conclusion that no offence
			<lb />
			had been made out, the Magistrate has to apply his mind to direct the
			<lb />
			registration of FIR, however, in such cases want of sanction is mandatory
			<lb />
			and once it is noticed that there was no previous sanction, the Magistrate
			<lb />
			cannot order investigation against a public servant while invoking powers
			<lb />
			under Section 156(3) CrPC.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			25. In view of the above submissions, it is submitted that the instant
			<lb />
			petition is devoid of merits and this Court may be pleased to dismiss the
			<lb />
			present petition.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			26. Heard learned counsels appearing on behalf of parties at length and
			<lb />
			perused the record.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<head>
			QUESTION FOR ADJUDICATION
			<lb />
		</head>
		<p>
			27. A mere perusal of the impugned order makes it evident that the
			<lb />
			ACMM has not entered into the merits of the case and has decided the
			<lb />
			complaint before it on the ground of jurisdiction, on the point that he
			<lb />
			lacked the jurisdiction to entertain the complaint on merits because of
			<lb />
			want of sanction from the Competent authority to prosecute the two
			<lb />
			named individuals.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			28. Thus, the only question for consideration before this Court is
			<lb />
			limited to the extent of adjudicating whether the ACMM has rightly
			<lb />
			dismissed the said complaint.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<head>
			ANALYSIS
			<lb />
		</head>
		<p>
			29. In the instant case, the concerned Court in its impugned order
			<lb />
			dismissed the Petitioners&apos; Application under Section 156(3) of the Code
			<lb />
			seeking investigation/registration of FIR, finding that the application was
			<lb />
			not tenable in the eyes of law on the ground that there was no previous
			<lb />
			sanction obtained by the petitioners from the competent authority to
			<lb />
			prosecute the named individuals for the offences alleged in the complaint.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			30. For a better appreciation of the case at hand, it is pertinent to
			<lb />
			peruse and analyse the provisions of law invoked in the instant petition
			<lb />
			before delving deeper into the facts of the case.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<head>
			Scheme of the Code for Initiation of Criminal Proceedings
			<lb />
		</head>
		<p>
			31. Section 154 of the Code reads as under:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				154. Information in cognizable cases.-(1) Every information
				<lb />
				relating to the commission of a cognizable offence, if given
				<lb />
				orally to an officer in charge of a police station, shall be
				<lb />
				reduced to writing by him or under his direction, and be read
				<lb />
				over to the informant; and every such information, whether
				<lb />
				given in writing or reduced to writing as aforesaid, shall be
				<lb />
				signed by the person giving it, and the substance thereof shall
				<lb />
				be entered in a book to be kept by such officer in such form as
				<lb />
				the State Government may prescribe in this behalf:
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				Provided that if the information is given by the woman
				<lb />
				against whom an offence under Section 326-A, Section
				<lb />
				326-B, Section 354, Section 354-A, Section 354-B,
				<lb />
				Section 354-C, Section 354-D, Section 376, Section 376-
				<lb />
				A, Section 376-AB, Section 376-B, Section 376-C, Section
				<lb />
				376-D, Section 376-DA, Section 376-DB, Section 376-E
				<lb />
				or Section 509 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860) is
				<lb />
				alleged to have been committed or attempted, then such
				<lb />
				information shall be recorded, by a woman police officer
				<lb />
				or any woman officer:
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				Provided further that-
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(a) in the event that the person against whom an
				<lb />
				offence under Section 354, Section 354-A,
				<lb />
				Section 354-B, Section 354-C, Section 354-D,
				<lb />
				Section 376, Section 376-A, Section 376-AB,
				<lb />
				Section 376-B, Section 376-C, Section 376-D,
				<lb />
				Section 376-DA, Section 376-DB, Section 376-E
				<lb />
				or Section 509 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of
				<lb />
				1860) is alleged to have been committed or
				<lb />
				attempted, is temporarily or permanently
				<lb />
				mentally or physically disabled, then such
				<lb />
				information shall be recorded by a police
				<lb />
				officer, at the residence of the person seeking to
				<lb />
				report such offence or at a convenient place of
				<lb />
				such person&apos;s choice, in the presence of an
				<lb />
				interpreter or a special educator, as the case
				<lb />
				may be;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(b) the recording of such information shall be
				<lb />
				videographed;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(c) the police officer shall get the statement of
				<lb />
				the person recorded by a Judicial Magistrate
				<lb />
				under clause (a) of sub-section (5-A) of Section
				<lb />
				164 as soon as possible.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(2) A copy of the information as recorded under sub-section (1)
				<lb />
				shall be given forthwith, free of cost, to the informant.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(3) Any person aggrieved by a refusal on the part of an officer
				<lb />
				in charge of a police station to record the information referred
				<lb />
				to in sub-section (1) may send the substance of such
				<lb />
				information, in writing and by post, to the Superintendent of
				<lb />
				Police concerned who, if satisfied that such information
				<lb />
				discloses the commission of a cognizable offence, shall either
				<lb />
				investigate the case himself or direct an investigation to be
				<lb />
				made by any police officer subordinate to him, in the manner
				<lb />
				provided by this Code, and such officer shall have all the
				<lb />
				powers of an officer in charge of the police station in relation to
				<lb />
				that offence.
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			32. Section 154 although does not mention the phrase &quot;First
			<lb />
			Information Report&quot;, it pertains to the registration of First Information
			<lb />
			Report. It provides that every information relating to the commission of a
			<lb />
			cognizable offence, if given orally to an officer in charge of a police
			<lb />
			station, shall be reduced to writing by him or under his direction, and be
			<lb />
			read over to the informant; and every such information, whether given in
			<lb />
			writing or reduced to writing as aforesaid, shall be signed by the person
			<lb />
			giving it, and the substance thereof shall be entered in a book to be kept
			<lb />
			by such officer in such form as prescribed by the State Government.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			33. As held in the case of Hasib v. State of Bihar, (1972) 4 SCC 773,
			<lb />
			the object and scope of the first information report from the point of view
			<lb />
			of the informant is to set the criminal law in motion and from the point of
			<lb />
			view of the investigating authorities is to obtain information about the
			<lb />
			alleged criminal activity so as to be able to take suitable steps for tracing
			<lb />
			and bringing to book the guilty party.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			34. The only condition precedent for registering an FIR is that the
			<lb />
			information should disclose a cognizable offence. The requirement of
			<lb />
			Section 154 of the Code is only that the report must disclose the
			<lb />
			commission of a cognizable offence and that is sufficient to set the
			<lb />
			investigating machinery into action.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			35. In Section 154(1) of the Code, the Parliament in its wisdom has
			<lb />
			used the expression &apos;information&apos; without qualifying the same as was
			<lb />
			done in Section 41(1)(a) or (g) of the Code wherein the expressions,
			<lb />
			&apos;reasonable complaint&apos; and &apos;credible information&apos; are used. Evidently, the
			<lb />
			non-qualification of the word &apos;information&apos; in Section 154(1) unlike in
			<lb />
			Section 41(1)(a) and (g) of the Code can be interpreted to be existing for
			<lb />
			the reason that the Police Officer ought not to refuse to record an
			<lb />
			information/register a case relating to the commission of a cognizable
			<lb />
			offence on the ground of him not being satisfied with the reasonableness
			<lb />
			or credibility of the information. Thus, it is evident that &apos;reasonableness&apos;
			<lb />
			or &apos;credibility&apos; of the said information is not a condition precedent for
			<lb />
			registration of a case.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			36. A Constitution Bench of the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court in Lalita
			<lb />
			Kumari v. Govt. of U.P., (2014) 2 SCC 1 held that registration of First
			<lb />
			Information Report is mandatory under Section 154 of the CrPC, if the
			<lb />
			information discloses commission of a cognizable offence. If the
			<lb />
			information received does not disclose a cognizable offence but indicates
			<lb />
			the necessity for an inquiry, a preliminary inquiry may be conducted only
			<lb />
			to ascertain whether a cognizable offence is disclosed or not.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			37. At this stage it is enough if the Police Officer on the basis of the
			<lb />
			information given suspects the commission of a cognizable offence, and
			<lb />
			not that he must be convinced or satisfied that a cognizable offence has
			<lb />
			been committed. If he has reasons to suspect, based on the information
			<lb />
			received, that a cognizable offence may have been committed, he is
			<lb />
			bound to record the information and conduct an investigation. At this
			<lb />
			stage it is also not necessary for him to satisfy himself about the
			<lb />
			truthfulness of the information.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			38. The legislative intent is thus unambiguous -to ensure that every
			<lb />
			cognizable offence is promptly investigated in accordance with law.
			<lb />
			Having stated so, there is no reason that there should be any discretion or
			<lb />
			option left with the police to register or not to register an FIR when
			<lb />
			information is given about the commission of a cognizable offence. Every
			<lb />
			cognizable offence must be investigated promptly in accordance with law
			<lb />
			and all information provided under Section 154 of the Code about the
			<lb />
			commission of a cognizable offence must be registered as an FIR so as to
			<lb />
			initiate an offence.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			39. Now, the next question that flows from the aforesaid discussion is
			<lb />
			what options are available upon a refusal of lodging of FIR by the police.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<head>
			Remedies for Refusal to Lodge an FIR &amp; Scope of 156(3)
			<lb />
		</head>
		<p>
			40. Section 154 (3) in itself provides the recourse. Any person
			<lb />
			aggrieved by a refusal on the part of an officer in charge of a police
			<lb />
			station to lodge the FIR may send the substance of such information, in
			<lb />
			writing and by post, to the Superintendent of Police concerned who, if
			<lb />
			satisfied that such information discloses the commission of a cognizable
			<lb />
			offence, shall either investigate the case himself or direct an investigation
			<lb />
			to be made by any police officer subordinate to him, in the manner
			<lb />
			provided by this Code, and such officer shall have all the powers of an
			<lb />
			officer in charge of the police station in relation to that offence.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			41. The insertion of sub-section (3) of Section 154, by an amendment,
			<lb />
			reveals the intention of the Legislature to ensure that no information of
			<lb />
			commission of a cognizable offence must be ignored or not acted upon.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			42. In the landmark case of Sakiri Vasu v. State of U.P., (2008) 2 SCC
			<lb />
			409, the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court held as under:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				26. If a person has a grievance that his FIR has not been
				<lb />
				registered by the police station his first remedy is to approach
				<lb />
				the Superintendent of Police under Section 154(3) CrPC or
				<lb />
				other police officer referred to in Section 36 CrPC. If despite
				<lb />
				approaching the Superintendent of Police or the officer referred
				<lb />
				to in Section 36 his grievance still persists, then he can
				<lb />
				approach a Magistrate under Section 156(3) CrPC instead of
				<lb />
				rushing to the High Court by way of a writ petition or a petition
				<lb />
				under Section 482 CrPC. Moreover, he has a further remedy of
				<lb />
				filing a criminal complaint under Section 200 CrPC. Why then
				<lb />
				should writ petitions or Section 482 petitions be entertained
				<lb />
				when there are so many alternative remedies?
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				27. As we have already observed above, the Magistrate has very
				<lb />
				wide powers to direct registration of an FIR and to ensure a
				<lb />
				proper investigation and for this purpose he can monitor the
				<lb />
				investigation to ensure that the investigation is done properly
				<lb />
				(though he cannot investigate himself). The High Court should
				<lb />
				discourage the practice of filing a writ petition or petition under
				<lb />
				Section 482 CrPC simply because a person has a grievance that
				<lb />
				his FIR has not been registered by the police, or after being
				<lb />
				registered, proper investigation has not been done by the
				<lb />
				police. For this grievance, the remedy lies under Sections 36
				<lb />
				and 154(3) before the police officers concerned, and if that is of
				<lb />
				no avail, under Section 156(3) CrPC before the Magistrate or
				<lb />
				by filing a criminal complaint under Section 200 CrPC and not
				<lb />
				by filing a writ petition or a petition under Section 482 CrPC.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				28. It is true that alternative remedy is not an absolute bar to a
				<lb />
				writ petition, but it is equally well settled that if there is an
				<lb />
				alternative remedy the High Court should not ordinarily
				<lb />
				interfere.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			43. After exhausting the steps mentioned in Section 154(1) and Section
			<lb />
			154(3) the aggrieved person can file a complaint before the Magistrate for
			<lb />
			a direction under Section 156(3) to police to register FIR.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot;156. Police officer&apos;s power to investigate cognizable case.-
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(1) Any officer in charge of a police station may, without the
				<lb />
				order of a Magistrate, investigate any cognizable case which a
				<lb />
				court having jurisdiction over the local area within the limits of
				<lb />
				such station would have power to inquire into or try under the
				<lb />
				provisions of Chapter XIII.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(2) No proceeding of a police officer in any such case shall at
				<lb />
				any stage be called in question on the ground that the case was
				<lb />
				one which such officer was not empowered under this section to
				<lb />
				investigate.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(3) Any Magistrate empowered under Section 190 may order
				<lb />
				such an investigation as abovementioned.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			44. Section 156(3) unambiguously states that any Magistrate
			<lb />
			empowered under Section 190 may order an investigation into a
			<lb />
			cognizable offence. However, the Magistrate cannot act as a mere &apos;Post
			<lb />
			Office&apos; in forwarding such a complaint for investigation, meaning thereby
			<lb />
			that the direction by the Magistrate for investigation under S.156(3)
			<lb />
			should not be issued as a matter of routine or passed in a mechanical
			<lb />
			manner, without application of judicial mind.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			45. While expounding the nature of power exercised by the Magistrate
			<lb />
			under Section 156(3) of the Code, a three-Judge Bench of the Hon&apos;ble
			<lb />
			Supreme Court in Devarapalli Lakshminarayana Reddy v. V. Narayana
			<lb />
			Reddy (1976) 3 SCC 252, held as under:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot;17. … It may be noted further that an order made under sub-
				<lb />
				section (3) of Section 156, is in the nature of a peremptory
				<lb />
				reminder or intimation to the police to exercise their plenary
				<lb />
				powers of investigation under Section 156(1). Such an
				<lb />
				investigation embraces the entire continuous process which
				<lb />
				begins with the collection of evidence under Section 156 and
				<lb />
				ends with a report or charge-sheet under Section 173.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			46. The Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court in the case of Dilawar Singh v. State
			<lb />
			of Delhi (2007) 12 SCC 641 ruled as under:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot;18. …&apos;11. The clear position therefore is that any Judicial
				<lb />
				Magistrate, before taking cognizance of the offence, can order
				<lb />
				investigation under Section 156(3) of the Code. If he does so, he
				<lb />
				is not to examine the complainant on oath because he was not
				<lb />
				taking cognizance of any offence therein. For the purpose of
				<lb />
				enabling the police to start investigation it is open to the
				<lb />
				Magistrate to direct the police to register an FIR. There is
				<lb />
				nothing illegal in doing so. After all registration of an FIR
				<lb />
				involves only the process of entering the substance of the
				<lb />
				information relating to the commission of the cognizable
				<lb />
				offence in a book kept by the officer in charge of the police
				<lb />
				station as indicated in Section 154 of the Code. Even if a
				<lb />
				Magistrate does not say in so many words while directing
				<lb />
				investigation under Section 156(3) of the Code that an FIR
				<lb />
				should be registered, it is the duty of the officer in charge of the
				<lb />
				police station to register the FIR regarding the cognizable
				<lb />
				offence disclosed by the complainant because that police officer
				<lb />
				could take further steps contemplated in Chapter XII of the
				<lb />
				Code only thereafter.&apos; [Ed. : See Mohd. Yousuf v. Afaq Jahan,
				<lb />
				(2006) 1 SCC 627, SCC p. 631, para 11 : (2006) 1 SCC (Cri)
				<lb />
				460.] &quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			47. In CREF Finance Ltd. v. Shree Shanthi Homes (P) Ltd. (2005) 7
			<lb />
			SCC 467, the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court while dealing with the power of
			<lb />
			the Magistrate taking cognizance of the offences, has opined that having
			<lb />
			considered the complaint, the Magistrate may consider it appropriate to
			<lb />
			send the complaint to the police for investigation under Section 156(3) of
			<lb />
			the Code of Criminal Procedure.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			48. Subsequently, in the case of Madhao v. State of Maharashtra,
			<lb />
			(2013) 5 SCC 615, the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court held:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot;18. When a Magistrate receives a complaint he is not bound to
				<lb />
				take cognizance if the facts alleged in the complaint disclose the
				<lb />
				commission of an offence. The Magistrate has discretion in the
				<lb />
				matter. If on a reading of the complaint, he finds that the
				<lb />
				allegations therein disclose a cognizable offence and the
				<lb />
				forwarding of the complaint to the police for investigation
				<lb />
				under Section 156(3) will be conducive to justice and save the
				<lb />
				valuable time of the Magistrate from being wasted in enquiring
				<lb />
				into a matter which was primarily the duty of the police to
				<lb />
				investigate, he will be justified in adopting that course as an
				<lb />
				alternative to taking cognizance of the offence itself. As said
				<lb />
				earlier, in the case of a complaint regarding the commission of
				<lb />
				a cognizable offence, the power under Section 156(3) can be
				<lb />
				invoked by the Magistrate before he takes cognizance of the
				<lb />
				offence under Section 190(1)(a). However, if he once takes such
				<lb />
				cognizance and embarks upon the procedure embodied in
				<lb />
				Chapter XV, he is not competent to revert back to the pre-
				<lb />
				cognizance stage and avail of Section 156(3).&quot; [Ed. : See also
				<lb />
				Devarapalli Lakshminarayana Reddy v. V. Narayana Reddy,
				<lb />
				(1976) 3 SCC 252 : 1976 SCC (Cri) 380, SCC p. 257, paras 13-
				<lb />
				14.]
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			49. The Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court in Priyanka Srivastava v. State of
			<lb />
			U.P., (2015) 6 SCC 287 held as under:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot;29. At this stage it is seemly to state that power under Section
				<lb />
				156(3) warrants application of judicial mind. A court of law is
				<lb />
				involved. It is not the police taking steps at the stage of Section
				<lb />
				154 of the Code. A litigant at his own whim cannot invoke the
				<lb />
				authority of the Magistrate. A principled and really grieved
				<lb />
				citizen with clean hands must have free access to invoke the
				<lb />
				said power. It protects the citizens but when pervert litigations
				<lb />
				takes this route to harass their fellow citizens, efforts are to be
				<lb />
				made to scuttle and curb the same.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			50. It was also held that in an appropriate case, the learned Magistrate
			<lb />
			would be well advised to verify the truth and also can verify the veracity
			<lb />
			of the allegations. The Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court went on to held as under:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot;30. In our considered opinion, a stage has come in this
				<lb />
				country where Section 156(3) CrPC applications are to be
				<lb />
				supported by an affidavit duly sworn by the applicant who seeks
				<lb />
				the invocation of the jurisdiction of the Magistrate. That apart,
				<lb />
				in an appropriate case, the learned Magistrate would be well
				<lb />
				advised to verify the truth and also can verify the veracity of the
				<lb />
				allegations. This affidavit can make the applicant more
				<lb />
				responsible. We are compelled to say so as such kind of
				<lb />
				applications are being filed in a routine manner without taking
				<lb />
				any responsibility whatsoever only to harass certain persons.
				<lb />
				That apart, it becomes more disturbing and alarming when one
				<lb />
				tries to pick up people who are passing orders under a statutory
				<lb />
				provision which can be challenged under the framework of the
				<lb />
				said Act or under Article 226 of the Constitution of India. But it
				<lb />
				cannot be done to take undue advantage in a criminal court as
				<lb />
				if somebody is determined to settle the scores.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				31. We have already indicated that there has to be prior
				<lb />
				applications under Sections 154(1) and 154(3) while filing a
				<lb />
				petition under Section 156(3). Both the aspects should be
				<lb />
				clearly spelt out in the application and necessary documents to
				<lb />
				that effect shall be filed. The warrant for giving a direction that
				<lb />
				an application under Section 156(3) be supported by an
				<lb />
				affidavit is so that the person making the application should be
				<lb />
				conscious and also endeavour to see that no false affidavit is
				<lb />
				made. It is because once an affidavit is found to be false, he will
				<lb />
				be liable for prosecution in accordance with law. This will deter
				<lb />
				him to casually invoke the authority of the Magistrate under
				<lb />
				Section 156(3). That apart, we have already stated that the
				<lb />
				veracity of the same can also be verified by the learned
				<lb />
				Magistrate, regard being had to the nature of allegations of the
				<lb />
				case. We are compelled to say so as a number of cases
				<lb />
				pertaining to fiscal sphere, matrimonial dispute/family disputes,
				<lb />
				commercial offences, medical negligence cases, corruption
				<lb />
				cases and the cases where there is abnormal delay/laches in
				<lb />
				initiating criminal prosecution, as are illustrated in Lalita
				<lb />
				Kumari [(2014) 2 SCC 1 : (2014) 1 SCC (Cri) 524] are being
				<lb />
				filed. That apart, the learned Magistrate would also be aware of
				<lb />
				the delay in lodging of the FIR.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			51. In the case of Ramdev Food Products (P) Ltd. v. State of
			<lb />
			Gujarat (2015) 6 SCC 439, while dealing with the exercise of power
			<lb />
			under Section 156(3) by the Magistrate, a three-Judge Bench has held
			<lb />
			that:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot;22.1. The direction under Section 156(3) is to be issued, only
				<lb />
				after application of mind by the Magistrate. When the
				<lb />
				Magistrate does not take cognizance and does not find it
				<lb />
				necessary to postpone instance of process and finds a case
				<lb />
				made out to proceed forthwith, direction under the said
				<lb />
				provision is issued. In other words, where on account of
				<lb />
				credibility of information available, or weighing the interest of
				<lb />
				justice it is considered appropriate to straightaway direct
				<lb />
				investigation, such a direction is issued.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				22.2. The cases where Magistrate takes cognizance and
				<lb />
				postpones issuance of process are cases where the Magistrate
				<lb />
				has yet to determine &apos;existence of sufficient ground to
				<lb />
				proceed&apos;.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			52. Another question that arises is the scope of the powers of the
			<lb />
			magistrate under Section 156(3). In the case of Anil Kumar v. M.K.
			<lb />
			Aiyappa (2013) 10 SCC 705, the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court held:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot;11. The scope of Section 156(3) CrPC came up for
				<lb />
				consideration before this Court in several cases. This Court
				<lb />
				in Maksud Saiyed [Maksud Saiyed v. State of Gujarat, (2008) 5
				<lb />
				SCC 668 : (2008) 2 SCC (Cri) 692] examined the requirement
				<lb />
				of the application of mind by the Magistrate before exercising
				<lb />
				jurisdiction under Section 156(3) and held that where
				<lb />
				jurisdiction is exercised on a complaint filed in terms of Section
				<lb />
				156(3) or Section 200 CrPC, the Magistrate is required to
				<lb />
				apply his mind, in such a case, the Special Judge/Magistrate
				<lb />
				cannot refer the matter under Section 156(3) against a public
				<lb />
				servant without a valid sanction order. The application of mind
				<lb />
				by the Magistrate should be reflected in the order. The mere
				<lb />
				statement that he has gone through the complaint, documents
				<lb />
				and heard the complainant, as such, as reflected in the order,
				<lb />
				will not be sufficient. After going through the complaint,
				<lb />
				documents and hearing the complainant, what weighed with the
				<lb />
				Magistrate to order investigation under Section 156(3) CrPC,
				<lb />
				should be reflected in the order, though a detailed expression of
				<lb />
				his views is neither required nor warranted. We have already
				<lb />
				extracted the order passed by the learned Special Judge which,
				<lb />
				in our view, has stated no reasons for ordering investigation.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			53. In the case of Vinubhai Haribhai Malaviya v. State of Gujarat,
			<lb />
			(2019) 17 SCC 1, it was held that the scope of Magistrate&apos;s power under
			<lb />
			Section 156(3) is very wide. Under Section 156(3), by virtue of Article 21
			<lb />
			of the Constitution, all powers necessary, which may also be incidental or
			<lb />
			implied, are available to the Magistrate to ensure a proper investigation in
			<lb />
			the matter in the sense of a fair and just investigation by the police. The
			<lb />
			said power includes ordering of further investigation after submission of
			<lb />
			police report under Section 173(2) CrPC. Exercise of that power is
			<lb />
			available even at post-cognizance stage until trial commences i.e. charges
			<lb />
			are framed. This power can also be exercised suo motu by the Magistrate
			<lb />
			himself, depending on the facts of each case.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			54. When the information is laid with the police, but no action in that
			<lb />
			behalf is taken, then the complainant has another option to his recourse -
			<lb />
			under Section 190 read with Section 200 of the Code, to lay the complaint
			<lb />
			before the Magistrate having jurisdiction to take cognizance of the
			<lb />
			offence and the Magistrate is required to enquire into the complaint as
			<lb />
			provided in Chapter XV of the Code. In case the Magistrate, after
			<lb />
			recording evidence, finds a prima facie case, instead of issuing process to
			<lb />
			the accused, he is empowered to direct the police concerned to investigate
			<lb />
			into offence under Chapter XII of the Code and to submit a report. If he
			<lb />
			finds that the complaint does not disclose any offence to take further
			<lb />
			action, he is empowered to dismiss the complaint under Section 203 of
			<lb />
			the Code. In case he finds that the complaint/evidence recorded prima
			<lb />
			facie discloses an offence, he is empowered to take cognizance of the
			<lb />
			offence and could issue process to the accused.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			55. In Section 156 (3), the word used is &quot;may&quot;. The use of the word
			<lb />
			&quot;shall&quot; in Section 154(3) and the use of word &quot;may&quot; in Section 156 (3)
			<lb />
			clearly lays down the intention of the legislation. Had the legislature
			<lb />
			intended to mandate and close options for the Magistrate, they could have
			<lb />
			used the word &quot;shall&quot; as has been done in S.154(3). Instead, they chose to
			<lb />
			use the word &quot;may&quot;. This is significant, and gives a very clear indication,
			<lb />
			that the Magistrate has the discretion in the matter, and can, in
			<lb />
			appropriate cases, refuse to order registration.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			56. Magistrate may direct the police to register a case and investigate
			<lb />
			or he may treat the same as a complaint and proceed in matter
			<lb />
			contemplated in Chapter XV of Code. He should apply his judicial mind.
			<lb />
			Magistrate if takes cognizance, may proceed to follow the procedure
			<lb />
			provided in Chapter XV of Code. Magistrate may either take cognizance
			<lb />
			under S.190 or may forward the complaint to police under S.156(3) for
			<lb />
			investigation.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			57. In the case of Sukhwasi v. State of Uttar Pradesh, 2007 SCC
			<lb />
			OnLine ALL 1088, the Allahabad HC held that the Magistrate is not
			<lb />
			bound to order for registration of an FIR in all cases where a cognizable
			<lb />
			offence has been disclosed and the Magistrate has authority to treat it as a
			<lb />
			complaint.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			58. Having dealt with the scheme of the Code, and before dealing with
			<lb />
			the correctness of the Order of the Magistrate, since the speeches in
			<lb />
			question were allegedly hate speeches, it is pertinent to refer to the law
			<lb />
			against hate speech.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<head>
			Law regarding Hate Speech
			<lb />
		</head>
		<p>
			59. Hate speeches incite violence and feelings of resentment against
			<lb />
			members of specific communities, thereby causing fear and feeling of
			<lb />
			insecurity in the minds of the members of those communities. In fact, it
			<lb />
			marginalizes individuals based on their membership in a group by using
			<lb />
			expressions that expose the group to hatred. Hate speeches are almost
			<lb />
			invariably targeted towards a community to impart a psychological
			<lb />
			impact on their psyche, creating fear in the process. Hate speeches are the
			<lb />
			beginning point of attacks against the targeted community that can range
			<lb />
			from discrimination to ostracism, ghettoization, deportation, and, even to
			<lb />
			genocide.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			60. The methodology is not restricted to any religion or community in
			<lb />
			specific. There have been and there continue to be instances of hate
			<lb />
			speeches in different parts of the country targeted against people of
			<lb />
			specific communities, based upon the demographic composition. There
			<lb />
			have even been instances of demographic shifts in the aftermath of such
			<lb />
			Hate/Inflammatory speeches, the exodus of Kashmiri Pandits from the
			<lb />
			Kashmir valley is a prime example.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			61. Article 19 of the Indian Constitution provides for freedom of
			<lb />
			speech and expression with reasonable restrictions and the same is not an
			<lb />
			absolute right. The reasonable restrictions include public order, decency
			<lb />
			or morality or in relation to contempt of court, defamation or incitement
			<lb />
			to an offence. Hate speeches not only cause defamation but also incite
			<lb />
			offences against a particular sect of religion of this nation.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			62. Black&apos;s Law Dictionary, 9th Edition defines the expression &apos;hate
			<lb />
			speech&apos; as under:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot;Speech that carries no meaning other than the expression of
				<lb />
				hatred for some group, such as a particular race, especially in
				<lb />
				circumstances in which the communication is likely to provoke
				<lb />
				violence.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			63. Article 7 of the Universal Declaration of Human Rights (UDHR)
			<lb />
			as adopted by General Assembly provides that everyone is equal and
			<lb />
			entitled to equal protection against discrimination, and against incitement
			<lb />
			to such discrimination.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			64. Further, the International Covenant on Civil &amp; Political Rights,
			<lb />
			1966 (ICCPR), which India ratified in 1992 places positive obligations to
			<lb />
			limit speech on governments. Article 20(2) of the ICCPR states that &quot;any
			<lb />
			advocacy of national, racial or religious hatred that constitutes incitement
			<lb />
			to discrimination, hostility or violence shall be prohibited by law.&quot; In
			<lb />
			other words, Article 20(2) requires the signatory governments to prohibit
			<lb />
			&quot;hate speech.&quot;
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			65. Similarly, Articles 4 and 6 of the International Convention on the
			<lb />
			Elimination of All Forms of Racial Discrimination, 1965 (ICERD)
			<lb />
			prohibits the elements of hate speech and mandates the member states to
			<lb />
			make a law prohibiting any kind of hate speech through a suitable
			<lb />
			framework of law.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			66. The Courts of the United Kingdom and Canada have recognized a
			<lb />
			&apos;duty of care&apos; by the police as a component of both private and public
			<lb />
			law.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			67. In Robinson v West Yorkshire Police [2018] UKSC 4 at Paragraph
			<lb />
			69, speaking for the majority, Lord Reed stated that:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot;(1) I do not suggest that the discussion of policy
				<lb />
				considerations in cases such as Hill, Brooks and Smith should
				<lb />
				be consigned to history. But it is important to understand that
				<lb />
				such discussions are not a routine aspect of deciding cases in
				<lb />
				the law of negligence, and are unnecessary when existing
				<lb />
				principles provide a clear basis for the decision, as in the
				<lb />
				present appeal. I would not agree with Lord Hughes&apos;s statement
				<lb />
				that they are the ultimate reason why there is no duty of care
				<lb />
				towards victims, suspects or witnesses imposed on police
				<lb />
				officers engaged in the investigation and prevention of crime.
				<lb />
				The absence of a duty towards victims of crime, for example,
				<lb />
				does not depend merely on a policy devised by a recent
				<lb />
				generation of judges in relation to policing: it is based on the
				<lb />
				application of a general and long-established principle that the
				<lb />
				common law imposes no liability to protect persons against
				<lb />
				harm caused by third parties, in the absence of a recognised
				<lb />
				exception such as a voluntary assumption of responsibility.[ ...]
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(4) The distinction between careless acts causing personal
				<lb />
				injury, for which the law generally imposes liability, and
				<lb />
				careless omissions to prevent acts (by other agencies) causing
				<lb />
				personal injury, for which the common law generally imposes
				<lb />
				no liability, is not a mere alternative to policy-based reasoning,
				<lb />
				but is inherent in the nature of the tort of negligence. For the
				<lb />
				same reason, although the distinction, like any other distinction,
				<lb />
				can be difficult to draw in borderline cases, it is of fundamental
				<lb />
				importance. The central point is that the law of negligence
				<lb />
				generally imposes duties not to cause harm to other people or
				<lb />
				their property: it does not generally impose duties to provide
				<lb />
				them with benefits (including the prevention of harm caused by
				<lb />
				other agencies). Duties to provide benefits are, in general,
				<lb />
				voluntarily undertaken rather than being imposed by the
				<lb />
				common law, and are typically within the domain of contract,
				<lb />
				promises and trusts rather than tort. It follows from that basic
				<lb />
				characteristic of the law of negligence that liability is generally
				<lb />
				imposed for causing harm rather than for failing to prevent
				<lb />
				harm caused by other people or by natural causes. It is also
				<lb />
				consistent with that characteristic that the exceptions to the
				<lb />
				general non-imposition of liability for omissions include
				<lb />
				situations where there has been a voluntary assumption of
				<lb />
				responsibility to prevent harm (situations which have sometimes
				<lb />
				been described as being close or akin to contract), situations
				<lb />
				where a person has assumed a status which carries with it a
				<lb />
				responsibility to prevent harm, such as being a parent or
				<lb />
				standing in loco parentis, and situations where the omission
				<lb />
				arises in the context of the defendant&apos;s having acted so as to
				<lb />
				create or increase a risk of harm&quot;.
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			68. The Supreme Court of Canada in Saskatchewan (Human Rights
			<lb />
			Commission) v. Whatcott 2013 SCC 11, succeeded in bringing out the
			<lb />
			&quot;human rights&quot; obligations leading to control on publication of &quot;hate
			<lb />
			speeches&quot; for protection of human rights defining the expression &quot;hate
			<lb />
			speech&quot; observing that the definition of &quot;hatred&quot; set out in Canada
			<lb />
			(Human Rights Commission) v. Taylor, (1990) 3 SCR 892, with some
			<lb />
			modifications, provides a workable approach to interpreting the word
			<lb />
			&quot;hatred&quot; as is used in legislative provisions prohibiting hate speech.
			<lb />
			Three main prescriptions must be followed. First, courts must apply the
			<lb />
			hate speech prohibition objectively. The question courts must ask is
			<lb />
			whether a reasonable person, aware of the context and circumstances,
			<lb />
			would view the expression as exposing the protected group to hatred.
			<lb />
			Second, the legislative term &quot;hatred&quot; or &quot;hatred or contempt&quot; must be
			<lb />
			interpreted as being restricted to those extreme manifestations of the
			<lb />
			emotion described by the words &quot;detestation&quot; and &quot;vilification&quot;. This
			<lb />
			filters out expression which, while repugnant and offensive, does not
			<lb />
			incite the level of abhorrence, delegitimization and rejection that risks
			<lb />
			causing discrimination or other harmful effects. Third, the Courts must
			<lb />
			focus their analysis on the effect of the expression at issue, namely -
			<lb />
			whether it is likely to expose the targeted person or group to hatred by
			<lb />
			others. The repugnancy of the ideas being expressed is not sufficient to
			<lb />
			justify restricting the expression, and whether or not the author of the
			<lb />
			expression intended to incite hatred or discriminatory treatment is
			<lb />
			irrelevant. The key is to determine the likely effect of the expression on
			<lb />
			its audience, keeping in mind the legislative objectives to reduce or
			<lb />
			eliminate discrimination.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			69. Referring back to the Indian position as laid down by the Courts, in
			<lb />
			Ramesh v. Union of India, AIR 1988 SC 775, while dealing with the
			<lb />
			subject, the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court observed:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot;... that the effect of the words must be judged from the
				<lb />
				standards of reasonable, strong-minded, firm and courageous
				<lb />
				men, and not those of weak and vacillating minds, nor of those
				<lb />
				who scent danger in every hostile point of view.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			70. Article 15 of the Constitution of India provides for prohibition of
			<lb />
			discrimination against any citizen on grounds of only of religion, race,
			<lb />
			caste, sex, or place of birth or any of them. The Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court
			<lb />
			on numerous instances has reiterated the same, in Zahira Habibulla H.
			<lb />
			Sheikh v. State of Gujarat (2004) 4 SCC 158, this Hon&apos;ble Court held
			<lb />
			that:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot;65. In a country like ours with heterogeneous religions and
				<lb />
				multiracial and multilingual society which necessitates
				<lb />
				protection against discrimination on the ground of caste or
				<lb />
				religion taking lives of persons belonging to one or the other
				<lb />
				religion is bound to have dangerous repercussions and reactive
				<lb />
				effect on the society at large and may tend to encourage
				<lb />
				fissiparous elements to undermine the unity and security of the
				<lb />
				nation on account of internal disturbances. It strikes at the very
				<lb />
				root of an orderly society, which the founding fathers of our
				<lb />
				Constitution dreamt of.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				66. When the ghastly killings take place in the land of Mahatma
				<lb />
				Gandhi, it raises a very pertinent question as to whether some
				<lb />
				people have become so bankrupt in their ideology that they
				<lb />
				have deviated from everything which was so dear to him. When
				<lb />
				a large number of people including innocent and helpless
				<lb />
				children and women are killed in a diabolic manner it brings
				<lb />
				disgrace to the entire society. Criminals have no religion. No
				<lb />
				religion teaches violence and cruelty-based religion is no
				<lb />
				religion at all, but a mere cloak to usurp power by fanning ill
				<lb />
				feeling and playing on feelings aroused thereby. The golden
				<lb />
				thread passing through every religion is love and compassion.
				<lb />
				The fanatics who spread violence in the name of religion are
				<lb />
				worse than terrorists and more dangerous than an alien
				<lb />
				enemy.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			71. The Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court has recognized &apos;hate speech&apos; as being
			<lb />
			violative of constitutional guarantees under Article 14, 15 and 21. In the
			<lb />
			case of Pravasi Bhalai Sangathan v. Union of India (2014) 11 SCC 477,
			<lb />
			at Paragraph 8, it has been held that it is the idea of discrimination that
			<lb />
			lies at the heart of hate speech principles. It was held as under:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot;8. Hate speech is an effort to marginalise individuals based on
				<lb />
				their membership in a group. Using expression that exposes the
				<lb />
				group to hatred, hate speech seeks to delegitimise group
				<lb />
				members in the eyes of the majority, reducing their social
				<lb />
				standing and acceptance within society. Hate speech, therefore,
				<lb />
				rises beyond causing distress to individual group members. It
				<lb />
				can have a societal impact. Hate speech lays the groundwork
				<lb />
				for later, broad attacks on 26 vulnerable sections that can
				<lb />
				range from discrimination, to ostracism, segregation,
				<lb />
				deportation, violence and, in the most extreme cases, to
				<lb />
				genocide. Hate speech also impacts a protected group&apos;s ability
				<lb />
				to respond to the substantive idea under debate, thereby placing
				<lb />
				a serious barrier to their full participation in our democracy.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			72. By way of the said judgment, the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court has
			<lb />
			specified that laws related to &quot;Hate Speech&quot; must be applied
			<lb />
			&quot;objectively&quot; and has noted that the problem with laws relating to Hate
			<lb />
			Speech is rooted in their non-execution.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			73. Pursuant to the aforesaid judgment of Pravasi Bhalai Sangathan
			<lb />
			(supra) the Law Commission of India reviewed the laws on Hate speech
			<lb />
			and made recommendations in its 267 th Report. Relevant extracts from
			<lb />
			the same are reproduced hereunder:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot;Tests for determining hate speech
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				4.13 Three tests have been adopted by the courts while
				<lb />
				recognising whether a speech amounts hate speech or not.
				<lb />
				Once it has been established that there has been an interference
				<lb />
				with freedom of the courts resort to a three-fold
				<lb />
				analysis to determine the legitimacy of such interference:
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(a) Is the interference prescribed by law? The law that
				<lb />
				allows limitation of article 10 of ECHR must be
				<lb />
				prescribed by the statute and must be precise so that
				<lb />
				the citizens can regulate their conduct in accordance
				<lb />
				with the law and foresee the consequences of the
				<lb />
				impermissible conduct.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(b) Is the interference proportionate to the legitimate
				<lb />
				aim pursued? It has been opined by the court in
				<lb />
				Handyside v. United Kingdom,49 that the restrictions
				<lb />
				imposed by the State under article 10(2) on freedom of
				<lb />
				expression must be &apos;proportionate to the legitimate
				<lb />
				aim pursued.&apos;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(c) Is the interference necessary in a democratic
				<lb />
				society? This test requires a careful examination of the
				<lb />
				fact to determine whether the freedom was limited in
				<lb />
				pursuance of a legitimate social need and in order to
				<lb />
				protect the principles and values underlying ECHR.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				XXX
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				5.3 In order to qualify as hate speech, the speech must be
				<lb />
				offensive and project the extreme form of emotion. Every
				<lb />
				offensive statement, however, does not amount to hate speech.
				<lb />
				The expressions advocacy and discussion of sensitive and
				<lb />
				unpopular issue have been termed &apos;low value speech&apos;
				<lb />
				unqualified for constitutional protection.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				XXX
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				6.2 Incitement to violence cannot be the sole test for
				<lb />
				determining whether a speech amounts to hate speech or not.
				<lb />
				Even speech that does not incite violence has the potential of
				<lb />
				marginalising a certain section of the society or individual. In
				<lb />
				the age of technology, the anonymity of internet allows a
				<lb />
				miscreant to easily spread false and offensive ideas. These ideas
				<lb />
				need not always incite violence but they might perpetuate the
				<lb />
				discriminatory attitudes prevalent in the society. Thus,
				<lb />
				incitement to discrimination is also a significant factor that
				<lb />
				contributes to the identification of hate speech.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			74. This Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court in the case of Amish Devgan v Union
			<lb />
			of India 2020 SCC OnLine SC 994, has reiterated the continuing
			<lb />
			obstruction that &apos;Hate Speech&apos; causes to targeted groups in terms of their
			<lb />
			participation in social, economic and political life. This Hon&apos;ble Court
			<lb />
			held as under:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot;31.3. … Hate propaganda argues for a society with subversion
				<lb />
				of democracy and denial of respect and dignity to individuals
				<lb />
				based on group identities.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				***
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				108. … in a polity committed to pluralism, hate speech cannot
				<lb />
				conceivably contribute in any legitimate way to democracy and,
				<lb />
				in fact, repudiates the right to equality&quot;.
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			75. In the case of Patricia Mukhim v. State of Meghalaya and Ors., in
			<lb />
			Criminal Appeal No. 141 of 2021, dated 25 th March 2021, the Hon&apos;ble
			<lb />
			Supreme Court while referring to its earlier rulings including Bilal
			<lb />
			Ahmed Kaloo v. State of A.P. (1997) 7 SCC 431 and Ramesh v. Union
			<lb />
			of India (1998) 1 SCC 668, and Pravasi Bhalai Sangathan v. of
			<lb />
			India &amp; Ors. (supra), the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court held that:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot;Free speech of citizens of this country cannot be stifled by
				<lb />
				implicating them in criminal cases, unless such speech as the
				<lb />
				tendency to affect public order.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			76. Therefore, before initiating criminal proceedings for what one
			<lb />
			thinks it to be hate speech, the words of the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court must
			<lb />
			be taken into consideration.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			77. In India, the constitutionality of hate speech restrictions has been
			<lb />
			upheld in the interest of &apos;public order&apos; in as much as it continues to be
			<lb />
			punishable under the Indian Penal Code, 1860 as well as other laws and
			<lb />
			statutes in force, an illustrative list of which is provided hereunder:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<figure type="table">
			Statute
			<lb />
			Provisions
			<lb />
			Indian Penal Code, 1860
			<lb />
			Sections 124A, 153A, 153B,
			<lb />
			295-A, 298, 505(1), 505(2)
			<lb />
			The Representation of People Act,
			<lb />
			1951
			<lb />
			Sections 8, 123 (3A), 125
			<lb />
			Information Technology Act, 2000 &amp;
			<lb />
			Information
			<lb />
			Technology
			<lb />
			(Intermediaries guidelines) Rules,
			<lb />
			2011
			<lb />
			Sections 66A, 69, 69A Rule
			<lb />
			3(2)(b), Rule 3(2)(i)
			<lb />
			Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973
			<lb />
			Sections 95, 107, 144, 151, 160
			<lb />
			Unlawful Activities (Prevention)
			<lb />
			Act, 1967
			<lb />
			Sections 2(f), 10, 11, 12
			<lb />
			Protection of Civil Rights Act, 1955 Section 7
			<lb />
			Religious Institutions (Prevention of
			<lb />
			Misuse) Act, 1980
			<lb />
			Sections 3 and 6
			<lb />
			The Cable Television Networks
			<lb />
			(Regulation) Act, 1995 and The
			<lb />
			Cable Television Network (Rules),
			<lb />
			1994
			<lb />
			Sections 5,6,11,12,16, 17, 19, 20
			<lb />
			&amp; Rules 6 &amp; 7
			<lb />
			The Cinematographers Act, 1952
			<lb />
			Sections 4, 5B, 7
			<lb />
		</figure>
		<p>
			78. The statutory provisions and particularly the penal law provide
			<lb />
			sufficient remedy to curb the menace of &quot;hate speeches&quot;. The executive
			<lb />
			as well as civil society has to perform its role in enforcing the already
			<lb />
			existing legal regime.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			79. Effective regulation of &quot;hate speeches&quot; at all levels is required and
			<lb />
			all the law enforcing agencies must ensure that the existing law is not
			<lb />
			rendered a dead letter. Enforcement of the aforesaid provisions is
			<lb />
			required being in consonance with the proposition &quot;salus reipublicae
			<lb />
			suprema lex&quot; (safety of the state is the supreme law).
			<lb />
		</p>
		<head>
			Section 196 of the Code and Requirement of Sanction
			<lb />
		</head>
		<p>
			80. Before delving into the question regarding the requirement of
			<lb />
			sanction under Section 196 and the stage at which such a sanction is
			<lb />
			required to be seen, it is pertinent that the provision be perused and
			<lb />
			analysed.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			81. Section 196 of the Code reads as under:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot;196. Prosecution for offences against the State and for
				<lb />
				criminal conspiracy to commit such offence.-
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(1) No Court shall take cognizance of-
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(a) any offence punishable under Chapter VI or under
				<lb />
				Section 153-A, Section 295-A or sub-section (1) of
				<lb />
				Section 505 of the Indian Penal Code, 1860 (45 of
				<lb />
				1860), or
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(b) a criminal conspiracy to commit such offence, or
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(c) any such abetment, as is described in Section 108-A
				<lb />
				of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860),
				<lb />
				except with the previous sanction of the Central Government or
				<lb />
				of the State Government.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(1-A) No Court shall take cognizance of-
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(a) any offence punishable under Section 153-B or
				<lb />
				sub-section (2) or sub-section (3) of Section 505 of the
				<lb />
				Indian Penal Code, 1860 (45 of 1860), or
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(b) a conspiracy to commit such offence,
			</item>
			<lb />
			<item>
				except with the previous sanction of the Central Government or
				<lb />
				of the State Government or of the District Magistrate.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(2) No court shall take cognizance of the offence of any
				<lb />
				criminal conspiracy punishable under Section 120-B of the
				<lb />
				Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860), other than a criminal
				<lb />
				conspiracy to commit an offence punishable with death,
				<lb />
				imprisonment for life or rigorous imprisonment for a term of
				<lb />
				two years or upwards, unless the State Government or the
				<lb />
				District Magistrate has consented in writing to the initiation of
				<lb />
				the proceedings:
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				Provided that where the criminal conspiracy is one to
				<lb />
				which the provisions of Section 195 apply, no such consent
				<lb />
				shall be necessary.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(3) The Central Government or the State Government may,
				<lb />
				before according sanction under sub-section (1) or sub-section
				<lb />
				(1-A) and the District Magistrate may, before according
				<lb />
				sanction under sub-section (1-A) and the State Government or
				<lb />
				the District Magistrate may, before giving consent under sub-
				<lb />
				section (2), order a preliminary investigation by a police officer
				<lb />
				not being below the rank of Inspector, in which case such police
				<lb />
				officer shall have the powers referred to in sub-section (3) of
				<lb />
				Section 155.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			82. Upon studying the aforesaid provision one can unambiguously
			<lb />
			infer that no court can take cognizance of any offence punishable under
			<lb />
			Chapter VI or under Section 153A, 295A or sub-section (1) of Section
			<lb />
			505 of IPC without previous sanction of the Central Government or the
			<lb />
			State Government as the case may be. Similarly, Section 197 provides
			<lb />
			that when any person who is or was a public servant not removable from
			<lb />
			his office save by or with the sanction of the Government is accused of
			<lb />
			any offence alleged to have been committed by him while acting or
			<lb />
			purporting to act in discharge of his official duty, no court shall take
			<lb />
			cognizance of such offence except with the previous sanction. In the
			<lb />
			instant case, the allegations have been levelled under various Sections
			<lb />
			including Section 295-A, 153-A and Section 505 of the IPC, all of which
			<lb />
			require prior sanction for prosecution under Section 196 of the Code.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			83. For deciding the question as to at what stage the requirement of
			<lb />
			sanction is to be seen, it is pertinent to refer to the decided case laws
			<lb />
			relied upon by the parties.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			84.
			<lb />
			In the case of Anil Kumar v. M.K. Aiyappa, (2013) 10 SCC 705,
			<lb />
			it was held as under:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot;11. The scope of Section 156(3) CrPC came up for
				<lb />
				consideration before this Court in several cases. This Court in
				<lb />
				Maksud Saiyed case [(2008) 5 SCC 668 : (2008) 2 SCC (Cri)
				<lb />
				692] examined the requirement of the application of mind by
				<lb />
				the Magistrate before exercising jurisdiction under Section
				<lb />
				156(3) and held that where jurisdiction is exercised on a
				<lb />
				complaint filed in terms of Section 156(3) or Section 200 CrPC,
				<lb />
				the Magistrate is required to apply his mind, in such a case, the
				<lb />
				Special Judge/Magistrate cannot refer the matter under Section
				<lb />
				156(3) against a public servant without a valid sanction order.
				<lb />
				The application of mind by the Magistrate should be reflected in
				<lb />
				the order. The mere statement that he has gone through the
				<lb />
				complaint, documents and heard the complainant, as such, as
				<lb />
				reflected in the order, will not be sufficient. After going through
				<lb />
				the complaint, documents and hearing the complainant, what
				<lb />
				weighed with the Magistrate to order investigation under
				<lb />
				Section 156(3) CrPC, should be reflected in the order, though a
				<lb />
				detailed expression of his views is neither required nor
				<lb />
				warranted. We have already extracted the order passed by the
				<lb />
				learned Special Judge which, in our view, has stated no reasons
				<lb />
				for ordering investigation.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				13. The expression &quot;cognizance&quot; which appears in Section 197
				<lb />
				CrPC came up for consideration before a three-Judge Bench of
				<lb />
				this Court in State of U.P. v. Paras Nath Singh [(2009) 6 SCC
				<lb />
				372 : (2009) 2 SCC (L&amp;S) 200] , and this Court expressed the
				<lb />
				following view: (SCC pp. 375, para 6)
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				&quot;6. … &apos;10. … And the jurisdiction of a Magistrate to
				<lb />
				take cognizance of any offence is provided by Section
				<lb />
				190 of the Code, either on receipt of a complaint, or
				<lb />
				upon a police report or upon information received
				<lb />
				from any person other than a police officer, or upon
				<lb />
				his knowledge that such offence has been committed.
				<lb />
				So far as public servants are concerned, the
				<lb />
				cognizance of any offence, by any court, is barred by
				<lb />
				Section 197 of the Code unless sanction is obtained
				<lb />
				from the appropriate authority, if the offence, alleged
				<lb />
				to have been committed, was in discharge of the
				<lb />
				official duty. The section not only specifies the persons
				<lb />
				to whom the protection is afforded but it also specifies
				<lb />
				the conditions and circumstances in which it shall be
				<lb />
				available and the effect in law if the conditions are
				<lb />
				satisfied. The mandatory character of the protection
				<lb />
				afforded to a public servant is brought out by the
				<lb />
				expression, &apos;no court shall take cognizance of such
				<lb />
				offence except with the previous sanction&apos;. Use of the
				<lb />
				words &apos;no&apos; and &apos;shall&apos; makes it abundantly clear that
				<lb />
				the bar on the exercise of power of the court to take
				<lb />
				cognizance of any offence is absolute and complete.
				<lb />
				The very cognizance is barred. That is, the complaint
				<lb />
				cannot be taken notice of. According to Black&apos;s Law
				<lb />
				Dictionary the word &apos;cognizance&apos; means &apos;jurisdiction&apos;
				<lb />
				or &apos;the exercise of jurisdiction&apos; or &apos;power to try and
				<lb />
				determine causes&apos;. In common parlance, it means
				<lb />
				taking notice of. A court, therefore, is precluded from
				<lb />
				entertaining a complaint or taking notice of it or
				<lb />
				exercising jurisdiction if it is in respect of a public
				<lb />
				servant who is accused of an offence alleged to have
				<lb />
				been committed during discharge of his official duty.&apos;
				<lb />
				[Ed.: As observed in State of H.P. v. M.P. Gupta,
				<lb />
				(2004) 2 SCC 349, 358, para 10 : 2004 SCC (Cri)
				<lb />
				539.] &quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			85. Further, the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court in Army Headquarters v. CBI
			<lb />
			(2012) 6 SCC 228 opined as follows:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot;82. Thus, in view of the above, the law on the issue of sanction
				<lb />
				can be summarised to the effect that the question of sanction is
				<lb />
				of paramount importance for protecting a public servant who
				<lb />
				has acted in good faith while performing his duty. In order that
				<lb />
				the public servant may not be unnecessarily harassed on a
				<lb />
				complaint of an unscrupulous person, it is obligatory on the
				<lb />
				part of the executive authority to protect him.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				83. If the law requires sanction, and the court proceeds against
				<lb />
				a public servant without sanction, the public servant has a right
				<lb />
				to raise the issue of jurisdiction as the entire action may be
				<lb />
				rendered void ab initio….&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			86. In the case of L. Narayana Swamy v. State of Karnataka, (2016) 9
			<lb />
			SCC 598, it was held as under:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot;12. As is clear from the plain language of the said section, the
				<lb />
				court is precluded from taking &quot;cognizance&quot; of an offence
				<lb />
				under certain sections mentioned in this provision if the
				<lb />
				prosecution is against the public servant, unless previous
				<lb />
				sanction of the Government (Central or State, as the case may
				<lb />
				be) has been obtained. What is relevant for our purposes is that
				<lb />
				this section bars taking cognizance of an offence. The question
				<lb />
				is whether it will cover within its sweep, order directing
				<lb />
				investigation under Section CrPC? The High Court has
				<lb />
				taken the view, in the impugned judgment [Shashidhar v. State
				<lb />
				of Karnataka, 2014 SCC OnLine Kar 12287], that bar is from
				<lb />
				taking cognizance which would not apply at the stage of
				<lb />
				investigation by the investigating officer. It is observed that
				<lb />
				sanction is required only after investigation and that too when,
				<lb />
				after investigation, it is found that there is substantial truth in
				<lb />
				the investigation report as to what amounts to cognizance of
				<lb />
				offence.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			87. In the same judgment, it was further held as under:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			&quot;14. In State of W.B. v. Mohd. Khalid [State of W.B. v. Mohd.
			<lb />
			Khalid, (1995) 1 SCC 684 : 1995 SCC (Cri) 266] , this Court
			<lb />
			has observed as follows:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&apos;13. It is necessary to mention here that taking
				<lb />
				cognizance of an offence is not the same thing as
				<lb />
				issuance of process. Cognizance is taken at the initial
				<lb />
				stage when the Magistrate applies his judicial mind to
				<lb />
				the facts mentioned in a complaint or to a police report
				<lb />
				or upon information received from any other person
				<lb />
				that an offence has been committed. The issuance of
				<lb />
				process is at a subsequent stage when after
				<lb />
				considering the material placed before it the court
				<lb />
				decides to proceed against the offenders against whom
				<lb />
				a prima facie case is made out.&apos; [Ed.: As considered in
				<lb />
				State of Karnataka v. Pastor P. Raju, (2006) 6 SCC
				<lb />
				728, 734, para 13 : (2006) 3 SCC (Cri) 179]
				<lb />
				The meaning of the said expression was also considered by this
				<lb />
				Court in Subramanian Swamy case [Subramanian Swamy v.
				<lb />
				Manmohan Singh, (2012) 3 SCC 64 : (2012) 1 SCC (Cri) 1041 :
				<lb />
				(2012) 2 SCC (L&amp;S) 666] .
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				15. The judgments referred to hereinabove clearly indicate that
				<lb />
				the word &quot;cognizance&quot; has a wider connotation and is not
				<lb />
				merely confined to the stage of taking cognizance of the offence.
				<lb />
				When a Special Judge refers a complaint for investigation
				<lb />
				under Section 156(3) CrPC, obviously, he has not taken
				<lb />
				cognizance of the offence therefore, it is a pre-cognizance
				<lb />
				stage and cannot be equated with post-cognizance stage. When
				<lb />
				a Special Judge takes cognizance of the offence on a complaint
				<lb />
				presented under Section 200 CrPC and the next step to be taken
				<lb />
				is to follow up under Section 202 CrPC. Consequently, a
				<lb />
				Special Judge referring the case for investigation under Section
				<lb />
				156(3) is at pre-cognizance stage.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				***
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				21. The learned Senior Counsel appearing for the appellants
				<lb />
				raised the contention that the requirement of sanction is only
				<lb />
				procedural in nature and hence, directory or else Section 19(3)
				<lb />
				would be rendered otiose. We find it difficult to accept that
				<lb />
				contention. Sub-section (3) of Section 19 has an object to
				<lb />
				achieve, which applies in circumstances where a Special Judge
				<lb />
				has already rendered a finding, sentence or order. In such an
				<lb />
				event, it shall not be reversed or altered by a court in appeal,
				<lb />
				confirmation or revision on the ground of absence of sanction.
				<lb />
				That does not mean that the requirement to obtain sanction is
				<lb />
				not a mandatory requirement. Once it is noticed that there was
				<lb />
				no previous sanction, as already indicated in various judgments
				<lb />
				referred to hereinabove, the Magistrate cannot order
				<lb />
				investigation against a public servant while invoking powers
				<lb />
				under Section 156(3) CrPC. The above legal position, as
				<lb />
				already indicated, has been clearly spelt out in Paras Nath
				<lb />
				Singh [State of U.P. v. Paras Nath Singh, (2009) 6 SCC 372 :
				<lb />
				(2009) 2 SCC (L&amp;S) 200] and Subramanian Swamy
				<lb />
				[Subramanian Swamy v. Manmohan Singh, (2012) 3 SCC 64 :
				<lb />
				(2012) 1 SCC (Cri) 1041 : (2012) 2 SCC (L&amp;S) 666] cases.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				Having regard to the ratio of the aforesaid judgment [Anil
				<lb />
				Kumar v. Aiyappa, (2013) 10 SCC 705 : (2014) 1 SCC
				<lb />
				(Cri) 35] , we have no hesitation in answering the questions of
				<lb />
				law, as formulated in para 10 above, in the negative. In other
				<lb />
				words, we hold that an order directing further investigation
				<lb />
				under Section 156(3) CrPC cannot be passed in the absence of
				<lb />
				valid sanction.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			88. The term &quot;cognizance&quot; has not been defined anywhere in the Code.
			<lb />
			Its origin can be traced to the Old French root &quot;conoisance&quot;, as well as to
			<lb />
			the Latin word &quot;cognoscere&quot;. The word has been defined in Black&apos;s Law
			<lb />
			Dictionary, 8 th Edition as follows:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot;Cognizance-
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(1) A court&apos;s right and power to try and to determine cases;
				<lb />
				Jurisdiction,
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(2) The taking of judicial or authoritative notice.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(3) Acknowledgement or admission of an alleged fact.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(4) Common Law Pleading. In a replevin action, a plea by the
				<lb />
				defendant that the goods are held in bailment for another.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			89. The Advanced Law Lexicon by P. Ramanatha Aiyar defines
			<lb />
			&apos;Cognizance&apos; in the following manner:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot;Cognizance. -Judicial notice or knowledge; the judicial
				<lb />
				recognition or hearing of a cause; jurisdiction, or right to try
				<lb />
				and determine causes. It is a word of the largest import:
				<lb />
				embracing all power, authority and jurisdiction. The word
				<lb />
				&quot;cognizance&quot; is used in the sense of &quot;right to take notice of and
				<lb />
				determine a cause.&quot; Taking cognizance does not involve any
				<lb />
				formal action, or indeed action of any kind, but occurs as soon
				<lb />
				as a Magistrate, as such, applies his mind of the suspected
				<lb />
				commission of an offence....&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			90. The Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court in the case of State of Himachal
			<lb />
			Pradesh v. M.P. Gupta, (2004) 2 SCC 349, had the occasion to consider
			<lb />
			the expression &apos;Cognizance&apos;. In paragraph 10 of the judgment, following
			<lb />
			was stated:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot;10. … According to Black&apos;s Law Dictionary the word
				<lb />
				&quot;cognizance&quot; means &quot;jurisdiction&quot; or &quot;the exercise of
				<lb />
				jurisdiction&quot; or &quot;power to try and determine causes&quot;. In
				<lb />
				common parlance, it means taking notice of. A court, therefore,
				<lb />
				is precluded from entertaining a complaint or taking notice of it
				<lb />
				or exercising jurisdiction if it is in respect of a public servant
				<lb />
				who is Accused of an offence alleged to have been committed
				<lb />
				during discharge of his official duty.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			91. Taking cognizance by the court only means that the court has taken
			<lb />
			note of the offence which has been alleged against the accused persons.
			<lb />
			The judgments referred to hereinabove clearly indicate that the word
			<lb />
			&quot;cognizance&quot; has a wider connotation and is not merely confined to the
			<lb />
			stage of taking cognizance of the offence.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			92. It is well settled law that the court while exercising power under
			<lb />
			Section 156(3) of CrPC is required to apply its mind before any order for
			<lb />
			registration of FIR can be passed.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			93. Furthermore, an additional layer of scrutiny albeit discretionary has
			<lb />
			been provided under Section 196(3) which says that the Government
			<lb />
			before granting such sanction may order a preliminary investigation by a
			<lb />
			police officer not below the rank of police officer. Such safeguard has
			<lb />
			neither been envisioned nor been provided for under Section 197.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			94. Therefore, the legislative intent behind the provision was crystal
			<lb />
			clear that the offences mentioned under Section 196 should not be
			<lb />
			ordered to be investigated in a routine manner. If such investigations are
			<lb />
			ordered in routine manner for the offences under Section 295-A, 153-A
			<lb />
			and Section 505, that would lead to a situation where thousands of FIRs
			<lb />
			would be registered to settle scores against political opponents across the
			<lb />
			country. This would not only be undesirable and an abuse of process but
			<lb />
			would also result in choking of the already overburdened criminal justice
			<lb />
			machinery.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			95. Thus, the Legislature, being wary of such a situation, in its wisdom
			<lb />
			has incorporated this two-tier mechanism, firstly, in the form of a
			<lb />
			sanction and secondly, in the form of a preliminary investigation before
			<lb />
			granting any sanction.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			96. The learned counsel for the petitioner has argued that the sanction
			<lb />
			is only required when the court takes cognizance after filing of a
			<lb />
			chargesheet and for the purpose of giving directions for investigation
			<lb />
			under Section 156(3) of CrPC, no such sanction is required. This issue is,
			<lb />
			however, no longer res integra. The Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court in the case
			<lb />
			of Anil Kumar (supra) and L. Narayana Swamy v. State of Karnataka &amp;
			<lb />
			Ors. (2016) 9 SCC 598 has specifically held that the court cannot direct
			<lb />
			registration of FIR or investigation into an offence while exercising
			<lb />
			power under Section 156(3) of Code in relation to offence where the
			<lb />
			sanction is required to be taken before a court can take cognizance.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<head>
			Limitations of Writ Jurisdiction
			<lb />
		</head>
		<p>
			97. In order to appreciate the case at hand, it is pertinent to refer to the
			<lb />
			of law laid down as to the exercise of the writ jurisdiction by the
			<lb />
			High Court.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			98. In the landmark case of Whirlpool Corporation. v. Registrar of
			<lb />
			Trade Marks (1998) 8 SCC 1, the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court had held as
			<lb />
			follows: -
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot;15. Under Article 226 of the Constitution, the High Court,
				<lb />
				having regard to the facts of the case, has a discretion to
				<lb />
				entertain or not to entertain a writ petition. But the High Court
				<lb />
				has imposed upon itself certain restrictions one of which is that
				<lb />
				if an effective and efficacious remedy is available, the High
				<lb />
				Court would not normally exercise its jurisdiction. But the
				<lb />
				alternative remedy has been consistently held by this Court not
				<lb />
				to operate as a bar in at least three contingencies, namely,
				<lb />
				where the writ petition has been filed for the enforcement of any
				<lb />
				of the Fundamental Rights or where there has been a violation
				<lb />
				of the principle of natural justice or where the order or
				<lb />
				proceedings are wholly without jurisdiction or the vires of an
				<lb />
				Act is challenged.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			99. Another ancillary question that is -can a person straightaway
			<lb />
			approach the High Court against the refusal of police to register an FIR?
			<lb />
			The same stands answered by the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court in the case of
			<lb />
			Sudhir Bhaskarrao Tambe v. Hemant Yashwant Dhage, 2016 (6) SCC
			<lb />
			277. It was held that if a person has a grievance that the police have not
			<lb />
			registered his complaint, or having registered it, they have not
			<lb />
			investigated it properly, then the aggrieved person&apos;s remedy is not to go to
			<lb />
			the High Court under Article 226 of the Constitution of India, but to
			<lb />
			approach the Magistrate concerned under Section 156(3) of the Code.
			<lb />
			The Hon&apos;ble Court held as under:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot;2. This Court has held in Sakiri Vasu v. State of U.P. [Sakiri
				<lb />
				Vasu v. State of U.P., (2008) 2 SCC 409 : (2008) 1 SCC (Cri)
				<lb />
				440 : AIR 2008 SC 907] , that if a person has a grievance that
				<lb />
				his FIR has not been registered by the police, or having been
				<lb />
				registered, proper investigation is not being done, then the
				<lb />
				remedy of the aggrieved person is not to go to the High Court
				<lb />
				under Article 226 of the Constitution of India, but to approach
				<lb />
				the Magistrate concerned under Section 156(3) CrPC. If such
				<lb />
				an application under Section 156(3) CrPC is made and the
				<lb />
				Magistrate is, prima facie, satisfied, he can direct the FIR to be
				<lb />
				registered, or if it has already been registered, he can direct
				<lb />
				proper investigation to be done which includes in his discretion,
				<lb />
				if he deems it necessary, recommending change of the
				<lb />
				investigating officer, so that a proper investigation is done in
				<lb />
				the matter. We have said this in Sakiri Vasu case [Sakiri
				<lb />
				Vasu v. State of U.P., (2008) 2 SCC 409 : (2008) 1 SCC (Cri)
				<lb />
				440 : AIR 2008 SC 907] because what we have found in this
				<lb />
				country is that the High Courts have been flooded with writ
				<lb />
				petitions praying for registration of the first information report
				<lb />
				or praying for a proper investigation.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				3. We are of the opinion that if the High Courts entertain such
				<lb />
				writ petitions, then they will be flooded with such writ petitions
				<lb />
				and will not be able to do any other work except dealing with
				<lb />
				such writ petitions. Hence, we have held that the complainant
				<lb />
				must avail of his alternate remedy to approach the Magistrate
				<lb />
				concerned under Section 156(3) CrPC and if he does so, the
				<lb />
				Magistrate will ensure, if prima facie he is satisfied,
				<lb />
				registration of the first information report and also ensure a
				<lb />
				proper investigation in the matter, and he can also monitor the
				<lb />
				investigation.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			100. A Division Bench of the Allahabad High Court while deciding the
			<lb />
			case of Waseem Haider v. State of U. P. Through Principal Secretary
			<lb />
			Home, Lucknow and Ors. Misc. Bench No. 24492 of 2020, decided on
			<lb />
			14 th December 2020, was of the opinion that the power to issue a writ of
			<lb />
			mandamus has its own well defined self-imposed limitations, one of
			<lb />
			which is the availability of alternative efficacious remedy. In the
			<lb />
			aforesaid judgment, the Division Bench has exhaustively dealt with the
			<lb />
			alternative remedies available to a person aggrieved by non-registration
			<lb />
			of FIR by the police. The Bench inter alia held that:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot;The writ remedy is extra-ordinary remedy and equitable
				<lb />
				remedy. Further, the writ Court need not entertain a writ
				<lb />
				petition merely because a case is made out of alleged inaction
				<lb />
				or negligent in acting on an issue by an authority vested with
				<lb />
				power, in these cases to register crime/to complete investigation
				<lb />
				into crime, if statutorily engrafted remedy is available to seek
				<lb />
				redress on such grievance. Even if, a case is made out on
				<lb />
				alleged illegal action by statutory authority, which require
				<lb />
				redressal, ordinarily writ Court does not entertain the writ
				<lb />
				petition if the aggrieved person has not availed other remedies,
				<lb />
				more so, such remedies are incorporated in a statute.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			101. While explaining the remedies available under the Code, the Court
			<lb />
			also observed:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot;Code of Criminal Procedure incorporates enough safeguards
				<lb />
				to victims and accused. It lays down detailed procedure in
				<lb />
				conducting investigation, filing of final report, taking of
				<lb />
				cognizance, conducting of trial. It provides enough safeguards
				<lb />
				against illegal action of police. It is a self contained code and
				<lb />
				comprehensive on all aspects of criminal law. A complainant
				<lb />
				has statutorily engrafted remedies to ensure that his complaint
				<lb />
				is taken to its logical end. Thus, he must first exhaust said
				<lb />
				remedies and cannot invoke extra-ordinary writ remedy as a
				<lb />
				matter of course, even when crime is not registered and there is
				<lb />
				no progress in the investigation.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			102. In the case of Radha Krishan Industries v. State of Himachal
			<lb />
			Pradesh 2021 SCC OnLine SC 334, the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court has
			<lb />
			reiterated and summarized the principles governing the exercise of writ
			<lb />
			jurisdiction by the High Court in the presence of an alternate remedy. The
			<lb />
			Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court has observed:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot;28. The principles of law which emerge are that:
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(i) The power under Article 226 of the Constitution to
				<lb />
				issue writs can be exercised not only for the
				<lb />
				enforcement of fundamental rights, but for any other
				<lb />
				purpose as well;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(ii) The High Court has the discretion not to entertain
				<lb />
				a writ petition. One of the restrictions placed on the
				<lb />
				power of the High Court is where an effective
				<lb />
				alternate remedy is available to the aggrieved person;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(iii) Exceptions to the rule of alternate remedy arise
				<lb />
				where (a) the writ petition has been filed for the
				<lb />
				enforcement of a fundamental right protected by Part
				<lb />
				III of the Constitution; (b) there has been a violation of
				<lb />
				the principles of natural justice; (c) the order or
				<lb />
				proceedings are wholly without jurisdiction; or (d) the
				<lb />
				vires of a legislation is challenged;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(iv) An alternate remedy by itself does not divest the
				<lb />
				High Court of its powers under Article 226 of the
				<lb />
				Constitution in an appropriate case though ordinarily,
				<lb />
				a writ petition should not be entertained when an
				<lb />
				efficacious alternate remedy is provided by law;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(v) When a right is created by a statute, which itself
				<lb />
				prescribes the remedy or procedure for enforcing the
				<lb />
				right or liability, resort must be had to that particular
				<lb />
				statutory remedy before invoking the discretionary
				<lb />
				remedy under Article 226 of the Constitution. This rule
				<lb />
				of exhaustion of statutory remedies is a rule of policy,
				<lb />
				convenience and discretion; and
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(vi) In cases where there are disputed questions of fact,
				<lb />
				the High Court may decide to decline jurisdiction in a
				<lb />
				writ petition. However, if the High Court is objectively
				<lb />
				of the view that the nature of the controversy requires
				<lb />
				the exercise of its writ jurisdiction, such a view would
				<lb />
				not readily be interfered with.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			103. While deciding the case of Assistant Commissioner of State Tax v.
			<lb />
			Commercial Steel Limited, 2021 SCC OnLine SC 884, a 3-judge bench
			<lb />
			of the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court held as under:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot;11. … The existence of an alternate remedy is not an absolute
				<lb />
				bar to the maintainability of a writ petition under Article 226 of
				<lb />
				the Constitution. But a writ petition can be entertained in
				<lb />
				exceptional circumstances where there is:
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(i)
				<lb />
				a breach of fundamental rights;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(ii) a violation of the principles of natural justice;
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(iii) an excess of jurisdiction; or
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				(iv) a challenge to the vires of the statute or delegated
				<lb />
				legislation.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				12. In the present case, none of the above exceptions was
				<lb />
				established. There was, in fact, no violation of the principles of
				<lb />
				natural justice since a notice was served on the person in
				<lb />
				charge of the conveyance. In this backdrop, it was not
				<lb />
				appropriate for the High Court to entertain a writ petition.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			104. Recently, while deciding the case of Kotak Mahindra Bank
			<lb />
			Limited v Dilip Bhosale, [2022 LiveLaw (SC) 545] SLP (C) 13241 of
			<lb />
			2019, the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court reiterated that when a remedy under
			<lb />
			the statute is available, filing of a writ petition under Article 226 of the
			<lb />
			Constitution is to be discouraged by the High Court. It was held as under:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot;Before parting with the order, we would like to observe that
				<lb />
				this Court is consistent of the view and can be noticed from the
				<lb />
				judgment in United Bank of India vs. Satyawati Tandon &amp;
				<lb />
				Ors. (2010) 8 SCC 110, that when a remedy under the statute is
				<lb />
				available and in the instant case which indeed was availed by
				<lb />
				the respondent/borrower, filing of a writ petition under Article
				<lb />
				226 of the Constitution is to be discouraged by the High
				<lb />
				Court.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			105. The principle that emerges from the aforementioned judgments is
			<lb />
			that the extraordinary writ jurisdiction is to be exercised only in rare cases
			<lb />
			or certain contingencies in the interest of justice, including the
			<lb />
			exceptional cases delineated above.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			106. Thus, a writ to compel the police to conduct an investigation or
			<lb />
			lodge an FIR can be denied for not exhausting the alternative and
			<lb />
			efficacious remedy available under the provisions of the Code, unless the
			<lb />
			exceptions enumerated in the decision of the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court in
			<lb />
			the aforementioned judgment are satisfied. In the instant case, the
			<lb />
			petitioner is yet to exercise and exhaust his alternative remedies available
			<lb />
			under the provisions of the Code including challenging the impugned
			<lb />
			order of the Magistrate.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			107. In light of the aforesaid, it is settled law that the power to issue writ
			<lb />
			has its own well-defined limitations imposed by the High Courts, one of
			<lb />
			which is the availability of alternative efficacious remedy. Considering
			<lb />
			the law laid down by the judicial precedents, the procedure laid down by
			<lb />
			the Code Criminal Procedure and as well as the fact that alternate and
			<lb />
			efficacious remedy is available to the petitioner which is yet to be
			<lb />
			exhausted, this Court is also of the opinion that the High Court should not
			<lb />
			ordinarily, as a matter of routine, exercise its extraordinary writ
			<lb />
			jurisdiction under Article 226 of the Constitution if an effective and
			<lb />
			efficacious alternate remedy is available.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			108. Before applying the jurisprudence delineated above to the facts of
			<lb />
			the instant case, it is pertinent to take note of a worrying phenomenon that
			<lb />
			has gained traction and is in vogue these days is of bypassing the
			<lb />
			procedure under the Code. The beauty of procedural law lies in the stages
			<lb />
			and remedies available during the course of a criminal proceeding. The
			<lb />
			High Courts have been flooded with writ petitions praying for registration
			<lb />
			of FIRs or praying for a proper investigation. If the High Courts entertain
			<lb />
			such writ petitions, it will open pandora&apos;s box and would crumble the
			<lb />
			already overtaxed system. Therefore, the alternate remedies wherever
			<lb />
			available must be exhausted, save in exceptional circumstances where the
			<lb />
			urgent intervention of this Court is required in the interest of justice,
			<lb />
			before approaching this Court.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			109. In the instant case, the petitioner also seems to have adopted a
			<lb />
			similar attitude. As per the petition, the petitioners on 29 th January 2020
			<lb />
			made a complaint against Mr. Anurag Thakur and Mr. Parvesh Verma to
			<lb />
			the Commissioner of Police, Delhi asking for registration of FIR against
			<lb />
			the two directly, without approaching the SHO. In furtherance of the said
			<lb />
			complaint, on 31 st January 2020, another letter was addressed to the
			<lb />
			Commissioner stating therein that because of inaction of police over their
			<lb />
			complaint has led to an incident wherein, according to the letter, an armed
			<lb />
			man shot at protesting students.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			110. It was only on 2 nd February 2020, the petitioners, by way of a letter
			<lb />
			addressed to the SHO, Parliament Street Police Station, New Delhi, made
			<lb />
			a request to immediately file FIRs against Mr. Anurag Thakur and Mr.
			<lb />
			Parvesh Verma, enclosing therein the two aforementioned representations
			<lb />
			made earlier to the Commissioner. And within three days of the said
			<lb />
			letter, on 5 th February 2020, the Petitioners filed an Application under
			<lb />
			Section 156(3) of the Code seeking registration of FIR before the
			<lb />
			ACMM. Again, upon a dismissal of the said complaint, the petitioners
			<lb />
			had the alternate remedy to approach the revisional court against the
			<lb />
			impugned Order rather than approaching this Court directly by way of a
			<lb />
			writ petition.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			111. Therefore, this Court holds that the instant petition despite being
			<lb />
			maintainable, does not warrant the exercise of writ jurisdiction by this
			<lb />
			Court since, first, no rights, whether fundamental or legal, of the
			<lb />
			petitioners stands violated which would have otherwise required the
			<lb />
			intervention of this Court, in so far as the right to report a cognizable
			<lb />
			offence is concerned. Second, there is no gross illegality committed in the
			<lb />
			entire proceedings before the Court below. Section 156(3) remedy had
			<lb />
			been availed of wherein the ACMM after having taken note of the Status
			<lb />
			Report filed by the Investigating Agency and applying its judicial mind to
			<lb />
			the complaint dismissed the same. Third, as discussed in the foregoing
			<lb />
			paragraphs, the petitioners have failed to follow the prescribed
			<lb />
			mechanism under the Code.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<head>
			Analysis of the Impugned Order
			<lb />
		</head>
		<p>
			112. This Court shall now test the validity of the impugned Order
			<lb />
			passed by the ACMM. The petitioners had approached the ACMM under
			<lb />
			Section 156(3) of the Code seeking order of registration of FIR against
			<lb />
			the two named persons for the alleged offences.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			113. Under the scheme of Section 156(3) of the Code, on the first date
			<lb />
			of the proceedings, ATR was called from the DCP District New Delhi.
			<lb />
			Subsequently, as per the record of the proceedings of the Court below, on
			<lb />
			11 th February 2020, ATR was filed by the Special Investigation Unit of
			<lb />
			Crime Branch and was taken on record. On the said date, the Crime
			<lb />
			Branch was directed to expedite the preliminary inquiry and file the
			<lb />
			detailed ATR in next 15 days.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			114. In the proceedings dated 26 th February 2020, the status report was
			<lb />
			filed by the investigating agency, wherein it was recorded that on the
			<lb />
			basis of allegations levelled in the complaint, prima facie no cognizable
			<lb />
			offence was found to be committed. The Copy of the Status Report was
			<lb />
			supplied to the other side and arguments were heard.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			115. On 2 nd March 2020, the Court of ACMM was informed that a WP
			<lb />
			(CRL) 565/2020 titled as &quot;Harsh Mander and Another v. GNCTD and
			<lb />
			Others&quot; was pending before this High Court containing the same
			<lb />
			averments and seeking the same relief as was being made in the
			<lb />
			petitioners&apos; application. In view of the fact that the High Court was
			<lb />
			already seized of the matter and had listed the matter for 13 th April 2020
			<lb />
			giving the opportunity to the Union of India for filing its response, the
			<lb />
			ACMM chose not to pass any order in the application till the outcome of
			<lb />
			the said writ petition.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			116. Finally, on 26 th August 2020, the ACMM-I dismissed the
			<lb />
			Petitioners&apos; Application under Section 156(3) of the Code, recording the
			<lb />
			finding that the application was not tenable in the eyes of law on the
			<lb />
			ground that there was no previous sanction obtained by the
			<lb />
			complainants/petitioners from the competent authority to prosecute the
			<lb />
			named individuals for the offences alleged in the complaint.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				117. Before analysing the validity of the impugned Order, it is pertinent
				<lb />
				to peruse the findings of the Status Report filed by the Investigating
				<lb />
				Agency, which was considered by the ACMM. The contents of the said
				<lb />
				Status Report are paraphrased hereunder:
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				a. Regarding the allegations against Mr. Thakur, it is stated
				<lb />
				that the connotation/meaning of the word &quot;gaddar&quot; is
				<lb />
				traitor, and as such does not target or refer to any specific
				<lb />
				community. Thus, it does not amount to commission of
				<lb />
				any cognizable offence as alleged by the complainants.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				b. Qua the allegations regarding Mr. Verma, it is stated that
				<lb />
				the speaker has only stated his position on the erstwhile
				<lb />
				protest ongoing in Shaheen Bagh, and not any specific
				<lb />
				community or its members. It is further recorded by the
				<lb />
				agency that no provocation whatsoever has been made
				<lb />
				instigating the crowd to riot or for taking any retaliatory
				<lb />
				action against the protestors.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				c. Regarding other allegations of incidents of violence being
				<lb />
				inspired by the speeches of the two leaders, it has been
				<lb />
				recorded in the Status Report that first, separate FIRs had
				<lb />
				been lodged against the accused in those cases, second,
				<lb />
				the cases had been referred to Crime Branch for further
				<lb />
				investigation, third, none of the accused as alleged of
				<lb />
				having committed the acts of violence had attributed their
				<lb />
				actions to either of the speeches made, and fourth, there
				<lb />
				was no connection whatsoever to the speeches in
				<lb />
				question and the acts of violence.
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			In light of the aforesaid, it has been recorded in the Status Report
			<lb />
			that on the basis of allegation levelled in the complaint, prima facie no
			<lb />
			cognizable offence has been found to be committed.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			118. Every institution in this country has a purpose to serve in a
			<lb />
			democratic and constitutional framework governed by the rule of law.
			<lb />
			The mandate of investigative agency such as the police is sui generis. It
			<lb />
			performs a key function to investigate the cases of crime, to detect and
			<lb />
			collect crucial evidence that would assist the Courts of law in imparting
			<lb />
			justice. Therefore, the opinion/findings of the agency merit its own
			<lb />
			significance and despite the same being contestable and justiciable in a
			<lb />
			Court, it cannot be prima facie discarded or brushed aside without
			<lb />
			application of judicial mind.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			119. On a perusal of the said report, it is evident that upon applying its
			<lb />
			mind to the facts as alleged in the complaint, the Investigating Agency in
			<lb />
			the present case has filed the status report specifically stating that no
			<lb />
			cognizable offence has been made out.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			120. Once the investigating agency upon conducting its preliminary
			<lb />
			enquiry, has come to the conclusion that prima facie no cognizable
			<lb />
			offence is made out, the ACMM must apply its mind to direct the
			<lb />
			investigation or for registration of FIR. However, as discussed earlier, for
			<lb />
			the purpose of ordering any investigation, the ACMM in the instant case
			<lb />
			would be required to take cognizance of the facts/evidence before it,
			<lb />
			which is not permissible without there being a valid sanction.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			121. Another question that has been contested by the petitioners is that
			<lb />
			the judgment of Anil Kumar (supra) is not a good law on the grounds of
			<lb />
			it being contrary to the settled law regarding Section 156(3) and
			<lb />
			cognizance; as well as on the ground that the said judgment is per
			<lb />
			incuriam. The petitioners have relied on the judgment of Manju Surana
			<lb />
			v. Sunil Arora and Ors. (supra).
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			122. As held in the case of Maharashtra v. Sarva Shramik Sangh
			<lb />
			(2013) 16 SCC 16, it is an established principle of law that until a
			<lb />
			judgment which has been referred to a larger bench is overruled, the said
			<lb />
			judgment occupies the field and continues to operate as a good law. This
			<lb />
			would continue until the larger bench decides the matter reliance is
			<lb />
			placed.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			123. As held in Union of India v. S.K. Kapoor, (2011) 4 SCC 589 at
			<lb />
			paragraph 9, it is also well settled that if a subsequent coordinate Bench
			<lb />
			of strength wants to take a different view, it can only refer the
			<lb />
			matter to a larger Bench, otherwise the prior decision of a coordinate
			<lb />
			Bench is binding on the subsequent Bench of equal strength. Therefore,
			<lb />
			reliance placed on Manju Surana (supra) is clearly misplaced.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			124. The said view taken by the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court has recently
			<lb />
			been applied by the High Court of Calcutta in the case of Dr. Nazrul
			<lb />
			Islam v. Basudeb Banerjee and Ors, 2022 SCC Online Cal 183. It was
			<lb />
			held as under: -
			<lb />
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				&quot;The subsequent judgment in Manju Surana (supra) case has
				<lb />
				referred the issue to a Larger Bench but did not declare the
				<lb />
				ratio laid down in the earlier two judgments as either per
				<lb />
				incuriam or a bad law. To that extent the submission of the
				<lb />
				learned Advocate General that an issue which could not be
				<lb />
				decided subsequently by the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court cannot be
				<lb />
				decided by a High Court on the mere asking of the petitioner,
				<lb />
				cannot be brushed aside. The submission of the learned
				<lb />
				Advocate General that in case a reference has been made on a
				<lb />
				point of law then the last of the judgment which is authority on
				<lb />
				the point would be valid is the correct proposition to be
				<lb />
				followed by this Court, as was held in M.S. Bhati Vs. National
				<lb />
				Insurance Company Ltd., (2019) 12 SCC 248; P. Sudhakar Rao
				<lb />
				&amp; Ors. Vs U. Govinda Rao &amp; Ors. (2013) 8 SCC 693; Ashoke
				<lb />
				Sadarangani &amp; Anr. Vs. Union of India and Ors., (2012) 11
				<lb />
				SCC 321; Harbhajan Singh &amp; Anr. Vs State of Punjab &amp; Anr.,
				<lb />
				(2009) 13 SCC 608.
				<lb />
			</item>
			<item>
				Having regard to the subject matter by way of which the
				<lb />
				petitioner has attempt to invoke the provisions of Section 156(3)
				<lb />
				of the Code of Criminal Procedure against the public servants
				<lb />
				this Court is of the opinion that as the provision of Section 197
				<lb />
				of the Code of Criminal Procedure has been incorporated in the
				<lb />
				statute, the same has been for a meaningful purpose of allowing
				<lb />
				the public servants to discharge their duties without fear or
				<lb />
				favour or without any anticipation of being harassed because of
				<lb />
				the rigors of law. Therefore, ordinarily a valid sanction would
				<lb />
				be required in a proceeding where the provisions of Section
				<lb />
				156(3) Cr. P.C. are invoked against public servants. However,
				<lb />
				in this case substantive offences as alleged have not been made
				<lb />
				out, so the issue of sanction is an additional consideration.&quot;
				<lb />
			</item>
		</list>
		<p>
			125. What emerges is that until a judgment which has been referred to a
			<lb />
			larger bench is overruled, the said judgment occupies the field and
			<lb />
			continues to operate as a good law. Thus, the said issue of non-
			<lb />
			applicability of the judgment of Anil Kumar (supra) stands answered in
			<lb />
			the aforesaid terms.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			126. Further, the ACMM rightly did not comment on the merits of the
			<lb />
			case while dismissing the application under Section 156(3) of the Code
			<lb />
			for want of sanction. It is a settled position of law that if the court is
			<lb />
			dismissing the case on the ground of maintainability, it should refrain
			<lb />
			from passing any order on the merits of the case.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			127. In light of the aforesaid discussion and reasoning, what emerges is
			<lb />
			firstly, that the appropriate sanction of government is required for
			<lb />
			investigation under Section 196 of the Code. Secondly, there is alternative
			<lb />
			and efficacious remedy available under the Code that needs to be taken
			<lb />
			resort of, before invoking the writ jurisdiction of this Court. Thirdly, in
			<lb />
			the instant case, the ACMM has rightly decided the application before it.
			<lb />
			The provisions of Section 156(3) for directing investigation qua offences
			<lb />
			mentioned in Section 196 of the Code cannot be exercised by the Court
			<lb />
			without sanction. There is no prima facie irregularity that is apparent
			<lb />
			upon a perusal of the impugned order. Fourthly, the petitioners have
			<lb />
			failed to satisfy Court and no case is made out warranting the
			<lb />
			intervention of this Court at this stage.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			128. Hence, in light of the foregoing discussion and analysis, there are
			<lb />
			no cogent reasons to entertain the petition and allow the prayers sought
			<lb />
			therein. In the aforesaid terms, the petition stands dismissed.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			129. Pending applications, if any, also stand disposed of.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			130. It is made clear that any observations made herein shall have no
			<lb />
			bearings whatsoever on the merits of the case during any other
			<lb />
			proceedings before any other Court.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			131. The judgment be uploaded on the website forthwith.
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			(CHANDRA DHARI SINGH)
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			JUDGE
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			June 13, 2022
			<lb />
		</p>
		<p>
			@j/@dityak.
		</p>
	</text>
</tei>
