<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
            <head> P.S.TEJI, J <lb/> </head>

			<p>1.<lb/> Aggrieved by the order dated 09.12.2015, passed by learned<lb/> Additional Sessions Judge (NW), Rohini Courts, Delhi, the petitioners<lb/> have preferred the present bail applications under Section 438 of Code<lb/> of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (hereinafter referred to as Cr. P.C.),<lb/> seeking anticipatory bail in FIR No. 811/2015 under Section<lb/> 498A/304-B/34 of IPC registered at Police Station North Rohini,<lb/> Delhi.<lb/></p>

			<p>2.<lb/> Since the present bail applications arise out of common FIR and<lb/> impugns the common order, therefore both these applications are<lb/> heard together and are being disposed of together.<lb/></p>

			<p>3.<lb/> The present case is registered at the complaint of Mr. Raj<lb/> Singh, who is father of Komal (now deceased). According to the<lb/> complainant, the marriage of his elder daughter Komal was<lb/> solemnised with Ashwini on 19.01.2014 as per Hindu Rites and<lb/> Rituals and he had spent Rs.30-32 lacs in the marriage, which<lb/> included a Hyndai Verna Car, 25 Tolas Gold and Rs.6 lacs cash for<lb/> household goods. It is alleged by the complainant that after a few days<lb/> of marriage, husband and parents-in-laws of Komal used to beat her<lb/> and demanded Rs.10 lacs from him, for which they regularly harassed<lb/> his daughter. It is further alleged by the complainant that on<lb/> 23.10.2015, her daughter called him and told him that her husband,<lb/> mother-in-law, father-in-law and sister-in-law are beating her and in<lb/> case she does not bring dowry, they will hang her. Thereupon,<lb/> complainant made his daughter understand by stating that he will<lb/> come next day, in evening and according to the complainant, on<lb/> 24.10.2015, at around 12-12.30 pm, he received a call from Police<lb/> Station that his daughter has hanged herself. Complainant has raised<lb/> doubt of his daughter been hanged forcibly by her husband Ashwini,<lb/> mother-in-law, father-in-law and sister-in-law and requested for<lb/> taking an appropriate legal action against them.<lb/></p>

			<p>4.<lb/> The case was registered, investigation was started and during<lb/> investigation, a suicide note written by the deceased was recovered<lb/> from the place of incident. Crime team was also called at spot for<lb/> inspection of the scene of crime. The dead body of the deceased was<lb/> preserved at mortuary of Dr. BSA Hospital, Rohini, Delhi. Since the<lb/> matter being death within seven years of marriage, SDM Saraswati<lb/> Vihar was intimated, who recorded the statement of parents of<lb/> deceased. Parents of deceased gave statement that before marriage no<lb/> demand of dowry was made by husband and in-laws of deceased but<lb/> after marriage husband and in-laws of deceased started manhandling<lb/> their daughter on pretext of dowry demand. It is also stated that on<lb/> 23.10.2015, the deceased Smt. Komal made a call to her father telling<lb/> him that her husband and in-laws were assaulting her and threatening<lb/> her that they will hang her if she does not give them Rs.10 lacs, upon<lb/> which her father told that he would come on 24.10.2015.<lb/></p>

			<p>5.<lb/> During the course of investigation, autopsy of the deceased was<lb/> conducted at Dr. BSA Hospital on 25.10.2015 and viscera of deceased<lb/> was preserved by doctor and sent to FSL for opinion and analysis.<lb/> The cause of death of deceased was opined by doctor on Post Motem<lb/> No. 691/15 as &quot;death is due to asphyxia consequent upon ante-<lb/>mortem hanging.&apos;&apos;<lb/></p>

			<p>6.<lb/> State has filed its status report stating that after registration of<lb/> the case, all the family members have been absconding from their<lb/> place of residence and when raids were conducted at their residence,<lb/> the house was found to be locked. It is further submitted by the State<lb/> that CDRs of mobile phones of accused persons have been obtained<lb/> and have been analysed but their whereabouts could not be traced till<lb/> now.<lb/></p>

			<p>7.<lb/> Mr. Jatan Singh, counsel, though argued on behalf of both the<lb/> petitioners, but for the purpose of the scrutiny of the case, the same<lb/> are being considered separately. Let us first take up the case of<lb/> petitioner -Shivani (Bail Appl. No.2706/2015). While arguing on<lb/> behalf of the petitioner Shivani, Mr. Jatan Singh, contended that she is<lb/> a qualified girl, having a M.Tech degree and presently working at SB<lb/> Global School, Meerut Road, Sonepat, Haryana. It is further<lb/> contended that the petitioner -Shivani leaves home at 7.30 in the<lb/> morning and comes back home at 5.30 in the evening and on the date<lb/> of incident, at the relevant time, the petitioner -Shivani was at school<lb/> and driver of her bus namely Anand Singh, has also sworn an<lb/> affidavit to this effect. It is also contended that the petitioner -Shivani<lb/> lives at the first floor of the property No.134, Pocket A-2, Sector 8,<lb/> Rohini, Delhi alongwith her parents and the deceased and her husband<lb/> lived on the third floor of the same property and had minimum<lb/> interaction with them. It is further contended that due to being<lb/> occupied in her own personal and professional life, she had no<lb/> interference in the matrimonial life of her brother and sister-in-law<lb/> and her name has been implicated by the complainant only to exert<lb/> pressure upon the family members of the petitioners. It is further<lb/> argued that the present FIR is the fabrication of the unscrupulous<lb/> mind of the complainant who is acting in connivance with his family<lb/> members and the local police and has fabricated the entire chain of<lb/> events to implicate the entire family of the petitioner and send them<lb/> behind bars. Counsel has also drawn attention of the Court towards<lb/> allegation of the complainant that he had given Hyundai Verna car to<lb/> the in-laws of the deceased at the time of her marriage, but the fact<lb/> was that the same was purchased by the complainant on 30.12.2013<lb/> on installments while the marriage was performed only on<lb/> 19.01.2014, which alone establishes the falsity of allegations levelled<lb/> by the complainant against the in-laws of the deceased. Counsel for<lb/> the petitioner further contended that since the date of marriage and till<lb/> the date of unfortunate incident, even a single complaint was not<lb/> made by the deceased or her family members against her in-laws<lb/> alleging dowry harassment and cruelty.<lb/></p>

			<p>8.<lb/> While controverting the suicide note, recovered by the<lb/> investigating agency, from the place of incident, it is argued that the<lb/> same completely exonerates all the family members from the<lb/> allegations levelled by the complainant and the said suicide letter<lb/> nowhere mentions that the deceased was being harassed by her in-<lb/>laws for dowry or that she was subjected to cruelty and harassment.<lb/> The said suicide note does not mention even the name of the<lb/> petitioners. It is further contended on behalf of the petitioner -Shivani<lb/> that she is an unmarried lady and till date has never been found guilty<lb/> of violating the law and grave prejudice shall be caused to the<lb/> petitioner -Shivani if she is sent behind bars in the company of<lb/> hardened criminals and the same would have daunting effect on her<lb/> psychological and future prospects. Counsel for the petitioner further<lb/> contended that no recovery is to be effected from the petitioner -<lb/>Shivani or at her instance, therefore she is not at all required for the<lb/> purpose of custodial interrogation, therefore the petitioner -Shivani<lb/> sought grant of anticipatory bail in this case.<lb/></p>

			<p>9.<lb/> Counsel for the petitioner -Shivani also undertook that the<lb/> petitioner -Shivani is ready to join the investigation and shall extend<lb/> full cooperation to the investigation and shall appear before the Court<lb/> as well as Investigating Officer as and when called.<lb/></p>

			<p>10. Now let the case of petitioner -Nikhil Choudhary (Bail Appln.<lb/> No. 2710/2015), who is also represented through Mr. Jatan Singh,<lb/> Advocate, be discussed. After perusing the bail application of<lb/> petitioner -Nikhil Choudhary , this Court finds that both the<lb/> applications arise out of common FIR and the contents and grounds<lb/> taken by counsel for the petitioner in both the applications are similar<lb/> and what distinguishing factor of the petitioner -Nikhil Choudhary<lb/> as contended by counsel is that petitioner -Nikhil Choudhary is<lb/> employed as a System Engineer at Infosys since 01.12.2014 and after<lb/> his initial training at Mysore, he is posted in Pune and petitioner -<lb/>Nikhil Choudhary is not living at his parental house since<lb/> 01.12.2014. In support of his contention, counsel for the petitioner has<lb/> also annexed a document showing the employment of petitioner -<lb/>Nikhil Choudhary at Infosys at Pune.<lb/></p>

			<p>11. While arguing the case of petitioner -Nikhil Choudhary ,<lb/> counsel for the petitioner contended that the petitioner -Nikhil<lb/> Choudhary was not even present at the said place of incident at the<lb/> relevant time and he was also not one of the persons who gave<lb/> beatings to the deceased on 23.10.2015. At last, it is contended on<lb/> behalf of both the petitioners that impulsiveness, dispersion,<lb/> frustration, anger or even undue or hypersensitivity of the deceased<lb/> Komal could have actuated the thought of suicide and if it led to the<lb/> deceased taking her own life, then the blame cannot be thrown at any<lb/> other person, even if he/she is in adversary. It is also contended on<lb/> behalf of the petitioner -Nikhil Choudhary that there is no mention<lb/> of his name in the suicide note recovered at the place of incident,<lb/> which however, exonerates all the family members from the<lb/> allegations levelled by the complainant.<lb/></p>

			<p>12. Lastly, it is contended on behalf of petitioner -Nikhil<lb/> Choudhary that the petitioner -Nikhil Choudhary is a 24 years old<lb/> boy and is a well educated, qualified person and his antecedents are<lb/> clear. Counsel for the petitioner further undertook that the petitioner -<lb/>Nikhil Choudhary shall remain present before the Investigating<lb/> Officer as and when required and since no recovery is to be effected<lb/> from petitioner -Nikhil Choudhary at his instance, therefore there is<lb/> no need for his custodial interrogation.<lb/></p>

			<p>13. Mr. G.M. Farooqui, Additional Public Prosecutor for the State<lb/> vehemently opposed the aforesaid contentions of counsel for the<lb/> petitioners and submitted that the marriage of deceased did not last<lb/> even for two years and there are specific allegations of demand of<lb/> Rs.10 lacs as dowry and inflicting of cruelties upon the deceased, in<lb/> the present FIR /complaint. It is further submitted that the case is very<lb/> serious in nature and the custodial interrogation of these petitioners is<lb/> necessary, especially when both the petitioners are absconding from<lb/> arrest therefore, the bail applications of the petitioners be rejected.<lb/></p>

			<p>14. I have heard the submissions made by learned counsel for the<lb/> petitioners and have gone through the status report, impugned order<lb/> and the material placed on record.<lb/></p>

			<p>15. Upon careful scrutiny of the case what this Court observes is<lb/> that there are specific allegations of demand of Rs.10 lacs as dowry<lb/> and inflicting of cruelties upon the deceased in the present FIR, also<lb/> that all the family members are absconding and the victim died an<lb/> unnatural death and the cause of death opined by the doctor, who<lb/> conducted the Post Mortem is due to asphyxia consequent upon ante-<lb/>mortem hanging. This Court also notes the observation regarding<lb/> suicide note made by learned Additional Sessions Judge in impugned<lb/> order dated 09.12.2015, which read as under:<lb/></p>

			<list>
            
            <item> &quot;The suicide note on police file does not exonerate these<lb/> two applicants. Though it does not name these applicants<lb/> anywhere, but the very opening lines of suicide note are<lb/> that the deceased was extremely harassed.&quot;<lb/></item>

            </list>

			<p>16. After considering all the facts and circumstances of the present<lb/> case and the contents of the FIR, this Court is not inclined to grant<lb/> anticipatory bail to the petitioner -Shivani at this stage, especially<lb/> when there is no arrest in this case and all the family members are<lb/> absconding. Accordingly, the bail application (Bail Appln.<lb/> No.2706/2015) filed by petitioner -Shivani is dismissed.<lb/></p>

			<p>17. So far as the Bail Appln No.2710/2015, filed by petitioner -<lb/>Nikhil Choudhary is concerned, the only ground which distinguishes<lb/> the case of petitioner -Nikhil Choudhary from the case of petitioner<lb/> -Shivani is that he is working as a System Engineer at Infosys since<lb/> 1 st December 2014 and after his initial training at Mysore, he is posted<lb/> in Pune and he is not living at his parental house since 1 st December<lb/> 2014 and in support thereof he has annexed the appointment letter<lb/> dated 13 th November 2014 issued by the Infosys Limited, duly signed<lb/> digitally with the address as 44, Infosys Avenue, Electronics City,<lb/> Hosur Road, Bangalore 560 100, India. In such a situation, where<lb/> there is hardly any possibility of petitioner -Nikhil Choudhary being<lb/> present at the time and place of incident, this Court finds some merit<lb/> in the contentions raised in his petition. Therefore, in the peculiar fact<lb/> and circumstances of the case of the petitioner -Nikhil Choudhary ,<lb/> this Court finds that his case is fit to grant anticipatory bail.<lb/></p>

			<p>18. Accordingly, petitioner -Nikhil Choudhary is directed to<lb/> appear before the Investigating Officer as and when called and to<lb/> cooperate in investigation of this case and in the event of arrest, the<lb/> petitioner -Nikhil Choudhary be released on bail upon furnishing his<lb/> personal bail bond in the sum of Rs.30,000/-with two sureties of the<lb/> like amount to the satisfaction of the arresting officer, subject to the<lb/> following conditions:<lb/></p>

			<list>
            
            <item> a)<lb/> The petitioner shall not flee from justice and shall not<lb/> leave the country without the prior permission of the<lb/> Court concerned.<lb/></item>

			<item> b)<lb/> The petitioner shall not try to influence or threaten or<lb/> even contact any prosecution witness in any manner.<lb/></item>

            </list>

			<p>19. In view of the aforesaid discussion, the bail application of<lb/> petitioner -Shivani Choudhary (Bail Appln. No.2706/2015) is<lb/> dismissed and the bail application of petitioner -Nikhil Choudhary<lb/> (Bail Appln. No.2710/2015) is allowed in the aforesaid terms.<lb/></p>

			<p>20. Before parting with the aforesaid order, it is made clear that<lb/> anything observed in this order shall not have any bearing on the<lb/> merits of the case during trial.<lb/></p>

			<p>21. With aforesaid directions, both the bail applications stand<lb/> disposed of.<lb/></p>

			<p>22. Dasti.<lb/></p>

			<p>(P.S.TEJI)<lb/> JUDGE<lb/> </p>
            
            <p> DECEMBER 22, 2015<lb/> pkb</p>


	</text>
</tei>
