<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<p>the material placed on record.<lb/> The appellant writ petitioner<lb/> applied for the post of Police Constable pursuant to the<lb/> recruitment notification issued by the respondents in the year<lb/> 2018.<lb/> He appeared in the written test, whereafter he was<lb/> summoned for Physical Standard Test/Physical Efficiency Test<lb/> (PST/PET). His name was reflected in the merit list and he was<lb/> called for document verification. During police verification, it<lb/> came to light in the year 2015, the appellant had been convicted<lb/> for the offences punishable under Sections 419 and 420 IPC by<lb/> the Court of Chief Judicial Magistrate, Kaithal, Haryana.<lb/> Consequently, his candidature was rejected vide order dated<lb/> 05.03.2019 (Annex.5), which was unsuccessfully assailed in the<lb/> writ petition as stated above.<lb/> Mr. Nitin Gokhlani, learned counsel representing the<lb/> appellant, vehemently and fervently contended that the appellant<lb/> was granted probation in the criminal case, wherein he was<lb/> convicted for the offences punishable under Section 419 and 420<lb/> IPC. Thus, as per Mr. Gokhlani, the petitioner&apos;s candidature is<lb/> saved by virtue of Section 12 of the Probation of Offenders Act.<lb/> As per Mr. Gokhlani, the learned Single Judge did not consider this<lb/> legal aspect in the correct perspective. He placed reliance on the<lb/> Supreme Court judgment in the case of Avtar Singh Vs. Union<lb/> of India &amp; Ors. [(2016) 8 SCC 471] and the Delhi High Court<lb/> judgment in a bunch of writ petitions led by Commissioner of<lb/> Police &amp; Anr. Vs. Narender Kumar Singh [W.P. (C)<lb/> No.8499/2011 decided on 13.02.2013] and urged that the<lb/> appellant is entitled to claim protection from disqualification based<lb/> on conviction by virtue of Section 12 of the Probation of Offenders<lb/> Act and thus, the respondents were totally unjustified in declaring<lb/> the appellant to be disqualified and in cancelling his appointment<lb/> to the post of Police Constable despite being selected on merit.<lb/> He, thus urged that the impugned orders are arbitrary and bad in<lb/> the eyes of law and hence, the same deserve to be set aside. On<lb/> these submissions, Mr. Gokhlani implored the court to accept the<lb/> appeal, set aside the impugned orders and direct appointment of<lb/> the appellant as Police Constable in the subject selection process.<lb/> Per contra, Mr. Manish Vyas, learned AAG, vehemently<lb/> and fervently opposed the submissions advanced by the<lb/> appellant&apos;s counsel. He contended that while rejecting his<lb/> candidature of the appellant, his conduct was taken into account<lb/> and it was found that the appellant had been convicted for the<lb/> offences of moral turpitude, i.e. Sections 419 and 420 IPC. He<lb/> was apprehended while impersonating another person in a<lb/> recruitment examination for the post of Conductor and thus, his<lb/> candidature was rightly rejected by the recruiting authority. He<lb/> urged that the removal of disqualification by virtue of Section 12<lb/> of the Probation of Offenders Act does not apply to the situation at<lb/> hand. He placed reliance on the judgment rendered by Hon&apos;ble<lb/> Supreme Court in the case of State of Rajasthan &amp; Ors. Vs.<lb/> Love Kush Meena (AIR 2021 SC 1610) and sought dismissal of<lb/> the appeal.<lb/> We have given our thoughtful consideration to the<lb/> submissions advanced at bar and have gone through the material<lb/> placed on record. Suffice it to say that the fact regarding the<lb/> appellant herein having been convicted for the offences punishable<lb/> under Section 419 and 420 IPC is not in dispute. The only ground<lb/> on which the impugned action is questioned is that after being<lb/> convicted in the aforesaid criminal case, the appellant was<lb/> extended the benefit of Probation of Offenders Act and hence, the<lb/> appellant is entitled to protection from disqualification by virtue of<lb/> Section 12 of the Probation of Offenders Act. The said argument,<lb/> though attractive superficially, has no legs to stand whatsoever.<lb/> The Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court in the case of Girraj Prasad Meena<lb/> Vs. State of Rajasthan [(2014) 13 SCC 674] has settled this<lb/> aspect beyond pale by holding that the disqualification under<lb/> Section 12 of the Probation of Offenders Act refers to<lb/> disqualification provided in other statutes.<lb/> Despite grant of<lb/> probation, the conviction remains. The employer is entitled to<lb/> take disciplinary action on the basis of the conviction and the<lb/> employee cannot claim a right to continue in service merely on the<lb/> ground that he had been given benefit of probation under the<lb/> Probation of Offenders Act. While dealing with this issue, the<lb/> Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court held as below :-<lb/></p>

			<p>10. In State of U.P. v. Ranjit Singh, AIR 1999 SC 1201,<lb/> this Court has held that the High Court, while deciding<lb/> a criminal case and giving the benefit of the U.P. First<lb/> Offenders&apos; Probation Act, 1938, or similar enactment,<lb/> has no competence to issue any direction that the<lb/> accused shall not suffer any civil consequences. The<lb/> Court has held as under:<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot;5. We also fail to understand how the High Court<lb/> while deciding a criminal case, can direct that the<lb/> accused must be deemed to have been in<lb/> continuous service without break and, therefore,<lb/> he should be paid his full pay and [dearness<lb/> allowance] during the period of his suspension.<lb/> This direction and observation is wholly without<lb/> jurisdiction….&quot;<lb/> (Emphasis added)<lb/></item>

			<p>11. In Shankar Dass v. Union of India &amp; Anr., AIR 1985<lb/> SC 772, this Court has held that the order of dismissal<lb/> from service, consequent upon a conviction, is not a<lb/> disqualification within the meaning of Section 12 of the<lb/> Act 1958 observing as under:<lb/> &quot;4. … There are statutes which provide that<lb/> persons who are convicted for certain offences<lb/> shall incur certain disqualifications. For example,<lb/> Chapter III of the Representation of the People<lb/> Act,<lb/> 1951,<lb/> entitled<lb/> &apos;Disqualifications<lb/> for<lb/> membership of Parliament and State Legislatures&apos;<lb/> and Chapter IV entitled &apos;Disqualifications for<lb/> Voting&apos; contain provisions which disqualify<lb/> persons convicted of certain charges from being<lb/> members of legislatures or from voting at<lb/> elections to legislatures. That is the sense in<lb/> which the word &apos;disqualification&apos; is used in Section<lb/> 12 of the Probation of Offenders Act. [Therefore,<lb/> it is not possible to accept the reasoning of the<lb/> High Court that Section 12 of the 1958 Act takes<lb/> away the effect of conviction for the purpose of<lb/> service also.&quot;<lb/></p>

			<p>12. The provision of the Act 1958 has been dealt with<lb/> by this Court elaborately in Sushil Kumar Singhal v.<lb/> Regional Manager, Punjab National Bank, (2010) 8 SCC<lb/> 573, wherein after considering the judgments of this<lb/> court in Aitha Chander Rao v. State of A.P., 1981 Supp<lb/> SCC 17; Harichand v. Director of School Education, AIR<lb/> 1998 SC 788; Divisional Personnel Officer, Southern<lb/> Railway &amp; Anr. v. T.R. Chellappan, AIR 1975 SC 2216;<lb/> and Trikha Ram v. V.K. Seth &amp; Anr., AIR 1988 SC 285,<lb/> the court held as under:<lb/> &quot;In view of the above, the law on the issue can be<lb/> summarised to the effect that the conviction of an<lb/> employee in an offence permits the disciplinary<lb/> authority to initiate disciplinary proceedings<lb/> against the employee or to take appropriate steps<lb/> for his dismissal/removal only on the basis of his<lb/> conviction. The word &quot;disqualification&quot; contained<lb/> in Section 12 of the 1958 Act refers to a<lb/> disqualification provided in other statutes, as<lb/> explained by this Court in the abovereferred<lb/> cases, and the employee cannot claim a right to<lb/> continue in service merely on the ground that he<lb/> had been given the benefit of probation under the<lb/> 1958 Act.&quot;<lb/></p>

			<p>(See also: Karamjit Singh v. State of Punjab, (2009) 7<lb/> SCC 178).&quot;<lb/> In addition thereto, we have carefully perused the<lb/> application form submitted by the appellant, wherein in the<lb/> column of &quot;Character Verification Details&quot;, where the following<lb/> query has been made &quot;Whether any FIR has been ever lodged<lb/> against you?&quot;, the appellant has answered in negative.<lb/> The<lb/> image of relevant part of the application form submitted by the<lb/> petitioner is reproduced hereinbelow :-<lb/>Manifestly, thus, the appellant herein concealed the<lb/> factum of lodging of the FIR and of his conviction while submitting<lb/> the application for recruitment. The impact of an applicant for a<lb/> public post concealing the fact of conviction was considered by<lb/> Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court in the case of Rajasthan Rajya Vidyut<lb/> Prasaran Nigam Limited Vs. Anil Kanwariya [(2021) 10 SCC<lb/> 136], wherein it was held that the appointment obtained by<lb/> concealing the factum of conviction for the offence under Section<lb/> 341 and 323 IPC amounts to suppression of material fact of<lb/> having been involved in a criminal case. Grant of benefit of<lb/> Section 12 of the Probation of Offenders Act was reckoned as<lb/> being of no help to the employee inasmuch as the question was<lb/> about making a false declaration. The Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court<lb/> reversed the order of the Division Bench whereby the termination<lb/> of the employee had been set aside. The relevant paras of the<lb/> aforesaid judgment are reproduced hereinbelow for the sake of<lb/> ready reference :-<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot;3.2 Aggrieved by the order of termination, the<lb/> respondent-employee preferred Writ Petition No. 6969<lb/> of 2016 before the learned Single Judge of the High<lb/> Court. The learned Single Judge of the High Court<lb/> solely relying on the judgment of this Court in the case<lb/> of Avtar Singh v. Union of India, reported in (2016) 8<lb/> SCC 471, and also on order dated 9.9.2015 passed by<lb/> the learned Sessions Judge in appeal granting benefit<lb/> of Section 12 of the Act 1958, allowed the writ petition<lb/> and quashed and set aside the order of termination and<lb/> directed the appellants to reinstate the respondent-<lb/>employee with all consequential benefits.<lb/></item>

			<p>3.3 Feeling aggrieved and dissatisfied with the<lb/> judgment and order passed by the learned Single<lb/> Judge, quashing and setting aside the order of<lb/> termination and directing the appellants to reinstate<lb/> the respondent-employee, the appellants-employer<lb/> preferred appeal before the Division Bench being D.B.<lb/> Special Appeal Writ No. 560 of 2019. The Division<lb/> Bench also solely relying upon para 38.4.1 of the<lb/> decision of this Court in the case of Avtar Singh (supra)<lb/> and observing that the employee was held guilty in a<lb/> dispute of trivial nature with his father, uncle, brother<lb/> and cousin and as it was a trivial nature dispute and<lb/> such a dispute which even if disclosed could have been<lb/> ignored by the employer because of the benefit of<lb/> Section 12 of the Act 1958, the Division Bench by the<lb/> impugned judgment and order has dismissed the said<lb/> appeal and has confirmed the judgment and order<lb/> passed by the learned Single Judge, directing<lb/> reinstatement of the employee with all consequential<lb/> benefits. The review petition preferred by the<lb/> appellants herein has also been dismissed.<lb/></p>

			<p>4.3 It is further submitted that in the present case at<lb/> the time when the respondent-employee applied for the<lb/> advertised post, he was already convicted for the<lb/> offences under Sections 341 and 323 IPC by the<lb/> competent criminal court which he did not disclose. It<lb/> is submitted that even thereafter also when he<lb/> submitted the declaration at the time of documents<lb/> verification on 14.04.2015, the respondent-employee<lb/> though already suffered a conviction for the offences<lb/> under Sections 341 and 323 IPC and at that time, i.e.,<lb/> on 14.04.2015, only the benefit under Sections 3 &amp; 4 of<lb/> the Act 1958 was given, he filed a false declaration. It<lb/> is submitted that the learned trial Court did not grant<lb/> the benefit of Section 12 of the Act 1958, which benefit<lb/> of Section 12 of the Act 1958 was given only vide<lb/> judgment and order dated 9.9.2015 by the learned<lb/> Sessions Judge. It is submitted that as the respondent-<lb/>employee suppressed the material fact of criminal case<lb/> firstly in the year 2013 when he submitted the<lb/> application and thereafter subsequently on 14.04.2015<lb/> when he submitted the declaration at the time of<lb/> documents verification and thereafter when the<lb/> services of the respondent were terminated after giving<lb/> him an opportunity of being heard, the same ought not<lb/> to have interfered with by the learned Single Judge and<lb/> thereafter by the Division Bench.<lb/></p>

			<p>5. The present appeals are vehemently opposed by Shri<lb/> Navin Prakash, learned Advocate appearing for the<lb/> respondent-employee. It is submitted that in the facts<lb/> and circumstances of the case and more particularly<lb/> the order passed by the learned Sessions Court<lb/> granting the benefit under Section 12 of the Act 1958<lb/> and considering the fact that the dispute was of a<lb/> trivial nature with the family members, the learned<lb/> Single Judge rightly set aside the order of termination<lb/> which has been rightly confirmed by the Division<lb/> Bench.<lb/></p>

			<p>6. We have heard the learned counsel for the<lb/> respective parties at length. At the outset, it is required<lb/> to be noted that the appellants herein -employer<lb/> terminated the services of the respondent on non-<lb/>disclosure of the pending criminal case against him at<lb/> the time when he submitted the application for<lb/> appointment,<lb/> submitted<lb/> in<lb/> the<lb/> month<lb/> of<lb/> October/November, 2013 and thereafter in the<lb/> declaration<lb/> dated<lb/> 14.04.2015.<lb/> As<lb/> observed<lb/> hereinabove, the respondent was chargesheeted for the<lb/> offences under Sections 143, 341 and 323 IPC vide<lb/> chargesheet dated 17.01.2011. The learned trial Court<lb/> convicted the respondent for the offences under<lb/> Sections 341 &amp; 323 IPC, vide judgment and order<lb/> dated 5.8.2013. However, granted the benefit under<lb/> Section 3 of the Act 1958 only. In the month of<lb/> October, 2013, the appellants issued an advertisement<lb/> for the post of Technical Helper and the last date for<lb/> submission of the application was 14.11.2013.<lb/> Pursuant to the said advertisement, the respondent<lb/> applied for the said post and the written test was held<lb/> on 02.02.2014 and the result of which was declared on<lb/> 31.03.2015. The respondent submitted declaration on<lb/> 14.04.2015 declaring that neither any criminal case is<lb/> pending against him nor he has been convicted by any<lb/> court of law. The date fixed for documents verification<lb/> was 14.04.2015 and along with the documents<lb/> verification he was required to file a declaration which<lb/> he submitted stating that neither any criminal case is<lb/> pending against him nor he has been convicted by any<lb/> court of law. Therefore, on the date of submitting an<lb/> application and even at the time when declaration was<lb/> filed on 14.04.2015, there was already an order of<lb/> conviction against him. Even at the relevant time, the<lb/> benefit of Section 12 of the Act 1958 was not granted<lb/> to the respondent, which was given subsequently vide<lb/> judgment of the learned Sessions Court dated<lb/> 09.09.2015.<lb/></p>

			<p>6.3 Thus, at the time when he submitted the<lb/> application for appointment in the month of<lb/> October/November 2013, the respondent already<lb/> suffered a conviction by the competent court which not<lb/> only he did not disclose, but in fact, a false declaration<lb/> was filed that neither any criminal case is pending<lb/> against him nor he has been convicted by any court of<lb/> law. That thereafter after receipt of the police<lb/> verification/antecedents report dated 5.6.2015 from<lb/> the Superintendent of Police, Sawai Madhopur and after<lb/> giving a show cause notice and an opportunity of being<lb/> heard to the respondent, the employer terminated the<lb/> services of the respondent on the ground of non-<lb/>disclosure /suppression of material fact and filing a<lb/> false declaration.<lb/></p>

			<p>8.2 In the case of Devendra Kumar (supra), while<lb/> joining the training, the employee was asked to submit<lb/> an affidavit giving certain information, particularly,<lb/> whether he had ever been involved in any criminal<lb/> case. The employee submitted an affidavit stating that<lb/> he had never been involved in any criminal case. The<lb/> employee completed his training satisfactorily and it<lb/> was at this time that the employer in pursuance of the<lb/> process of character verification came to know that the<lb/> employee was in fact involved in a criminal case. It was<lb/> found that the final report in that case had been<lb/> submitted by the prosecution and accepted by the<lb/> Judicial Magistrate concerned. On the basis of the<lb/> same, the employee was discharged abruptly on the<lb/> ground that since he was a temporary government<lb/> servant, he could be removed from service without<lb/> holding an enquiry. The said order was challenged by<lb/> the employee by filing a writ petition before a Single<lb/> Judge of the High Court which was dismissed. The<lb/> Division Bench upheld that order, which was the<lb/> subject matter of appeal before this Court. Dismissing<lb/> the appeal, this Court observed and held that the<lb/> question is not whether the employee is suitable for the<lb/> post. The pendency of a criminal case/proceeding is<lb/> different from suppressing the information of such<lb/> pendency. The case pending against a person might<lb/> not involve moral turpitude but suppressing of this<lb/> information itself amounts to moral turpitude. It is<lb/> further observed that the information sought by the<lb/> employer if not disclosed as required, would definitely<lb/> amount to suppression of material information and in<lb/> that eventuality, the service becomes liable to be<lb/> terminated, even if there had been no further trial or<lb/> the person concerned stood acquitted/discharged. It is<lb/> further observed by this Court in the said decision that<lb/> where an applicant/employee gets an order by<lb/> misrepresenting the facts or by playing fraud upon the<lb/> competent authority, such an order cannot be<lb/> sustained in the eye of the law. &quot;Fraud avoids all<lb/> judicial acts, ecclesiastical or temporal&quot;. It is further<lb/> observed and held that dishonesty should not be<lb/> permitted to bear the fruit and benefit those persons<lb/> who have defrauded or misrepresented themselves and<lb/> in such circumstances the court should not perpetuate<lb/> the fraud by entertaining petitions on their behalf. The<lb/> relevant observations in the said decision are in paras<lb/> 12, 13, 18 &amp; 25, which are as under:<lb/> 12. So far as the issue of obtaining the<lb/> appointment by misrepresentation is concerned, it<lb/> is no more res integra. The question is not<lb/> whether the applicant is suitable for the post. The<lb/> pendency of a criminal case/proceeding is<lb/> different from suppressing the information of such<lb/> pendency. The case pending against a person<lb/> might not involve moral turpitude but suppressing<lb/> of this information itself amounts to moral<lb/> turpitude. In fact, the information sought by the<lb/> employer if not disclosed as required, would<lb/> definitely amount to suppression of material<lb/> information. In that eventuality, the service<lb/> becomes liable to be terminated, even if there<lb/> had been no further trial or the person concerned<lb/> stood acquitted/discharged. 13. It is a settled<lb/> proposition of law that where an applicant gets an<lb/> office by misrepresenting the facts or by playing<lb/> fraud upon the competent authority, such an<lb/> order cannot be sustained in the eye of the law.<lb/> &quot;Fraud avoids all judicial acts, ecclesiastical or<lb/> temporal.&quot; [Vide S.P. Chengalvaraya Naidu v.<lb/> Jagannath (1994) 1 SCC 1: AIR 1994 SC 853.] In<lb/> Lazarus Estates Ltd. V. Beasley [(1956) 1 QB<lb/> 702: (1956) 2 WLR 502: (1956) 1 ALL ER 341<lb/> (CA)] the Court observed without equivocation<lb/> that: (QB p. 712) &quot;… No judgment of a court, no<lb/> order of a Minister can be allowed to stand if it<lb/> has been obtained by fraud, for fraud unravels<lb/> everything.&quot; 18. The ratio laid down by this Court<lb/> in various cases is that dishonesty should not be<lb/> permitted to bear the fruit and benefit those<lb/> persons who have frauded or misrepresented<lb/> themselves. In such circumstances the court<lb/> should not perpetuate the fraud by entertaining<lb/> petitions on their behalf. In Union of India v. M.<lb/> Bhaskaran (1995) Supp (4) SCC 100 this court,<lb/> after placing reliance upon and approving its<lb/> earlier judgment in Vizianagaram Social Welfare<lb/> Residential School Society v. M. Tripura Sundari<lb/> Devi (1990) 3 SCC 655, observed as under: (M.<lb/> Bhaskaran case, SCC p. 104, para 6) If by<lb/> committing fraud any employment is obtained,<lb/> the same cannot be permitted to be countenanced<lb/> by a court of law as the employment secured by<lb/> fraud renders it voidable at the option of the<lb/> employer. 25. More so, if the initial action is not in<lb/> consonance with law, the subsequent conduct of<lb/> party cannot sanctify the same. Sublato<lb/> fundamento cadit opus -a foundation being<lb/> removed, the superstructure falls. A person<lb/> having done wrong cannot take advantage of his<lb/> own wrong and plead bar of any law to frustrate<lb/> the lawful trial by a competent court. In such a<lb/> case the legal maxim nullus commodum caprere<lb/> potest de injuria sua propria applies. The persons<lb/> violating the law cannot be permitted to urge that<lb/> their offence cannot be subjected to inquiry, trial<lb/> or investigation. [Vide Union of India v. Major<lb/> General Madan Lal Yadav (1996) 4 SCC 127:1996<lb/> SCC (Cri) 592: AIR 1996 SC 1340 and Lily<lb/> Thomas v. Union of India (2000) 6 SCC 224:<lb/></p>

			<item>2000 SCC (Cri) 1056.] Nor can a person claim any<lb/> right arising out of his own wrongdoing (jus ex<lb/> injuria non oritur).&quot;<lb/></item>

			<p>In the case of State of Rajasthan &amp; Ors. Vs. Love<lb/> Kush Meena (supra) relied upon by the learned A.A.G., the<lb/> factum regarding involvement of the candidate in a criminal case<lb/> was disclosed in the application form and the applicant therein had<lb/> been acquitted of the charges, but despite that, the Hon&apos;ble<lb/> Supreme Court went on to hold that as the acquittal was by giving<lb/> benefit of doubt, the factum thereof would not entitle the<lb/> candidate for appointment.<lb/> In view of the above discussion, we are of the opinion<lb/> that the appellant herein is dis-entitled and disqualified to seek<lb/> appointment on the post of Police Constable owing to his conduct<lb/> as he stands convicted for the offences punishable under Sections<lb/> 419 and 420 IPC, which are crimes of moral turpitude, in light of<lb/> the memorandum dated 29.04.1995 issued by the Police<lb/> Headquarters.<lb/> In addition, the appellant, having concealed the fact of<lb/> registration of the FIR and his conviction for the offences<lb/> pertaining to moral turpitude while submitting application form, is<lb/> also disentitled to seek appointment on a public post.<lb/> The<lb/> impugned order dated 13.08.2019, whereby the writ petition filed<lb/> by the appellant was dismissed as well as the order dated<lb/> 05.03.2019, whereby he was declared ineligible and his<lb/> appointment on the post of Police Constable was cancelled do not<lb/> suffer from any infirmity or illegality whatsoever warranting<lb/> interference therein.<lb/> Accordingly, the appeal fails and is hereby dismissed as<lb/> being devoid of merit.<lb/> No order as to costs.<lb/></p>

			<p>(SAMEER JAIN),J<lb/> (SANDEEP MEHTA),J<lb/> Pramod/-</p>


	</text>
</tei>
