<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<p>Judgment<lb/> 20/12/2018<lb/> This writ petition has been filed by the petitioner with the<lb/> following prayers:-<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot;1. by an appropriate writ, order or direction, the<lb/> respondents may kindly be directed to allow the<lb/> petitioners to fill up the Examination Forms for main<lb/> examination 2019 of their regular B.Ed. Course for the<lb/> Academic Year 2018-19 and for BA-B.Ed./B.Sc-B.Ed.<lb/> Intergrated Course for 2018-19.<lb/></item>

			<item>2.<lb/> Further, the respondents may kindly be directed<lb/> to allow the petitioners to appear in the examination<lb/> of their respective courses and may kindly be<lb/> permitted to continue their B.Ed., B.A./B.Ed. Course<lb/> of 2018-19.<lb/></item>

			<item>3.<lb/> Any other order or direction which the court may<lb/> deem fit and proper be pass in favour of the<lb/> petitioner.&quot;<lb/></item>

			<p>Counsel for the petitioners submitted that the petitioners<lb/> were given admission by the respondent No.3 in B.Ed. Course on<lb/> 1.10.2018. However, the respondent No.4 is not allowing the<lb/> petitioners to fill the examination form.<lb/> Counsel for the respondent submitted that the respondent<lb/> No.3 has committed an illegality in giving admissions to the<lb/> petitioners in B.Ed. Course on 1.10.2018 which is contrary to the<lb/> guidelines fixed by the Division Bench of this Court in Smt. Jyanki<lb/> Devi Teacher Training College Vs. The State of Rajasthan &amp; Ors.<lb/></p>

			<p>(D.B. Civil Writ Petition No.6237/2014) decided on 2.9.2016<lb/> wherein the Division Bench has provided Schedule with regard to<lb/> conducting the process of admission and course for B.Ed.<lb/> Programme which reads as under:-<lb/></p>

			<item>Taking decision regarding policy for<lb/> granting<lb/> NOC<lb/> (for<lb/> new<lb/> institutions/additional<lb/> courses/<lb/> additional<lb/> intake/shifting<lb/> of<lb/> premises/closure etc) for teacher<lb/> education colleges/courses. This<lb/> will<lb/> be<lb/> the<lb/> basis<lb/> of<lb/> recommendations/ NOC of State<lb/> Govt. as required in the sub-<lb/>regulation 5 of regulation 7 of<lb/> NCTE Regulations, 2014.<lb/> . Communicating policy to NCTE/<lb/> affiliating universities and uploading<lb/> policy decision on website of Higher<lb/> Education Department for benefit of<lb/> investors,<lb/> . If a decision to impose ban on any<lb/> course is to be taken then the ban<lb/> will not apply on pending<lb/> applications with NCTE/NRC-<lb/>NCTE.<lb/> However,<lb/> no<lb/> new<lb/> applications to be invited by NCTE/<lb/> NRC-NCTE.<lb/></item>

			<item>. NCTE/NRC-NCTE not to allow<lb/> change in location/type of college in<lb/> later<lb/> years<lb/> if<lb/> the<lb/> State<lb/> recommendation is given for<lb/> exclusive area or specific nature of<lb/> colleges (e.g. If State Govt. has<lb/> allowed opening of colleges in a<lb/> tehsil deprived of teacher-education<lb/> college it should not be allowed to<lb/> shift its premises to locations where<lb/> ban is imposed; if only women<lb/> college has been recommended then<lb/> it should not be allowed to change to<lb/> co-ed college).<lb/> Department<lb/> of Higher<lb/> Education<lb/> 31st Jan<lb/> ( X year)<lb/> (for applications<lb/> to be invited by<lb/> NCTE from 1st<lb/> March for next<lb/> session as per<lb/> regulation 5(5) of<lb/> Regulations,<lb/> 2014)<lb/></item>

			<item>2<lb/> Invitations by NCTE/NRC-NCTE<lb/> for inviting online applications for<lb/> new colleges/new courses/increase<lb/> in seats as per the regulation 5(5) of<lb/> NCTE Regulations, 2014.<lb/> For the State of Rajasthan,<lb/> applications to be invited only in<lb/> compliance of policy of the State<lb/> Govt.<lb/> Applications to apply for NOC of<lb/> affiliating body (State university) as<lb/> per provisions of regulation 5(3) of<lb/> Regulations, 2014<lb/> NCTE/NRC-NCTE<lb/> 1st March to 31st<lb/> May as per the<lb/> regulation 5(5) of<lb/> NCTE<lb/> Regulations, 2014<lb/> Without late fee:<lb/> 15th May or 15<lb/> days prior to last<lb/> date of applying<lb/> (whichever is<lb/> later)<lb/> With late fee: 7<lb/> days prior to last<lb/> Issuance of NOC by affiliating<lb/> universities, according to policy of<lb/> the<lb/> State Govt. subject to conditions of<lb/> fulfillment<lb/> of<lb/> conditions<lb/> of<lb/> affiliation.<lb/> Simultaneous<lb/> processing<lb/> of<lb/> applications by NRC-NCTE as per<lb/> regulation 7 of NCTE Regulations,<lb/> 2014<lb/> Affiliating<lb/> universities<lb/> date of applying<lb/> to NCTE<lb/> 31st May (last date<lb/> of filing<lb/> applications)<lb/></item>

			<item>3<lb/> Applicants to apply to State Govt.<lb/> on a prescribed format with requisite<lb/> fee, if any, other annexure including<lb/> proof of submitting application to<lb/> NRC-NCTE. Prescribed format of<lb/> application shall be made available<lb/> on website of Department of College<lb/> Education/Higher Education portal<lb/> and shall include fields to ascertain<lb/> whether the applicant fulfills<lb/> conditions mentioned in the State<lb/> Government&apos;s policy.<lb/></item>

			<item>Sponsoring<lb/> bodies/Institution<lb/> Without late fee:<lb/> 30th June or within<lb/> one month of last<lb/> date of receiving<lb/> applications by<lb/> NCTE.<lb/> With late fee: 15th<lb/> July (or within 45<lb/> days of last date<lb/> of receiving<lb/> applications by<lb/> NCTE).<lb/></item>

			<item>4<lb/> NRC-NCTE to communicate with<lb/> State Govt. for its recommendations<lb/> on new applications (as per<lb/> Regulation 7(5 &amp; 6))<lb/> NRC_NCTE<lb/> 30th June<lb/> 5<lb/> State<lb/></item>

			<item>Govt.<lb/> to<lb/> give<lb/> its<lb/> recommendations on the basis of its<lb/> policy on applications sent by the<lb/> NRC-NCTE (no inspection to be<lb/> carried out by State Govt. for<lb/> verification<lb/> of<lb/> infrastructure/qualification<lb/> of<lb/> teachers which is to be verified by<lb/> VT of NCTE as per regulations 7 &amp;<lb/> 8 of Regulations, 2014<lb/> State Govt.<lb/></item>

			<p>30th September<lb/> 6<lb/> Appointment of Nodal agency/<lb/> Coordinating agency (university) for<lb/> Entrance examination by the State<lb/> Government<lb/> State Govt.<lb/></p>

			<p>15th Dec<lb/> 7<lb/> Submission of applications by<lb/> Institutions of University for<lb/> renewal of affiliation (existing<lb/> institutions).<lb/> Department of Higher<lb/> Education<lb/> Without late fee:<lb/> 31st December<lb/> With late fee: 15th<lb/> Jan (X+1 Year)<lb/></p>

			<p>8<lb/></p>

			<item>Granting recognition to new colleges<lb/> by NCTE as per regulation 7 &amp; 8<lb/> (on the basis of recommendation &amp;<lb/> policy of State Govt (regulation<lb/> 7(5)) ; report of the visiting team<lb/> constituted as per regulation 7(7) etc<lb/> after satisfying itself that the<lb/> institution fulfills all the conditions<lb/> prescribed by the National Council<lb/> under the Act, rules or regulations,<lb/> including, the norms and standards<lb/> laid down for the relevant teacher<lb/> education programmes (regulation<lb/> Sponsoring<lb/> bodies/Institution<lb/> 03 March (X+1<lb/> Year)<lb/></item>

			<item>7(10)).<lb/></item>

			<p>9<lb/> Submission of applications by<lb/> Institutions to University for new<lb/> affiliation<lb/> NRC_NCTE<lb/></p>

			<p>10 March (X+1<lb/> Year)<lb/></p>

			<p>10<lb/> Submission of recognition letters<lb/> received by institutions to State<lb/> Government (new/fresh/restoration<lb/> Sponsoring<lb/> bodies/Institution<lb/> 10 March (X+1<lb/> Year)<lb/></p>

			<p>11<lb/></p>

			<item>Issuance of NOC/list of colleges<lb/> (with<lb/> seats) by State Government for<lb/> affiliating universities and<lb/> coordinating<lb/> agency for admissions on the basis<lb/> of<lb/> policy of State Govt. (not to be<lb/> based on<lb/> field inspection but on the basis of<lb/> State<lb/> policy applied on application of the<lb/> sponsoring body/institution).<lb/></item>

			<p>Department of Higher<lb/> Education<lb/> 30 March<lb/> (X+1 Year)<lb/></p>

			<p>12<lb/></p>

			<item>Prescribing schedule or academic<lb/> calendar in respect of each<lb/> programme<lb/> at least three months in advance of<lb/> the<lb/> commencement of each academic<lb/> session and to give due publicity by<lb/> providing details of publication of<lb/> notice inviting applications for<lb/> admissions, last date of receipt of<lb/> applications for admissions, date of<lb/> selection test/interview, date of<lb/> publication of 1st, 2nd, 3rd, list of<lb/> candidates and last date of closure of<lb/> admissions ( as per regulation 11 of<lb/> NCTE, 2014<lb/> Admission<lb/> agency/Affiliating<lb/> Universities<lb/> 01 May (X+1<lb/> Year)<lb/></item>

			<item>13<lb/> Decision<lb/> on<lb/> application<lb/> for<lb/> affiliation<lb/> and issuance of affiliation letter to<lb/> eligible institutions by the concerned<lb/> university as per regulation 8(10) of<lb/> 2014 (i) affiliating bodies to carry<lb/> out<lb/> inspection only for criteria/norms<lb/> not<lb/> already inspected by visiting team of<lb/> NCTE or as per provisions of its<lb/> Act/affiliating rules (ii) renewal of<lb/> affiliation to be done one the basis<lb/> NOC issued by State Govt. earlier, if<lb/> not<lb/> withdrawn by State Govt/NCTE; no<lb/> renewal/extension of NOC to be<lb/> issued<lb/> by State)<lb/></item>

			<p>Affiliating<lb/> universities<lb/> 10th May<lb/> (X+1 Year)<lb/></p>

			<p>14<lb/> Conveying list of affiliated colleges<lb/> (with no. of seats for each course) to<lb/> admission agency &amp; NRC-NCTE<lb/> Affiliating<lb/> universities<lb/> 15th May<lb/> (X+1 Year)<lb/></p>

			<p>15<lb/> Entrance test for B.Ed. Programmes Admission agencies<lb/> 15th May<lb/> (X+1 Year)<lb/></p>

			<p>16<lb/> Declaration of results of entrance<lb/> tests<lb/> for B.Ed. Programmes<lb/> Admission agencies<lb/> 25th May<lb/> (X+1 Year)<lb/> Affiliating universities to declare<lb/> results<lb/> of eligibility examinations<lb/> Affiliating<lb/> universities<lb/> Prior to beginning<lb/> of counselling<lb/> 18<lb/> Last date of Counselling<lb/> Admission agencies<lb/> 30 July<lb/> (X+1 Year)<lb/></p>

			<p>19<lb/> Commencement<lb/> of<lb/> Academic<lb/> Session<lb/> for teacher education programmes<lb/> Admission<lb/> agencies &amp;<lb/> affiliating<lb/> universities<lb/> 01 August<lb/> (X+1 Year)<lb/></p>

			<p>20<lb/> End of Academic session (to ensure<lb/> 200<lb/> teaching days as per the NCTE<lb/> Regulations, 2014; No. of Teaching<lb/> days for various months for session<lb/> 2016-17 are given in annexure-1)<lb/> Affiliating<lb/> universities<lb/> 07.05.2018<lb/> (X+2 Year)<lb/></p>

			<p>21<lb/> Completion of annual examination Affiliating<lb/> universities<lb/> 30th May<lb/> (X+2 Year)<lb/></p>

			<p>22<lb/> Declaration of result of annual<lb/> examination<lb/> Affiliating<lb/> universities<lb/> 07th July<lb/> (X+2 Year)<lb/> According to the Schedule prescribed by the Division Bench<lb/> of this Court, the last date for granting the admission in B.Ed.<lb/> Course was fixed as 30.07.2018. The Division Bench further<lb/> observed as under:-<lb/></p>

			<item>&quot;We accordingly, direct the State of Rajasthan, NRC-<lb/>NCTE, Jaipur &amp; University of Rajasthan, Jaipur to<lb/> strictly follow the Schedule/Calender of activities for<lb/> the session of B.Ed. Programme and any deviation<lb/> from it will not be permissible and if any, exigency<lb/> arises in future, either party is at liberty to move an<lb/> application<lb/> to<lb/> this<lb/> Court<lb/> seeking<lb/> clarification/modification, if required.&quot;<lb/></item>

			<p>Counsel for the respondent-University submits that the<lb/> Division Bench of this Court further extended the last date of<lb/> admission upto 14.08.2018 on the application being submitted by<lb/> the University.<lb/> Heard counsel for the parties.<lb/> Admittedly, the petitioners were given admission by the<lb/> respondent No.3 after the cut off date fixed by the Division Bench<lb/> of this Court, therefore, in my considered view, this writ petition<lb/> filed by the petitioner deserves to be dismissed in view of the<lb/> judgment passed by the Division Bench of this Court in Smt.<lb/> Jyanki Devi Teacher Training College (Supra). However, the<lb/> petitioners are at liberty to file appropriate proceedings against<lb/> the respondent No.3 for compensation.<lb/> The writ petition is accordingly dismissed with the above<lb/> observations.<lb/></p>

			<p>(INDERJEET SINGH),J<lb/></p>

			<p>285-praveen/</p>


	</text>
</tei>
