<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc xml:id="0" />
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <p>
            These 3 [three] writ petitions -W.P.(C) no. 2883/2016, W.P.(C) no.
            <lb />
            7402/2016 and W.P.(C) no. 1046/2017 -filed under Article 226 of the Constitution of
            <lb />
            India have a common issue which has arisen out of settlements of a number of
            <lb />
            Government notified public ferries. A number of Government notified public ferries were
            <lb />
            settled by the respondent authorities in the Transport Department in favour of the
            <lb />
            petitioners pursuant to two tender processes of similar nature. The main question
            <lb />
            involves in this batch of writ petition is with regard to the claims of the petitioners for
            <lb />
            grant of remission on the ground that they were not permitted to collect tolls as per
            <lb />
            revised rates though the estimated amounts for the different Government notified
            <lb />
            public ferries in the tender notices were assessed and arrived at as per the revised toll
            <lb />
            rates and the refusal on the part of the respondent authorities to grant such remission.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            2.
            <lb />
            In the writ petition, W.P.(C) no. 2833/2016, 5 [five] petitioners have
            <lb />
            joined together projecting that they have a common cause of action in preferring the
            <lb />
            writ petition. In the writ petition, W.P.(C) no. 7402/2016, a total of 9 [nine] petitioners
            <lb />
            have joined together similarly projecting a common cause of action. The writ petition,
            <lb />
            W.P.(C) no. 1046/2017 has been preferred by a single petitioner. As the subject-matter
            <lb />
            in these 3 [three] writ petitions and the reliefs sought therein are similar, all the 3
            <lb />
            [three] writ petitions have been taken up together for adjudication at the stage of
            <lb />
            admission, as agreed to by the learned counsel for the parties and in view of the
            <lb />
            position that exchange of pleadings has been complete.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            3.
            <lb />
            A tender notice vide Order no. 292 was published on 14.11.2014 by the
            <lb />
            respondent no. 3 in the two writ petitions -W.P.(C) no. 2833/2016 and W.P.(C) no.
            <lb />
            7402/2016 i.e. the Executive Engineer, Inland Water Transport Division, Guwahati,
            <lb />
            whereby, sealed tenders were invited to lease out 46 [forty-six] nos. of Government
            <lb />
            notified public ferries under the Inland Water Transport Division of the respondent
            <lb />
            Transport Department for a period of 2 [two] consecutive years i.e. 2015-2016 and
            <lb />
            2016-2017. Similarly, another tender notice dated 09.12.2014 was issued by the
            <lb />
            respondent no. 3 in the writ petition, W.P.(C) no. 1046/2017 i.e. the Executive
            <lb />
            Engineer, Inland Water Transport Division, Dibrugarh, whereby, sealed tenders were
            <lb />
            invited for a number of Government notified public ferries including Bogibeel-Karengbali
            <lb />
            Ferry Service in the district of Dibrugarh. The petitioners in the two writ petitions -
            <lb />
            W.P.(C) no. 2833/2016 and W.P.(C) no. 7402/2016 -participated in the said tender
            <lb />
            process, initiated by the tender notice dated 14.11.2014, by submitting their tenders.
            <lb />
            On the other hand, the petitioner in the writ petition, W.P.(C) no. 1046/2017, by
            <lb />
            responding to the tender notice dated 09.12.2014, submitted his tender in connection
            <lb />
            with Bogibeel-Karengbali Ferry Service.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            4.
            <lb />
            In the afore-mentioned two tender processes, the petitioners emerged as
            <lb />
            the successful bidders and they were settled with different Government notified public
            <lb />
            ferries [&apos;public ferries&apos;, for short] at the settlement amounts indicated hereinbelow, with
            <lb />
            2015-2017 as the period of settlement, vide separate orders of settlement passed by
            <lb />
            the Government in the Transport Department and the same were as under :-
            <lb />
        </p>

        <table>
            Sl.
            <lb />
            Petitioner
            <lb />
            Date of
            <lb />
            Settlement
            <lb />
            Public Ferry Service
            <lb />
            Period of
            <lb />
            Settlement
            <lb />
            Settlement amount
            <lb />
            W.P.(C) no. 2833/2016
            <lb />
            1
            <lb />
            Petitioner no. 1
            <lb />
            28.05.2015
            <lb />
            Dokuchi-Bhokuradia-Rangeswari-
            <lb />
            Pijupara Ferry Service
            <lb />
            2015-2017
            <lb />
            Rs. 3,85,255/-
            <lb />
            2
            <lb />
            Petitioner no. 2
            <lb />
            05.05.2015
            <lb />
            Guwahati-North Guwahati Ferry
            <lb />
            Service
            <lb />
            2015-2017
            <lb />
            Rs. 14,00,000/-
            <lb />
            3
            <lb />
            Petitioner no. 3
            <lb />
            21.04.2015
            <lb />
            Bagbor-Goalpara Ferry Service
            <lb />
            2015-2017
            <lb />
            Rs. 9,80,000/-
            <lb />
            4
            <lb />
            Petitioner no. 4
            <lb />
            09.04.2015
            <lb />
            Larkuchi-Majorchar-Kalachar Ferry
            <lb />
            Service
            <lb />
            2015-2017
            <lb />
            Rs. 16,10,000/-
            <lb />
            5
            <lb />
            Petitioner no. 5
            <lb />
            03.07.2015
            <lb />
            Gumaghat Ferry Service
            <lb />
            2015-2017
            <lb />
            Rs. 6,42,000/-
            <lb />
            W.P.(C) no. 7402/2016
            <lb />
            1
            <lb />
            Petitioner no. 1
            <lb />
            16.03.2015
            <lb />
            Sontali-Bohari-Alikash Ferry Service
            <lb />
            2015-2017
            <lb />
            Rs. 33,51,000/-
            <lb />
            2
            <lb />
            Petitioner no. 2
            <lb />
            14.05.2015
            <lb />
            Bhuragaon-Badlichar-Via-Pavakati-
            <lb />
            Malahu-Magumari-Chitalmari and
            <lb />
            Karikhowa Ferry Service
            <lb />
            2015-2017
            <lb />
            Rs. 7,20,000/-
            <lb />
            3
            <lb />
            Petitioner no. 3
            <lb />
            02.06.2015
            <lb />
            Adabari-Sialmari-Kurihamari Ferry
            <lb />
            Service
            <lb />
            2015-2017
            <lb />
            Rs. 6,51,000/-
            <lb />
            4
            <lb />
            Petitioner no. 4
            <lb />
            08.04.2015
            <lb />
            [1] Borghola-Kahibari-Borghola-
            <lb />
            Telphukhuri (Club) Ferry Service
            <lb />
            2015-2017
            <lb />
            Rs. 3,50,000/-
            <lb />
            [2] Nayerala -Gauranga Ferry
            <lb />
            Service
            <lb />
            2015-2017
            <lb />
            Rs. 1,00,000/-
            <lb />
            5
            <lb />
            Petitioner no. 5
            <lb />
            02.07.2015
            <lb />
            Baralimari-Gadhuwa-Via-Borbari-
            <lb />
            Kacharigaon-Nizsaharia Ferry
            <lb />
            Service
            <lb />
            2015-2017
            <lb />
            Rs. 5,05,000/-
            <lb />
            6
            <lb />
            Petitioner no. 6
            <lb />
            10.04.2015
            <lb />
            Gerimari-Kachasila-Via-Serang 4
            <lb />
            No. Kaymari-Jaljali Ferry Service
            <lb />
            2015-2017
            <lb />
            Rs. 2,41,000/-
            <lb />
            7
            <lb />
            Petitioner no. 7
            <lb />
            06.06.2015
            <lb />
            Choulkhowa-Aparia-Gobordhan
            <lb />
            Ferry Service
            <lb />
            2015-2017
            <lb />
            Rs. 1,05,000/-
            <lb />
            8
            <lb />
            Petitioner no. 8
            <lb />
            06.06.2015
            <lb />
            Bamundi-Sialmari-Guimari Ferry
            <lb />
            Service
            <lb />
            2015-2017
            <lb />
            Rs. 3,06,000/-
            <lb />
            9
            <lb />
            Petitioner no. 9
            <lb />
            02.04.2015
            <lb />
            Dongra-Kholabandha Ferry Service
            <lb />
            2015-2017
            <lb />
            Rs. 2,30,000/-
            <lb />
            W.P.(C) no. 1046/2017
            <lb />
        </table>

        <p>
            5.
            <lb />
            Upon being settled with the afore-mentioned public ferries, the petitioners
            <lb />
            started to operate the public ferries after completing the requisite formalities in terms of
            <lb />
            the respective settlement orders but they were denied to collect the tolls at the revised
            <lb />
            rates which were notified by a notification dated 02.07.2014 published under the hand
            <lb />
            of the Secretary to the Government of Assam, Transport Department. When the
            <lb />
            respondent authorities insisted for deposit of the settlement amounts as per the
            <lb />
            installment schedule prepared in terms of the revised toll rates while denying the
            <lb />
            petitioners as lessees to collect the tolls at the revised toll rates in terms of the
            <lb />
            notification dated 02.07.2014, the petitioners being aggrieved thereby, have preferred
            <lb />
            these writ petitions seeking inter alia the reliefs, mentioned above.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            6.
            <lb />
            Heard Mr. S. Kataki, learned counsel for the petitioners and Ms. M.D.
            <lb />
            Bora, learned Standing Counsel, Transport Department for all the respondents.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            7.
            <lb />
            Mr. Kataki, learned counsel for the petitioners has submitted that by the
            <lb />
            notification dated 02.07.2014, the Government in the Transport Department had inter
            <lb />
            alia revised the toll rates for Government notified public ferries under the Directorate of
            <lb />
            Inland Water Transport, Assam as per Annexure-I and Annexure-II therein. As per the
            <lb />
            said notification, the revised toll rates came into force with immediate effect. The two
            <lb />
            tender notices in question herein, were published on 04.11.2014 and 19.12.2014
            <lb />
            respectively, that is, they were issued after the revised toll rates had come into force.
            <lb />
            He has further submitted that the estimated amounts for different Government notified
            <lb />
            public ferries, sealed tenders for each of which were invited by either of the said two
            <lb />
            tender notices, were assessed and arrived at on the basis of the revised toll rates in
            <lb />
            terms of the notification dated 02.07.2014. The petitioners had prepared their bids with
            <lb />
            the knowledge that the estimated amounts for different Government notified public
            <lb />
            ferries were assessed and arrived at as per the revised toll rates. When the petitioners
            <lb />
            were not permitted to collect the revised toll rates during the settlement period, they
            <lb />
            approached the respondent authorities for remission of the settlement amounts as
            <lb />
            denial to collect the revised toll rates had caused both prejudice and loss in terms of
            <lb />
            money to them. But such remission had been denied to them unjustly and the said fact
            <lb />
            could be evident from the reasons assigned by the respondent no. 1 in the office order
            <lb />
            dated 03.02.2017 passed in respect of the representation submitted by the petitioner in
            <lb />
            the writ petition, W.P.(C) no. 1046/2017. Mr. Kataki has submitted that the other
            <lb />
            petitioners had also been denied the benefit of remission on the very same ground, as
            <lb />
            could be evident from the stand taken by the respondent authorities in their counter
            <lb />
            affidavits.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            8.
            <lb />
            Ms. Bora, learned Standing Counsel for the Transport Department has
            <lb />
            submitted that though it is true that the revised toll rates were notified by the
            <lb />
            notification dated 02.07.2014 but it was decided not to enforce the revised toll rates
            <lb />
            due to public protest all over the State against collection of tolls at such revised rates.
            <lb />
            She has further submitted that despite collection of tolls at the old rates by the
            <lb />
            petitioners as lessees for the public ferries herein none of the petitioners had suffered
            <lb />
            losses in terms of money. The monthly statements maintained under Rule 12 of the
            <lb />
            Control and Management Ferries Rules, 1968 in respect of these petitioners go to
            <lb />
            indicate that during the settlement period, the amounts collected by these petitioners
            <lb />
            as lessees were over and above the settlement amounts at which the public ferries
            <lb />
            were settled in their favour. Contending as such, she has submitted that as no loss had
            <lb />
            been suffered by these petitioners as lessees the relief sought for by these petitioners
            <lb />
            regarding remission is not sustainable. The petitioners did not approach the respondent
            <lb />
            authorities seeking remission of the settlement amounts during the settlement period
            <lb />
            and their continuance with operation of the public ferries without demur goes to
            <lb />
            indicate that they had not suffered any loss.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            9.
            <lb />
            I have considered the respective submissions of the learned counsel for
            <lb />
            the parties and also perused the materials brought on record by the pleadings of the
            <lb />
            parties. I have also gone through the provisions of the Northern India Ferries Act, 1878
            <lb />
            and the Control and Management of Ferries Rules, 1968.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            10.
            <lb />
            There is no dispute on the fact that the ferries settled with the petitioners
            <lb />
            are Government notified public ferries, declared as such under Section 4 of the
            <lb />
            Northern India Ferries Act, 1878, as amended [&apos;the Ferries Act, 1878&apos;, for short]. The
            <lb />
            terms and conditions of such settlement are governed and regulated by the provisions
            <lb />
            of the Ferries Act, 1878 and the Control and Management of Ferries Rules, 1968, as
            <lb />
            amended, which have been framed by the State Government in exercise of the powers
            <lb />
            conferred under Rule 12 of the Ferries Act, 1878. Under Section 4, the power has been
            <lb />
            vested in the Government to declare a ferry, by notification in the Official Gazette, to be
            <lb />
            a public ferry. Section 15 of the Ferries Act, 1878 has provided for &apos;toll&apos; and it states
            <lb />
            that toll, according to such rates as are from time to time fixed by the State
            <lb />
            Government, shall be levied on all persons, animals, vehicles and other things crossing
            <lb />
            any river by a public ferry and not employed or transmitted on the public service. It has
            <lb />
            been further provided that the State Government may, from time to time, declare that
            <lb />
            any persons, animals, vehicles or other things shall be exempt from payment of such
            <lb />
            tolls. As per sub-rule [1] of Rule 4 of the Control and Management of Ferries Rules,
            <lb />
            1968, all public ferries which are let by public auction or by calling for tenders shall be
            <lb />
            managed by the lessees subject to the said Rules and the conditions entered in the
            <lb />
            lease granted for each ferry. Under Rule 15 thereof, it is the Director who decides the
            <lb />
            period for which the public ferry shall be leased, subject to the approval of the State
            <lb />
            Government in the Transport Department.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            11.
            <lb />
            It was in exercise of the power conferred under Section 15 of the Ferries
            <lb />
            Act, 1878, the State Government issued the notification dated 02.07.2014 [supra]
            <lb />
            revising inter alia the toll rates for Inland Water Transport public ferries and rates of
            <lb />
            special trips under the Directorate of Inland Water Transport, Assam. Annexure-I and
            <lb />
            Annexure-II of the said notification had specified the different revised toll rates for
            <lb />
            different items like passengers, bicycles, goods, motorcycles/scooters, auto rickshaws,
            <lb />
            light motor vehicle, etc. The notification had clearly declared that the rate shall come
            <lb />
            into force with immediate effect. For examples, the base rate per km per passenger in
            <lb />
            modern vessel was increased from Rs. 2.40 to Rs. 5.00. Similarly, the rate for one
            <lb />
            motor cycle/scooter with rider in modern vessel was increased from Rs. 5.00 to
            <lb />
            Rs. 9.00.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            12.
            <lb />
            It was subsequent to the publication of the said notification dated
            <lb />
            02.07.2014, the tender notice dated 14.11.2014 and the tender notice dated
            <lb />
            09.12.2014 were published, whereby, sealed tenders were invited for a number of
            <lb />
            Government notified public ferries, including the Government notified public ferries
            <lb />
            indicated in the Table above.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            13.
            <lb />
            Rule 16 of the Control and Management of Ferries Rules, 1968 has laid
            <lb />
            down the procedure how the tender process has to be initiated and completed. As per
            <lb />
            Rule 19 of the Control and Management of Ferries Rules, 1968, the tender shall
            <lb />
            generally be settled to the highest bidder. As has been noted above, the petitioners in
            <lb />
            these 3 [three] writ petitions had participated in the said competitive tender processes
            <lb />
            initiated by the above two tender notices by submitting their tenders and had emerged
            <lb />
            successful in the said processes. On having emerged as the successful bidders, the
            <lb />
            afore-mentioned public ferries were settled in favour of the petitioners by different
            <lb />
            settlement orders in their favour by the State Government in the Transport Department
            <lb />
            specifying the amounts at which the public ferries were settled with them, as indicated
            <lb />
            in the Table above. As all the settlement orders were with similar terms and conditions,
            <lb />
            a reference to the settlement order dated 04.03.2015 issued in favour of the petitioner
            <lb />
            in the writ petition, W.P.(C) no. 1046/2017 would suffice for the purpose of
            <lb />
            adjudication of the issue involved herein.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            14.
            <lb />
            It is reflected from the order dated 04.03.2015 itself that the settlement
            <lb />
            order in respect of Bogibeel-Karengbali Ferry Service was passed by the State
            <lb />
            Government after reaching a satisfaction regarding fulfillment of the provisions laid
            <lb />
            down in Rule 16 and Rule 19 of the Control and Management of Ferries Rules, 1968
            <lb />
            and accordingly, the said public ferry i.e. Bogibeel-Karengbali Ferry Service was settled
            <lb />
            with the petitioner for a period of 2 [two] years w.e.f. 01.04.2015 to 31.03.2017 at a
            <lb />
            settlement amount of Rs. 3,23,00,000/-under the provisions of Section 4 [1] of Control
            <lb />
            and Management of Ferries Rules, 1968. It was further mentioned that the settlement
            <lb />
            was subject to the condition that if any subsequent hike in rates/tolls etc. was made by
            <lb />
            the Government, there would be proportionate increase in the lease amount [based on
            <lb />
            the proportionate increase in the estimated amount] and the lessee would have to
            <lb />
            accept it on usual terms and conditions.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            15.
            <lb />
            When the said petitioner submitted a representation before the
            <lb />
            respondent no. 2 i.e. the Director of Inland Water Transport, Assam seeking remission
            <lb />
            of the settlement amount due to non-implementation of the revised toll rates, the
            <lb />
            matter was considered, at first, at the end of the respondent no. 3 therein i.e. the
            <lb />
            Executive Engineer, Inland Water Transport Division, Dibrugarh. By a communication
            <lb />
            dated 29.12.2015, the said respondent no. 3 had informed the respondent no. 2 i.e. the
            <lb />
            Director of Inland Water Transport, Assam that the said petitioner as lessee was made
            <lb />
            to collect the toll @ Rs. 18/-only per passenger as per the old toll rate, instead of the
            <lb />
            revised toll rate @ Rs. 24/-per passenger, notified vide the notification dated
            <lb />
            02.07.2014 during the year 2015-2016. From the said communication, it is evident that
            <lb />
            the revised toll rates were not implemented by the respondent authorities during the
            <lb />
            year 2015-2016. The fact that the estimated amount in the concerned tender notice for
            <lb />
            the Bogibeel-Karengbali Ferry Service was assessed as per the revised toll rate is
            <lb />
            evident from a communication bearing no. DWT-224/2012-13/342 made by the Director
            <lb />
            of Inland Water Transport, Assam on 30.01.2016 to the Government in the Transport
            <lb />
            Department. In the said communication, the Director of Inland Water Transport, Assam
            <lb />
            had admitted that the assessment value as well as the tender bid value was considered
            <lb />
            as per the revised toll rates which was 33.33% above the old rates, but the revised toll
            <lb />
            rates were not implemented by the Department due to non-receipt of instruction from
            <lb />
            the Government. By indicating so, the Director of Inland Water Transport, Assam
            <lb />
            requested the Government in the Transport Department to consider remission of the
            <lb />
            tendered bid value. When the matter of remission was not considered by the
            <lb />
            Government, the petitioner in the writ petition, W.P.(C) no. 1046/2017 preferred a writ
            <lb />
            petition, W.P.(C) no. 2369/2016. The said writ petition, W.P.(C) no. 2369/2016 was
            <lb />
            disposed of by an order dated 20.09.2016 with a direction to the respondent no. 1 to
            <lb />
            consider and dispose of the representation submitted by the said petitioner taking note
            <lb />
            of the communication dated 29.12.2015 of the Inland Water Transport [IWT] Division,
            <lb />
            Dibrugarh.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            16.
            <lb />
            Pursuant thereto, the respondent no. 1 considered the said representation
            <lb />
            and disposed of the same by an office order dated 03.02.2017. While considering the
            <lb />
            representation of the petitioner [Sri Arup Chetia], notice was taken of the fact that the
            <lb />
            concerned public ferry was settled in favour of the petitioner at a tendered bid value at
            <lb />
            Rs. 3,23,00,000/-for the period from 2015 to 2017, that is, Rs. 1,61,50,000/-per year
            <lb />
            and a report submitted by the respondent no. 3 i.e. the Executive Engineer, Inland
            <lb />
            Water Transport Division, Dibrugarh amongst others. Notice was also taken of the fact
            <lb />
            that for Bogibeel-Karengbali Ferry Service, the assessment value for the year 2015-
            <lb />
            2016 was assessed at Rs. 95,92,000/-on calculation done on the basis of the revised
            <lb />
            toll rates, in comparison to the assessment value of Rs. 28,60,032/-during the year
            <lb />
            2014-2015 based on old toll rates. It was recorded therein that during the first year of
            <lb />
            settlement of the said public ferry i.e. 2015-2016, the petitioner [Sri Arup Chetia] as the
            <lb />
            lessee was able to collect an amount of Rs. 4,32,93,071/-whereas he had to deposit an
            <lb />
            amount of Rs. 1,61,50,000/-only to the State Exchequer. As the lessee had earned
            <lb />
            more than the amount he was required to deposit to the State Exchequer even after
            <lb />
            collecting tolls at the old rates, the prayer for remission was negated on the ground
            <lb />
            that the lessee did not incur any loss. By holding so, it was held that there was no
            <lb />
            justification for remission. The same stand has been taken by the respondent
            <lb />
            authorities in all the counter affidavits filed in these 3 [three] writ petitions where the
            <lb />
            common relief that has been sought for is remission in respect of the respective
            <lb />
            settlement amounts.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            17.
            <lb />
            In the back drop of afore-mentioned factual scenario, it is to be
            <lb />
            considered as to whether the relief of remission that has been sought for by the
            <lb />
            petitioners in these writ petitions had been unjustly denied and if yes, as to whether the
            <lb />
            relief that has been sought for in these writ petitions preferred under Article 226 of the
            <lb />
            Constitution of India can be granted to them or not.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            18.
            <lb />
            The communication dated 29.12.2015 reflects that during the period from
            <lb />
            2015 to 2016, the lessee of afore-mentioned public ferry was not allowed by the
            <lb />
            respondent authorities to collect the tolls at the revised rates notified by the notification
            <lb />
            dated 02.07.2014 and the lessee was made to collect the tolls at the old rates. The
            <lb />
            letter dated 30.01.2016 of the Director of Inland Water Transport, Assam has
            <lb />
            demonstrated that the estimated amounts indicated in the tender notices were arrived
            <lb />
            at by taking into consideration the revised toll rates notified by the notification dated
            <lb />
            02.07.2014 which was above 33.33% above the old toll rates. The office order dated
            <lb />
            03.02.2017 has further fortified the fact that the estimated amounts of different public
            <lb />
            ferries in order to settle the same for the period from 2015 to 2017 were arrived at on
            <lb />
            the basis of calculation made as per the revised toll rates notified by the notification
            <lb />
            dated 02.07.2014. From the office order dated 03.02.2017, it has further emerged that
            <lb />
            the State Government did not implement the revised toll rates, notified vide the
            <lb />
            notification dated 02.07.2014, due to protests from general public in various parts of
            <lb />
            the State. Such fact of non-implementation of the revised toll rates has been further
            <lb />
            reiterated in all the counter affidavits filed in the 3 [three] writ petitions.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            19.
            <lb />
            It has been observed in Noble Resources Limited vs. State of Orissa and
            <lb />
            another, reported in [2006] 10 SCC 236, that it is trite that if an action on the part of
            <lb />
            the State is violative of the equality clause contained in Article 14 of the Constitution of
            <lb />
            India, a writ petition would be maintainable even in the contractual field. A distinction
            <lb />
            indisputably must be made between a matter which is at the threshold of a contract
            <lb />
            and a breach of contract; whereas in the former the court&apos;s scrutiny would be more
            <lb />
            intrusive, in the latter the court may not ordinarily exercise its discretionary jurisdiction
            <lb />
            of judicial review, unless it is found to be violative of Article 14 of the Constitution of
            <lb />
            India. While exercising contractual powers also, the government bodies may be
            <lb />
            subjected to judicial review in order to prevent arbitrariness or favouritism on their part.
            <lb />
            Though inherent limitations exist, but it would not be correct to opine that under no
            <lb />
            circumstances a writ will lie only because it involves a contractual matter. It is, at the
            <lb />
            same time, observed that where serious disputed questions of fact are raised requiring
            <lb />
            appreciation of evidence, and thus, for determination thereof, examination of witnesses
            <lb />
            would be necessary; it may not be convenient to decide the dispute in a proceeding
            <lb />
            under Article 226 of the Constitution of India.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            20.
            <lb />
            In Mahabir Auto Stores vs. Indian Oil Corporation, reported in [1990] 3
            <lb />
            SCC 752, it has been held that even when the State or its instrumentality is engaged in
            <lb />
            commercial transactions, its action must be reasonable, fair and just. Therein, the
            <lb />
            respondent Indian Oil Corporation, an instrumentality of the State, who had monopoly
            <lb />
            business in lubricants, etc. suddenly discontinued the supply to the appellant, who was
            <lb />
            being supplied lubricant for a long period from 1965 to 1983. In such backdrop, the
            <lb />
            Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court observed that even though the rights of the citizens are in the
            <lb />
            nature of contractual rights, even in such a case, rule of reason and rule against
            <lb />
            arbitrariness and discrimination, rules of fair play and natural justice are part of the rule
            <lb />
            of law applicable in situation or action by State instrumentality in dealing with citizens
            <lb />
            like in that case.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            21.
            <lb />
            In ABL International Limited and another vs. Export Credit Guarantee
            <lb />
            Corporation of India Limited and others, reported in [2004] 3 SCC 553, the Hon&apos;ble
            <lb />
            Supreme Court after considering a number of previous decisions on the aspect, has
            <lb />
            held as under :-
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;27.
            <lb />
            From the above discussion of ours, the following legal principles
            <lb />
            emerge as to the maintainability of a writ petition :
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (a)
            <lb />
            In an appropriate case, a writ petition as against a State or an
            <lb />
            instrumentality of a State arising out of a contractual obligation is
            <lb />
            maintainable.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (b)
            <lb />
            Merely because some disputed questions of fact arise for consideration,
            <lb />
            same cannot be a ground to refuse to entertain a writ petition in all
            <lb />
            cases as a matter of rule.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (c)
            <lb />
            A writ petition involving a consequential relief of monetary claim is
            <lb />
            also maintainable.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            28.
            <lb />
            However, while entertaining an objection as to the maintainability of a
            <lb />
            writ petition under Article 226 of the Constitution of India, the court should
            <lb />
            bear in mind the fact that the power to issue prerogative writs under Article
            <lb />
            226 of the Constitution is plenary in nature and is not limited by any other
            <lb />
            provisions of the Constitution. The High Court having regard to the facts of
            <lb />
            the case, has a direction to entertain or not to entertain a writ petition. The
            <lb />
            Court has imposed upon itself certain restrictions in the exercise of this
            <lb />
            power. [See : Whirlpool Corporation vs. Registrar of Trade Marks, [1998] 8
            <lb />
            SCC 1] And this plenary right of the High Court to issue a prerogative writ will
            <lb />
            not normally be exercised by the Court to the exclusion of other available
            <lb />
            remedies unless such action of the State or its instrumentality is arbitrary and
            <lb />
            unreasonable so as to violate the constitutional mandate of Article 14 or for
            <lb />
            other valid and legitimate reasons, for which the Court thinks it necessary to
            <lb />
            exercise the said jurisdiction.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            22.
            <lb />
            In Maharashtra Chess Association vs. Union of India and others, reported
            <lb />
            in [2020] 13 SCC 285, the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court has observed that in exercising its
            <lb />
            discretion to entertain a particular case under Article 226, a High Court may take into
            <lb />
            consideration various factors including the nature of the injustice that is alleged by the
            <lb />
            petitioner, whether or not an alternate remedy exists, or whether the facts raise a
            <lb />
            question of constitutional interpretation.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            23.
            <lb />
            Having regard to the facts and circumstances of the case in hand, it is
            <lb />
            found that there is no disputed fact involved as the State respondents have themselves
            <lb />
            admitted that though revised toll rates were notified by the notification dated
            <lb />
            02.07.2014, the same were not implemented during the settlement period from 2015 to
            <lb />
            2017 and as a result, these petitioners as lessees were not allowed to collect the toll
            <lb />
            rates at the revised rates. Meaning thereby, the petitioners were compelled to collect
            <lb />
            the tolls at the old rates, despite the revised toll rates coming into effect by way of a
            <lb />
            statutory notification. While granting the settlements, the State respondents had made
            <lb />
            it a condition for the lessees that the settlement would be the subject to the condition
            <lb />
            that if any subsequent hike in rates/tolls, etc. was made by the Government, there
            <lb />
            would be proportionate increase in the lease amount [based on the proportionate
            <lb />
            increase in the estimated amount] and the lessee would have to accept it on usual
            <lb />
            terms and conditions. In the same analogy, the position should have been reversed in
            <lb />
            that if during the settlement period, there was subsequent decrease in rates/trolls, etc.
            <lb />
            by any decision on the part of the Government, there would be proportionate decrease
            <lb />
            in the lease amount [based on the proportionate decrease in the estimated amount]
            <lb />
            and lessees would be allowed to deposit the installment amounts based on such
            <lb />
            proportionate decrease. The decision of not to implement the revised toll rates was of
            <lb />
            the Government taken unilaterally but the incidence of such decision had also fallen on
            <lb />
            the lessees like the petitioners, of public ferries. It should not always operate in one
            <lb />
            single way, notwithstanding any change in the situation in the opposite way from the
            <lb />
            situation which was envisaged at the inception.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            24.
            <lb />
            In the instant case, by the aforesaid two tender notices [supra], the
            <lb />
            bidders were invited to submit their tenders on the basis of the estimated amounts
            <lb />
            assessed and arrived at on the basis of the revised toll rates. Such transactions are
            <lb />
            commercial transactions for the bidders participating in the tender process initiated for
            <lb />
            settlement of public ferries, which fall in the category of distribution of State largesses.
            <lb />
            The bidders are prudent businessmen who prepare their tenders by taking into
            <lb />
            consideration a host of factors including the terms and conditions incorporated in the
            <lb />
            tender document, the estimated amounts and the quantums of profit they are likely to
            <lb />
            earn and accordingly, they arrive at their tendered bid values. One prepares his tender,
            <lb />
            to the best of his estimation, by quoting his tendered bid value at a definite amount on
            <lb />
            the premise that at such amount, he would be able to perform the obligations under
            <lb />
            the contract if the tender is settled in his favour and at the same time, would also be
            <lb />
            able to earn a particular amount of profit. A number of bidders participate in a tender
            <lb />
            process and the bidders tender different bid values but only one of them emerges
            <lb />
            successful. Thus, the preparation of the tendered bid value is at the peril of the
            <lb />
            rejection of one&apos;s tender if the same does not emerge as the highest valid one and a
            <lb />
            tender process is always competitive. The petitioners in these cases submitted their
            <lb />
            tenders by preparing them only after taking into consideration that they would be able
            <lb />
            to collect the tolls at the new revised rates and accordingly, the tendered bid values
            <lb />
            were quoted. The representation of the State respondents was clear in that the
            <lb />
            estimated values were assessed and arrived at by taking into account the revised toll
            <lb />
            rates, notified vide the notification dated 02.07.2014. Acting on such representation,
            <lb />
            the petitioners had changed their positions.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            25.
            <lb />
            In Unitech Limited and others vs. Telengana State Industrial
            <lb />
            Infrastructure Corporation [TSSIC] and others, reported in [2020] 13 SCC 285, the
            <lb />
            Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court of India has observed that having invited private entrepreneurs
            <lb />
            to submit bids on stipulated terms and conditions, it must be held down to make good
            <lb />
            its representations. The State and its instrumentalities are duty bound to act fairly
            <lb />
            under Article 14 of the Constitution. They cannot, even in the domain of contract, claim
            <lb />
            an exemption from the public law duty to act fairly. The State and its instrumentalities
            <lb />
            do not shed either their character or their obligation to act fairly in their dealings with
            <lb />
            private parties in the realm of contract. Investors who respond to the representations
            <lb />
            held out by the State while investing in public projects are legitimately entitled to assert
            <lb />
            that the representations must be fulfilled and to enforce compliance with duties which
            <lb />
            have been contractually assumed.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            26.
            <lb />
            The State respondents had denied the grant of remission solely on the
            <lb />
            ground that while operating the public ferries, none of the petitioners as lessees had
            <lb />
            suffered losses and all of them had collected beyond the settlement amounts during the
            <lb />
            two years of settlement period. The deviation on their part from the terms and
            <lb />
            conditions of the tender process in that the lessees was not allowed to collect tolls at
            <lb />
            the revised rates was completely ignored. As has been noted above, a bidder submits
            <lb />
            his tender with an objection to collect a certain amount of profit in the event he
            <lb />
            emerges successful in the competitive tender process and earning of profit at a lesser
            <lb />
            amount than was expected by him at the unjust intervention of the State authorities
            <lb />
            cannot be held to be any justification, much less proper justification, on the part of the
            <lb />
            State and its authorities. The earning of lesser profit by the successful bidder as the
            <lb />
            lessee than he was expecting to earn on the basis of the clear representation of the
            <lb />
            State that he would be allowed to collect the tolls at the revised rates by virtue of the
            <lb />
            revised toll rates notified by a statutory notification is also a loss in relative term. The
            <lb />
            requirement of Article 14 of the Constitution of India is to act fairly, justly and
            <lb />
            reasonably without any element of arbitrariness by the State by virtue of its dominant
            <lb />
            position. The action of the State respondents in the case in hand is found to be contrary
            <lb />
            to the principle of non-arbitrariness embodied in Article 14 of the Constitution of India.
            <lb />
            It is settled that the jurisdiction of this Court under Article 226 of the Constitution of
            <lb />
            India is discretionary as well as equitable. The fact situation obtaining in the case in
            <lb />
            hand is not such that after one is put in an adverse and vulnerable position the
            <lb />
            situation cannot be rectified.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            27.
            <lb />
            In the light of the above discussion, this Court is of the unhesitant view
            <lb />
            that the petitioners herein are treated in an unfair, unjust and arbitrary manner by the
            <lb />
            State respondents who were in dominant bargaining positions, and such action of
            <lb />
            denying the benefit of remission to the petitioners is found to be in violation of the
            <lb />
            principle embodied in Article 14 of the Constitution of India. Consequently, the
            <lb />
            petitioners are found entitled to the grant of remission in an appropriate manner, which
            <lb />
            has to be worked out in the same analogy as incorporated in the settlement orders
            <lb />
            itself, albeit in a reverse manner, in that if there is any subsequent decrease in
            <lb />
            rates/tolls, etc. there would be a proportionate decrease in the lease amount [based on
            <lb />
            the proportionate decrease in the estimated amount]. The entire exercise shall be
            <lb />
            completed by the respondent authorities as expeditiously as possible, but not beyond
            <lb />
            an outer limit of 4 [four] months from the date of receipt of a certified copy of this
            <lb />
            order. While undertaking such exercise, the deposits made by the petitioners against
            <lb />
            their respective settlement amounts qua the settlement amounts shall have to be taken
            <lb />
            into account. If any amount is found entitled to these petitioners, after such exercise, it
            <lb />
            shall be disbursed to them forthwith thereafter.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            28.
            <lb />
            Resultantly, the 3 [three] writ petitions are allowed to the extent indicated
            <lb />
            above. There shall, however, be no order as to cost.
        </p>
        <lb />
        <p>
            JUDGE
            <lb />
            Comparing Assistant
        </p>


    </text>
</tei>