<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc xml:id="0" />
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <p>
            The appellant was initially appointed as a Clerk in the
            <lb />
            Canara Bank. He earned his promotion in due course and at the
            <lb />
            point in time he was employed as Special Assistant and was
            <lb />
            posted in the Sikh Temple Branch, Guwahati since 17.06.1994.
            <lb />
            The appellant was served with a Show-Cause notice dated
            <lb />
            26.08.2002 issued by the Deputy General Manager (DGM), Circle
            <lb />
            Office, Calcutta alleging irregular adjustments in Suspense
            <lb />
            Deposit Account. The appellant replied to the Show-Cause notice
            <lb />
            denying the allegations made. The Disciplinary Authority did not
            <lb />
            accept his explanations/reply. Thereafter, an Enquiry Officer was
            <lb />
            appointed and enquiry proceedings were initiated against the
            <lb />
            appellant. The appellant participated in the enquiry proceedings
            <lb />
            and the Enquiry Officer submitted his enquiry report dated
            <lb />
            14.06.2003 holding all the charges levelled against the appellant
            <lb />
            to be proved. On the basis of the Enquiry Report, the Disciplinary
            <lb />
            Authority imposed major punishment of &quot;Compulsory Retirement&quot;
            <lb />
            as provided for under Regulation 4 (B) of Chapter XI of the
            <lb />
            Canara Bank Service Code (hereinafter referred as &quot;Service
            <lb />
            Code&quot;). The appellant being aggrieved by the order of
            <lb />
            &quot;Compulsory Retirement&quot;, preferred an appeal before the
            <lb />
            Authority prescribed under the Service Code. His appeal also
            <lb />
            being rejected by the Appellate Authority, he preferred a writ
            <lb />
            petition being W.P(C) No. 6377/2005 challenging the validity,
            <lb />
            legality and proprietary of the order of &quot;Compulsory Retirement&quot;
            <lb />
            dated 27.09.2003 as well as the order dated 30.12.2004 passed
            <lb />
            by the Appellate Authority. The learned Single Judge vide
            <lb />
            Judgment dated 17.09.2013 dismissed the writ petition declining
            <lb />
            to interfere with the order of Compulsory Retirement passed by
            <lb />
            the Disciplinary Authority. Being dissatisfied with the order passed
            <lb />
            by the learned Single Judge, the present writ appeal has been
            <lb />
            preferred.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            2.
            <lb />
            Mr. N.C. Das, learned Senior counsel assisted by Mr. A. Das,
            <lb />
            learned counsel for the appellant submits that the
            <lb />
            allegations/charges against the appellant were totally uncalled for
            <lb />
            as the appellant had been diligent in rendering his service since
            <lb />
            his date of appointment. The learned Senior counsel referring to
            <lb />
            the communication dated 26.08.2002 would submit that the same
            <lb />
            was issued to the appellant to explain Irregular Adjustment in
            <lb />
            suspense Deposit Account at your Branch-Irregularities observed
            <lb />
            on your part. There was no allegation of causing financial loss to
            <lb />
            the bank or wrongful gain by the appellant. That apart, the
            <lb />
            learned Senior counsel urged that during the enquiry proceedings,
            <lb />
            there are management witnesses who had testified that the
            <lb />
            appellant was one of the excellent employees of the Branch. The
            <lb />
            learned Senior counsel also submits that as per the Canara Bank
            <lb />
            Service Code &quot;Misconduct&quot; may be &quot;gross misconduct&quot; or &quot;minor
            <lb />
            misconduct&quot;. Referring to Clause 3 of the Service Code, he
            <lb />
            submits that the acts and omission of &quot;gross misconduct&quot; referred
            <lb />
            thereunder does not relate to any of the charges made against
            <lb />
            the appellant. Instead at best, the acts or omissions provided for
            <lb />
            under Clause 5 (d) can be attributed to the appellant namely
            <lb />
            &quot;breach of any rule of business of the bank or instruction for the
            <lb />
            running of any department&quot;. He refers to Clause 6 of the Service
            <lb />
            Code and submits that the punishment pursuant to any finding
            <lb />
            arrived at in respect of minor misconduct are provided for under
            <lb />
            Clause 6 of the Service Code. The learned Senior counsel,
            <lb />
            therefore submits that besides the enquiry being conducted in
            <lb />
            gross violation of the procedures mandated under law and with
            <lb />
            total disregard to the lack of evidence against the appellant, even
            <lb />
            assuming though not admitting that pursuant to the enquiry any
            <lb />
            punishment was required to be imposed upon the appellant, the
            <lb />
            same could only have been done as provided for under the
            <lb />
            Service Code for those which relate to minor misconduct. The
            <lb />
            learned Senior counsel, therefore, submits that the punishment of
            <lb />
            &quot;Compulsory Retirement&quot; imposed by the Disciplinary Authority
            <lb />
            and upheld by the Appellant Authority is wholly disproportionate
            <lb />
            and the learned Single Judge having failed to pass appropriate
            <lb />
            orders in this regard, the order of the learned Single Judge needs
            <lb />
            to be interfered with, set aside and consequently, the punishment
            <lb />
            imposed by the Bank Authorities be set aside and quashed. In
            <lb />
            support of his contentions, the learned Senior counsel would
            <lb />
            relied upon the following Judgments:
        </p>
        <lb />
        <p>
            1. Roop Singh Negi Vs. Punjab National Bank and Ors.
            <lb />
            reported in (2009) 2 SCC 570
        </p>
        <lb />
        <p>
            2. State Bank of India and Ors. vs. Ramesh Dinkar Punde,
            <lb />
            reported in (2006) 7 SCC 212
        </p>
        <lb />
        <p>
            3. State of Meghalaya and Ors. Vs. Mecken Singh N. Marak,
            <lb />
            reported in (2008) 7 SCC 580
        </p>
        <lb />
        <p>
            4. State of Uttar Pradesh and Ors. Vs. Ram Daras Yadav,
            <lb />
            reported in (2010) 2 SCC 236
        </p>
        <lb />
        <p>
            5. M.S. Bindra vs. Union of India and Ors., reported in
            <lb />
            (1998) 7 SCC 310
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            6. Ram Janam Singh Vs. State of U.P. and anr. reported in
            <lb />
            AIR 1994 SC 1722
        </p>
        <lb />
        <p>
            7. Kailash Nath Gupta Vs. Enquiry Officer (R.K. Rai),
            <lb />
            Allahabad Bank and Ors. reported in AIR 2003 SC 1377
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            8. Regional Manager, UP SRTC, Etawah and Ors. Vs. Hoti
            <lb />
            Lal and Anr, reported in (2003) 3 SCC 605
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            3.
            <lb />
            Per contra, Mr. S. Chamaria, learned counsel for the Bank
            <lb />
            strongly disputes the contentions of the learned Senior counsel for
            <lb />
            the appellant that the appellant did not cause any financial loss to
            <lb />
            the Bank. On the contrary, referring to the communication dated
            <lb />
            26.08.2002, he submits that the said communication gave a
            <lb />
            detailed descriptions of irregularities caused by the appellant in
            <lb />
            respect of a Suspense Account maintained at the Bank by
            <lb />
            preparing an unauthorized debit and credit vouchers in favour of
            <lb />
            one M/S Ishu Sales Corporation. According to the Bank, such
            <lb />
            casting mistakes were occasioned due to the failure of the
            <lb />
            appellant to adhere to the instructions of Senior Manager by not
            <lb />
            verifying the old records before debiting the Suspense Deposit.
            <lb />
            The learned counsel for the Bank further disputes the contention
            <lb />
            that the acts and omissions of the appellant at best can be
            <lb />
            termed to be &quot;minor misconduct&quot; and not &quot;gross misconduct&quot; as
            <lb />
            has been held by the Bank. The learned counsel for the Bank
            <lb />
            submits that the appellant had admitted before the Bank
            <lb />
            Authorities which is also reflected in his reply as well as in the
            <lb />
            appeal that the casting mistakes were at the instance of the
            <lb />
            instructions of Senior Manager. The learned counsel for the Bank
            <lb />
            submits that such casting mistakes did not happen in a single day
            <lb />
            rather it was spread over a period of time. It is submitted that in
            <lb />
            terms of Clause 3 of the Service Code amongst the acts and
            <lb />
            omissions of any employee which are construed to be gross
            <lb />
            misconduct, habitual act of minor misconduct as well as doing any
            <lb />
            act which is prejudicial to the interest of the Bank are some of the
            <lb />
            acts and omissions which are considered to be gross misconduct
            <lb />
            and which are attributable to the appellant. The learned counsel
            <lb />
            for the Bank relied upon a Judgment of the Apex Court rendered
            <lb />
            in Boloram Bordoloi Vs. Lakhimi Gaolia bank and Ors reported in
            <lb />
            (2021) 3 SCC 806 to support his contention. The learned counsel
            <lb />
            for the Bank submits that any deviation from the procedural
            <lb />
            guidelines of the Bank would lead to erosion of public trust of the
            <lb />
            Banks. The learned counsel for the Bank submits that the
            <lb />
            appellant being a Bank Officer, a great deal of trust is required to
            <lb />
            be reposed upon an Officer of the Bank and any dereliction of
            <lb />
            duty in respect of flouting of the norms and procedures cannot be
            <lb />
            viewed to be a minor mistake or minor misconduct. He, therefore
            <lb />
            submits that there is no infirmity in the enquiry proceedings and
            <lb />
            the appellant having admitted that there were casting mistakes,
            <lb />
            the imposition of punishment of &quot;Compulsory Retirement&quot; is
            <lb />
            appropriate and no interference thereof is called for by this Court
            <lb />
            in exercise of judicial review.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            4.
            <lb />
            We have heard the learned counsels for the parties and
            <lb />
            have perused the pleadings on record.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            5.
            <lb />
            To understand the allegations made against the appellant, it
            <lb />
            will be appropriate to extract the contents of the letter dated
            <lb />
            26.08.2002 which details the irregularities stated to have been
            <lb />
            resorted to by the appellant.
        </p>
        <lb />
        <item>
            &quot;CANARA BANK
            <lb />
            STAFF SECTION (OFFICER), CIRCLE OFFICE, KOLKATA.
            <lb />
            KC:: 4455: E_113(i) SKH: 2002
            <lb />
            AUGUST 26, 2002
            <lb />
            Shri Ashis Kumar Goon (38469)
            <lb />
            Special Assistant
            <lb />
            Canara Bank
            <lb />
            Sikh Temple
            <lb />
            Guwahati.
            <lb />
            Dear Sir,
        </item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            Sub: Irregular Adjustment in suspense Deposit Account at
            <lb />
            your Branch-Irregularities observed on your Part.
        </item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            It has been reported to us that at the time of creation of master
            <lb />
            date for computerization of your Branch, it was found that suspense
            <lb />
            Deposit Account was not tallied since 30.09.2001 and there was a
            <lb />
            difference of Rs. 18,552/-in the account. A detailed investigation
            <lb />
            into the matter has revealed the following:
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            1.
            <lb />
            One Mr. Dilip Das vide his letter dated 29.06.2001 requested
            <lb />
            to pay back Rs. 18,522/-through pay order as he had
            <lb />
            deposited a cheque on 02.08.1989 without writing the
            <lb />
            account number in the pay-in-slip and the same is kept in
            <lb />
            Suspense Deposit Account of the branch for want of full
            <lb />
            particulars. On the top of the said letter, the Senior Manager
            <lb />
            of the Branch instructed to verify the old records and then
            <lb />
            credit.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            2.
            <lb />
            On 30.06.2001 you have prepared the debit slip for debiting
            <lb />
            Rs. 18,522/-to Suspense Deposit Account and also credit
            <lb />
            slip for DD favouring Shri Dilip Das for Rs. 18,522/-. Basing
            <lb />
            on the same the Senior Manager has signed the debit slip
            <lb />
            authorizing debit to Suspense Deposit account. The
            <lb />
            transaction has been put through on 02-07-2001 and DD No.
            <lb />
            550694 dated 02-07-2001 for Rs. 18,522/-has been issued
            <lb />
            favouring Shri Dilip Das.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            3.
            <lb />
            The Suspense Deposit Account has been presumably debited
            <lb />
            against the following credits:
            <lb />
        </item>

        <table>
            Date of Credit:
            <lb />
            Amount:
            <lb />
            05-09-1989
            <lb />
            Rs. 3,000/-
            <lb />
            06-09-1989
            <lb />
            Rs. 3,000/-
            <lb />
            06-09-1989
            <lb />
            Rs. 3,000/-
            <lb />
            03-08-1989
            <lb />
            Rs. 8,000/-
            <lb />
            06-09-1989
            <lb />
            Rs. 1,500/-
            <lb />
            03-08-1989
            <lb />
            Rs. 22/-
            <lb />
            _______________
            <lb />
            Rs. 18,522/-
        </table>
        <lb />
        <item>
            However, these amounts have already been reversed during
            <lb />
            August to September&apos; 89 and credited to the following
            <lb />
            accounts:
        </item>
        <lb />
        <table>
            DETAILS/NAME: TYPE OF TRANS. AMOUNT ADJUSTED ON
            <lb />
            ADJUSTED TO
            <lb />
            T. Singh
            <lb />
            Clearing
            <lb />
            3,000/-05-09-89
            <lb />
            SB 539
            <lb />
            B.C. Baid
            <lb />
            -do-
            <lb />
            3,000/-06-09-89
            <lb />
            SB 537
            <lb />
            B.K. Sharma
            <lb />
            -do-
            <lb />
            3,000/-06-09-89
            <lb />
            SB 1130
            <lb />
            U.C. Medhi
            <lb />
            -do-
            <lb />
            3,000/-03-08-89
            <lb />
            SB 491
            <lb />
            S.D. Singh
            <lb />
            -do-
            <lb />
            1,500/-06-09-89
            <lb />
            SB 41
            <lb />
            D.C. Jain
            <lb />
            -do-
            <lb />
            22/-03-08-89
            <lb />
            Illegible
            <lb />
            ___________
            <lb />
            18,522/-
            <lb />
        </table>

        <item>
            Thus the second debit of the amount on 30-06-2001 has
            <lb />
            been done without any corresponding credit being available
            <lb />
            in Suspense Deposit Account.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            4.
            <lb />
            During investigation, it has also been observed that no
            <lb />
            person named Shri Dilip Das is residing at the address given
            <lb />
            in letter dated 29-06-01.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            5.
            <lb />
            On 05-07-2001, the said DD dated 30-06-2001 favouring
            <lb />
            Shri Dilip Das was received by you at the branch at Clearing
            <lb />
            Deptt. With credit challan for credit to CA 1925 of M/S. Ishu
            <lb />
            Sales Corpn. The amount has been credited to the subject
            <lb />
            account on 06-07-2001 after clearing.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            On further verification, the following is observed:
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            i)
            <lb />
            On 12-08-2000, there was a casting mistake in Current
            <lb />
            Account No. 1925 of M/S Ishu Sales Corpn. when you were
            <lb />
            the Supervisor of Current Account Department resulting in
            <lb />
            debit balance of Rs. 1,97,327.87. The party has repaid the
            <lb />
            amount gradually and a sum of Rs. 22,143/-is debited to
            <lb />
            the account till 30-06-2001 as TOD interest.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            ii)
            <lb />
            After crediting Rs. 18,522/-on 06-07-2001, further Rs.
            <lb />
            7,000/-has been recovered by way of cash on 07-07-2001
            <lb />
            and the Current Account TOD has been regularized.
        </item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            From the above it is observed that you have failed to adhere
            <lb />
            to the instructions of the Senior Manager by not verifying the
            <lb />
            old records before debiting Suspense Deposit. You have also
            <lb />
            accepted the DD issued in favour of Shri Dilip Das and have
            <lb />
            credited the proceeds to the Current Account No. 1925 of
            <lb />
            M/S Ishu Sales Corpn.
        </item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            In view of the above you are hereby called upon to explain
            <lb />
            as to what you have to say in the matter within 7 days of
            <lb />
            receipt of this letter.
        </item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            Yours faithfully,
            <lb />
            Sd/-Illegible
            <lb />
            (N.Jeevagan)
            <lb />
            DEPUTY GENERAL MANAGER.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            Copy to:-
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            1. Sikh Temple, Guwahati Branch: Please deliver the original
            <lb />
            to the converned employee against his dated
            <lb />
            acknowledgement and sent the acknowledged copy to us
            <lb />
            (1) for their files.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            2. Regional Office, Guwahati
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            3. Staff Section (Workmen), Circle Office, Kolkata.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            4. goon 2. Txt.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            6.
            <lb />
            In the reply, the appellant made a categorical statement
            <lb />
            that the Senior Manager instructed him to prepare debit vouchers
            <lb />
            debiting Suspense Deposit Account for Rs. 18,522/-and also the
            <lb />
            corresponding credit slips to be prepared for DD favouring Shri
            <lb />
            Dilip Das. The appellant stated that he had prepared both the
            <lb />
            slips and had handed over to the Senior Manager and after being
            <lb />
            duly authorized, the amount of Rs. 18,522/-vide DD no. 550694
            <lb />
            dated 02.07.2001 was issued in favour of the said Sri Dilip Das. In
            <lb />
            respect of the casting mistake relating to Current Account No.
            <lb />
            1925 of M/S Ishu Sales Corporation on 12.08.2000 resulting in
            <lb />
            debit balance of Rs. 1,97,327.87 and its regularization thereof on
            <lb />
            07.07.2001. It is stated that the same are available in the records
            <lb />
            of the Branch. The reply of the appellant in response to the letter
            <lb />
            dated 26.08.2002 is also reproduced below:
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;From
            <lb />
            Sri Asish Kumar Goon, (38469),
            <lb />
            Canara Bank,
            <lb />
            Sikh Temple,
            <lb />
            Guwahati.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            To:
            <lb />
            The Deputy General Manager,
            <lb />
            Canara Bank,
            <lb />
            Circle Office,
            <lb />
            Kolkata.
            <lb />
            (Through the Manager, Sikh Temple Brach)
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            Dear Sir,</item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            I Acknowledge receipt of your KC:SSO:4455 E_113(i) SKH 2002,
            <lb />
            dated 26 th August, 2002 and submit the following for your kind
            <lb />
            perusal and favourable consideration.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            1.
            <lb />
            At the outset permit me to place on record that the said letter
            <lb />
            dated 29.06.01 nor the instructions &quot;Verify the old records and
            <lb />
            then credit&quot; was neither given/shown to me by the then Senior
            <lb />
            Manager of the branch and hence cannot be held against me in
            <lb />
            any manner.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            2.
            <lb />
            The fact that on 30.06.01 the Senior Manager had instructed me
            <lb />
            to prepare Debit voucher debiting Suspense Deposit Account for
            <lb />
            Rs. 18,500/-and also the corresponding Credit slip to be prepared
            <lb />
            to DD favouring Shri Dilip Das. I had prepared both the slips and
            <lb />
            handed over to the then Senior Manager., On 2.7.01 the then
            <lb />
            Senior Manager had duly authorized both the debit slip and the
            <lb />
            corresponding credit slip and the DD 550694 dated 2.7.01 for Rs.
            <lb />
            18,522/-was issued in favour of Sri Dilip Das.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            3.
            <lb />
            For your information the Suspense Deposit Account was not being
            <lb />
            rounded off at that time for a long period. Hence this procedure
            <lb />
            was not adhered at all. The amount of debit of Rs. 18,522/-was
            <lb />
            indicated by the then Senior Manager and it was not debited as
            <lb />
            presumed by you under point number three of page one of your
            <lb />
            above cited letter.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            4.
            <lb />
            Even though all the six debits under Suspense Deposit Account
            <lb />
            were reversed during August-September 1989, the individual
            <lb />
            debits laying under Suspense Deposit Account were not rounded
            <lb />
            off.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            5.
            <lb />
            On 5.7.01 I was working in the Clearing Department. The said DD
            <lb />
            was received in the National Course and credited to Current
            <lb />
            Account 1925 of M/S Ishu Sales Corporation.
            <lb />
            The other observation is about the casting mistake in the Current
            <lb />
            Account 1925 of M/S. Ishu Sales Corporation on 12.8.00 resulted
            <lb />
            in Debit Balance of Rs. 1,97,327.87 and its regularization thereof
            <lb />
            on 7.7.01 are available in the records of the Branch.
            <lb />
            I have just prepared the debit and credit
        </item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            For Rs. 18,522/-as instructed by him on 30-06-01 prior to his
            <lb />
            relief on SVRS…. The service of the Bank on the said date.
            <lb />
            I have neither met Sri Dilip Das nor the letter dated 29-06-01
            <lb />
            shown me with the alleged instructions of the then Senior
            <lb />
            Manager &quot;Verify the old records and then credit&quot;. Hence the
            <lb />
            question of failure to adhere to the instructions of the then Senior
            <lb />
            Manager as stated does not arise at all. I was really surprised to
            <lb />
            note such instructions were written by the then Senior Manager
            <lb />
            who was fully aware about the position of the unbalanced
            <lb />
            Suspense Deposit Account and procedure for reversing the entries
            <lb />
            from Suspense Deposit Account were not being adhered to.
        </item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            Hence proceeding against me on the alleged lapse of not adhering
            <lb />
            to the procedure and system that too for preparing the slips as
            <lb />
            directed is not fair.
        </item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            I have put in more than two decades of unblemished record of
            <lb />
            service in our institution. I have also stood with the Branch on
            <lb />
            many difficult situations. I request you to consider this reply
            <lb />
            dispassionately and drop further proceedings and render justice to
            <lb />
            me.
        </item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            Thanking you,
            <lb />
            Your&apos;s faithfully
            <lb />
            Dated: 20 th September, 2002.
            <lb />
            Sd/-Illegible
            <lb />
            Place: Guwahati.
            <lb />
            (Asish Kumar Goon)&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            7.
            <lb />
            What is evident from the letter dated 26.08.2002 and the
            <lb />
            reply thereto by the appellant is that there were two irregularities
            <lb />
            noticed by the Bank during investigation. The first pertains to the
            <lb />
            Suspense Deposit Account in respect of an amount of Rs.
            <lb />
            18,522/-which was debited against the following credits:
            <lb />
        </p>

        <table>
            Date of Credit:
            <lb />
            Amount:
            <lb />
            05-09-1989
            <lb />
            Rs. 3,000/-
            <lb />
            06-09-1989
            <lb />
            Rs. 3,000/-
            <lb />
            06-09-1989
            <lb />
            Rs. 3,000/-
            <lb />
            03-08-1989
            <lb />
            Rs. 8,000/-
            <lb />
            06-09-1989
            <lb />
            Rs. 1,500/-
            <lb />
            03-08-1989
            <lb />
            Rs. 22/-
            <lb />
            _______________
            <lb />
            Rs. 18,522/-
        </table>
        <lb />
        <p>
            The said amounts were however reversed during August to
            <lb />
            September, 1989 and credited to the following accounts:
        </p>
        <lb />
        <table>
            DETAILS/NAME: TYPE OF TRANS. AMOUNT ADJUSTED ON ADJUSTED TO
            <lb />
            T. Singh
            <lb />
            Clearing
            <lb />
            3,000/-05-09-89
            <lb />
            SB 539
            <lb />
            B.C. Baid
            <lb />
            -do-
            <lb />
            3,000/-06-09-89
            <lb />
            SB 537
            <lb />
            B.K. Sharma
            <lb />
            -do-
            <lb />
            3,000/-06-09-89
            <lb />
            SB 1130
            <lb />
            U.C. Medhi
            <lb />
            -do-
            <lb />
            3,000/-03-08-89
            <lb />
            SB 491
            <lb />
            S.D. Singh
            <lb />
            -do-
            <lb />
            1,500/-06-09-89
            <lb />
            SB 41
            <lb />
            D.C. Jain
            <lb />
            -do-
            <lb />
            22/-03-08-89 Illegible
            <lb />
            ___________
            <lb />
            18,522/-
            <lb />
        </table>

        <p>
            8.
            <lb />
            Therefore, the second debit entry of the said amount on
            <lb />
            30.06.2001 was done without any corresponding credit being
            <lb />
            available in the Suspense Deposit Account. Further the person in
            <lb />
            whose favour the DD of Rs. 18,522/-was issued and was found
            <lb />
            to be not a resident of the address and the said DD favouring the
            <lb />
            said Shri Dilip Das was received by the appellant himself at the
            <lb />
            Branch with a Credit challan for credit to the Current Account No.
            <lb />
            1925 of M/S Ishu Sales Corporation. Thereafter, on 12.08.2000
            <lb />
            there was a casting mistake in the Current Account No. 1925 of
            <lb />
            M/S Ishu Sales Corporation resulting in a debit balance of Rs.
            <lb />
            1,97,327.87. The said account holder thereafter repaid the
            <lb />
            amount gradually and a sum of Rs. 22,143/-is debited to the
            <lb />
            account till 30.06.2001 as TOD interest. As such, the allegations
            <lb />
            against the appellant is that contrary to the instructions of Senior
            <lb />
            Manager, the old records were not verified before debiting the
            <lb />
            Suspense Account. He had also accepted Demand Draft in favour
            <lb />
            of one Shri Dilip Das and credited the proceeds to the Current
            <lb />
            Account No. 1925 of M/S Ishu Sales Corporation. The Bank
            <lb />
            Authorities being dissatisfied with his explanations in response the
            <lb />
            letter dated 26.08.2002 framed charges and issued charge-sheet.
            <lb />
            The charge-sheet was accompanied by the lists of documents and
            <lb />
            names of the witnesses. The charge-sheet dated 13.11.2002 is
            <lb />
            extracted below:
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;CANARA BANK
            <lb />
            DISCIPLINARY ACTION CELL : : CIRCLE OFFICE : : KOLKATA
            <lb />
            REF NO: KC: DAC: 747: CH(W-3/2002)
            <lb />
            CHARGE SHEET VIDE CHAPTER XI. REGULATION 9(1)(a) OF CANARA BANK
            <lb />
            SERVICE CODE
        </item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            IN THE MATTER OF :
            <lb />
            act of misconduct on the part of-
            <lb />
            NAME
            <lb />
            : SRI ASISH KUMAR GOON
            <lb />
            STAFF NUMBER
            <lb />
            : 38469
            <lb />
            DESIGNATION
            <lb />
            : SPECIAL ASSISTANT (U/S)
            <lb />
            BRANCH AT WHICH
            <lb />
            : SIKH TEMPLE, GUWAHATI
            <lb />
            WORKING.
        </item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            To,
            <lb />
            SRI ASHISH KUMAR GOON (38469)
            <lb />
            SPECIAL ASSISTANT (U/S)
            <lb />
            CANARA BANK
            <lb />
            SIKH TEMPLE BRANCH
            <lb />
            GUWAHATI.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            Whereas there are Prima facie grounds for believing that you have committed
            <lb />
            misconduct, the particulars whereof are given below, this charge sheet has been
            <lb />
            drawn up against you and you are hereby required to submit your explanation in
            <lb />
            writing within fifteen days of receipt of this charge sheet, meeting forth your
            <lb />
            defence, if any, any stating cause as to why disciplinary action should not be
            <lb />
            taken against you.
        </item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            C H A R G E :
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            You are working at our Sikh Temple, Guwahati Branch as Special Assistant (U/S)
            <lb />
            since 17-06-94. At the time of creation Master Data for back office
            <lb />
            Computerisation of Sikh Temple, Guwahati Branch, it was revealed that the
            <lb />
            suspense deposit account was not tallied after June, 2001 and there was a
            <lb />
            difference of Rs.18,522/-.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            An investigation was conducted in this regard and the following has been
            <lb />
            revealed.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            Vide Letter dated 29-06-2001, one Mr. Dilip Das requested to pay back
            <lb />
            Rs.18,522/-through pay order as he deposited a Cheque on 02-08-89 without
            <lb />
            writing the account No. in the pay-in-slip and the same was kept in Suspense
            <lb />
            Deposit Account of the branch for want of full particulars. On the top of the said
            <lb />
            letter the Senior Manager has specifically mentioned to verify the old records and
            <lb />
            then credit.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            On 30-06-2001 you prepared the debit slip for debiting Rs.18,522/-the Suspense
            <lb />
            Deposit Account towards payment of below mentioned credit items dated 02-08-
            <lb />
            89.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <table>
            Date of credits:
            <lb />
            Amount :
            <lb />
            02-08-1989
            <lb />
            ::
            <lb />
            Rs. 3,000/-
            <lb />
            02-08-1989
            <lb />
            ::
            <lb />
            Rs. 3,000/-
            <lb />
            02-08-1989
            <lb />
            ::
            <lb />
            Rs. 3,000/-
            <lb />
            02-08-1989
            <lb />
            ::
            <lb />
            Rs. 1,500/-
            <lb />
            02-08-1989
            <lb />
            ::
            <lb />
            Rs. 8,000/-
            <lb />
            02-08-1989
            <lb />
            ::
            <lb />
            Rs. 22/-
        </table>
        <lb />
        <item>
            Contra Credit slip for the like amount for preparing DD favouring Sri Dilip Das was
            <lb />
            prepared by you.
        </item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            However, these amounts have already been reversed during August-
            <lb />
            September 1989 and credited to the following accounts.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            (Amount in Rs.)
            <lb />
        </item>

        <table>
            Details/Name Type of Trans. Amount
            <lb />
            Adjusted on
            <lb />
            Adjusted to
            <lb />
            T. Singh
            <lb />
            Clearing
            <lb />
            3,000/-
            <lb />
            05-09-89
            <lb />
            SB 539
            <lb />
            B.C.Baid
            <lb />
            -do-
            <lb />
            3,000/-
            <lb />
            06-09-89
            <lb />
            SB 537
            <lb />
            B.K.Sharma
            <lb />
            -do-
            <lb />
            3,000/-
            <lb />
            06-09-89
            <lb />
            SB 1130
            <lb />
            S.D.Singh
            <lb />
            -do-
            <lb />
            1,500/-
            <lb />
            06-09-89
            <lb />
            SB 41
            <lb />
            U.C. Medhi
            <lb />
            -do-
            <lb />
            8,000/-
            <lb />
            03-08-89
            <lb />
            SB 491
            <lb />
            D.C. Jain
            <lb />
            -do-
            <lb />
            22/-
            <lb />
            03-08-89
            <lb />
            To clearing
            <lb />
            Cheque
            <lb />
            returned
            <lb />
            ---------------------------------------------------
            <lb />
        </table>

        <item>
            Thus, the debit for the amount of Rs.18,522/-on 02-07-2001 has been done
            <lb />
            without any corresponding credit being available in Suspense Deposit Account.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            During the investigation it is revealed that no person named Sri Dilip Das is
            <lb />
            residing at the address given in the letter dated 29-06-01.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            On 17-08-2000 you were working as the supervisor of the Current Account
            <lb />
            department of the branch. On that date, there was casting mistake in CA No.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>1925 of M/S. Ishu Sales Corporation resulting in debit balance of Rs.1,97,327.</item>

        <item>
            87.
            <lb />
            The party has repaid the amount gradually and a sum of Rs.22,143/-is debited to
            <lb />
            the account till 30-06-2001 as TOD interest. On 05-07-2001 DD dtd. 02.07.2001
            <lb />
            favouring Sri Dilip Das was received by you at the branch with credit challan for
            <lb />
            credit to CA No. 1925 of M/S. Ishu Sales Corporation. The amount of Rs.18,522/-
            <lb />
            has been credited to the Account of M/S. Ishu Sales Corporation on 06-07-2001.
            <lb />
            After crediting Rs.18,522/-on 06-07-2001, a further amount of Rs.7,000/-has
            <lb />
            been recovered by way of cash regularised.
        </item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            You have failed to adhere to the instructions of the Senior Manager to verify the
            <lb />
            old records before debiting Suspense Deposit. On 30-06-2001 you have prepared
            <lb />
            the debit Slip for debiting the suspense deposit by Rs.18,522/-even though there
            <lb />
            was no contra credit outstanding for the same. You have also accepted the DD
            <lb />
            issued in favour of Sri Dilip Das for credit to the CA No. 1925 of M/S. Ishu Sales
            <lb />
            Corporation.
        </item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            It is revealed that even though you prepared the slip on dated 30-06-
            <lb />
            2001 and got the same signed by the Senior Manager but passed the entry on 02-
            <lb />
            07-2001 when the concerned Senior Manager was not in the service of the bank.
        </item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            Further, it is revealed that you have addressed a letter dtd. 04-07-2001 to Mr.
            <lb />
            Manoj Kumar Tekriwal, Proprietor of M/S. Ishu Sales Corporation, in the capacity
            <lb />
            of the branch Manager giving a commitment regarding waiver of interest of
            <lb />
            Rs.18,000/-in case the balance amount of Rs.7,000/= is paid by the party on or
            <lb />
            before 10-07-2001. However, you have not obtained any permission from the
            <lb />
            Competent Authority to waive any interest amount due from M/S. Ishu Sales
            <lb />
            Corporation and you were not at all authorized by the bank to issue such letter to
            <lb />
            the party. Further, a letter dtd. 07-07-2001 of M/S. Ishu Sales Corporation
            <lb />
            addressed to the Branch confirming credit of Rs. 7,000/-to their Current Account
            <lb />
            had also been received by you and the said letter bears you __ initial alongwith
            <lb />
            the bank&apos;s stamp (transfer stamp). The above fact in respect to the letters dated
            <lb />
            04-07-01-and dtd. 07-07-01 have not been brought to the knowledge/intimated
            <lb />
            to the Manager of the branch on 04-07-2001 and 07-07-2001 with an intention to
            <lb />
            suppress the facts thereby favouring the party.
        </item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            Thus, you had unauthorisedly issued the letter dated 04-07-2001 to Mr. Manoj
            <lb />
            Kumar Tekriwal, Proprietor of M/S. Ishu Sales Corporation informing waiving of
            <lb />
            interest. You had also fraudulently debited an amount of Rs.18,522/-to suspense
            <lb />
            deposit account without having any corresponding entry for issue of DD favouring
            <lb />
            Sri Dilip Das and got the DD proceeds credited to CA No. 1925 of M/S. Ishu Sales
            <lb />
            Corporation to make good the TOD interest waiver which you had committed to
            <lb />
            the customer vide letter dated 04-07-2001.
        </item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            Thus, you have misused your official position in the bank by committing a
            <lb />
            fraud in the books of the bank and writing letters unauthorisedly in the capacity of
            <lb />
            Manager thereby exposing the bank to financial loss. Further, you have failed to
            <lb />
            ensure and protect the interest of the bank and discharge your duties with utmost
            <lb />
            integrity, honesty, devotion and diligence. Thereby you have committed Gross
            <lb />
            Misconduct within the meaning of Chapter XI, Regulation 2A(i) and 3(j) of Canara
            <lb />
            Bank Service Code.
        </item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            Further, your above actions being prejudicial to the interest of the bank,
            <lb />
            you have also committed Gross Misconduct within the meaning of Chapter XI,
            <lb />
            Regulation 3, Clause (m) of Canara Bank Code.
        </item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            CIRCLE OFFICE
            <lb />
            KOLKATA
            <lb />
            Sd/-Illegible
            <lb />
            Deputy General Manager
            <lb />
            Disciplinary Authority
            <lb />
            Date, 13 NOV 2002&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            9.
            <lb />
            Pursuant to the issuance of the charges, the appellant
            <lb />
            submitted his reply and also participated in the enquiry
            <lb />
            proceedings. The Enquiry Officer in his Enquiry Report held that
            <lb />
            all the charges were proved against the appellant. From the
            <lb />
            report of Enquiry Officer, it is evident that Demand Draft for an
            <lb />
            amount of Rs. 18,522/-favouring to one Shri Dilip Das was
            <lb />
            received at the credit section by the appellant along with a credit
            <lb />
            slip for crediting amount to Current Account No. 1925 of M/S Ishu
            <lb />
            Sales Corporation. Further, the said Credit account was overdrawn
            <lb />
            by an amount of Rs. 1,97,327.87 since 17.08.2001 due to a
            <lb />
            casting mistake which was again attributed to the appellant. On
            <lb />
            the basis of such findings in the enquiry report which are
            <lb />
            pursuant to a detailed and extensive enquiry conducted by the
            <lb />
            Enquiry Officer appointed, the Enquiry Officer held that the
            <lb />
            charges levelled against the appellant are proved and the
            <lb />
            appellant was held to be guilty. The Enquiry Officer submitted his
            <lb />
            report before the Disciplinary Authority who agreed with the
            <lb />
            findings of the Enquiry Officer and proposed to impose a
            <lb />
            punishment of &quot;Compulsory Retirement&quot; as provided under
            <lb />
            Regulation 4(B) of Chapter XI Canara Bank Service Code. The
            <lb />
            appellant was given an opportunity of personal hearing. The
            <lb />
            Disciplinary Authority upon hearing the appellant vide order dated
            <lb />
            27.09.2003 imposed the punishment of &quot;Compulsory Retirement&quot;.
            <lb />
            The appeal preferred by the appellant against the punishment
            <lb />
            imposed by the Disciplinary Authority was also rejected by the
            <lb />
            Appellate Authority.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            10. Perusal of the pleadings on record reveals that the appellant
            <lb />
            had indeed admitted inter alia to the casting mistake in respect of
            <lb />
            the Current Account No. 1925 relating to M/S Ishu Sales
            <lb />
            Corporation. Although a plea of defence was sought to be raised
            <lb />
            by the appellant that the same was at the instructions of the
            <lb />
            Senior Manager, however, such plea of defence raised by the
            <lb />
            appellant cannot be accepted in view of the fact that the
            <lb />
            appellant is an employee of a Nationalised Bank and such acts or
            <lb />
            omissions on the part of the appellant had resulted in infraction of
            <lb />
            the procedures as well as the instructions relating to financial
            <lb />
            and/or banking transactions. The responsibility of a Bank Officer
            <lb />
            is to be viewed from the standpoint of the high degree of faith
            <lb />
            and confidence reposed by the depositors in respect of their
            <lb />
            deposits made in the bank of which he is an Officer. The
            <lb />
            explanations of the appellant, in respect of the allegations made
            <lb />
            regarding the transaction pertaining to the said Shri Dilip Das as
            <lb />
            well as the casting mistake resulting in unauthorized debit balance
            <lb />
            in the Current Account no. 1925 relating to M/S Ishu Sales
            <lb />
            Corporation cannot be brushed aside as being minor discrepancies
            <lb />
            as the findings of the Enquiry Officer reveal that such
            <lb />
            discrepancies did not happen in a single day. The appellant was
            <lb />
            aware of such discrepancies which had occurred over a period of
            <lb />
            time. However, there is no statement of the appellant to suggest
            <lb />
            that these discrepancies upon having been noticed by him were
            <lb />
            brought to the notice of the higher authorities and/or appropriate
            <lb />
            authorities in the Branch and also as to what remedial steps were
            <lb />
            undertaken by the appellant to rectify these mistakes. The
            <lb />
            appellant merely states that these transactions were as per the
            <lb />
            instructions of Senior Manager. It is not even stated that as to
            <lb />
            what steps were taken by the appellant in respect of
            <lb />
            discrepancies referred to in the charge-sheet, as also it is not the
            <lb />
            case of the appellant that he was unaware of the transactions
            <lb />
            which are related to the discrepancies alleged.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            11. The Judgment of the Apex Court in Roop Singh Negi(supra)
            <lb />
            referred to does not come to aid of the appellant in view of the
            <lb />
            fact that the appellant does not deny his act or omission in
            <lb />
            respect of the charges alleged. Rather he has consistently
            <lb />
            maintained that the said transactions were pursuant to
            <lb />
            instructions of the Senior Manager. The appellant has not stated
            <lb />
            that the transactions in respect of against which the charge-sheet
            <lb />
            is issued are acceptable as per the banking procedures and
            <lb />
            conventions. The appellant is a sufficiently experienced Bank
            <lb />
            Officer and therefore, unless it is specifically stated that the
            <lb />
            transactions in respect of which the charge-sheet is issued, are
            <lb />
            not contrary to banking procedures and conventions, his mere
            <lb />
            defence that the same were entered upon the instructions of the
            <lb />
            Senior Manager cannot be countenanced.
        </p>
        <lb />
        <p>
            The Judgment of the Apex Court in Ramesh Dinkar
            <lb />
            Punde(supra) relied upon by the appellant relates to the scope of
            <lb />
            judicial review in respect of departmental enquiry. The Apex court
            <lb />
            held that the re-appreciation of evidence is impermissible in
            <lb />
            judicial review. It is held by the Apex Court that the bank officer
            <lb />
            committing misconduct for his personal ends and against the
            <lb />
            interest of the bank and the depositors must be dealt with iron
            <lb />
            hand without any leniency.
        </p>
        <lb />
        <p>
            In Mecken Singh N. Marak(Supra), the Apex Court held that
            <lb />
            the punishment pursuant to the Departmental Enquiry unless
            <lb />
            shockingly disproportionate, is not subject to judicial interference
            <lb />
            and therefore, in such cases judicial review is extremely limited.
        </p>
        <lb />
        <p>
            In Ram Daras Yadav(Supra), the Apex Court held that
            <lb />
            where it is difficult to examine the veracity of the allegations
            <lb />
            against the employee and in the absence of definite conclusion,
            <lb />
            punishment of dismissal is disproportionate.
        </p>
        <lb />
        <p>
            In M.S. Bindra (supra), the Apex Court held that where the
            <lb />
            conclusions arrived at by the administrative authority were not
            <lb />
            supported by way of available material, such action can be
            <lb />
            judicially reviewed
        </p>
        <lb />
        <p>
            The Judgment of the Apex Court in Ram Janam Singh
            <lb />
            (Supra) pressed into service by the appellant pertains to the date
            <lb />
            of reckoning on notional seniority. The Judgment is clearly not
            <lb />
            related to the facts and issues raised in the present case.
        </p>
        <lb />
        <p>
            The Judgment of the Apex Court in Kailash Nath Gupta
            <lb />
            (Supra) is in respect of an order the High Court of Allahabad
            <lb />
            where the question of punishment of removal from service
            <lb />
            whether grossly disproportionate to the charge was not decided
            <lb />
            and was therefore, remitted back for a decision on the issue.
        </p>
        <lb />
        <p>
            The Judgment in Regional Manager UP SRTC, Etawah
            <lb />
            (supra) also relied upon by the appellant holds that the scope of
            <lb />
            judicial review in respect of penalty and punishment is extremely
            <lb />
            limited and restricted to exceptional cases. Where the Court holds
            <lb />
            the punishment to be not commensurate with the charges,
            <lb />
            reasons must be given for coming to such a finding.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            12. In the facts of the present proceedings, there is a clear
            <lb />
            finding by the Enquiry Officer in respect of the charges alleged
            <lb />
            coupled with the admission of the appellant that such transactions
            <lb />
            were indeed resorted to but only upon the instructions of the
            <lb />
            Senior Manager of the Bank. The facts of the present case are
            <lb />
            clearly distinguishable from the facts in the judgments referred to
            <lb />
            by the appellant. Therefore the Judgments of the Apex Court on
            <lb />
            the facts of this case is clearly not applicable and therefore does
            <lb />
            not come to the aid of the appellant.
        </p>
        <lb />
        <p>
            In view of the specific findings arrived at by the Enquiry
            <lb />
            Officer coupled with the admission of the appellant in respect of
            <lb />
            his involvement with regard to the transactions against which the
            <lb />
            enquiry was conducted, the ratio of the Judgment of the Apex
            <lb />
            Court is not applicable as the facts are distinguishable.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            13. In the context of the facts in the present proceedings, the
            <lb />
            ratio of the Judgment of the Apex Court rendered in Boloram
            <lb />
            Bordoloi(supra) is clearly applicable. The Apex Court held that the
            <lb />
            appellant therein had verbally admitted to the charges but was
            <lb />
            trying to explain such lapses due work before and even
            <lb />
            expression his willingness to bear the loss suffered by the Bank
            <lb />
            on account of his lapses. It was held that the procedural
            <lb />
            guidelines which are issued for grant of loans, are expected to be
            <lb />
            followed meticulously by the officers and the employees, as any
            <lb />
            deviation would lead to erosion of public trust on the banks. The
            <lb />
            Apex Court held that since the charges levelled against the
            <lb />
            appellant therein were grave and serious in nature, the
            <lb />
            Disciplinary Authority was liberal in imposing punishment of
            <lb />
            Compulsory Retirement. The relevant extract of the Judgment is
            <lb />
            reproduced below:
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;12. Even, the last submission of the learned counsel for the
            <lb />
            appellant that the punishment imposed is disproportionate to the
            <lb />
            gravity of charges, also cannot be accepted. The charges framed
            <lb />
            against the appellant in the departmental enquiry are serious and
            <lb />
            grave. If we look at the response, in his letter dated 16-8-2005,
            <lb />
            to the show-cause notice issued by the disciplinary authority, it is
            <lb />
            clear that he has virtually admitted the charges, however, tried
            <lb />
            to explain that such lapses occurred due to work pressure.
            <lb />
            Further he went to the extent of saying -he is ready to bear
            <lb />
            the loss suffered by the Bank on account of his lapses.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            13. The Manager of a bank plays a vital role in managing the
            <lb />
            affairs of the bank. A bank officer/employee deals with the public
            <lb />
            money. The nature of his work demands vigilance with the in-
            <lb />
            built requirement to act carefully. If an officer/employee of the
            <lb />
            bank is allowed to act beyond his authority, the discipline of the
            <lb />
            bank will disappear. When the procedural guidelines are issued
            <lb />
            for grant of loans, officers/employees are required to follow the
            <lb />
            meticulously and any deviation will lead to erosion of public
            <lb />
            trust on the banks. If the Manager of a bank indulges in such
            <lb />
            misconduct, which is evident from the charge memo dated 18-6-
            <lb />
            2004 and the findings of the enquiry officer, it indicates that such
            <lb />
            charges are grave and serious. In spite of proved misconduct on
            <lb />
            such serious charges, disciplinary authority itself was liberal in
            <lb />
            imposing the punishment of compulsory retirement. In that view
            <lb />
            of the matter, it cannot be said that the punishment imposed in
            <lb />
            the disciplinary proceedings on the appellant, is disproportionate
            <lb />
            to the gravity of charges. As such, this submission of the learned
            <lb />
            counsel for the appellant also cannot be accepted.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            14. The facts which unfurl from the disciplinary proceedings
            <lb />
            initiated by the Bank and the facts which are evident pursuant to
            <lb />
            the enquiries made as well as upon due consideration of the reply
            <lb />
            submitted by the appellant, it is evident that the acts and
            <lb />
            omissions of the officer are covered by the expression &quot;gross
            <lb />
            misconduct&quot; as per the Clause 3 of the Service Code. The
            <lb />
            punishment in respect of &quot;gross misconducts&quot; is provided for
            <lb />
            under Clause 4 of the Service Code. The Bank Authorities upon
            <lb />
            the findings arrived at imposed the punishment of &quot;Compulsory
            <lb />
            Retirement&quot; which is prescribed under sub clause (c) of clause 4
            <lb />
            of the Service Code. In view of such specific findings, this Court
            <lb />
            comes to a finding that the &quot;gross misconduct&quot; has been resorted
            <lb />
            to by the acts or omissions on the part of the appellant and the
            <lb />
            punishment of &quot;Compulsory Retirement&quot; imposed by the bank
            <lb />
            authority is not disproportionate.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            15. Considering the discussions above, we do not find any
            <lb />
            occasion to interfere with the finding of the learned Single Judge.
            <lb />
            We, accordingly, uphold the Judgment of the learned Single
            <lb />
            Judge vide judgment dated 17.09.2013 and decline to allow the
            <lb />
            present appeal. The writ appeal is accordingly No order
            <lb />
            as to costs.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            JUDGE
            <lb />
            CHIEF JUSTICE
            <lb />
            Comparing Assistant
        </p>


    </text>
</tei>