<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc xml:id="0" />
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <p>
            1.
            <lb />
            By an Advertisement dated 14.08.2018, published by the Public Works
            <lb />
            Department [PWD], Government of Assam, applications were invited for filling up
            <lb />
            156 nos. of posts of Assistant Engineers [Civil] in the Public Works Department
            <lb />
            under Regulation 3[f] of the Assam Public Service Commission [Limitation of
            <lb />
            Functions] Regulations, 1951 [&apos;the APSC Regulations, 1951&apos;, for short] in the Pay
            <lb />
            Scale of Rs. 30,000 -Rs. 1,10,000 with Pay Band : Rs. 12,700.
        </p>
        <lb />
        <p>
            1.1. By another Advertisement, also dated 14.08.2018, published by the Public Works
            <lb />
            Department [PWD], Government of Assam, applications were invited for filling up
            <lb />
            307 nos. of posts of Junior Engineer [Civil] in the Public Works Department under
            <lb />
            Regulation 3[f] of the APSC Regulations, 1951 in the Pay Scale of Rs. 14,000 -
            <lb />
            Rs. 49,000 with Pay Band : Rs. 8,700.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            2.
            <lb />
            It was indicated in both the advertisements that the appointments would be
            <lb />
            purely on ad-hoc basis for a period of 4 [four] months and the details of the same
            <lb />
            could be seen in the concerned website. A common brief Advertisement dated
            <lb />
            14.08.2018 was published.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            3.
            <lb />
            As per the detail advertisements of even date published in the website, the total
            <lb />
            nos. of posts of Assistant Engineer [Civil] and Junior Engineer [Civil] were as
            <lb />
            under :-
        </p>
        <lb />
        <table>
            Assistant Engineer [Civil]
            <lb />
            Junior Engineer [Civil]
            <lb />
            UR
            <lb />
            No. of Posts
            <lb />
            157
            <lb />
            RFW
            <lb />
            47
            <lb />
            OBC/MOBC
            <lb />
            No. of Posts
            <lb />
            83
            <lb />
            RFW
            <lb />
            25
            <lb />
            STP
            <lb />
            No. of Posts
            <lb />
            31
            <lb />
            RFW
            <lb />
            9
            <lb />
            SC
            <lb />
            No. of Posts
            <lb />
            21
            <lb />
            RFW
            <lb />
            6
            <lb />
            STH
            <lb />
            No. of Posts
            <lb />
            15
            <lb />
            RFW
            <lb />
            5
            <lb />
            TOTAL
            <lb />
            No. of Posts
            <lb />
            307
            <lb />
            RFW
            <lb />
            92
            <lb />
            PwD
            <lb />
            Orthopedically Handicapped/Hearing Handicapped/Low Vision
            <lb />
            9
            <lb />
        </table>
        <p>
            RFW = Reserved for Women
            <lb />
            PwD = Person with Disability
            <lb />
        </p>
        <p>
            4.
            <lb />
            The advertisements prescribed the following as educational qualifications for the
            <lb />
            posts of Assistant Engineer [Civil] and Junior Engineer [Civil] :-
        </p>
        <lb />
        <p>
            Assistant Engineer [Civil] :-
            <lb />
            Education Qualification :-
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            (i) Bachelor Degree in Civil Engineering of an Indian or Foreign University
            <lb />
            recognised by the Government.
            <lb />
            OR
            <lb />
            Passed Parts A &amp; B of the Associate Membership Examination of the
            <lb />
            Institution of Engineers [India] and possessing a certificate to that effect
            <lb />
            from the Institution of Engineers [India].
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            (ii) Apart from English, the candidate should have adequate knowledge of at
            <lb />
            least 1 [one] official language of the State of Assam [i.e.
            <lb />
            Assamese/Bengali/Bodo], except candidates belonging to Karbi Anglong
            <lb />
            Autonomous Council and Dima Hasao Autonomous Council.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            Junior Engineer [Civil] :-
            <lb />
            Educational Qualification :-
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            (i) Diploma in Civil Engineering from a recognised Institute.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            (ii) Apart from English, the candidate should have adequate knowledge of at
            <lb />
            least 1 [one] official language of the State of Assam [i.e.
            <lb />
            Assamese/Bengali/Bodo], except candidates belonging to Karbi Anglong
            <lb />
            Autonomous Council and Dima Hasao Autonomous Council.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            5.
            <lb />
            The advertisements further stated that the selection would be done on the basis
            <lb />
            of total marks obtained in the written examination and viva-voce/interview. Out of
            <lb />
            total 200 marks, 160 marks were earmarked for written examination and balance
            <lb />
            40 marks were earmarked for viva-voce/interview. Both the detail advertisements
            <lb />
            also indicated that the Public Works Department would hold Multiple Choice
            <lb />
            Objective Type Written Examination for Paper-I and Part-I of Paper-II and
            <lb />
            Multiple Choice Objective Type Written Examination/Short Descriptive Type
            <lb />
            Examination for Parts -II &amp; III of Paper-II. The Public Works Department would
            <lb />
            make the syllabi for Paper-I [Civil Engineering] and Paper-II [General Studies]
            <lb />
            available in the departmental website.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            6.
            <lb />
            The petitioners in both the writ petitions having found themselves eligible in
            <lb />
            respect of the criteria prescribed therein, responded to the said advertisements by
            <lb />
            submitting their candidatures. The 132 nos. of writ petitioners in the writ petition,
            <lb />
            W.P.[C] no. 617/2020 vied for the post of Assistant Engineer [Civil] whereas the
            <lb />
            195 nos. of writ petitioners in the writ petition, W.P.[C] no. 744/2020 applied for
            <lb />
            the post of Junior Engineer [Civil].
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            7.
            <lb />
            Notices dated 06.10.2018 and 15.10.2018 were published thereafter, announcing
            <lb />
            that the written examinations for the posts of Assistant Engineer [Civil] and Junior
            <lb />
            Engineer [Civil] would be held separately on 11.11.2018 and the admit cards for
            <lb />
            the same would be issued from 24.10.2018. It was further mentioned that the
            <lb />
            respective syllabus for the written examination in respect of both the posts would
            <lb />
            be uploaded in the departmental website on the dates mentioned therein.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            8.
            <lb />
            After processing of applications, the Public Works Department issued admit cards
            <lb />
            to the candidates including the petitioners, for the written examinations scheduled
            <lb />
            on 11.11.2018 in respect of both the posts i.e. Assistant Engineer [Civil] and
            <lb />
            Junior Engineer [Civil]. Thereafter on 11.11.2018, the written examinations were
            <lb />
            held and the petitioners in both the writ petitions appeared in the said written
            <lb />
            examinations along with other candidates. In due course, the Public Works
            <lb />
            Department published results of the written examinations and the marks of the
            <lb />
            candidates scored in the written examinations for both papers were uploaded in
            <lb />
            the Public Works Department website.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            9.
            <lb />
            The petitioners in both the writ petitions were found successful in the written
            <lb />
            examinations and accordingly, they were called to appear along with others in the
            <lb />
            interviews scheduled to be held on different dates in January, 2019 by issuing
            <lb />
            individual call letters to the successful candidates in the written examinations.
            <lb />
            After completion of the interviews and scrutiny of marks obtained during the
            <lb />
            selection process, the petitioners in both the writ petitions were found selected.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            10.
            <lb />
            By a Notification dated 05.03.2019 issued under the hand of the Commissioner &amp;
            <lb />
            Special Secretary to the Government of Assam, Public Works Department, the
            <lb />
            Department notified the list of 156 nos. of candidates who were selected for
            <lb />
            appointment for the post of Assistant Engineer [Civil] provisionally under
            <lb />
            Regulation 3[f] of the APSC Regulations, 1951 pending receipt of their final police
            <lb />
            verification reports. In the said notification, the places of posting of the successful
            <lb />
            candidates were indicated. The names of the petitioners in W.P.[C] no. 617/2020
            <lb />
            figured in the said list of successful candidates who were offered the
            <lb />
            appointments. The successful candidates were directed to join their places of
            <lb />
            posting within stipulated time period along with a medical fitness certificate and
            <lb />
            self attested copies of the original documents viz. educational qualification, proof
            <lb />
            of age, caste certificate, etc. for official record.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            10.1. In terms of the notification dated 05.03.2019, all the petitioners in W.P.[C] no.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            617/2020 joined their respective places of posting by submitting joining reports.
            <lb />
            The police verifications of the petitioners were also carried out in due course and
            <lb />
            reports to that effect were also submitted. The petitioners were also made to
            <lb />
            undergo medical examinations. Though initially the appointments were made for
            <lb />
            a period of 4 [four] months, it was extended for a further period of 4 [four]
            <lb />
            months by a communication dated 16.08.2019. Thus, their services were
            <lb />
            continued through subsequent extension orders and their period of service was
            <lb />
            lastly extended for a further period of 4 [four] months vide communication dated
            <lb />
            27.11.2019.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            11.
            <lb />
            By another similar notification dated 04.06.2019 issued under the hand of the
            <lb />
            Commissioner &amp; Special Secretary to the Government of Assam, Public Works
            <lb />
            Department, the Department notified the list of 307 nos. of candidates who were
            <lb />
            selected and appointed for the post of Junior Engineer [Civil] provisionally under
            <lb />
            Regulation 3[f] of the APSC Regulations, 1951 pending receipt of their final police
            <lb />
            verification reports. In the said notification, the places of posting of the successful
            <lb />
            candidates were indicated. The names of the petitioners in W.P.[C] no. 744/2020
            <lb />
            figured in the said list of successful candidates who were offered the
            <lb />
            appointments. The successful candidates were directed to join their places of
            <lb />
            posting within stipulated time period along with a medical fitness certificate and
            <lb />
            self attested copies of the original documents viz. educational qualification, proof
            <lb />
            of age, caste certificate, etc. for official record.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            11.1. In terms of the notification dated 04.06.2019, all the petitioners in W.P.[C] no.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            744/2020 joined their respective places of posting by submitting joining reports.
            <lb />
            The police verifications of the petitioners were also carried out in due course and
            <lb />
            reports to that effect were also submitted. The petitioners were also made to
            <lb />
            undergo medical examinations. Though initially the appointments were made for
            <lb />
            a period of 4 [four] months, their services were thereafter, continued through
            <lb />
            subsequent extension orders and their period of service was lastly extended for a
            <lb />
            further period of 4 [four] months vide a communication dated 27.01.2020.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            12.
            <lb />
            After joining their services, the petitioners were receiving their salaries from time
            <lb />
            to time and there were incremental increases with the enhancement of DA, etc.
            <lb />
            The respondent authorities were also deducting the contributions towards
            <lb />
            National Pension Scheme [NPS] in respect of some of the petitioners who were
            <lb />
            allotted Permanent Retirement Account Numbers [PRAN].
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            13.
            <lb />
            When both the sets of petitioners in W.P.[C] no. 617/2020 and W.P.[C] no.
            <lb />
            744/2020 were so working in the posts of Assistant Engineer [Civil] and Junior
            <lb />
            Engineer [Civil] respectively in the Public Works Department, another
            <lb />
            advertisement came to be published by the Assam Public Service Commission
            <lb />
            [&apos;the APSC&apos;, and/or &apos;the Commission&apos;, for short] vide Advertisement no. 06/2019
            <lb />
            dated 19.11.2019 whereby applications were invited for filling up of 156 nos. of
            <lb />
            vacancies in the post of Assistant Engineer [Civil] and 307 nos. of vacancies in the
            <lb />
            post of Junior Engineer [Civil] respectively under the Public Works Department.
            <lb />
            The scale of pay, eligibility criteria and educational qualification criteria indicated
            <lb />
            in the Advertisement dated 19.11.2019 are same with the Advertisements dated
            <lb />
            14.08.2018 for both the posts. As per the said advertisement, the last date of
            <lb />
            submission of application was 21.12.2019. The 156 nos. of vacancies in the post
            <lb />
            of Assistant Engineer [Civil] and 307 nos. of vacancies in the post of Junior
            <lb />
            Engineer [Civil] have been identified in the following manner :-
        </p>
        <lb />
        <table>
            Assistant Engineer [Civil]
            <lb />
            Name of the Post
            <lb />
            Assistant Engineer [Civil] under Public Works Roads Department
            <lb />
            Open Category
            <lb />
            Total
            <lb />
            RFW
            <lb />
            RFW
            <lb />
            STH
            <lb />
            Total
            <lb />
            Total
            <lb />
            RFW
            <lb />
            RFW
            <lb />
            EWS
            <lb />
            Total
            <lb />
            Total
            <lb />
            RFW
            <lb />
            RFW
            <lb />
            Total
            <lb />
            Total
            <lb />
            Total
            <lb />
            RFW
            <lb />
            RFW
            <lb />
            Post for Reserved for
            <lb />
            PWD &amp; Type Disability
            <lb />
            i) Blindness &amp; LV=3 ii) Deaf &amp; HI=3 iii) Locomotor Disability etc.=2 iv) Autism etc.=3
            <lb />
        </table>

        <p>
            14.
            <lb />
            Aggrieved by the publication of the said advertisement by the APSC on
            <lb />
            19.11.2019, the petitioners submitted representations before the respondent
            <lb />
            authorities in the Public Works Department as well as to the APSC on 25.11.2019
            <lb />
            and 19.12.2019. Ventilating their grievances for undertaking a recruitment
            <lb />
            process for filling up 156 nos. of vacancies in the post of Assistant Engineer [Civil]
            <lb />
            and 307 nos. of vacancies in the post of Junior Engineer [Civil] in the Public
            <lb />
            Works Department again the petitioners, by the said representations, had
            <lb />
            requested for their regularization and also prayed for preference in terms of
            <lb />
            weightage in both the written examination as well as in the viva-voce/interview
            <lb />
            by taking into account the unblemished services they had been rendering in the
            <lb />
            Public Works Department since after their joining pursuant to a selection process.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            15.
            <lb />
            The petitioners thereafter, submitted their candidatures responding to the
            <lb />
            Advertisement no. 06/2019 dated 19.11.2019 of the APSC. In the Advertisement
            <lb />
            no. 06/2019, it was stipulated that the candidates for the post of Junior Engineer
            <lb />
            [Civil] should not be less than 21 years of age and not more than 38 years of age
            <lb />
            as on 01.01.2019. The upper age limit was relaxable for the candidates belonging
            <lb />
            to SC/ST/OBC/MOBC/PwD, as had been indicated therein. On 28.11.2019, the
            <lb />
            APSC published a Corrigendum whereby the minimum age for the post of Junior
            <lb />
            Engineer [Civil] had been reduced to 18 years instead of 21 years. By a
            <lb />
            subsequent notification dated 19.12.2019, the last date of submission of
            <lb />
            application forms for both the posts of Assistant Engineer [Civil] and Junior
            <lb />
            Engineer [Civil] was extended up to 01.01.2020. The APSC had subsequently
            <lb />
            notified the syllabi for the written examinations for both the posts of Assistant
            <lb />
            Engineer [Civil] and Junior Engineer [Civil] under the Public Works Department.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            16.
            <lb />
            When no response was received in respect of their representations seeking
            <lb />
            regularisation and also preference [weightage] in the selection process that was
            <lb />
            going to be undertaken pursuant to the Advertisement no. 06/2019, the two writ
            <lb />
            petitions under Article 226 of the Constitution of India have been preferred.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            17.
            <lb />
            The writ petition, W.P.[C] no. 617/2020 was filed on 30.01.2020 and the other
            <lb />
            writ petition, W.P.[C] no. 744/2020 was filed on 01.02.2020.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            18.
            <lb />
            In continuation of the Advertisement no. 06/2019 published on 19.11.2019, it had
            <lb />
            been notified by the APSC by way of an Addendum dated 06.05.2020 that the
            <lb />
            Government in the Public Works Department had intimated about additional 104
            <lb />
            nos. of vacancies in the post of Assistant Engineer [Civil] vide their letter dated
            <lb />
            20.03.2020. By the said Addendum, the break up of 104 nos. of vacancies as
            <lb />
            intimated by the Government, over and above 156 nos. of vacancies already
            <lb />
            advertised, had been published in the following manner :-
        </p>
        <lb />
        <table>
            Assistant Engineer
            <lb />
            UR
            <lb />
            Nos. of Post
            <lb />
            64
            <lb />
            RFW
            <lb />
            19
            <lb />
            OBC/MOBC
            <lb />
            Nos. of Post
            <lb />
            22
            <lb />
            RFW
            <lb />
            7
            <lb />
            STP
            <lb />
            Nos. of Post
            <lb />
            7
            <lb />
            RFW
            <lb />
            2
            <lb />
            STH
            <lb />
            Nos. of Post
            <lb />
            2
            <lb />
            RFW
            <lb />
            1
            <lb />
            SC
            <lb />
            Nos. of Post
            <lb />
            9
            <lb />
            RFW
            <lb />
            3
            <lb />
            EWS, 10%
            <lb />
            Nos. of Post
        </table>
        <lb />
        <p>
            It was informed by the said Addendum that those who intended to apply for the
            <lb />
            said 104 nos. of vacancies in the post of Assistant Engineer [Civil] should submit
            <lb />
            their applications in the prescribed form on or before the last date of receipt of
            <lb />
            application fixed on 16.06.2020. It was further informed that those who had
            <lb />
            already applied earlier in response to Advertisement no. 06/2019 need not apply
            <lb />
            again. In the Addendum, it was mentioned that the APSC had, on 06.03.2020,
            <lb />
            notified to hold screening test [OMR based] on the basis of the Advertisement no.
            <lb />
            06/2019 on 05.04.2020. Subsequently, however, the screening test [OMR based]
            <lb />
            was postponed due to outbreak of Corona Virus vide Notification dated
            <lb />
            26.03.2020 and the screening test so notified, stood suspended temporarily. It
            <lb />
            was further informed that a fresh notification for holding the screening test would
            <lb />
            be notified on the basis of the vacancy position in 260 [=156+104] nos. of posts
            <lb />
            of Assistant Engineer [Civil] later on.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            19.
            <lb />
            In the writ petition, W.P.[C] no. 617/2020, the advertisement made in relation to
            <lb />
            the vacancies in the post of Assistant Engineer [Civil] vide Advertisement no.
            <lb />
            06/2019 has been assailed. By seeking setting aside of Advertisement no.
            <lb />
            06/2019, the petitioners, 132 in nos., have sought for a direction for their
            <lb />
            regularization and/or absorption in the sanctioned permanent posts of Assistant
            <lb />
            Engineer [Civil] in the Public Works Department, Government of Assam. In
            <lb />
            addition, the petitioners have also sought for a direction to the respondent
            <lb />
            authorities to give quantitative preference [weightage] to the petitioners who are
            <lb />
            presently working as Assistant Engineer [Civil] in the Public Works Department, in
            <lb />
            the selection process initiated pursuant to the Advertisement no. 06/2019.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            19.1. In the other writ petition, W.P.[C] no. 744/2020, the advertisement made in
            <lb />
            relation to the vacancies in the post of Junior Engineer [Civil] vide Advertisement
            <lb />
            no. 06/2019 has been assailed in the similar manner. By seeking setting aside of
            <lb />
            Advertisement no. 06/2019, the petitioners, 195 in nos., have sought for a
            <lb />
            direction for their regularization and/or absorption in the sanctioned permanent
            <lb />
            post of Junior Engineer [Civil] in the Public Works Department, Government of
            <lb />
            Assam. In addition, the petitioners have also sought for a direction to the
            <lb />
            respondent authorities to give quantitative preference [weightage] to the
            <lb />
            petitioners who are presently working in the Public Works Department as Junior
            <lb />
            Engineer [Civil], in the selection process initiated pursuant to the Advertisement
            <lb />
            no. 06/2019.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            20.
            <lb />
            As both the writ petitions have arisen out of the same Advertisement no. 06/2019
            <lb />
            dated 19.11.2019; the prayers made in the two writ petitions are similar and the
            <lb />
            State respondents in both the writ petitions are same, the two writ petitions are
            <lb />
            taken up together for final consideration at the request of the learned counsel for the
            <lb />
            parties.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            21.
            <lb />
            I have heard Mr. D. Das, learned senior counsel assisted by Mr. R. Sarma, learned
            <lb />
            counsel for the petitioners in W.P.[C] no. 617/2020 and Mr. D.K. Mishra, learned
            <lb />
            senior counsel assisted by Ms. D. Saikia, learned counsel for the petitioners in
            <lb />
            W.P.[C] no. 744/2020. I have also heard Mr. D. Saikia, learned Advocate General,
            <lb />
            Assam assisted by Mr. P. Nayak, learned Standing Counsel, Public Works
            <lb />
            Department for the respondent nos. 1 -5 in both the writ petitions; Mr. T.J.
            <lb />
            Mahanta, learned senior Standing Counsel, APSC assisted by Mr. P.P. Dutta,
            <lb />
            learned Additional Standing Counsel, APSC for the respondent nos. 6 and 7 in
            <lb />
            both the writ petitions; and Mr. A.K. Sarma, learned counsel for the private
            <lb />
            respondent nos. 8 -50 in the writ petition, W.P.[C] no. 617/2020.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            Writ Petition, W.P.[C] no. 617/2020 :-
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            22.
            <lb />
            Mr. D. Das, learned senior counsel appearing for the petitioners in W.P.[C] no.
            <lb />
            617/2019 has, at the beginning, submitted that though a prayer for a direction to
            <lb />
            regularise the services of the petitioners who are working in the post of Assistant
            <lb />
            Engineer [Civil] in the Public Works Department in terms of their selection and
            <lb />
            recruitment under Regulation 3[f] of the APSC Regulations, 1951, has been made
            <lb />
            in the writ petition but he is not pressing the said prayer for regularisation of the
            <lb />
            petitioners&apos; services in the post of Assistant Engineer [Civil].
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            22.1. Advancing his submission on the issue of preference in the form of weightage, he
            <lb />
            has referred to the provisions of the Assam Engineering [Public Works
            <lb />
            Department] Service Rules, 1978 [&apos;the PWD Service Rules&apos;, for short]; the Assam
            <lb />
            Panchayat and Rural Development Officers [Technical] Service Rules, 2015 [&apos;the
            <lb />
            P&amp;RD Service Rules&apos;, for short] and the Assam Health Service Rules, 1995 [&apos;the
            <lb />
            Health Service Rules&apos;, for short]. Bringing specific reference to the clause with
            <lb />
            regard to relaxation appearing in all the said three sets of service rules i.e. [a]
            <lb />
            Rule 28 in the PWD Service Rules; [b] Rule 25 in the P&amp;RD Service Rules; and [c]
            <lb />
            Rule 26 in the Health Service Rules, he has submitted that all the said three rules
            <lb />
            appearing in the three sets of service rules are pari materia.
        </p>
        <lb />
        <p>
            22.2. It is his submission that if the Government is satisfied that the operation of any
            <lb />
            one of the rules in the service rules has caused undue hardship in any particular
            <lb />
            case, it may dispense with or relax the requirement of that rule to such an extent
            <lb />
            and subject to such conditions as the Government may consider necessary for
            <lb />
            dealing with a case in a just and equitable manner. Thus, the State Government
            <lb />
            in the concerned department has the power and authority to deal with the
            <lb />
            present situation by providing preference [weightage] to the candidates who are
            <lb />
            working in the Public Works Department for a substantial period of time, like the
            <lb />
            present petitioners, since it is apparent that the petitioners are likely to suffer
            <lb />
            hardship in facing open competitions vis-à-vis all other candidates in the written
            <lb />
            examination as well as in the viva-voce/oral interview.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            22.3. He has submitted that because of their rendering services in the post of Assistant
            <lb />
            Engineer [Civil] at different places of posting throughout the State of Assam, they
            <lb />
            cannot be equated with other candidates. Bringing reference to an Advertisement
            <lb />
            dated 24.06.2020 published by the APSC for filling up 344 nos. vacancies in the
            <lb />
            post of Junior Engineer [Civil] under the P&amp;RD Department, he has submitted that
            <lb />
            in the said advertisement, no preference was initially given to the eligible
            <lb />
            candidates who were serving as Contractual Accredited Engineers in the P. &amp; R.
            <lb />
            D. Department. When a writ petition, W.P.[C] no. 2839/2020 [All Assam
            <lb />
            Accredited Engineers Association vs. the State of Assam and others] was
            <lb />
            instituted before this Court, this Court by an order dated 21.07.2020 allowed the
            <lb />
            petitioners&apos; Association therein to make a representation collectively before the
            <lb />
            Government in the P&amp;RD Department raising their claim for a consideration of the
            <lb />
            relaxation clause under Rule 25 of the P&amp;RD Service Rules, 2015. The
            <lb />
            Government in the P&amp;RD Department thereafter, took a decision on 14.08.2020 in
            <lb />
            respect of filling up the 344 nos. of vacancies in the post of Junior Engineer and
            <lb />
            as per Rule 25 of the P&amp;RD Service Rules by relaxing the age and also by
            <lb />
            providing different weightages based on their service experiences in the
            <lb />
            department.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            22.4. He has also brought reference to another advertisement published by the APSC
            <lb />
            on 05.10.2016 for filing up 208 nos. of vacancies in the post of Registrar /
            <lb />
            Resident Physician / Resident Surgeon / Refractionist / Demonstrator, etc. in
            <lb />
            various departments of the Government Medical Colleges in the State of Assam
            <lb />
            under the Health &amp; Family Welfare [B] Department wherein it was specifically
            <lb />
            provided that preference would be given to doctors working under Regulation 3[f]
            <lb />
            of the APSC Regulations, 1951 while specifying M.D. or M.S. Degree in the
            <lb />
            concerned subject as the requisite educational qualification.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            22.5. Reference is also made to another Advertisement dated 20.06.2020 published by
            <lb />
            the Medical and Health Recruitment Board, Assam whereby applications for filing
            <lb />
            up 112 nos. of vacancies in the post of Medical Officer [Critical Care] in the
            <lb />
            Government Medical Colleges and Hospitals under the Health &amp; Family Welfare
            <lb />
            Department were invited. In the said advertisement, it was specifically mentioned
            <lb />
            that preference would be given to the Doctors working under Rule 17B of MHRB
            <lb />
            Regulations or on Contractual basis in Medical Colleges and Hospitals of Assam.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            22.6. There was two other advertisements published by the APSC on 01.11.2011 and
            <lb />
            30.12.2019 for filing up vacancies in the posts of Registrars / Resident Physician /
            <lb />
            Resident Surgeon / Refractionist / Demonstrator / Anaesthetist / Resident
            <lb />
            Pathologist, etc. in various departments of the Government Medical Colleges in
            <lb />
            the State of Assam under the Health &amp; Family Welfare Department and for filing
            <lb />
            up the post of Fishery Development Officers and Allied Cadre under the Fishery
            <lb />
            Department wherein it was mentioned that preference would be given to the
            <lb />
            Doctors working under Regulation 3[f] of the APSC Regulations, 1951 and to
            <lb />
            those candidates having experience in serving Fishery Department under various
            <lb />
            projects related to Aquaculture and Fishery Extension respectively.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            22.7. Bringing references to the aforesaid instances, he has submitted that it is very
            <lb />
            much evident that the Government in those cases had provided preference
            <lb />
            [weightage] to the candidates who were serving in the concerned department for
            <lb />
            a considerable period of time either under Regulation 3[f] of the APSC Regulation
            <lb />
            1951 or under contractual terms. The case of the present petitioners is no
            <lb />
            different from the candidates who were given preference [weightage] in the
            <lb />
            recruitment processes undertaken through those advertisements. It is, thus,
            <lb />
            incumbent on the part of the petitioners for providing preference in the form of
            <lb />
            weightage in the recruitment process undertaken vide Advertisement no. 06/2019
            <lb />
            dated 19.11.2019 by taking into account the experience as well as the hardships
            <lb />
            faced by the petitioners by dealing with the cases in a just and equitable manner.
            <lb />
            In support of his above submissions, Mr. Das has relied upon the decisions in
            <lb />
            Shankar K. Mandal and others vs. State of Bihar and others, reported in [2003] 9
            <lb />
            SCC 519. The decision in V. Lavanya and others vs. State of Tamil Nadu, reported
            <lb />
            in [2017] 1 SCC 322, is relied upon to canvas that even if the process of
            <lb />
            selection has already been initiated, it is permissible to grant relaxation, which
            <lb />
            would not amount to change of the rule of the game in the mid-way.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            22.8. Referring to the additional affidavit filed on behalf of the petitioners on
            <lb />
            19.08.2021, he has submitted that upon publication of the Addendum on
            <lb />
            06.05.2020 whereby additional 104 nos. of vacancies in the post of Assistant
            <lb />
            Engineer [Civil] were notified, more number of applications were received from
            <lb />
            the candidates. The last date of submission of application was 16.06.2020. As per
            <lb />
            the settled position of law, a candidate should have the essential educational
            <lb />
            qualification which is Bachelor Degree in Civil Engineering in the case in hand. But
            <lb />
            the APSC has allowed a number of ineligible candidates who did not have the
            <lb />
            above degree qualification as on 16.06.2020, to sit in the written examination
            <lb />
            held on 15.11.2020. By referring a few names of such candidates, as mentioned
            <lb />
            in the Table in paragraph 4 thereof, he has submitted that the final results of
            <lb />
            those candidates&apos; were declared only on 18.09.2020. Yet, the APSC has permitted
            <lb />
            those ineligible candidates to appear in the written examination. Such action on
            <lb />
            the part of the APSC has not only vitiated the selection process but also has
            <lb />
            caused prejudice to the chances of the petitioners, he submits. He has also made
            <lb />
            reference to a number of instances from Annexure-4 and Annexure-5, appended
            <lb />
            to the said additional affidavit, to submit that instances are found which go to
            <lb />
            show that the same candidate was issued two admit cards for the same written
            <lb />
            examination. It is his submission that the Commission is duty bound to adhere to
            <lb />
            the principle observed in Shankar K. Mandal [supra] with regard to issue of
            <lb />
            eligibility of the appearing candidates are concerned.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            Writ Petition, W.P.[C] no. 744/2020 :-
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            23.
            <lb />
            Mr. D.K. Mishra, learned senior counsel for the petitioners in the writ petition,
            <lb />
            W.P.[C] no. 744/2020 has submitted that the petitioners responded to the
            <lb />
            Advertisement dated 14.08.2018 and after completion of the selection process,
            <lb />
            the petitioners came to be appointed as Junior Engineer [Civil] vide the
            <lb />
            notification dated 04.06.2019. The petitioners are eligible to be appointed as
            <lb />
            Junior Engineer [Civil] in the Public Works Department. It was after completion of
            <lb />
            about 3 [three] months of their service as Junior Engineer [Civil], the impugned
            <lb />
            Advertisement was published whereby 307 nos. of vacancies in the post of Junior
            <lb />
            Engineer [Civil] have been sought to be filled up by the Public Works Department.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            23.1. Drawing attention to the syllabus published after the Advertisement dated
            <lb />
            14.08.2018 and the syllabus published after the Advertisement dated 19.11.2019,
            <lb />
            he has submitted that the contents of the two syllabi for the paper in Civil
            <lb />
            Engineering are almost similar. He has, thus, submitted that the syllabus for the
            <lb />
            selection process where the petitioners emerged successful was substantially
            <lb />
            similar to the syllabus published for the written examination in terms of the
            <lb />
            second advertisement. It is his submission that the said assertion of the
            <lb />
            petitioners has not been denied by the State respondents in their affidavit-in-
            <lb />
            opposition. It is his contention that when the petitioners had emerged successful
            <lb />
            pursuant to the first advertisement they ought not to have been compelled to
            <lb />
            undergo a selection process which is based on an almost similar syllabus.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            23.2. According to Mr. Mishra, learned senior counsel, the post of Junior Engineer
            <lb />
            [Civil] under the Public Works Department would not come under the purview of
            <lb />
            the APSC. It is his submission that the proviso to Clause [3] of Article 320 of the
            <lb />
            Constitution of India has provided enabling power to the Governor to make
            <lb />
            regulations specifying the matters in which it shall not be necessary for the State
            <lb />
            Public Service Commission to be consulted. It is in exercise of such enabling
            <lb />
            power, the APSC Regulations, 1951 have been made. The APSC Regulations,
            <lb />
            1951 have provided for three situations in respect of which there is no
            <lb />
            requirement to consult the APSC and they are, firstly, when the appointment to
            <lb />
            the service is made by an authority other than the Governor; secondly, when
            <lb />
            appointment is made to a post with a maximum pay scale of Rs. 1,166/-per
            <lb />
            month; and thirdly, when appointment is made to a post shown in the Schedule
            <lb />
            of the APSC Regulations, 1951, even if such post carries a pay scale exceeding
            <lb />
            Rs. 1,166/-per month. It is his submission that for appointment to the post of
            <lb />
            Junior Engineer [Civil] in the Public Works Department the Commission has no
            <lb />
            role to play as the post comes within the purview of the afore-mentioned first two
            <lb />
            situations.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            23.3. He has submitted that there is no service rules governing the selection and
            <lb />
            appointment to the post of Junior Engineer [Civil] in the Public Works
            <lb />
            Department. In absence of such service rules, the Public Works Department has
            <lb />
            followed the Assam Subordinate Engineering [Irrigation Department] Service
            <lb />
            Rules, 1978 [&apos;the Irrigation Department Service Rules, 1978&apos;, for short] for
            <lb />
            recruitment to the post of Junior Engineer [Civil] in the Public Works Department.
            <lb />
            Referring to a reply dated 03.02.2020 furnished under the Right to Information
            <lb />
            [RTI] Act, 2005, he has submitted that the respondent Public Works Department
            <lb />
            has admitted about the said position. In the affidavit-in-opposition also, the
            <lb />
            respondent no. 2 has admitted that the Public Works Department is following the
            <lb />
            Irrigation Department Service Rules, 1978 in the selection process initiated for
            <lb />
            filling up the vacancies in the post of Junior Engineer [Civil] in the Public Works
            <lb />
            Department. As the case of the respondents is that they are following Irrigation
            <lb />
            Department Service Rules, 1978, they cannot now be permitted to resile from the
            <lb />
            above stand. He has referred to the decision of the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court of
            <lb />
            India in Dr. Amarjit Singh Ahluwalia vs. the State of Pubjab and others, reported
            <lb />
            in [1975] 3 SCC 503, paragraph no. 9, to stress that as the State respondents had
            <lb />
            professed to have followed the Irrigation Department Service Rules, 1978 for the
            <lb />
            purpose of recruitment to the post of Junior Engineer [Civil] in the Public Works
            <lb />
            Department, it has to be held that they shall scrupulously observe the same rules
            <lb />
            at all times on pain of invalidation of an act in violation of those rules. Mr. Mishra
            <lb />
            has, thereby, canvassed that the process undertaken pursuant to Advertisement
            <lb />
            no. 06/2019 dated 19.11.2019 being contrary to law, is to be interdicted with by
            <lb />
            setting it aside.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            23.4. It is his submission that from a conjoint reading of Rule 2[a], Rule 3[1][ii] and
            <lb />
            Rule 3[5] of the Irrigation Department Service Rules, 1978, it is evident that the
            <lb />
            Appointing Authority for the post of Subordinate Engineer Grade-I is the Chief
            <lb />
            Engineer, Irrigation Department and the post of Subordinate Engineer Grade-I is
            <lb />
            a Class-III, non-Gazetted post. The post of Subordinate Engineer Grade-I was re-
            <lb />
            designated as Junior Engineer by a notification dated 27.06.1983 of the Finance
            <lb />
            [Pay Commission] Department on the basis of the report of the Assam Pay
            <lb />
            Commission, 1979 and the same was published in the Official Gazette on
            <lb />
            22.07.1983. From Rule 6 of the Irrigation Department Service Rules, 1978, it is
            <lb />
            clear that direct recruitment to the post of Junior Engineer i.e. erstwhile
            <lb />
            Subordinate Engineer Grade-I is to be made by the Chief Engineer of the
            <lb />
            Department on the basis of selection made by a Selection Board, constituted
            <lb />
            under Rule 13 of the Irrigation Department Service Rules, 1978, as per the
            <lb />
            procedure laid down in Rule 6.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            23.5. Mr. Mishra has, thus, submitted that viewed from the above context, the post of
            <lb />
            Junior Engineer [Civil] in the Public Works Department is also a non-Gazetted post
            <lb />
            in respect of which the Appointing Authority is the Chief Engineer, Public Works
            <lb />
            Department. That the post of Junior Engineer [Civil] in the Public Works
            <lb />
            Department is a non-Gazetted post is also reflected from the pay-slip of the
            <lb />
            petitioners. As such, the procedure laid down in the Irrigation Department Service
            <lb />
            Rules, 1978 are mandatorily required to be followed and the same was followed
            <lb />
            in the selection process undertaken pursuant to the Advertisement dated
            <lb />
            14.08.2018. Moreover, the posts of Junior Engineer [Civil] in which the petitioners
            <lb />
            are presently working, are permanent posts and not temporary posts. Since one
            <lb />
            of the essential conditions for making recruitment under Regulation 3[f] of the
            <lb />
            APSC Regulations, 1951 is that the post[s] is/are to be temporary post[s] the
            <lb />
            posts of Junior Engineer [Civil] in the Public Works Department where the
            <lb />
            petitioners are presently working, do not fall under the purview of the
            <lb />
            Commission and they could not have been appointed under Regulation 3[f] of the
            <lb />
            Regulations, 1951.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            23.6. He has placed reliance in the observation made in paragraph no. 16 of the
            <lb />
            decision of the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court of India in M.T. Khan and others vs. Govt.
            <lb />
            of A.P. and others, reported in [2004] 2 SCC 267, where it has reiterated the well-
            <lb />
            settled principle of law that non-mentioning or wrong mentioning of a provision of
            <lb />
            law does not invalidate an order in the event it is found that a power therefor
            <lb />
            exists. He has also placed reliance in the decision in State of Sikkim vs. Dorjee
            <lb />
            Tshering Bhutia and others, reported in [1991] 4 SCC 243, wherein, in paragraph
            <lb />
            no. 16, it has been observed that when the source of power can be validly traced
            <lb />
            then the State action in the exercise of such power cannot be struck down on the
            <lb />
            ground that it was labelled under a different provision.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            23.7. With such contentions, the learned Senior Counsel for the petitioners has
            <lb />
            submitted that the procedure adopted for selection and appointment of Junior
            <lb />
            Engineer [Civil] in the Public Works Department by the impugned advertisement
            <lb />
            is contrary to law and as such, the impugned advertisement as well as the
            <lb />
            process of selection in the case in hand is liable to be set aside. He has
            <lb />
            strenuously argued that for all intents and purposes, the Advertisement dated
            <lb />
            14.08.2018 is to be treated as an advertisement for direct recruitment under Rule
            <lb />
            6 of the Irrigation Department Service Rules, 1978 and the appointments of the
            <lb />
            petitioners in the posts in which they are presently working, have to be treated as
            <lb />
            regular appointments. Merely because the Advertisement dated 14.08.2018
            <lb />
            mentioned about the recruitment to be under Regulation 3[f] of the APSC
            <lb />
            Regulations, 1951 it could not be labelled as such. In such situation, the
            <lb />
            petitioners ought to be treated as regular appointees as the entire process of
            <lb />
            recruitment for the post falls outside the purview of the Commission.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            23.8. The learned Senior Counsel has also referred to the decision in Roshan Lal
            <lb />
            Tandon vs. Union of India [UOI], reported in AIR 1967 SC 1889, to highlight the
            <lb />
            point that once a person is appointed to a post or an office in the Government he
            <lb />
            acquires a status. He has further submitted that in the present scenario, the
            <lb />
            possibility of securing a Government job is a tough task as there is a huge force
            <lb />
            of educated unemployed persons. In such difficult situation, the petitioners took
            <lb />
            part in the earlier selection process and secured employment in the Government
            <lb />
            after emerging successful therein. The Court cannot be oblivious of existence of
            <lb />
            gross inequality in bargaining powers between the employer and the employees.
            <lb />
            The manner in which the services of the petitioners have been sought to be
            <lb />
            dispensed with is, he has contended, unconscionable in the context of the
            <lb />
            decision of the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court of India in Central Inland Water Transport
            <lb />
            Corporation Limited and another vs. Brojo Nath Ganguly and another, reported in
            <lb />
            [1986] 3 SCC 156.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            Writ Petition, W.P.[C] no. 617/2020 and Writ Petition, W.P.[C] no. 744/2020 :-
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            24.
            <lb />
            Mr. D. Saikia, learned Advocate General, Assam has submitted that in the
            <lb />
            Advertisements published on 14.08.2018, it was made clear that the process of
            <lb />
            selection was undertaken under Regulation 3[f] of the APSC Regulations, 1951
            <lb />
            and the appointments would be purely on ad-hoc basis for a period of 4 [four]
            <lb />
            months initially. It was further made clear that to become eligible for regular
            <lb />
            appointment, a candidate must qualify in the regular recruitment process as and
            <lb />
            when held. The petitioners in both the writ petitions are highly qualified persons
            <lb />
            and they cannot contend that they responded to the said advertisements for
            <lb />
            filling up the posts of Assistant Engineer [Civil] and Junior Engineer [Civil] under
            <lb />
            Regulation 3[f] of the APSC Regulations, 1951 without knowing about the
            <lb />
            resultant consequences when a regular selection process would be undertaken to
            <lb />
            fill up the posts.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            24.1. It is his submission that the petitioners herein had hardly about 5 [five] months or
            <lb />
            3 [three] months of experience when the Advertisement no. 06/2019 was
            <lb />
            published on 19.11.2019. He has submitted that it is well settled that an
            <lb />
            appointee under Regulation 3[f] cannot claim regularization as such appointment
            <lb />
            is purely ad-hoc pending regular selection. Adverting to the submissions made by
            <lb />
            the learned senior counsel for the petitioners in the writ petition, W.P.[C] no.
            <lb />
            617/2020, Mr. Saikia has submitted that the prayer for regularisation of services
            <lb />
            of the petitioners therein has rightly been dropped in view of the authoritative
            <lb />
            pronouncements on the point by several Division Bench decisions of this Court in
            <lb />
            [i] Hemanta Kumar Pegu and others vs. State of Assam and others, reported
            <lb />
            in1988 [1] GLJ 383; [ii] Pranjit Kumar Das vs. State of Assam and others,
            <lb />
            reported in1995 [2] GLT 28; [iii] Debabrat Bargohain and others vs. Dilip Hazarika
            <lb />
            and others, reported in 1996 [3] GLT 310; [iv] Santanu Baruah and others vs.
            <lb />
            State of Assam and others, reported in 1996 [3] GLT 323; and [v] Nabin Chandra
            <lb />
            Bordoloi vs. State of Assam and others, reported in 2003 [2] GLT 147. His further
            <lb />
            submission is that the principles emerging from these decisions would go to show
            <lb />
            that the petitioners&apos; other pleas also do not have any merit and the ratios laid
            <lb />
            down therein are also applicable in respect of the petitioners in the writ petition,
            <lb />
            W.P.[C] no. 744/2020.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            24.2. When the Advertisements dated 14.08.2018 were published for appointment
            <lb />
            under Regulation 3[f] a large number of candidates holding the requisite
            <lb />
            educational qualifications for the posts of Assistant Engineer [Civil] and Junior
            <lb />
            Engineer [Civil] did not apply knowing fully well that the appointments made
            <lb />
            under the said advertisements would be only under Regulation 3[f] and the
            <lb />
            appointees had to make way ultimately to the regularly selected candidates at a
            <lb />
            later point of time.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            Writ Petition, W.P.[C] no. 617/2020 :-
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            25.
            <lb />
            Responding to the submissions of the petitioners in the writ petition, W.P.[C] no.
            <lb />
            617/2020 with regard to the contention regarding grant of preference in the form
            <lb />
            of weightage with reference to Rule 28 of the PWD Service Rules, the learned
            <lb />
            Advocate General has submitted the said relaxation clause can be invoked only
            <lb />
            when the Appointing Authority reaches a satisfaction in the facts and
            <lb />
            circumstances obtaining in a particular case that the operation of any of the rules
            <lb />
            has caused or will cause undue hardship in that particular case. It is only then the
            <lb />
            requirement of that rule can be dispensed with or relaxed. In the case in hand,
            <lb />
            the Appointing Authority has not reached any such satisfaction regarding
            <lb />
            hardship, not to speak of undue hardship. It is his submission that absence of
            <lb />
            hardship can be gauged from the large number of candidates participating in the
            <lb />
            selection process for both the posts initiated vide the Advertisement dated
            <lb />
            19.11.2019. Any grant of preference in the form of weightage in the selection
            <lb />
            process under reference to the appointees appointed under Regulation 3[f] like
            <lb />
            the petitioners, would be in conflict with Article 14 and Article 16 of the
            <lb />
            Constitution of India.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            25.1. It has been submitted that the selection process which is being undertaken
            <lb />
            pursuant to the Advertisement dated 19.11.2019, is neither in violation of any
            <lb />
            extant service rules nor in violation of any norms inconsistent with Article 14 and
            <lb />
            Article 16 of the Constitution of India. The petitioners have failed to show any
            <lb />
            legal right to insist for any kind of preference [weightage] in the ensuing selection
            <lb />
            process.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            25.2. It is his further submission that the comparison that has been sought to be made
            <lb />
            by the petitioners with the other advertisements where the preference clause
            <lb />
            existed, is completely misplaced. In the other advertisements, the Government in
            <lb />
            the concerned Department had decided to give preference Regulation 3[f]
            <lb />
            appointees considering either the long years of experience gained by the
            <lb />
            Regulation 3[f] appointees or due to dearth of qualified candidates in the
            <lb />
            concerned discipline/field. The State Government had especially experienced
            <lb />
            dearth of candidates intending to serve in the State Health Services and
            <lb />
            accordingly, it was consciously decided, on those occasions, to give preference to
            <lb />
            the doctors working under Regulation 3[f] of the APSC Regulations, 1951. The
            <lb />
            case of the petitioners in view of large pool of candidates available in the
            <lb />
            field/branch of Civil Engineering for the posts of Assistant Engineer [Civil] and
            <lb />
            Junior Engineer [Civil], is not comparable.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            25.3. It is contended by him that the petitioners cannot claim that the State
            <lb />
            Government should extend the benefit of preference [weightage] to them when
            <lb />
            no satisfaction about hardship has been reached by the State Government. One
            <lb />
            of the relevant factors to consider with regard to hardship to dispense with or
            <lb />
            relax the requirement of any rule is the duration of service one renders in the
            <lb />
            department. The services rendered by the petitioners herein fall short on that
            <lb />
            count. He has, thus, submitted that in the fact situation obtaining in the case, it is
            <lb />
            not even possible to give consideration about relaxation and/or weightage, not to
            <lb />
            speak of grant of preference and/or weightage.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            25.4. He has further placed reliance in the decisions in State of Orissa and others vs.
            <lb />
            Prasanta Kumar Sahoo, reported in [2007] 15 SCC 129; Bedanga Talukdar vs.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            Saifudaullah Khan and others, reported in [2011] 12 SCC 85; and Dr. M.
            <lb />
            Laitphlang and others vs. State of Meghalaya and others, reported in [2004] 2
            <lb />
            GLR 546.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            Writ Petition, W.P.[C] no. 744/2020 :-
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            26.
            <lb />
            The learned Advocate General responding to the submissions advanced on behalf
            <lb />
            of the petitioners in the writ petition, W.P.[C] no. 744/2020, has submitted some
            <lb />
            of the contentions advanced are without necessary pleadings.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            26.1.
            <lb />
            He has submitted that the contention advanced on behalf of the petitioners to the
            <lb />
            effect that there has been admission on the part of the State respondents that
            <lb />
            the Public Works Department [PWD] has been following the Irrigation Department
            <lb />
            Service Rules, 1978 for recruitment to the post of Junior Engineer [Civil] in the
            <lb />
            Public Works Department [PWD] is a misstatement. A look at the question no. 7
            <lb />
            and the answer given thereof in the reply dated 03.02.2020 furnished under the
            <lb />
            RTI Act, 2005 and the statement in the affidavit-in-opposition would completely
            <lb />
            displace the notion.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            26.2.
            <lb />
            Mr. Saikia has submitted that the post of Junior Engineer [Civil] in the Public
            <lb />
            Works Department [PWD] is admittedly not a post within the Schedule of the
            <lb />
            APSC Regulations, 1951 and the same cannot be a ground of challenge for the
            <lb />
            petitioners in W.P.[C] no. 744/2020. The petitioners&apos; case does not attract the
            <lb />
            provision of Regulation 3[a] of the APSC Regulations, 1951 on the count of
            <lb />
            maximum pay scale also. Regulation 3[a] of the APSC Regulations, 1951 has
            <lb />
            mentioned about a post on a pay scale the maximum of which is less than Rs.
            <lb />
            1,166/-per month in respect of which it is not necessary for the Commission to
            <lb />
            be consulted. The said part of the APSC Regulations, 1951 was amended in the
            <lb />
            year 1987 but even in the year 1983 the maximum of the pay scale of the post of
            <lb />
            Junior Engineer in the Public Works Department [PWD] was not less than Rs.
            <lb />
            1,166/-. He has contended that vide a notification dated 26.07.2000, Gazetted
            <lb />
            status was conferred on the post of Junior Engineer in the Public Works
            <lb />
            Department [PWD] and the Appointing Authority for the post of Junior Engineer in
            <lb />
            the Public Works Department [PWD] is the Governor. On that basis, it has been
            <lb />
            contended that there is no applicability of the third ground of exemption
            <lb />
            contained in Regulation 3[a] of the APSC Regulations, 1951. Consequently, all the
            <lb />
            contentions of the petitioners sought to be built on the premises of Regulation
            <lb />
            3[a] have fallen flat.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            26.3. The petitioners had participated in the process of recruitment undertaken under
            <lb />
            Regulation 3[f] of the APSC Regulations, 1951 knowing fully well from the
            <lb />
            advertisement itself that their engagements would be temporary and the
            <lb />
            appointees under Regulation 3[f] must have to qualify through regular
            <lb />
            recruitment process as and when held and such appointment shall not be a
            <lb />
            ground for claiming regular appointment whatsoever in future. Now, the
            <lb />
            petitioners cannot make a volte face to claim that their appointments were
            <lb />
            regular appointments. The learned Advocate General has, thus, contended that
            <lb />
            the decisions relied upon on behalf of the petitioners in W.P.[C] no. 744/2020 are
            <lb />
            not applicable to the facts and circumstances in the case in hand.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            26.4. It has been submitted that it is correct that the petitioners in W.P.[C] no.
            <lb />
            744/2020 came to be appointed in the post of Junior Engineers [Civil] pursuant to
            <lb />
            a process of selection conducted by a selection body pursuant to the
            <lb />
            advertisement dated 14.08.2018 and by a notification issued by the Appointing
            <lb />
            Authority on 04.06.2019. But it was made specific in the advertisement dated
            <lb />
            14.08.2018 that their appointments would be purely on ad-hoc basis for a period
            <lb />
            of 4 [four] months and to be eligible for regular appointment under the Public
            <lb />
            Works Department [PWD], they had to qualify themselves through regular
            <lb />
            recruitment process. It was also made clear that their appointments under
            <lb />
            Regulation 3[f] of the APSC Regulations, 1951 shall not be a ground for claiming
            <lb />
            regular appointments whatsoever in future. The notification dated 04.06.2019
            <lb />
            was also specific to the extent that they were appointed provisionally under
            <lb />
            Regulation 3[f] of the APSC Regulations, 1951. Thus, it is not open for the
            <lb />
            petitioners to claim continuation in the post as regular recruitees even if they had
            <lb />
            undergone some kind of selection process prior to their appointments under
            <lb />
            Regulation 3[f].
            <lb />
        </p>
        <p>
            Writ Petition, W.P.[C] no. 617/2020 :-
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            27.
            <lb />
            Mr. T.J. Mahanta, learned Senior Counsel appearing for the respondent APSC
            <lb />
            authorities has submitted that the Commission had published the advertisement
            <lb />
            as per the draft advertisement forwarded by the Government in the Public Works
            <lb />
            Department. It is submitted by him that when the extant service rules, that is, the
            <lb />
            PWD Service Rules, have not provided for any preference [weightage], the
            <lb />
            petitioners merely because they are working after being appointed under
            <lb />
            Regulation 3[f] of the APSC Regulations, 1951, do not have any legal right for any
            <lb />
            preference [weightage]. The petitioners have not been able to make out any case
            <lb />
            for preference in the form of weightage on the ground of hardship. He has further
            <lb />
            submitted that the preference [weightage] can be given only when there is
            <lb />
            specific mention in the concerned advertisement.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            27.1. He has submitted that as to when the relaxation clause can be invoked has been
            <lb />
            settled by a catena of decisions of the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court of India. The
            <lb />
            power of relaxation, as incorporated in Rule 28 of the PWD Service Rules, would
            <lb />
            be applicable to mitigate undue hardship and to meet a particular situation.
            <lb />
            Resort to the said relaxation clause is not to be taken in a normal situation but in
            <lb />
            an extreme situation when eligible and qualified candidates in sufficient numbers
            <lb />
            are not available or interested for selection and appointment, which is albeit not
            <lb />
            the case in hand. To support his such submissions, he has placed reliance in the
            <lb />
            decision of Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court of India in Rajendra Kumar Agrawal vs. State
            <lb />
            of Uttar Pradesh and others, reported in 1 SCC 642, wherein the decision
            <lb />
            in J.C. Yadav vs. State of Haryana, reported in [1992] 2 SCC 189, was referred to
            <lb />
            as the said decision had dealt on the issue of relaxation of rule. He has also
            <lb />
            referred to the decision in State of U.P. and another vs. Om Prakash and others,
            <lb />
            reported in [2006] 6 SCC 474, where the decision in Secy., A.P. Public Service
            <lb />
            Commission vs. Y.V.V.R. Srinivashulu, reported in [2003] 5 SCC 341, was referred
            <lb />
            to as to how and when preference can be granted. To buttress his submissions,
            <lb />
            he has also relied upon the decision in State of Gujarat and others vs.
            <lb />
            Arvindkumar T. Tiwari and another, reported in [2012] 9 SCC 545.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            27.2. In reply to the submissions made by Mr. Das, learned Senior Counsel for the
            <lb />
            petitioners in W.P.[C] no. 617/2020 on the basis of the additional affidavit, Mr.
            <lb />
            Mahanta has referred to the averments made in the Commission&apos;s affidavit-in-
            <lb />
            reply filed in response to the said additional affidavit. Denying the contentions of
            <lb />
            the petitioners, he has submitted that there was no violation of the terms of the
            <lb />
            Advertisement no. 06/2019 dated 19.11.2019 in allowing some candidates who
            <lb />
            were not qualified for the post of Assistant Engineer [Civil] till the last date of
            <lb />
            submission of application i.e. 16.06.2020, in the written examination for the post
            <lb />
            of Assistant Engineer [Civil] held on 15.11.2020. It is submitted by him that
            <lb />
            considering the urgency for recruitment and to save time, a resolution was taken
            <lb />
            by the Commission on 27.08.2020 to conduct the screening of applications after
            <lb />
            the written examination was over and before calling the required number of
            <lb />
            candidates for interview as per the prescribed ratio. All the candidates who have
            <lb />
            applied for the post of Assistant Engineer [Civil], have been allowed to appear in
            <lb />
            the written examination.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            27.3. It has been pleaded by the APSC that scrutiny of all the applications for the
            <lb />
            recruitment process has been completed and lists of selected candidates and
            <lb />
            rejected candidates have been made ready for publication before declaration of
            <lb />
            the OMR based test results. The rejection list has not been published by the
            <lb />
            Commission due to operation of the interim order in the present two writ
            <lb />
            petitions. It has been clarified that the shortlisting of candidates for viva-
            <lb />
            voce/interview at the ratio of 1:3 would be made only from the eligible candidates
            <lb />
            as per the advertisement. With regard to the allegation of issuance of more than
            <lb />
            one admit cards for the same candidate, it has been averred that not more than
            <lb />
            one admit card was issued against one single application. In case any candidate
            <lb />
            had submitted two application forms, admit cards might have been issued against
            <lb />
            it accordingly because admit cards were issued based on the applications only.
            <lb />
            There was no instance to the effect that two candidates had appeared in the
            <lb />
            written examination held on 15.11.2020 against two admit cards issued against
            <lb />
            one particular candidate. He has, thus, submitted that the apprehensions raised
            <lb />
            through the additional affidavit is completely misplaced. Furthermore, there is no
            <lb />
            prejudice caused to the petitioners in any manner whatsoever at this stage.
            <lb />

        </p>
        <p>
            Writ Petition, W.P.[C] no. 744/2020 :-
            <lb />
        </p>
        <p>
            28.
            <lb />
            Mr. Mahanta, learned Senior Standing Counsel appearing for the APSC in the writ
            <lb />
            petition, W.P.[C] no. 744/2020, has submitted that there is no service rules
            <lb />
            framed either under Article 309 or under the proviso to Article 309 of the
            <lb />
            Constitution of India to govern the matter of recruitment to the post of Junior
            <lb />
            Engineer [Civil]. In such a case, it is the executive instructions received from the
            <lb />
            Government which would govern the field. The Commission has published the
            <lb />
            Advertisement no. 06/2019 dated 19.11.2019 as per the draft Advertisement
            <lb />
            received from the Government in the Public Works Department vide
            <lb />
            communication bearing no. RBEB.159/2018/66 dated 19.08.2019. It did not
            <lb />
            contain any instruction to follow the provisions of the Irrigation Department
            <lb />
            Service Rules, 1978.
            <lb />

        </p>
        <p>
            Writ Petition, W.P.[C] no. 617/2020 :-
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            29.
            <lb />
            Mr. A.K. Sarma, learned counsel appearing for the private respondent nos. 8 -50
            <lb />
            has adopted the submissions made by the learned Advocate General and learned
            <lb />
            Senior Standing Counsel, APSC. The private respondents have impleaded
            <lb />
            themselves as party-respondents in the writ petition, W.P.[C] no. 617/2020. It is
            <lb />
            the case of these respondents that they had applied pursuant to the
            <lb />
            advertisement published and on the basis of their eligibility, they were allowed to
            <lb />
            appear in the written examination. As they all had performed well, they are
            <lb />
            legitimately expecting that they would clear the written examination and would be
            <lb />
            called for the viva voce/interview. Their further case is that all of them were
            <lb />
            eligible at the time of submission of the applications. Merely because the
            <lb />
            petitioners are working in the Department on ad-hoc basis after their selection
            <lb />
            under Regulation 3[f] of the APSC Regulations, 1951 no right has accrued to the
            <lb />
            petitioners either to claim regularization or to claim preference [weightage] for
            <lb />
            such period of service. Only because the private respondents did not apply in
            <lb />
            response to the earlier Advertisement dated 14.08.2018 for the fact that the
            <lb />
            advertisement was only for ad-hoc service the same cannot be a ground to put
            <lb />
            the petitioners on a higher pedestal over and above them as it would amount to
            <lb />
            unjust discrimination and as such, none of the prayers made in the writ petition is
            <lb />
            tenable.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            30.
            <lb />
            I have duly considered the rival submissions advanced by the learned counsel for
            <lb />
            the parties and also have gone through the materials brought on record by the
            <lb />
            parties through their respective pleadings. I have also gone through the decisions
            <lb />
            cited by the learned counsel for the parties in support of their respective
            <lb />
            submissions with the caveat that a decision is an authority for what it decides and
            <lb />
            not what can logically be deduced therefrom and even a slight distinction in fact
            <lb />
            or an additional or different fact may make a lot of difference in the decision
            <lb />
            making process.
            <lb />

        </p>
        <p>
            Writ Petition, W.P.[C] no. 617/2020 and Writ Petition, W.P.[C] no. 744/2020 :-
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            31.
            <lb />
            Article 14 enshrines the principle that the State shall not deny any person equality
            <lb />
            before the law or the equal protection of the laws within the territory of India.
            <lb />
            Article 16 of the Constitution of India states that there shall be equality of
            <lb />
            opportunity for all citizens in matters relating to employment or appointment to
            <lb />
            any office under the State. The purport and object of this fundamental right is to
            <lb />
            extend the right to equality of opportunity in getting employment in public offices.
            <lb />
            Article 14 is the genus and Article 16 is one of the species of the same principle of
            <lb />
            equality contained in broad terms in Article 14. The word, employment or
            <lb />
            appointment includes initial appointment. The initial appointment to any post
            <lb />
            under the State like the posts in the cases in hand, can only be made after widest
            <lb />
            possible publication of an advertisement, thereby, inviting applications from
            <lb />
            eligible and interested candidates. It envisages a process of selection conducted
            <lb />
            by a selection committee/board and wherever it is necessary, by the Public
            <lb />
            Service Commission consisting of a written examination and/or interview/viva-
            <lb />
            voce or some other rational criteria with the aim to judge the inter se merits of
            <lb />
            the participating candidates in a fair, transparent and non-discriminatory manner.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            32.
            <lb />
            The background facts leading to the institution of these two writ petitions have
            <lb />
            already been delineated above. It can be noticed easily that both the sets of
            <lb />
            petitioners are highly qualified having degrees and diplomas in the Civil
            <lb />
            Engineering branch. It is, therefore, not open for both the sets of petitioners to
            <lb />
            say that they applied to the advertisements dated 14.08.2018 without knowing
            <lb />
            that the applications were invited for filing up the posts under Regulation 3[f] of
            <lb />
            the APSC Regulations, 1951.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            33.
            <lb />
            The written examinations for the vacancies in the post of Assistant Engineer
            <lb />
            [Civil] and Junior Engineer [Civil] pursuant to the Advertisement dated
            <lb />
            19.11.2019 were already over where all the petitioners along with the other
            <lb />
            candidates appeared. By the dates of filing of the writ petitions on 30.01.2020
            <lb />
            and 01.02.2020 respectively, the concerned advertisement had already been
            <lb />
            published on 19.11.2019. At the times of filing of the writ petitions, the written
            <lb />
            examinations were not held but during the pendency of the writ petitions, the
            <lb />
            written examinations were held on 15.11.2020.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            34.
            <lb />
            Both the sets of petitioners herein have got appointments in the Public Works
            <lb />
            Department after being appointed under Regulation 3[f] of the APSC Regulations,
            <lb />
            1951. It would, thus, be appropriate to refer to the provisions of Regulation 3[f]
            <lb />
            of the APSC Regulations, 1951. Contentions are also advanced on behalf of the
            <lb />
            set of the petitioners in the writ petition, W.P.[C] no. 744/2020 regarding non-
            <lb />
            requirement of consultation with the Commission for recruitment to the post of
            <lb />
            Junior Engineer [Civil] in the Public Works Department and such reference is also
            <lb />
            necessary in that context.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            35.
            <lb />
            Having regard to such contentions made in the two writ petitions, the relevant
            <lb />
            parts of Regulation 3 of the APSC Regulations, 1951 are extracted hereinbelow :-
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;3. It shall not be necessary for the Commission to be consulted in matters
            <lb />
            relating to methods of recruitment to civil services and post or the
            <lb />
            suitability of the candidates for such appointments, in the following cases,
            <lb />
            namely -
        </item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            [a] When an appointment is to be made by an authority other than the
            <lb />
            Governor or by the Governor to a post on a pay scale the maximum
            <lb />
            of which is less than &quot;Rupees Eleven hundred and Sixty six&quot; per
            <lb />
            month and in respect of post as shown in the Schedule although the
            <lb />
            maximum of the pay scale of these posts exceed &quot;Rupees Eleven
        </item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            [f] When an appointment is to be made by direct recruitment to a
            <lb />
            temporary post created in a service, if it is necessary in the public
            <lb />
            interest that the appointment should be made immediately and
            <lb />
            reference to the Commission would cause undue delay; provided
            <lb />
            that if the post has been sanctioned for, or is likely to last for more
            <lb />
            than four months, the Commission shall, as soon as possible, be
            <lb />
            consulted in all matters mentioned in sub-clause 3 of Article 320 of
            <lb />
            the Constitution;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            [g] *
            <lb />
            *
            <lb />
            *
            <lb />
            *
            <lb />
            *
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            [h] *
            <lb />
            *
            <lb />
            *
            <lb />
            *
            <lb />
            *
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            36.
            <lb />
            Regulation 3[f] of the APSC Regulations, 1951 has inter alia provided that when
            <lb />
            an appointment is to be made by direct recruitment to a temporary post created
            <lb />
            in civil service and post, if it is necessary in the public interest that the
            <lb />
            appointment should be made immediately and the reference to the Commission
            <lb />
            would cause undue delay, the Commission is not required to be consulted in
            <lb />
            matters relating to the methods of recruitment or with regard to the suitability of
            <lb />
            the candidates for such appointment. The proviso to it has provided that if the
            <lb />
            post has been sanctioned for or is likely to last for more than four months, the
            <lb />
            Commission shall, as soon as possible, be consulted inter alia in all matters
            <lb />
            mentioned in sub-clause [3] of Article 320 of the Constitution. Regulation 3[f] of
            <lb />
            the APSC Regulations, 1951 has indicated that an appointment, made under
            <lb />
            Regulation 3[f], shall be in a post which is temporary in nature. If the State
            <lb />
            Government is of the view that there is an immediate need to make an
            <lb />
            appointment in such temporary post and a reference to the Commission would
            <lb />
            cause undue delay, the State Government can make such appointment in the
            <lb />
            temporary post in a service or post by way of direct recruitment under Regulation
            <lb />
            3[f]. From the narrative of Regulation 3[f], it is clear that an appointment made
            <lb />
            under Regulation 3[f] is purely ad-hoc in nature until the regular selection is
            <lb />
            made by the Commission in accordance with the provisions laid down in the
            <lb />
            concerned service rules, if any, and in the absence of any service rules, in a
            <lb />
            manner consistent with Article 14 and Article 16 of the Constitution of India. The
            <lb />
            proviso has further made it clear that if the post has been sanctioned or likely to
            <lb />
            last for more than four months, the only option available is to fill up the post in a
            <lb />
            regular selection process held in consultation with the Commission. As a natural
            <lb />
            corollary, once regular selection is made, the appointee who is working in the
            <lb />
            post by virtue his appointment under Regulation 3[f], has to make way for the
            <lb />
            candidate selected through the regular selection process and the
            <lb />
            Government/Appointing Authority when any candidate selected through the
            <lb />
            regular selection process is available, has to give appointment to such regular
            <lb />
            selectee and it shall not be open for the Government/Appointing Authority to keep
            <lb />
            such regular selectee at bay while allowing the appointee under Regulation 3[f] to
            <lb />
            continue working in the post. If such an eventuality arises, the regularly selected
            <lb />
            candidate has to be appointed even by terminating the services of the appointee
            <lb />
            appointed under Regulation 3[f] of the APSC Regulations, 1951.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            37.
            <lb />
            Issues pertaining to Regulation 3[f] of the APSC Regulations, 1951 came up for
            <lb />
            consideration in a number of cases before this Court, as has been indicated
            <lb />
            above.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            37.1. In Pranjit Kumar Das [supra], an advertisement was published by the
            <lb />
            Commissioner and Secretary to the Government of Assam, Handloom, Textile and
            <lb />
            Sericulture Department on 29.07.1989 calling for applications for ad-hoc
            <lb />
            appointments in the post of Senior Inspector of Handloom and Textile. The writ
            <lb />
            appellants-petitioners along with others were interviewed by a selection
            <lb />
            committee and a select list was prepared. Thereafter, the writ appellants-
            <lb />
            petitioners were appointed under the provisions of the Assam Public Service
            <lb />
            Commission [Ad-hoc] Appointment Rules, 1986 on different dates in 1990. After
            <lb />
            one year of their services, they were terminated w.e.f. 22.05.1991 and they were
            <lb />
            re-appointed in the same post on the next date i.e. 23.05.1991. The Government
            <lb />
            of Assam by a letter dated 30.05.1991 requested the APSC to take necessary
            <lb />
            steps for regularisation of the writ appellants-petitioners&apos; posts. The Assam Public
            <lb />
            Service Commission [Ad-hoc] Appointment Rules, 1986 was, thereafter, repealed
            <lb />
            by a notification dated 18.05.1992 and the earlier appointments of the writ
            <lb />
            appellants-petitioners were converted to appointments under Regulation 3[f] of
            <lb />
            the APSC Regulations, 1951, initially for a period of 4 [four] months and
            <lb />
            subsequently extended from time to time. Another advertisement was published
            <lb />
            by the Commission on 09.10.1991 calling for applications for filling up the
            <lb />
            vacancies in the post of Senior Inspector of Handloom and Textile which posts the
            <lb />
            writ appellants-petitioners were holding. The writ appellants-petitioners also
            <lb />
            applied in response to the advertisement dated 09.10.1991 but in the select list
            <lb />
            prepared on the basis of merits, the names of the writ appellants-petitioners did
            <lb />
            not figure as they failed to qualify in the interview conducted by the Commission
            <lb />
            for the post.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            37.2. In the backdrop of those events when the writ appellants-petitioners approached
            <lb />
            this Court, the Division Bench of this Court in Pranjit Kumar Das [supra] had held
            <lb />
            as under :-
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;11. This Regulation 3[f] of the Regulation of 1951 came up for
            <lb />
            consideration by the Division Bench of this Court in Hemanta Kumar
            <lb />
            Pegu and others vs. State of Assam, 1988 [1] GLJ 383. The Division Bench
            <lb />
            considered Regulation 3[f] and held in paragraph 27 of the judgment that
            <lb />
            this Regulation does not provide a source of power for appointment, but
            <lb />
            only provides the mode of appointment and that regularise does not
            <lb />
            connote permanence. The contention that the persons who were appointed
            <lb />
            under Regulation 3[f] can be regularised if they are otherwise qualified was
            <lb />
            not accepted by the Court and it was held that regularisation means
            <lb />
            making regular appointment by selection irrespective of the question
            <lb />
            whether the petitioners were already appointed under Regulation 3[f] or
            <lb />
            not. The ratio laid down in the above decision in our opinion is the correct
            <lb />
            proposition of law and there is no reason to take a different view.
            <lb />
            Therefore, in view of the above ratio, we are constraint to hold that merely
            <lb />
            because of the appointments of the appellants were converted to
            <lb />
            appointment under Regulation 3[f] of the Regulation of 1951, they cannot
            <lb />
            claim regularisation due to length of their service.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            37.3. The observations made by two decisions of Division Benches of this Court in
            <lb />
            Debabrat Bargohain and others [supra] and Santanu Baruah and others [supra]
            <lb />
            can be referred to as both decisions were rendered in connection with Regulation
            <lb />
            3[f] of the APSC Regulations, 1951 qua appointments made in the Public Works
            <lb />
            Department, Government of Assam.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            37.4. The decision in Santanu Baruah and others [supra] was in reference to the Assam
            <lb />
            Engineering [Public Works Department] Service Rules, 1978 [&apos;the PWD Service
            <lb />
            Rules&apos;]. While explaining the rights of the candidates selected through process of
            <lb />
            selection undertaken by the APSC vis-à-vis the rights of the appointees under
            <lb />
            Regulation 3[f] of the APSC Regulations, 1951, the Division Bench had observed
            <lb />
            as under :-
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;19. In our opinion, this observation has been made by the learned Single
            <lb />
            Judge in the context of the rights of the selected candidates vis-à-vis the
            <lb />
            rights of the appointees under Regulation 3[f]. A reading of sub-Regulation
            <lb />
            [f] would show that the appointment made under it is purely temporary
            <lb />
            pending selection by the APSC and the appointment letters issued in
            <lb />
            favour of the appointees under Regulation 3[f] contains a clause that
            <lb />
            regularisation of service of the appointee will depend upon his selection by
            <lb />
            the APSC within the required position in the list of the candidates
            <lb />
            recommended by the APSC for regularisation. Since the parties in these
            <lb />
            batch of cases who were appointed under Regulation 3[f] did get the
            <lb />
            opportunity of applying to the APSC for the selection, and their names do
            <lb />
            not find place within the required position of the list of candidates
            <lb />
            recommended by the APSC for appointment to the 39 vacancies in the post
            <lb />
            of Assistant Engineer [Civil] under the PWD as on 30.12.1994, they should
            <lb />
            make room for appointment of the candidates selected by the APSC and
            <lb />
            the authorities would be entitled to terminate their services. To retain such
            <lb />
            appointees under Regulation 3[f] in the 39 vacancies as on 30.12.1994 for
            <lb />
            which candidates have been selected and recommended by the APSC
            <lb />
            would, in our opinion, violate the rights of the selected candidates under
            <lb />
            Articles 14 and 16 of the Constitution.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            37.5. In Debabrat Bargohain and others [supra], the subject-matter was recruitment to
            <lb />
            a number of vacancies in the posts of Junior Engineer [Civil] and Junior Engineer
            <lb />
            [Mechanical] in the Public Works Department for which the APSC after publishing
            <lb />
            an advertisement for the same on 21.10.1993, proceeded to conduct written
            <lb />
            examination and interview. After completion of written examination and
            <lb />
            interview, the APSC prepared a select list and a waiting list of candidates and
            <lb />
            submitted the same to the Government on 18.09.1995. Since the selection
            <lb />
            process was taking some time, those vacant posts, in the intervening period,
            <lb />
            were filled up temporarily by the petitioners under Regulation 3[f] of the APSC
            <lb />
            Regulations, 1951. While examining the same issue, the Division Bench had
            <lb />
            observed as follows :-
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;16. The law, thus, having been enunciated by the Apex Court, let us
            <lb />
            examine the cases of those petitioners who have been appointed under
            <lb />
            Regulation 3[f] and as to whether any of their rights under the statutory
            <lb />
            provision, the appointment letter or the Constitution have been violated.
            <lb />
            The statutory provision in Regulation 3[f] makes it clear that the
            <lb />
            appointment under it is purely temporary pending reference to and
            <lb />
            selection by the APSC. The appointment letters issued to the 3[f]
            <lb />
            appointees clearly contain a clause that the appointment being under
            <lb />
            Regulation 3[f] continuance in service vis-à-vis regularisation in service
            <lb />
            thereof will depend upon in being selected by the APSC within the required
            <lb />
            position in the list of candidates recommended by the APSC for
            <lb />
            regularisation. It will be the responsibility of the appointee, to apply and to
            <lb />
            appear in the selection notified/advertised by the APSC for filling up the
            <lb />
            posts of Junior Engineer and that in case he does not appear or is not able
            <lb />
            to appear or in case he is not selected by the APSC within the required
            <lb />
            position of the select list, the appointment will stand automatically
            <lb />
            terminated. From the facts narrated earlier, it is clear that except the two
            <lb />
            petitioners in Civil Rule No. 2623/95, all other appointees under
            <lb />
            Regulation 3[f] have had the opportunity of appearing in the APSC
            <lb />
            selection for public employment and hence their rights either under
            <lb />
            Articles 14 and 16 of the Constitution or under Regulation 3[f] or their
            <lb />
            appointment letters have not been violated. All these appointees, except
            <lb />
            two, did apply and appear and thus did avail of a chance and at the behest
            <lb />
            of such appointees under Regulation 3[f] who have been found
            <lb />
            unsuccessful, this Court in exercise of its extraordinary jurisdiction under
            <lb />
            Article 226 of the Constitution will not grant them any relief of quashing
            <lb />
            the selection of candidates by the APSC in excess of the advertised posts or
            <lb />
            in continuing them in the posts to which they were temporarily appointed
            <lb />
            pending regular selection by the APSC.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            37.6. It follows from the observations made in the decision in Santanu Baruah and
            <lb />
            others [supra] that if a person who has been serving in the Public Works
            <lb />
            Department after being appointed in terms of Regulation 3[f] of the APSC
            <lb />
            Regulations, 1951, wants himself to become a member of Assam Engineering
            <lb />
            [Public Works Department] Services Rules, 1978 then he has to apply and appear
            <lb />
            in the selection process when applications for filing up the vacancy in the post in
            <lb />
            which he is working are invited for filing up the same by an advertisement
            <lb />
            published by the Commission through a regular selection process. In the event
            <lb />
            such a person working under Regulation 3[f] does not appear or does not get
            <lb />
            selected after participation in the process of selection undertaken by the
            <lb />
            Commission then such person shall have to make way for a candidate who is
            <lb />
            selected in the selection process undertaken by the Commission. Similar is the
            <lb />
            proposition laid down in Debabrat Bargohain and others [supra].
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            37.7. In Nabin Chandra Bordoloi [supra], a Division Bench of Court after referring
            <lb />
            to paragraph no. 11 [supra] of the decision in Pranjit Kumar Das [supra], has
            <lb />
            gone on to observe, in paragraph no. 7 thereof, as under :-
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;7. ……… The Division Bench of this Court has taken a categorical view that
            <lb />
            the appointments made under Regulation 3[f] of Regulation 1951 does not
            <lb />
            authorise the very person to claim regularisation on the basis of
            <lb />
            appointment made under Regulation 3[f]. Thus, in other words this Court
            <lb />
            has held that the service rendered by any incumbent under the
            <lb />
            appointment made in exercise of power under Regulation 3[f] of
            <lb />
            Regulation 1951 cannot be a ground for regularisation of the incumbent on
            <lb />
            that basis. For the same reason, the services rendered by the incumbent
            <lb />
            cannot be counted for the purpose of assigning the seniority.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            38.
            <lb />
            At this juncture, reverting back to the factual matrices of both the cases, it is seen
            <lb />
            that the Advertisements dated 14.08.2018 as well as the common brief
            <lb />
            Advertisement dated 14.08.2018 had specifically mentioned that the applications
            <lb />
            were invited under Regulation 3[f] of the APSC Regulations, 1951 and the
            <lb />
            appointments would be purely on ad-hoc basis for a period of 4 [four] months
            <lb />
            and to become eligible for regular appointment, a candidate must qualify himself
            <lb />
            in the regular recruitment process as and when held. For ready reference, the
            <lb />
            relevant excerpts from the common brief Advertisement dated 14.08.2018 are
            <lb />
            quoted hereunder :-
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            Government of Assam
            <lb />
            Public Works Department, Dispur, Guwahati -6
            <lb />
            No. CON/B&amp;NH/22/2018/10
            <lb />
            Dated : Dispur, the August 14, 2018
            <lb />
            ADVERTISEMENT
            <lb />
            Public Works Department, Govt. of Assam invites applications from Indian
            <lb />
            Citizens for the under-mentioned posts under Public Works Department,
            <lb />
            Government of Assam under Regulation 3[f] of the Assam Public Service
            <lb />
            Commission [Limitation of Functions] Regulations, 1951, in the Scale of Pay
            <lb />
            and Grade Pay as indicated below along with usual allowances as admissible
            <lb />
            under Rules of the Govt. of Assam. The appointment will be purely on ad-hoc
            <lb />
            basis for a period of 4 [four] months and to become eligible for regular
            <lb />
            appointment a candidate must qualify himself in the regular recruitment test
            <lb />
            as and when held.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <table>
            Name of the post
            <lb />
            No. of vacancy Scale of Pay
            <lb />
            Assistant Engineer
            <lb />
            156
            <lb />
            Rs. 30,000/-to 1,10,00/-PB 4
            <lb />
            with Grade Pay of Rs. 12,700/-
            <lb />
            Junior Engineer
            <lb />
            307
            <lb />
            Rs. 14000-49000 PB with
            <lb />
            Grade Pay of Rs. 8700/-
            <lb />
        </table>

        <p>
            39.
            <lb />
            In the notification dated 05.03.2019 whereby the petitioners in W.P.[C] no.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            617/2020 came to be appointed in the post of Assistant Engineer [Civil] and in
            <lb />
            the notification dated 04.06.2019 whereby the petitioners in W.P.[C] no.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            744/2020 came be appointed in the post of Junior Engineer [Civil], it was
            <lb />
            specifically mentioned that they were appointed under Regulation 3[f] of the
            <lb />
            APSC Regulations, 1951. It is also noticed that both these notifications were
            <lb />
            issued as Orders by the Governor of Assam.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            40.
            <lb />
            Having accepted the position that in the event they were selected and recruited
            <lb />
            in the advertised posts pursuant to the advertisement dated 14.08.2018, they
            <lb />
            would be appointed only under Regulation 3[f] of the Regulations, 1951 and they
            <lb />
            would not be treated as regular appointees, all the petitioners are precluded from
            <lb />
            making the prayer for regularization. The principle that one cannot approbate and
            <lb />
            reprobate is found applicatory in the cases of the petitioners. The principle that
            <lb />
            an ad-hoc appointee appointed under Regulation 3[f] of the APSC Regulations,
            <lb />
            1951 cannot claim regularisation and has to make way for the regularly selected
            <lb />
            candidate, as authoritatively laid down in the decisions mentioned above, applies
            <lb />
            proprio vigore in the cases of both the sets of the petitioners in W.P.[C] no.
            <lb />
            617/2020 and W.P.[C] no. 744/2020.
            <lb />

        </p>
        <p>
            Writ Petition, W.P.[C] no. 617/2020 :-
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            41.
            <lb />
            One of the issues that has arisen for consideration in the writ petition, W.P.[C]
            <lb />
            no. 617/2020 is whether in view of their selection and appointment in the post of
            <lb />
            Assistant Engineer [Civil] pursuant to the Advertisement dated 14.08.2018 any
            <lb />
            right gets accrued to the petitioners to claim any preference in the form of
            <lb />
            weightage in the selection process undertaken by the APSC vide Advertisement
            <lb />
            No. 06/2019 dated 19.11.2019 for filing up 156 nos. of post of Assistant Engineer
            <lb />
            [Civil] under the Public Works Department.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            42.
            <lb />
            The Assam Engineering [Public Works Department] Services Rules, 1978 is
            <lb />
            framed in exercise of the powers conferred under the proviso to Article 309 of the
            <lb />
            Constitution of India. Under Article 309 of the Constitution of India, the
            <lb />
            Legislature is empowered to regulate the recruitment and conditions of service of
            <lb />
            persons appointed to public services and posts in connection with the affairs of
            <lb />
            the Union or of any State. The proviso to Article 309, inter alia, empowers the
            <lb />
            Governor, in the case of services and posts in connection with the affairs of the
            <lb />
            State, to make rules regulating the recruitment and conditions of service of
            <lb />
            persons appointed to such services and posts until provision in that behalf is
            <lb />
            made by or under an Act of the Legislature. It is settled that rules made under
            <lb />
            the proviso to Article 309 to the Constitution of India are legislative in character
            <lb />
            and, thus, such rules are constitutional rules, not like rules under a statute. They
            <lb />
            have the same force as a statute, though made by the executive. It is not a piece
            <lb />
            of delegated legislation like a rule made under a statute.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            43.
            <lb />
            Rule 6 of the PWD Service Rules has laid down the procedure for direct
            <lb />
            recruitment. For ready reference, the provision contained in Rule 6 is quoted
            <lb />
            hereunder :-
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;Rule 6 :-
            <lb />
            Direct Recruitment-[l] Subject to sub-rule [3] of Rule 11, direct
            <lb />
            recruitment to cadres of Assistant Engineers, Assistant Architects and
            <lb />
            Assistant Research Officers, Road Research Laboratory shall be made by
            <lb />
            the Governor on the basis of selection made by the Commission in
            <lb />
            accordance with the procedure hereinafter provided :
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            [a] Before the end of each year the Government shall make an assessment
            <lb />
            regarding the likely number of vacancies to be filled by direct
            <lb />
            recruitment during the next year and shall intimate the same to the
            <lb />
            Commission together with the details about reservation for candidates
            <lb />
            belonging to Scheduled Castes, Scheduled Tribes or any other category
            <lb />
            as laid down by Government, as provided under Rule 17 and about
            <lb />
            carry forward of such reservation;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            [b] The Government shall simultaneously request the Commission to
            <lb />
            recommend a list of candidates for direct recruitment, in order of
            <lb />
            preference;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            [c] The Commission shall make the selection in accordance with the
            <lb />
            scheme of selection prescribed by the Government in consultation with
            <lb />
            the Commission. The Commission may hold such test or interview and
            <lb />
            undertake scrutiny of published articles or thesis of the candidate, if
            <lb />
            any and the certificates and other documents, as may be considered
            <lb />
            necessary;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            [d] The Commission shall furnish Government with a list of candidates
            <lb />
            recommended by it in order of preference, found suitable for direct
            <lb />
            recruitment. The number of candidates in such a list may be
            <lb />
            approximately double the number of vacancies; and
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            [e] The Commission shall simultaneously publish the list in the Assam
            <lb />
            Gazette and such other place the Commission may consider proper.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            [2] The lists mentioned in clauses [d] and [e] of sub-rule [1] of this rule
            <lb />
            shall remain valid for 12 Calendar months from the date of
            <lb />
            recommendation.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            [3] In the event of the Commission being unable to recommend sufficient
            <lb />
            number of candidates to fill up the vacancies in a year, it shall in
            <lb />
            consultation with the Appointing Authority, repeat the procedure as
            <lb />
            mentioned herein before under sub-rule [1] of this rule far
            <lb />
            recommending a subsequent list in the year : provided that the
            <lb />
            Appointing Authority shall not make appointment of any candidate
            <lb />
            from the subsequent select list until all the candidates of the earliest
            <lb />
            list of the same year, eligible for appointment, have been offered the
            <lb />
            appointment.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            44.
            <lb />
            From Rule 6 of the PWD Service Rules, one thing is clear beyond any cavil of
            <lb />
            doubt that the process of regular selection for filling up the vacancies in the post
            <lb />
            of Assistant Engineer [Civil] can be made only through the Commission and not
            <lb />
            by any other body/agency.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            45.
            <lb />
            Before any dilation on the issue of preference in the form of weightage to the
            <lb />
            petitioners in W.P.[C] no. 617/2020, it would be apt to refer to Rule 28 of the
            <lb />
            PWD Service Rules, on which the petitioners have heavily relied, to grant them
            <lb />
            preference in the form of weightage in the process of selection initiated by the
            <lb />
            Advertisement no. 06/2019 dated 19.11.2019.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            46.
            <lb />
            Rule 28 of the PWD Service Rules reads as under :-
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;Rule 28.
            <lb />
            Relaxation :-
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            Where the Appointing Authority is satisfied that the
            <lb />
            operation of any of these rules causes undue hardship in any
            <lb />
            particular case, it may, dispense with or relax the
            <lb />
            requirement of that rules to such extent and subject to such
            <lb />
            conditions as it may consider necessary for dealing with the
            <lb />
            case in a just and equitable manner :
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            Provided that the case of any person shall not be dealt with
            <lb />
            in any manner less favourable to him than that provided in
            <lb />
            any of these rules.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            Rule 25 in the P&amp;RD Service Rules and Rule 26 in the Health Service Rules are
            <lb />
            almost similarly worded with the only difference therein is that instead of the
            <lb />
            word, &apos;the Appointing Authority&apos;, the word, &apos;the Government&apos; appears in the said
            <lb />
            two set of rules. As per Rule 2[a] of the PWD Service Rules, &apos;the Appointing
            <lb />
            Authority&apos; means the Governor of Assam. In that view of the matter, all the said
            <lb />
            three rules appearing in the three sets of service rules are pari materia.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            47.
            <lb />
            From the facts already adverted above, it is clear that the petitioners in W.P.[C]
            <lb />
            no. 617/2020 have the requisite eligibility prescribed in the PWD Service Rules to
            <lb />
            be appointed to the post of Assistant Engineer [Civil]. The petitioners have sought
            <lb />
            for weightage in the process of selection initiated by the Advertisement no.
            <lb />
            06/2019 dated 19.11.2019.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            48.
            <lb />
            The concept of preference aptly came to be considered in the decision of J.C.
            <lb />
            Yadav [supra] in the context of existence of a relaxation clause in the concerned
            <lb />
            service rules. In paragraph no. 6 in J.C. Yadav [supra], the Hon&apos;ble Supreme
            <lb />
            Court of India has observed as under :-
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;6. The Rule confers power on the Government to dispense with or to relax
            <lb />
            the requirement of any of the Rules to the extent, and with such conditions
            <lb />
            as it may consider necessary for dealing with the case in a just and
            <lb />
            equitable manner. The object and purpose of conferring this power on the
            <lb />
            Government is to mitigate undue hardship in any particular case, and to
            <lb />
            deal with a case in a just and equitable manner. If the Rules cause undue
            <lb />
            hardship or Rules operate in an inequitable manner in that event the State
            <lb />
            Government has power to dispense with or to relax the requirement of
            <lb />
            Rules. The Rules do not restrict the exercise of power to individual cases.
            <lb />
            The Government may in certain circumstances relax the requirement of
            <lb />
            Rules to meet a particular situation. The expression &apos;in any particular case&apos;
            <lb />
            does not mean that the relaxation should be confined only to an individual
            <lb />
            case. One of the meanings of the expression &apos;particular&apos; means &apos;peculiar or
            <lb />
            pertaining, to a specified person -thing time or place not common or
            <lb />
            general&apos;. The meaning of the word particular in relation to law means
            <lb />
            separate or special, limited or specific. The word &apos;case&apos; in ordinary usage
            <lb />
            means &apos;event&apos;, &apos;happening&apos;. &apos;situation&apos;, &apos;circumstances&apos;. The expression
            <lb />
            &apos;case&apos; in legal sense means &apos;a case&apos;, &apos;suit&apos; or &apos;proceeding in Court or
            <lb />
            Tribunal&apos;. Having regard to these meanings of the words &apos;particular&apos; and
            <lb />
            &apos;case&apos; the expression &apos;in any particular case&apos; would mean, in a particular or
            <lb />
            pertaining to an event, situation or circumstance. Rule 22 postulates
            <lb />
            relaxation of Rules to meet a particular event or situation, if the operation
            <lb />
            of the Rules causes hardship. The relaxation of the Rules may be to the
            <lb />
            extent the State Government may consider necessary for dealing with a
            <lb />
            particular situation in a just and equitable manner. The scope of Rule is
            <lb />
            wide, enough to confer power on the State Government to relax the
            <lb />
            requirement of Rules in respect of an individual or class of individuals to
            <lb />
            the extent it may consider necessary for dealing with the case in a just and
            <lb />
            equitable manner. The power of relaxation is generally contained in the
            <lb />
            Rules with a view to mitigate undue hardship or to meet a particular
            <lb />
            situation. Many a times strict application of service rules create a situation
            <lb />
            where a particular individual or a set of individuals may suffer undue
            <lb />
            hardship and further there may be a situation where requisite qualified
            <lb />
            persons may not be available for appointment to the service. In such a
            <lb />
            situation the Government has power to relax requirement of Rules. The
            <lb />
            State Government may in exercise of its powers issue a general order
            <lb />
            relaxing any particular Rule with a view to avail the services of requisite
            <lb />
            officers. The relaxation even if granted in a general manner would enure to
            <lb />
            the benefit of individual officers.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            48.1. With regard to the power of relaxation, the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court of India in
            <lb />
            paragraph no. 10 in the decision of Arvindkumar T. Tiwari [supra] has observed
            <lb />
            as under :-
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;10. …… In a particular case, where it is so required, relaxation of even
            <lb />
            educational qualification[s] may be permissible, provided that the rules
            <lb />
            empower the authority to relax such eligibility in general, or with regard to
            <lb />
            an individual case or class of cases of undue hardship. However, the said
            <lb />
            power should be exercised for justifiable reasons and it must not be
            <lb />
            exercised arbitrarily, only to favour an individual. The power to relax the
            <lb />
            recruitment rules or any other rule made by the State
            <lb />
            Government/Authority is conferred upon the Government/Authority to
            <lb />
            meet any emergent situation where injustice might have been caused or, is
            <lb />
            likely to be caused to any person or class of persons or, where the working
            <lb />
            of the said rules might have become impossible. [Vide: State of Haryana
            <lb />
            vs. Subhash Chandra Marwah, [1974] 3 SCC 220; J.C. Yadav vs. State of
            <lb />
            Haryana, [1992] 2 SCC 189; and Ashok Kumar Uppal vs. State of J &amp; K,
            <lb />
            [1998] 4 SCC 179].&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            48.2. Explaining as to how the preference clause is to be applied, the Hon&apos;ble Supreme
            <lb />
            Court of India in paragraph nos. 10 and 11 in the decision in Y.V.V.R. Srinivashulu
            <lb />
            [supra] has exposited as under :-
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;10…… The word &apos;preference&apos; in our view is capable of different shades of
            <lb />
            meaning taking colour from the context, purpose and object of its use under
            <lb />
            the scheme of things envisaged. Hence, it is to be construed not in an isolated
            <lb />
            or detached manner, ascribing a meaning of universal import, for all
            <lb />
            contingencies capable of an invariable application. The procedure for
            <lb />
            selection in the case involve, a qualifying test, a written examination and oral
            <lb />
            test or interview and the final list of selection has to be on the basis of the
            <lb />
            marks obtained in them. The suitability and all round merit if had to be
            <lb />
            adjudged in that manner only what justification could there be for overriding
            <lb />
            all these merely because, a particular candidate is in possession of an
            <lb />
            additional qualification on the basis of which, a preference has also been
            <lb />
            envisaged. The rules do not provide for separate classification of those
            <lb />
            candidates or apply different norms of selection for them. The `preference&apos;
            <lb />
            envisaged in the rules, in our view, under the scheme of things and
            <lb />
            contextually also cannot mean an absolute en bloc preference akin to
            <lb />
            reservation or separate and distinct method of selection for them alone. A
            <lb />
            mere rule of preference meant to give weightage to the additional qualification
            <lb />
            cannot be enforced as a rule of reservation or rule of complete precedence.
            <lb />
            Such a construction would not only undermine the scheme of selection
            <lb />
            envisaged through Public Service Commission, on the basis of merit
            <lb />
            performance but also would work great hardship and injustice to th0se who
            <lb />
            possess the required minimum educational qualification with which they are
            <lb />
            entitled to compete with those possessing additional qualification too, and
            <lb />
            demonstrate their superiority, merit-wise and their suitability for the post. It
            <lb />
            is not to be viewed as a preferential right conferred even for taking up their
            <lb />
            claims for consideration. On the other hand, the preference envisaged has to
            <lb />
            be given only when the claims of all candidates who are eligible are taken for
            <lb />
            consideration and when anyone or more of them are found equally positioned,
            <lb />
            by using the additional qualification as a tilting factor, in their favour vis-à-vis
            <lb />
            others in the matter of actual selection.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            11. Whenever, a selection is to be made on the basis of merit performance
            <lb />
            involving competition, and possession of any additional qualification or factor
            <lb />
            is also envisaged to accord preference, it cannot be for the purpose of putting
            <lb />
            them as a whole lot ahead of others, de hors their intrinsic worth or proven
            <lb />
            inter se merit and suitability, duly assessed by the competent authority.
            <lb />
            Preference, in the context of all such competitive scheme of selection would
            <lb />
            not mean that other things being qualitatively and quantitatively equal, those
            <lb />
            with the additional qualification have to be preferred. There is no question of
            <lb />
            eliminating all others preventing thereby even an effective and comparative
            <lb />
            consideration on merits, by according en bloc precedence in favour of those in
            <lb />
            possession of additional qualification irrespective of the respective merits and
            <lb />
            demerits of all candidates to be considered……….&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            49.
            <lb />
            When the observations made in the above decisions with regard to relaxation of
            <lb />
            rules are read together with Rule 28 of the PWD Service Rules, it can be said that
            <lb />
            the Government or the Appointing Authority, as the case may be, if conferred
            <lb />
            with the power to dispense with or to relax any rule, then such power of
            <lb />
            dispensing with or relaxing any rule can be exercised in a just and equitable
            <lb />
            manner to meet any emergent situation where undue hardship might have been
            <lb />
            caused or is likely to be caused to a person or a class of persons or where the
            <lb />
            working of any rule/rules might have become impossible. For example, the power
            <lb />
            can also be exercised when the Government/Appointing Authority arrives at a
            <lb />
            satisfaction that qualified persons in requisite nos. are not available for
            <lb />
            appointment to a post/service. It can be noted herein that the eligibility for the
            <lb />
            post of Assistant Engineer [Civil] means the minimum criteria for selection
            <lb />
            prescribed in the PWD Service Rules which the petitioners indubitably have. The
            <lb />
            question of relaxation of educational qualification has not arisen in the case of the
            <lb />
            petitioners. Having fulfilled the eligibility criteria in respect of educational
            <lb />
            qualification, the petitioners have now claimed preference in the form of
            <lb />
            weightage in the selection process for their experience.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            50.
            <lb />
            The principle that can be deduced from the above decisions is that relaxation of
            <lb />
            any rule is permissible only in case there is undue hardship. Undue hardship
            <lb />
            means something more than only hardship. It has to excessive hardship. It is the
            <lb />
            situation of only undue hardship which will permit the Appointing Authority to
            <lb />
            consider making any relaxation under Rule 28. If one proceeds with the
            <lb />
            assumption that it is implicit in Rule 28 that the relaxation can be in the form of
            <lb />
            weightage, then as and when a process of selection is undertaken for recruitment
            <lb />
            through a competitive examination consisting of written examination and viva
            <lb />
            voce/interview on the basis of merits, any preference [weightage] for any
            <lb />
            additional qualification or relevant experience has to be envisaged at the
            <lb />
            inception as to how such preference [weightage] would be given. But such
            <lb />
            preference in the form of weightage can be given for any additional qualification
            <lb />
            or relevant experience only after it is found that other things being equal and at
            <lb />
            the final stage of calculation of marks. But it is at the inception, there has to be a
            <lb />
            conscious decision on the part of the Government or the Appointing Authority that
            <lb />
            the particular situation calls for exercise of such discretion to grant preference in
            <lb />
            the form of weightage and there has to some rational basis to give such
            <lb />
            weightage to a candidate or a particular category of candidates.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            51.
            <lb />
            What the petitioners in W.P.[C] no. 617/2020 herein have contended that they
            <lb />
            should be given preference in the form of weightage in the selection process as
            <lb />
            they have gained experience for the post of Assistant Engineer [Civil] after being
            <lb />
            appointed in the post under Regulation 3[f] of the APSC Regulations, 1951 and
            <lb />
            putting them at par with other candidates would cause hardship to them. Such a
            <lb />
            contention is required to be considered in the backdrop of the fact situation
            <lb />
            obtaining in the case. It is to be noted that the Advertisement no. 06/2019 did
            <lb />
            not envisage any preference [weightage] to them as the Government/Appointing
            <lb />
            Authority did not take any conscious decision earlier to give such preference.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            52.
            <lb />
            Few instances have been referred on behalf of the petitioners in W.P.[C] no.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            617/2020 to support their case for grant of preference [weightage].
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            52.1. One such instance is an Advertisement no. 08/2019 dated 30.12.2019 whereby
            <lb />
            the APSC invited applications for filing up 12 [twelve] nos. of post of Fishery
            <lb />
            Development Officer and allied cadre under the Fishery Department. It was
            <lb />
            mentioned therein that preference should be given to those candidates having
            <lb />
            experience in serving the Fishery Department under various projects related to
            <lb />
            Aquaculture and Fishery Extension. Disputing the same, the learned senior
            <lb />
            counsel for the Commission by placing a Corrigendum dated 08.07.2021 issued by
            <lb />
            the Commission whereby it was notified that the preference clause from the said
            <lb />
            advertisement had been dropped/discarded pursuant to a communication
            <lb />
            received from the Government. Thus, the said instance is not of assistance to the
            <lb />
            case of the petitioners.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            52.2. 3 [three] advertisements -two of them published by the APSC vide
            <lb />
            Advertisement no. 14/2016 dated 05.10.2016 &amp; Advertisement no. 08/2011 dated
            <lb />
            01.11.2011 and the third one published by the Medical &amp; Health Recruitment
            <lb />
            Board [&apos;the MHRB, Assam&apos;] on 20.06.2020 -are also placed to further the
            <lb />
            contention. The advertisements published by the APSC were for filing up the
            <lb />
            posts of Registrar / Resident Physician / Resident Surgeon / Refractionist /
            <lb />
            Demonstrator, etc. in various departments of the Government Medical Colleges in
            <lb />
            the State of Assam under the Health &amp; Family Welfare Department. The
            <lb />
            prescribed qualification was M.D. or M.S. Degree in the concerned subject and it
            <lb />
            was mentioned that preference would be given to the doctors working under
            <lb />
            Regulation 3[f] of the Regulations, 1951. By the advertisement published by the
            <lb />
            MHRB on 20.06.2020, 112 nos. of Medical Officers [Critical Care] in the
            <lb />
            Government Medical College Hospitals under the Health &amp; Family Welfare
            <lb />
            Department, Government of Assam were sought to be filled up. The prescribed
            <lb />
            educational qualification was at least M.B.B.S. or equivalent degree from a
            <lb />
            university. The advertisement mentioned that weightage would be given to a
            <lb />
            candidate having degree/diploma in Anaesthesiology or Critical Care or
            <lb />
            Emergency Medicine and preference shall be given to the doctors working under
            <lb />
            Regulation 17[B] of MHRB Regulations or on contractual basis in Medical College
            <lb />
            Hospitals of Assam. What is notable is that in these three advertisements, all
            <lb />
            pertaining to posts in the Medical Colleges, the Government/Appointing Authority
            <lb />
            prior to issuance of the advertisements, had taken the decision to give preference
            <lb />
            to those eligible candidates who had gained experience in working in such posts
            <lb />
            under the Medical College Hospitals under Regulation 3[f]. But in the case in
            <lb />
            hand, no such prior decision was taken by the Government/Appointing Authority
            <lb />
            to give any preference [weightage] to the persons who had gained experience by
            <lb />
            working under Regulation 3[f]. The petitioners in W.P.[C] no. 617/2020 have
            <lb />
            sought a direction in the nature of mandamus to the State respondents to grant
            <lb />
            them preference [weightage] for their experience gained under Regulation 3[f].
            <lb />
            In so far as the weightage required to be given to a candidate having
            <lb />
            degree/diploma in Anesthesiology or Critical Care or Emergency Medicine is
            <lb />
            concerned, the same is not applicable in the case of the petitioners in W.P.[C] no.
            <lb />
            617/2020 as the petitioners have sought preference [weightage] in terms of
            <lb />
            experience and not in terms of any additional educational qualification relating to
            <lb />
            the Public Works Department. The decisions to grant preference [weightage], in
            <lb />
            the said three cases, were taken prior to the advertisements and those decisions
            <lb />
            might be for the reason that the experienced gained by those category candidates
            <lb />
            by working in the Medical College Hospitals would be of more value than that of
            <lb />
            the candidates with no experience at all. The situation existing in a different
            <lb />
            branch like Medical Science cannot be ipso facto made comparable and applicable
            <lb />
            in a completely different branch like Engineering, like the case here, without
            <lb />
            laying any foundation before the Court which is otherwise also does not sit as an
            <lb />
            expert in such matters, to see as to whether there can be any comparison
            <lb />
            between two situations and for that matter, any similarity. This Court is also not
            <lb />
            in a position to assess on its own to arrive at a decision as to whether the
            <lb />
            Government/Appointing Authority had exercised its discretion on a proper and
            <lb />
            valid basis in those occasions.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            52.3. The last instance was an Advertisement no. 03/2020 dated 24.06.2020 published
            <lb />
            by the Commission whereby vacancies in the post of Junior Engineer [Civil] under
            <lb />
            the P&amp;RD Department were sought to be filled up. Pursuant to an order dated
            <lb />
            21.07.2020 passed in W.P.[C] no. 2839/2020, the Governor of Assam took a
            <lb />
            policy decision to relax the age criteria and to give due weightage to the
            <lb />
            experience gained by a large number of Contractual Accredited Engineers under
            <lb />
            the Department in the said selection process. In the Executive Order dated
            <lb />
            14.08.2020, it was mentioned that the Contractual Accredited Engineers who
            <lb />
            were recruited through a selection process and had rendered long years of
            <lb />
            service, had evolved as trained manpower of the Department for implementation
            <lb />
            of various development schemes. By the Executive Order, it was decided that the
            <lb />
            Contractual Accredited Engineers who had experience in between 2 years and
            <lb />
            above would be given weightage in the form of additional marks out of the total
            <lb />
            marks and in the age criterion, relaxation up to 10 years would be given. By the
            <lb />
            order dated 21.07.2020, it was made clear that there was no direction to consider
            <lb />
            the claim of the petitioners by allowing it. It was stated that the requirement of
            <lb />
            consideration to be given by the Department and to pass a reasoned order either
            <lb />
            accepting or rejecting the claim as may be appropriate under the law. Thus, the
            <lb />
            Executive Order dated 14.08.2020 was the result of the discretion vested in the
            <lb />
            Government/Appointing Authority to grant relaxation ans it was not fettered in
            <lb />
            any manner by the order of this Court. The petitioners in W.P.[C] no. 617/2020
            <lb />
            have sought to bring similarity of their case to the case of the Contractual
            <lb />
            Accredited Engineers. But the vital distinctive feature is that it was those
            <lb />
            Contractual Accredited Engineers who had minimum 2 [two] years of experience,
            <lb />
            would be given the weightage in terms of marks. Another distinctive feature is
            <lb />
            that the Government/Appointing Authority had found those Contractual
            <lb />
            Accredited Engineers with above 2 [two] years of experience as trained
            <lb />
            manpower, but such kind of recognition is not available in the case of the
            <lb />
            petitioners herein who had about 5 ½ months of experience of working the Public
            <lb />
            Works Department prior to the Advertisement no. 06/2019 dated 19.11.2019.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            53.
            <lb />
            In all the above instances, the Government was found to have taken a policy
            <lb />
            decision to provide relaxation, that is, to extend preference or weightage to the
            <lb />
            identified category of candidates. Such policy decisions were taken before the
            <lb />
            initiation of the selection process or before the last date of submission of
            <lb />
            applications or before the date of holding of the examination. Even when such
            <lb />
            power of relaxation is available in the rules, it is obligatory on the part of the
            <lb />
            Government or the Appointing Authority to mention in the advertisement that
            <lb />
            relaxation is being provided to an identified category of candidates. Such
            <lb />
            publication of grant of relaxation, either in the form of preference or weightage or
            <lb />
            relaxation in age, etc., prior to the advertisement is necessary so that all the
            <lb />
            candidates who come within the identified category or who become eligible due
            <lb />
            to such relaxation, get equal opportunity to apply and participate. Extending the
            <lb />
            benefit of relaxation after the advertisement and after a part of the selection
            <lb />
            process is over would amount to re-writing the advertisement in the mid-stream.
            <lb />
            Any change in the norms when the selection process has already got underway
            <lb />
            would be contrary to the principle of equality contained in Article 14 and Article
            <lb />
            16 of the Constitution of India. The Court does not issue a direction to the
            <lb />
            Appointing Authority to take a policy decision in any particular manner.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            54.
            <lb />
            In the case in hand, the stand of the State respondents is that no policy decision
            <lb />
            has been taken to grant any relaxation in the form of weightage to the
            <lb />
            petitioners. It is the Governor or the Appointing Authority, as the case may be,
            <lb />
            who can lay down the essential qualification in the extant service rules and in
            <lb />
            addition, by making a policy decision, may prescribe additional or desirable
            <lb />
            qualification or provide relaxation in age or grant weightage for relevant
            <lb />
            experience, etc. in exercise of the power conferred on it under the extant service
            <lb />
            rules and or by taking a policy decision in exercise of its power under Article 162
            <lb />
            of the Constitution, without supplanting the extant service rules. The Court in
            <lb />
            exercise of its power of judicial review cannot lay down the condition of eligibility
            <lb />
            or relax the condition of eligibility or do not give direction to the Governor or the
            <lb />
            Appointing Authority to treat a particular qualification as additional or desirable
            <lb />
            qualification or to provide relaxation in age, qualification, etc., or grant weightage
            <lb />
            for having any particular experience as it does not sit in appeal in such situations
            <lb />
            which are the exclusive preserve of the Governor or the Appointing Authority. It
            <lb />
            is settled that if the language in the advertisement is clear and specific and there
            <lb />
            is no violation of the extant service rules, the Court is in no position to sit in
            <lb />
            judgment over the same. While exercising the power of judicial review, the Court
            <lb />
            does not decide what is best for the employer/the Appointing Authority unless
            <lb />
            there is infraction of any statutory provision.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            55.
            <lb />
            The power to relax or for that matter, to grant weightage under Rules 28 of the
            <lb />
            PWD Service Rules vests exclusively in the Appointing Authority, that is, the
            <lb />
            Governor and this power cannot be assumed by the Court in exercise of the
            <lb />
            power of judicial review by issuing any direction in the nature of mandamus. The
            <lb />
            writ of mandamus can be issued by the Court only when there is existence of a
            <lb />
            legal right in the writ petitioner and corresponding legal obligation in the State.
            <lb />
            The writ petitioners in the writ petition, W.P.[C] no. 617/2020 have not been able
            <lb />
            to show any legal right to the effect that just because they had worked in the
            <lb />
            same post of Assistant Engineer [Civil] for a period of about 5 [five] months they
            <lb />
            have acquired a legal right to be granted the privilege in the form of weightage in
            <lb />
            the selection process undertaken pursuant to the Advertisement no. 06/2019. A
            <lb />
            Division Bench of this Court in Dr. M. Laitphlang and others [supra] has held that
            <lb />
            notwithstanding the availability of the power of relaxation in the extant service
            <lb />
            rules, when the question of granting relaxation comes in the circumstances of a
            <lb />
            particular case, the satisfaction is to be reached by the Government or the
            <lb />
            Appointing Authority, as the case may be, about the undue hardship caused to
            <lb />
            any person or class of person and not by the Court.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            56.
            <lb />
            In V. Lavanya [supra], the policy decision of State Government to grant
            <lb />
            concessions/relaxation of 5% marks in the passing marks of 60% in State
            <lb />
            Teacher Eligibility Test [TET] to candidates belonging to Scheduled
            <lb />
            Castes/Scheduled Tribes/Backward Classes, etc. was challenged on a number of
            <lb />
            counts. It has been observed by the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court that Article of
            <lb />
            the Constitution has enabled the State to make provision for reservation in
            <lb />
            appointments or posts in favour of any backward class of citizens which, in its
            <lb />
            opinion, is not adequately represented in the services under the State.
            <lb />
            Preferential treatment or concession granted to SC/ST, Backward Classes, etc.
            <lb />
            has been held to be within the concept of equality and is in furtherance of the
            <lb />
            Constitutional obligation of the State to the underprivileged for creation of an
            <lb />
            equal level-playing field. The decision in V. Lavanya [supra] is found not relevant
            <lb />
            to the case of the petitioners in W.P.[C] no. 617/2020 as the claim of the
            <lb />
            petitioners herein is not relatable to any fundamental or constitutional or statutory
            <lb />
            right, but of seeking a direction in the nature of mandamus to the State
            <lb />
            Government/Appointing Authority to exercise its discretion available under Rule
            <lb />
            18 of the PWD Service Rules to grant preference [weightage] to them. The policy
            <lb />
            decision of the State to grant relaxation which was in tune with the Constitutional
            <lb />
            philosophy is to be followed in a selection process for public employment and it is
            <lb />
            immaterial at what stage of the selection process it came to be implemented.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            56.1. In Shankar K. Mandal [supra], the subject-matter was about illegally appointed
            <lb />
            elementary teachers. When orders for their termination were passed the same
            <lb />
            were challenged before the High Court. In the judgment passed therein, direction
            <lb />
            was passed to make appointment of teachers by inviting applications from all the
            <lb />
            persons who had been removed and to make relaxation for age, wherever
            <lb />
            necessary. The Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court affirmed the same. In the fresh exercise
            <lb />
            undertaken thereafter, the appellants were not selected and they filed writ
            <lb />
            petitions. The Division Bench of the High Court made different observations in
            <lb />
            respect of different appellants, affirming the age relaxation for some and
            <lb />
            discarding age relaxation for some. When the judgment of the Division Bench was
            <lb />
            challenged in one appeal laying down the tests to be followed regarding fulfilment
            <lb />
            of prescribed qualification relating to age by a candidate, the Hon&apos;ble Supreme
            <lb />
            Court directed the State respondents to find out the eligibility of the appellants by
            <lb />
            applying the tests indicated therein. In the other connected appeal, though the
            <lb />
            point of relaxation relating to age was found not to have been taken before the
            <lb />
            Single Judge and the Division Bench the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court in the second
            <lb />
            appeal finding the appellants therein to be similarly situated like the appellants in
            <lb />
            the first appeal in respect of whom direction for consideration of the age aspect
            <lb />
            was already made, observed it as appropriate if similar consideration was made in
            <lb />
            respect of the appellants in the second appeal too and directed in that manner.
            <lb />
            No law appeared to have been laid down by the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court in
            <lb />
            Shankar K. Mandal [supra] on the aspect of relaxation. It was a direction made
            <lb />
            under Article 142 of the Constitution. The fact situation obtaining in the case of
            <lb />
            Shankar K. Mandal [supra] is, thus, not applicable to the fact situation obtaining
            <lb />
            the case in hand and as such, the decision made therein and the direction are not
            <lb />
            relevant for the purpose of the case in hand.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            57.
            <lb />
            In the light of the above discussion, this Court is of the unhesitant view that the
            <lb />
            plea of the petitioners in the writ petition, W.P.[C] no. 617/2020 for issuance of a
            <lb />
            direction to grant them weightage in the process of selection initiated by the
            <lb />
            Advertisement no 06/2019 dated 19.11.2019 is found unsustainable.
            <lb />
            Consequently, the writ petition, W.P.[C] no. 617/2020 is found devoid of any
            <lb />
            merit and the same is liable to be dismissed. It is accordingly dismissed.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            THE WRIT PETITION, W.P.[C] NO. 744/2020
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            58.
            <lb />
            It is not a condition precedent and not obligatory for the Government and/or the
            <lb />
            Appointing Authority to make any rules under Article 309 of the Constitution of
            <lb />
            India or under the proviso to Article 309 of the Constitution of India before
            <lb />
            constitution of a service or creation of or filing up a post. The State Government
            <lb />
            has executive power under Article 162 of the Constitution, in relation to all
            <lb />
            matters in respect to which the Legislature of the State has power to make laws.
            <lb />
            Article 309 of the Constitution has not curtailed the executive power of the State
            <lb />
            Government to act under Article 162 of the Constitution when there are no rules
            <lb />
            framed either under Article 309 or under the proviso to Article 309 of the
            <lb />
            Constitution. If such rules have not been made, in a particular case, by the
            <lb />
            Legislature or by the Governor of the State then it would be open for the State
            <lb />
            Government under Article 162 of the Constitution to issue executive instructions
            <lb />
            regulating the matters of recruitment and conditions of service of persons
            <lb />
            appointed to civil services and posts in connection with the affairs of the State.
            <lb />
            The executive power is co-extensive with the legislative power of the State and in
            <lb />
            exercise of the powers under Article 162 the State can create civil posts and fill
            <lb />
            them up according to executive instructions which must be consistent with Article
            <lb />
            14 and Article 16 of the Constitution.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            59.
            <lb />
            It is an admitted position that there are no rules framed either under Article 309
            <lb />
            of the Constitution or under the proviso to Article 309 of the Constitution
            <lb />
            regulating the matter of recruitment to the post of Junior Engineer [Civil] in the
            <lb />
            Public Works Department [PWD]. In the absence of such rules, it is the executive
            <lb />
            instructions which will govern the same. Contentions have been raised on behalf
            <lb />
            of the petitioners in the writ petition, W.P.[C] no. 744/2020 that there is an
            <lb />
            admission on the part of the State respondents that in the matter of making
            <lb />
            recruitment to the post of Junior Engineer [Civil] in the Public Works Department
            <lb />
            [PWD], the Public Works Department has been following the Irrigation
            <lb />
            Department Service Rules, 1978. The basis of such contentions have already been
            <lb />
            recorded in the preceding paragraphs.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            60.
            <lb />
            Article 320[1] of the Constitution of India has laid down that it shall be the duty
            <lb />
            of the State Public Service Commission to conduct examination for appointments
            <lb />
            to the services of the State. It is the mandates of Article 320[3][a] and Article
            <lb />
            320[3][b] that the State Public Service Commission shall be consulted on all
            <lb />
            matters relating to methods of recruitment to civil services and for civil posts and
            <lb />
            on the principles to be followed in making appointments to civil services and posts
            <lb />
            and on the suitability of candidates for such appointments. There is a proviso to
            <lb />
            sub-clause [3] of Article 320 which amounts to an exception and it has provided
            <lb />
            that the Governor, as respects services and posts of a State, may make
            <lb />
            regulations specifying the matters in which either generally, or in any particular
            <lb />
            class of case or in any particular circumstances, it shall not be necessary for the
            <lb />
            State Public Service Commission to be consulted.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            61.
            <lb />
            It was in exercise of the power conferred by the provision to Clause [3] of Article
            <lb />
            320 of the Constitution of India, the Governor of Assam has made the Assam
            <lb />
            Public Service Commission [Limitation of Function] Regulations, 1951 [&apos;the APSC
            <lb />
            Regulations, 1951&apos;] as respects services and posts in connection with the affairs
            <lb />
            of the State of Assam, specifying matters in which it shall not be necessary for
            <lb />
            the State Public Service Commission to be consulted. The meaning ascribed to
            <lb />
            &apos;Service&apos; or &apos;Post&apos; in the APSC Regulations, 1951 is civil service or post in
            <lb />
            connection with the affairs of the State of Assam.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            61.1. The mandate under Article 320[3][a] of the Constitution is that the State Public
            <lb />
            Service Commission shall be consulted on all matters relating to methods of
            <lb />
            recruitment to civil services and for civil posts. Under Article 320[3][b] of the
            <lb />
            Constitution, the mandate is inter alia that the State Public Service Commission
            <lb />
            shall be consulted on the principles to be followed in making appointments to civil
            <lb />
            services and civil posts.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            61.2. The learned Senior Counsel for the petitioners in the writ petition, W.P.[C] no.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            744/2020 has advanced his submissions in a line that since the matter of
            <lb />
            recruitment to the post of Junior Engineer [Civil] is outside the purview of the
            <lb />
            Commission, there is prohibition for the Commission to enter into the arena of
            <lb />
            recruitment to fill up the vacancies in the post of Junior Engineer [Civil] in the
            <lb />
            Public Works Department by initiating the process of selection with the
            <lb />
            Advertisement no. 06/2019. He has sought to contend that the Advertisement no.
            <lb />
            06/2019 being an illegality and the earlier process of selection whereby the
            <lb />
            petitioners were appointed was in consonance with law, the petitioners should be
            <lb />
            treated as regular appointees.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            61.3. Such contention regarding prohibition cannot be countenanced when Article 320
            <lb />
            of the Constitution of India and Regulation 3 of the APSC Regulations, 1951 are
            <lb />
            read together. The word &apos;shall&apos; appearing in Article 320[1] of the Constitution of
            <lb />
            India has made it mandatory to involve the State Public Service Commission to
            <lb />
            conduct examinations for appointments to the services of the State. The word
            <lb />
            &apos;shall&apos; which appears in Article 320[3] of the Constitution makes the consultation
            <lb />
            with the State Public Service Commission obligatory for the purposes indicated in
            <lb />
            Clause [a] to Clause [e] therein. As per proviso to Article 320[3], the Governor, as
            <lb />
            respects other services and posts in connection with the affairs of a State, &apos;may&apos;
            <lb />
            make regulations specifying the matters in which either generally, or in any
            <lb />
            particular class of case or in any particular circumstance, it shall not be necessary
            <lb />
            for a State Public Service Commission to be consulted. While the word &apos;shall&apos;
            <lb />
            appearing in the substantive part of Article 320[1] and Article 320[3] of the
            <lb />
            Constitution has made such consultation mandatory but the opposite cannot be
            <lb />
            accepted as mandatory. It cannot be said that the words &apos;shall not be necessary&apos;
            <lb />
            appearing in the proviso to Article 320[3] of the Constitution as well as in
            <lb />
            Regulation 3 of the APSC Regulations, 1951 carries a meaning that if the State
            <lb />
            Public Service Commission is consulted then the matters included in the
            <lb />
            regulations framed in exercise of the powers conferred by the proviso to Article
            <lb />
            320[3] of the Constitution will bear a stamp of illegality.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            62.
            <lb />
            By the query no. 7 in their application under the RTI Act, 2005, the petitioners
            <lb />
            made a query to the respondent authorities in the Public Works Department
            <lb />
            about the rules which were used during the recruitment process made under
            <lb />
            Regulation 3 [f] of the APSC Regulations, 1951. By the reply dated 03.02.2020, it
            <lb />
            was informed that the Irrigation Department Service Rules, 1978 was followed
            <lb />
            during the said process of recruitment of Junior Engineer [Civil] under Regulation
            <lb />
            3[f]. In the affidavit-in-opposition also, the same position has been reiterated.
            <lb />
            Thus, it is apparent that it was only during the recruitment process undertaken
            <lb />
            under Regulation 3[f] whereby the petitioners themselves came to be appointed
            <lb />
            as Junior Engineer [Civil], the Public Works Department followed the provision of
            <lb />
            the Irrigation Department Service Rules, 1978 but not in the recruitment process
            <lb />
            initiated by the Advertisement no. 06/2019 dated 19.11.2019. Such a statement
            <lb />
            does not go to establish that the provisions of the Irrigation Department Service
            <lb />
            Rules, 1978 were followed in toto and in its entirety. The State respondents have
            <lb />
            not stated that in the matter of recruitment to the post of Junior Engineer [Civil]
            <lb />
            in the Public Works Department, there is adoption of the Irrigation Department
            <lb />
            Service Rules, 1978. It has been asserted and averred by the State respondents
            <lb />
            that due to absence of service rules for recruitment to the post of Junior Engineer
            <lb />
            [Civil] in the Public Works Department [PWD], the department is following the
            <lb />
            Irrigation Department Service Rules, 1978 as far as practicable and applicable
            <lb />
            with Irrigation Department being a similar works/technical department but there
            <lb />
            was no adoption of the Irrigation Department Service Rules, 1978, meaning
            <lb />
            thereby, the same are not binding upon the Public Works Department [PWD]. If
            <lb />
            there is no adoption of the Irrigation Department Service Rules, 1978 in the
            <lb />
            matter of recruitment to the post of Junior Engineer [Civil] in the Public Works
            <lb />
            Department, then it cannot be expected from the State respondents to produce
            <lb />
            something which is not in existence. Since it is the petitioners who have claimed
            <lb />
            that there was adoption of the Irrigation Department Service Rules, 1978 it is for
            <lb />
            them to produce something tangible in that respect. There is abject failure on the
            <lb />
            part of the petitioners save and except the bald allegations, on that count.
            <lb />
            Consequently, the decision in Dr. Amarjit Singh Ahluwalia [supra], cited by Mr.
            <lb />
            Mishra, is found not relevant to the case of the petitioners. Assuming for a
            <lb />
            moment that there was adoption of the Irrigation Department Service Rules, 1978
            <lb />
            by the Public Works Department by a resolution then also the Irrigation
            <lb />
            Department Service Rules of 1978 would not retain any statutory character in
            <lb />
            their application to an incumbent in the post of Junior Engineer in the Public
            <lb />
            Works Department under Regulation 3[f] and they would be mere executive
            <lb />
            instructions having no statutory colour and no enforceability, thus, leaving no
            <lb />
            ground for the petitioners to argue anything regarding violation of any of their
            <lb />
            constitutional or statutory or legal rights. The petitioners herein have even failed
            <lb />
            to establish that there is any kind of adoption.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            63.
            <lb />
            The State respondents in its affidavit-in-opposition have categorically asserted
            <lb />
            that it was since around 1982-1983, the APSC has been conducting the
            <lb />
            recruitment for the post of Junior Engineer [Civil] in the Public Works
            <lb />
            Department. The subject-matter in Debabrat Bargohain and others [supra] was
            <lb />
            also recruitment to a number of vacancies in the post of Junior Engineer [Civil] in
            <lb />
            the Public Works Department and the concerned advertisement was published by
            <lb />
            the APSC on 21.10.1993 and the consequent selection process was also held by
            <lb />
            the APSC. From the above stand and the advertisement, it is clear that the
            <lb />
            Commission has been conducting the recruitment process for the post of Junior
            <lb />
            Engineer [Civil] in the Public Works Department since a long time. In this case
            <lb />
            also, the Government in the Public Works Department by forwarding the draft
            <lb />
            Advertisement by its communication dated 19.08.2019, which was in the nature
            <lb />
            of executive instructions, entrusted the task of conducting the selection process
            <lb />
            to the APSC.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            64.
            <lb />
            By the notification dated 20.07.2000 of the State Government in the
            <lb />
            Administrative Reforms and Training Department and issued under an order by
            <lb />
            the Governor, the Junior Engineers under various department of the Government
            <lb />
            of Assam had been conferred the Gazetted status on entry into the service. The
            <lb />
            notification was issued in exercise of the powers under Article 162 of the
            <lb />
            Constitution. It can be iterated here, at the cost of repetition, that no rules have
            <lb />
            been framed till date either under Article 309 of the Constitution or under the
            <lb />
            proviso to Article 309 of the Constitution regulating the matter of recruitment in
            <lb />
            respect of vacancies in the post of Junior Engineer [Civil] in the Public Works
            <lb />
            Department [PWD]. Thus, conferment of such Gazette status to the Junior
            <lb />
            Engineer [Civil] in the Public Works Department is permissible by way of an
            <lb />
            executive instruction. But the same may not be the case in respect of the Junior
            <lb />
            Engineer serving in the Irrigation Department. The matter of recruitment to and
            <lb />
            the condition of service of the persons appointed to the Assam Subordinate
            <lb />
            Engineering [Irrigation Department] Service of which the cadre/post of Junior
            <lb />
            Engineer, earlier known as Subordinate Engineer Grade-I, is a part are regulated
            <lb />
            by the Irrigation Department Service Rules, 1978 which were framed in exercise
            <lb />
            of the powers conferred by the proviso to Article 309 of the Constitution. Sub-rule
            <lb />
            [5] of Rule 3 of the Irrigation Department Service Rules, 1978 states that the
            <lb />
            status of the members shall be non-Gazetted in Class-III Government Service. In
            <lb />
            such situation, the notification 20.02.2000 cannot supplant Rule 3[5] of the
            <lb />
            Irrigation Department Service Rules, 1978. Mere reflection of the word, non-
            <lb />
            Gazetted in the pay slip of the petitioners sans any other details, does not alter
            <lb />
            the above legal position regarding conferment of Gazetted status to the post of
            <lb />
            Junior Engineer [Civil] in the Public Works Department.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            65.
            <lb />
            It is also the stand of the State respondents that the Appointing Authority for the
            <lb />
            post of Junior Engineer [Civil] in the Public Works Department is the Governor of
            <lb />
            Assam and the Appointing Authority in case of the cadres under the Irrigation
            <lb />
            Department Service Rules, 1978 is the Chief Engineer, Irrigation Department,
            <lb />
            Assam since as per Rule 2[a] thereof, &apos;Appointing Authority&apos; means the Chief
            <lb />
            Engineer, Irrigation Department, Assam. The petitioners are found to have
            <lb />
            maintained silence as regards the Appointing Authority for the post of Junior
            <lb />
            Engineer [Civil] in the Public Works Department. The very notification dated
            <lb />
            04.06.2019 by which the petitioners in W.P.[C] no. 744/2020 came to be
            <lb />
            appointed under Regulation 3[f] of the APSC Regulations, 1951 as Junior
            <lb />
            Engineer [Civil] was also issued under an order by the Governor of Assam and
            <lb />
            under the hand of the Commissioner &amp; Special secretary to the Government of
            <lb />
            Assam, Public Works Department. Thus, the contention that the Chief Engineer,
            <lb />
            Public Works Department is the Appointing Authority for the post of Junior
            <lb />
            Engineer [Civil] in the Public Works Department is belied by the materials on
            <lb />
            record and has fallen flat.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            66.
            <lb />
            This Court does not find any merit in the contention regarding impermissibility for
            <lb />
            the Commission to hold recruitment process for appointment to the post of Junior
            <lb />
            Engineer [Civil] in the Public Works Department which is made by referring to
            <lb />
            Regulation 3[a] of the APSC Regulations, 1951. The concept of civil post definitely
            <lb />
            brings within its ambit the post of Junior Engineer [Civil] in the Public Works
            <lb />
            Department, Government of Assam. Though the post is not a part of any civil
            <lb />
            service but it is a civil post in the Public Works Department which is a part of the
            <lb />
            State Government. From the discussion above, it has already been established
            <lb />
            that the Appointing Authority for the post of Junior Engineer [Civil] in the Public
            <lb />
            Works Department is the Governor. It shall not be necessary for the Commission
            <lb />
            to be consulted, as contained in Regulation 3[a] of the APSC Regulations, 1951,
            <lb />
            in a matter relating to methods of recruitment to a civil post when an
            <lb />
            appointment is to be made by the Governor to a post on a pay scale the
            <lb />
            maximum of which is less than Rs. 1,166/-per month. It was by a notification no.
            <lb />
            ABP.2/84/77 dated 20.08.1987, the figure, &apos;Rs. 1,166/-&apos; was substituted in place
            <lb />
            of &apos;Rs. 651/-&apos; and it came into effect from the date of its publication in the Assam
            <lb />
            Gazette dated 20.08.1987. No dilation is necessary to say that the pay scale of
            <lb />
            Junior Engineer [Civil] in the Public Works Department does not come within the
            <lb />
            said condition to dispense with the necessity of consultation with the Commission.
            <lb />
            The post of Junior Engineer [Civil] in the Public Works Department does not also
            <lb />
            figure in the Schedule appended to the APSC Regulations, 1951 in reference to
            <lb />
            Regulation 3[a]. For the reasons above, the decisions in M.T. Khan [supra] and
            <lb />
            Dorjee Tshering Bhutia [supra] are not found of any assistance to the case of the
            <lb />
            petitioners.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            67.
            <lb />
            There is no necessity to deliberate anything further on the well settled proposition
            <lb />
            of law that an ad-hoc employee has no right to a post. Thus, the decision in
            <lb />
            Roshan Lal Tandon [supra] is not found of any relevance to the case of the
            <lb />
            petitioners. The decision in Central Inland Water Transport Corporation Limited
            <lb />
            [&apos;the appellant-Corporation&apos;, for short] was rendered in connection with
            <lb />
            termination of two permanent employees by invocation of Rule 9[i] of the &apos;Central
            <lb />
            Inland Water Transport Corporation Ltd. Service Discipline and Appeal Rules&apos; of
            <lb />
            1979, framed by the appellant-Corporation, an instrumentality of the State under
            <lb />
            Article 12 of the Constitution. The Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court of India had found that
            <lb />
            there were no laid down guidelines to indicate the circumstances when the power
            <lb />
            given by Rule 9[i] was to be exercised by the appellant-Corporation and there
            <lb />
            was no provision of giving any opportunity of a hearing whatsoever to the
            <lb />
            permanent employee who was sought to be terminated. Having found the power
            <lb />
            exercised by the appellant-Corporation an absolute, arbitrary and unguided one
            <lb />
            and in total violation of the audi alteram partem rule, one of the two great rules
            <lb />
            of natural justice, the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court of India regarded the same as
            <lb />
            arbitrary, discriminatory, opposed to public policy and violative of the Article 14 of
            <lb />
            the Constitution of India. It declared Rule 9[i] void, unconscionable and ultra vires
            <lb />
            to the extent it conferred power to the appellant-Corporation the right to
            <lb />
            terminate the employment of a permanent employee by giving him three months&apos;
            <lb />
            notice in writing or three months&apos; pay in lieu of such notice. The petitioners in writ
            <lb />
            petition, W.P.[C] no. 744/2020 being ad-hoc employees of 5½ months duration,
            <lb />
            cannot claim parity with two permanent employees who put in more than 15
            <lb />
            years&apos; of service in the appellant-Corporation before the impugned termination,
            <lb />
            and in view of their service of ad-hoc nature under Regulation 3[f] of the APSC
            <lb />
            Regulations, 1951. The legal position about such ad-hoc nature of service under
            <lb />
            Regulation 3[f] have already been dissertated by the decisions of this Court,
            <lb />
            referred herein above.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            68.
            <lb />
            On perusal of the two syllabi, it is noticed that the chapters pertaining to
            <lb />
            Hydraulics &amp; Structural Mechanics in the first advertisement for the post of Junior
            <lb />
            Engineer [Civil] were missing in the second advertisement and chapters
            <lb />
            pertaining to Water Supply Engineering &amp; Sanitary Engineering in the second
            <lb />
            advertisement were missing in the first advertisement. In the General Studies
            <lb />
            paper, the difference was in the portion relating to General English. While it was
            <lb />
            &apos;Comprehension and Expression&apos; in the first advertisement, it was replaced by
            <lb />
            &apos;Precis Writing&apos; in the second advertisement. This Court is not an expert in such
            <lb />
            academic matters to arrive at any finding as to whether the syllabus published for
            <lb />
            the post of Junior Engineer [Civil] in the first advertisement was substantially
            <lb />
            similar or different. As such, this Court has refrained itself from making any
            <lb />
            comment on such issues, which are to be left for academic experts in the field.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            69.
            <lb />
            There is another relevant aspect in the case. It was made clear and specific in the
            <lb />
            advertisement dated 14.08.2018 by the State respondents that the appointment
            <lb />
            made in terms of the advertisement would be ad-hoc in nature for a period of 4
            <lb />
            [four] months and the same would be under Regulation 3[f] of the APSC
            <lb />
            Regulations, 1951. Having noticed such specific condition of unambiguous nature
            <lb />
            and being aware of the legal position about such nature of appointments under
            <lb />
            Regulation 3[f] many a qualified candidates, who could be much meritorious than
            <lb />
            the petitioners, might not have responded to the advertisement and/or
            <lb />
            participated in the selection process undertaken pursuant to the advertisement
            <lb />
            with the anticipation to participate in the selection process as and when an
            <lb />
            advertisement to fill up the vacancies in the said posts in regular manner is
            <lb />
            published. There is also a possibility that many an eligible candidates who might
            <lb />
            working in some posts with the assurance of regular pay and better scope of
            <lb />
            gaining work experience, did not respond to the advertisement and/or did not
            <lb />
            participate in the selection process even after applying, because of the ad-hoc
            <lb />
            nature of the appointments. Any direction to treat the appointments of the
            <lb />
            petitioners in W.P.[C] no. 744/2020 under Regulation 3[f] of the APSC
            <lb />
            Regulations, 1951 as regular appointments to the cadre of Junior Engineer [Civil]
            <lb />
            in the Public Works Department would amount in denying all the other available
            <lb />
            eligible candidates which are albeit substantial in numbers, from the benefit of
            <lb />
            participation. Such denial of the benefit of participation would, in turn, be in
            <lb />
            violations of the fundamental rights enshrined in Article 14 and Article 16 of the
            <lb />
            Constitution of India.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            70.
            <lb />
            In view of the above discussion, this Court has not found merits in any of the
            <lb />
            contentions advanced on behalf of the petitioners in the writ petition, W.P.[C] no.
            <lb />
            744/2020. As a result, the writ petition stands dismissed.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            71.
            <lb />
            With regard to the contentions made by the learned Senior Counsel for the
            <lb />
            petitioners in the writ petition, W.P.[C] no. 617/2020 on the basis of the
            <lb />
            averments made in the additional affidavit, filed on 19.08.2021, about permitting
            <lb />
            ineligible candidates to appear and issuance of more than one admit card in the
            <lb />
            name of same candidate to appear in the written examination i.e. screening test
            <lb />
            [OMR based], held on 15.11.2020, for the post of Assistant Engineer [Civil], it is
            <lb />
            to be noted that by Advertisement no. 06/2019 dated 19.11.2019, applications
            <lb />
            were invited for filling up of 156 nos. of posts of Assistant Engineer [Civil]. As per
            <lb />
            the said advertisement, the last date of submission of applications was
            <lb />
            21.12.2019. In continuation of the Advertisement no. 06/2019 dated 19.11.2019,
            <lb />
            the Addendum was published on 06.05.2020 whereby it was notified that
            <lb />
            applications would also be received for an additional 104 nos. of vacancies in the
            <lb />
            post of Assistant Engineer [Civil]. In view of the publication of the Addendum, the
            <lb />
            last date of submission of applications was extended to 16.06.2020.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            71.1. It has been contended that the Commission had accepted the applications of a
            <lb />
            number of ineligible candidates to appear in the screening test for the post of
            <lb />
            Assistant Engineer [Civil] despite the fact that the results of the qualifying
            <lb />
            examination in respect of those candidates were declared much after 16.06.2020.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            To substantiate the said submission, the petitioners have mentioned the names of
            <lb />
            23 nos. of candidates and have brought on record the results of the 8 th Semester
            <lb />
            [Final] B.E. Civil Engineering Examination of the Gauhati University held in May,
            <lb />
            2020 and the list of candidates including the said 23 nos. of candidates, whose
            <lb />
            applications had been accepted by the Commission for appearing in the screening
            <lb />
            test for the post of Assistant Engineer [Civil]. A conjoint perusal of the same goes
            <lb />
            to indicate that the results of B.E. [Final] Civil Engineering Examination of those
            <lb />
            23 nos. of candidates were declared on 08.09.2020, meaning thereby, they
            <lb />
            passed the qualifying examination prescribed in the afore-stated advertisements
            <lb />
            for the post of Assistant Engineer [Civil] only on 08.09.2020. But, the Commission
            <lb />
            had permitted them to appear in the written examination i.e. screening test [OMR
            <lb />
            based] held on 15.11.2020. The petitioners have also been able to show from the
            <lb />
            list of candidates whose applications had been accepted by the Commission for
            <lb />
            appearing in the screening test for the post of Assistant Engineer [Civil] and other
            <lb />
            documents, annexed at Page nos. 15-105 of the said additional affidavit, that
            <lb />
            more than one admit card had been issued in the name of the same candidate to
            <lb />
            appear in the written examination i.e. screening test [OMR based] held on
            <lb />
            15.11.2020.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            71.2. With regard to the cut-off date fixed for fulfilling the prescribed qualification, the
            <lb />
            principle has been settled by the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court of India in Shankar K.
            <lb />
            Mandal [supra] in the following manner :-
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            5....the principles culled out from the decisions of this Court are as follows :
            <lb />
            [1] The cut-off date by reference to which the eligibility requirement must
            <lb />
            be satisfied by the candidate seeking a public employment is the date
            <lb />
            appointed by the relevant service rules.
            <lb />
            [2] If there is no cut-off date appointed by the rules then such date shall be
            <lb />
            as appointed for the purpose in the advertisement calling for
            <lb />
            applications.
            <lb />
            [3] If there is no such date appointed then the eligibility criteria shall be
            <lb />
            applied by reference to the last date appointed by which the
            <lb />
            applications were to be received by the competent authority.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            71.3. The Advertisement no. 06/2019 stipulated that only those candidates who fulfil all
            <lb />
            the terms and conditions of the advertisement in respect of the post for which
            <lb />
            they were applicants shall be entertained. It further stipulated that only those
            <lb />
            applications which were accompanied by all particulars as called for in the
            <lb />
            application form prescribed by the Commission shall be considered and the
            <lb />
            candidates fulfilling all the terms of the advertisement of the respective post shall
            <lb />
            be called for the screening/written test/viva-voce interview. The advertisement
            <lb />
            further mentioned that the applications which were not accompanied by the
            <lb />
            certificates and mark-sheets of the qualifying examination shall not be entertained
            <lb />
            and incomplete application in terms of the advertisement would be summarily
            <lb />
            rejected. The candidates had to ensure that they fulfil all the eligibility conditions.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            71.4. In view of the above terms and conditions of the advertisement and the position
            <lb />
            of law with to the cut-off date, it is evident that the candidatures of those
            <lb />
            candidates who did not have the prescribed qualification on 16.06.2020 are liable
            <lb />
            to be rejected.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            71.5. As per the notification dated 11.12.2020, the total number of candidates to be
            <lb />
            shortlisted for personality test/interview for the post of Assistant Engineer [Civil]
            <lb />
            would be at the ratio of 1:3.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            71.6. In view of the above fact situation, it clearly emerges that in the event the
            <lb />
            performance of ineligible candidates in the written examination, held on
            <lb />
            15.11.2020, are taken into consideration in shortlisting the candidates for
            <lb />
            personality test/interview then the interests of the eligible candidates including
            <lb />
            that of the petitioners, are liable to be prejudicially affected.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            71.7. In its affidavit-in-reply filed on 23.09.2021, the Commission has asserted that it
            <lb />
            will check the eligibility of the required number of candidates for interview at the
            <lb />
            ratio prescribed. It has further averred that a list of selected candidates and a list
            <lb />
            of rejected candidates are ready for publication before declaration of the OMR
            <lb />
            based screening test&apos;s results and the same have not been published due to the
            <lb />
            operation of the interim order. The Commission in its affidavit has further averred
            <lb />
            that instructions were issued to invigilators to verify the identity of the candidates
            <lb />
            who appeared in the screening test by taking into account the photograph and
            <lb />
            the facsimile signature of the candidates so as to prevent impersonation.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            71.8. In view of the above fact situation obtaining in the case, more particularly, to
            <lb />
            protect the interests of the eligible candidates the Commission shall ensure to
            <lb />
            remove the names of such candidates who did not have the requisite qualification
            <lb />
            on the last date of submission of the application, prior to shortlisting and
            <lb />
            publication of the list of eligible candidates to appear in the viva-voce/interview in
            <lb />
            the ratio of 1:3. The Commission shall also ensure that no two or more persons
            <lb />
            had appeared in the name of one single individual against whom more than one
            <lb />
            admit card had been issued.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            72.
            <lb />
            Summing up, both the writ petitions are dismissed. The interim orders stand
            <lb />
            recalled. The State respondents and the Commission are at liberty to proceed
            <lb />
            with the selection processes initiated by the Advertisement no. 06/2019 to bring
            <lb />
            the same to its logical conclusion by taking into consideration the observations
            <lb />
            made above. There shall, however, be no order as to cost.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            JUDGE
            <lb />
            Comparing Assistant
        </p>


    </text>
</tei>