<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc xml:id="0" />
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <p>
            The Mission Director, National Health Mission, Assam
            <lb />
            operates a scheme called &quot;Free Adarani Pick-up and Dropback
            <lb />
            Services&quot; in the state of Assam. A Notice inviting Expression of
            <lb />
            Interest (hereinafter referred to as &quot;EOI&quot;) was issued by the
            <lb />
            Mission Director, National Health Mission, Assam on 24.12.2020
            <lb />
            for shortlisting of eligible service providers for participating in a
            <lb />
            Request for Proposal (RFP) for the process for selection for being
            <lb />
            awarded the contract for operation and management of the said
            <lb />
            services. In response to the said EOI, as many as 5 (five) bidders
            <lb />
            submitted their bids including the present petitioner and the
            <lb />
            private respondent No. 3. During the process of evaluation of bids
            <lb />
            offered, the respondent No. 3&apos;s bid although initially was not
            <lb />
            found technically accepted, but subsequently it was also
            <lb />
            recommended for issuance of RFP alongwith other Bidders
            <lb />
            including the petitioner. The Respondent No. 3 was finally
            <lb />
            shortlisted as the L-1 Bidder. Being aggrieved, petitioner filed the
            <lb />
            writ petition being W.P.(C) No. 4543/2021 challenging the
            <lb />
            decision of the National Health Mission, Assam of permitting the
            <lb />
            respondent No. 3 to submit its Request for Proposal. During the
            <lb />
            pendency of this writ petition in the course of hearing, the
            <lb />
            petitioner came to be informed that the work order for the award
            <lb />
            of the contract was issued to the respondent No. 3. Accordingly,
            <lb />
            the W.P(C) No. 4683/2021 came to be filed by the petitioner
            <lb />
            challenging the letter of intent issued. This Court vide the order
            <lb />
            dated 22.09.2021 while issuing notice had suspended the work
            <lb />
            order dated 31.08.2021 till the next returnable date. The interim
            <lb />
            order passed subsequently came to be extended on various dates.
            <lb />
            Since both the writ petitions were connected together, the
            <lb />
            matters were taken up for hearing on various dates and was
            <lb />
            finally reserved for Judgment.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            2.
            <lb />
            The NHM, Assam issued a Notice inviting EOI for shortlisting
            <lb />
            of eligible applicants to participate in the RFP process for
            <lb />
            operation and management of &quot;Free Adarani Pick-up &amp; Dropback
            <lb />
            Services&quot; in the State of Assam under the Janani Shishu Suraksha
            <lb />
            Karyakram (JSSK). The Services, Target Group &amp; Coverage as
            <lb />
            specified under Clause-1.2 of the EOI indicates that the proposed
            <lb />
            services require 373 Vehicles covering all districts to be provided
            <lb />
            by the service providers. The Objectives &amp; Goals of the Project
            <lb />
            provides inter alia for creating better transportation facility in
            <lb />
            general to reduce the vulnerability of the New Mother and infants
            <lb />
            by providing accessibility at free of cost. It would provide pick up
            <lb />
            facility for postnatal check-ups of pregnant women from their
            <lb />
            homes to their nearest hospitals and for their return back to their
            <lb />
            homes.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            3.
            <lb />
            Initially the last date of submission of the EOI was 12.01.2021
            <lb />
            upto 2 PM. Thereafter, by a Corrigendum issued for submission of EOI
            <lb />
            was extended upto 1 PM of 22.01.2021. The purpose of the EOI is
            <lb />
            provided for under Clause 3.1. As per Para 1.2 of the EOI, the Authority
            <lb />
            will shortlist the qualified applicants as per eligibility criteria given under
            <lb />
            Para 1.2. Upon completion of the said shortlisting in the EOI process,
            <lb />
            the Authority shall recommend for issuance of the Request for Proposal
            <lb />
            (hereinafter referred to as &quot;RFP&quot;) to the shortlisted applicants requesting
            <lb />
            them to submit detailed proposal as per the RFP terms and conditions.
            <lb />
            In the RFP stage, the most suitable applicants shall be selected for
            <lb />
            award for contract based on evaluation of proposal submitted. As per
            <lb />
            the eligibility criteria prescribed under Clause 3.2, the Authority will
            <lb />
            shortlist the applicants in the EOI process for issuance of the RFP to the
            <lb />
            shortlisted applicants.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            4.
            <lb />
            On 25.01.2021, the Tender Committee meeting was held for
            <lb />
            examination of bids submitted for the EOI. Out of the Five (5) bidders,
            <lb />
            three (3) bidders were technically accepted. The three acceptable
            <lb />
            bidders are: a) M/s Ziqitza Health Care Limited, b) M/s GVK EMRI and c)
            <lb />
            M/s Community Action through motivation Programme &quot;CAMP&quot;. The
            <lb />
            petitioner was among the three (3) acceptable bidders. Respondent No.
            <lb />
            3 and one M/S Kria Health Care Pvt. Ltd. were held to be not technically
            <lb />
            acceptable. Details in respect of each of the five (5) bidders as is evident
            <lb />
            from the Minutes of the meeting held on 25.01.2021 extracted below for
            <lb />
            convenience.
        </p>
        <lb />
        <table>
            Sl No
            <lb />
            Firm Name
            <lb />
            Deviation if any from the EOI terms and
            <lb />
            conditions
            <lb />
            Result
            <lb />
            1
            <lb />
            M/s
            <lb />
            Ziqitza
            <lb />
            Health
            <lb />
            Care
            <lb />
            Limited
            <lb />
            No deviation
            <lb />
            Technically accepted
            <lb />
            2
            <lb />
            M/s GVK EMRI
            <lb />
            No deviation
            <lb />
            Technically accepted
            <lb />
            3
            <lb />
            M/s Community
            <lb />
            Action through
            <lb />
            motivation
            <lb />
            Programme
            <lb />
            &quot;CAMP&quot;.
            <lb />
            No Deviation
            <lb />
            Technically accepted
            <lb />
            4
            <lb />
            M/s
            <lb />
            Pashupatinath
            <lb />
            Ltd
            <lb />
            The experience details submitted by M/s
            <lb />
            Pashupatinath Ltd is a combination of
            <lb />
            experience of 2 firms namely Pashupati and
            <lb />
            Samman Foundation. The party had not
            <lb />
            clarified the matter inspite seeking the same
            <lb />
            through email. Hence, it is understood, that
            <lb />
            the party does not meet the eligibility criteria
            <lb />
            3.2.1
            <lb />
            Technically
            <lb />
            not
            <lb />
            accepted
            <lb />
            5
            <lb />
            M/S Kria Health
            <lb />
            Care Pvt Ltd
            <lb />
            (i)The party does not have average annual
            <lb />
            turnover of Rs 10 crores. They have
            <lb />
            standalone turnover of Rs. 6.23 crores. They
            <lb />
            have consortium turnover of Rs 23.22 crores,
            <lb />
            which cannot be considered as per EOI terms
            <lb />
            and conditions. (ii)The party has not properly
            <lb />
            Technically
            <lb />
            not
            <lb />
            accepted
            <lb />
            indicated the total no of vehicles operated by
            <lb />
            them as on 30.11.2020. Hence they deviate
            <lb />
            from the EOI clause 3.2.2
            <lb />
        </table>

        <p>
            5.
            <lb />
            The Committee, therefore, recommended the three (3) shortlisted
            <lb />
            bidders for seeking detailed RFP for the &quot;Free Adarani Pick-up and
            <lb />
            Dropback Services&quot; in the state of Assam. The said tender summary
            <lb />
            report was also uploaded on the website on 11.02.2021. The Tender
            <lb />
            Committee recommended issuance of the Request for Proposal (RFP)
            <lb />
            from the three shortlisted bidders including the writ petitioner.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            6.
            <lb />
            In the RFP, the process for Technical Evaluation is prescribed
            <lb />
            under Clause 1.10. As per Clause 1.10.5, the Technical Evaluation of the
            <lb />
            bidders will be carried out in terms of the criteria provided under the
            <lb />
            said Clause. In terms of the said Clause, the applicant/bidder who fails
            <lb />
            to score a minimum of 60 marks out of the 100 marks in technical
            <lb />
            evaluation shall not qualified for further evaluation. Financial Evaluation
            <lb />
            is prescribed under Clause 1.10.6. Under the said Clause, it is provided
            <lb />
            inter alia that the technically qualified applicant/bidder having the lowest
            <lb />
            financial quote will be declared as the winner and invited for signing the
            <lb />
            contract. The Authority however reserved their rights to invite the
            <lb />
            second lowest applicant for signing the contract at the lowest rate in
            <lb />
            case the preferred L-1 bidder fails to execute the contract within due
            <lb />
            date for whatever reasons.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            7.
            <lb />
            Subsequently, the petitioner came to be informed that the
            <lb />
            Authority reviewed its earlier decision held on 15.02.2021 and thereby
            <lb />
            arrived at a conclusion that respondent No. 3&apos;s bid was also technically
            <lb />
            acceptable and therefore, it recommended issuance of RPF to the
            <lb />
            Respondent No. 3 as well in addition to the other three (3) shortlisted
            <lb />
            bidders including the petitioner. Thereafter, financial bid was opened on
            <lb />
            31.03.2021 in which the respondent No. 3 was shortlisted as the
            <lb />
            selected bidder. The petitioner represented before the Authority against
            <lb />
            the shortlisting of the respondent No. 3 raising their objections on the
            <lb />
            eligibility qualification by their E-mail dated 19.05.2021. Subsequently,
            <lb />
            another representation was preferred before the Mission Director, NHM,
            <lb />
            Assam vide representation dated 23.05.2021. Similar representations
            <lb />
            were also submitted on 15.07.2021 as well as on 02.08.2021. A
            <lb />
            representation to that effect was also submitted before the Principal
            <lb />
            Secretary, Health and Family Welfare Department by representation
            <lb />
            dated 02.09.2021. However, since their representations remained
            <lb />
            unattended, the petitioner preferred the writ petition challenging the
            <lb />
            shortlisting of the respondent No. 3 pursuant to its initial rejection as
            <lb />
            being &quot;technically not accepted&quot; as well as the subsequent work order
            <lb />
            issued on 31.08.2021 to the respondent No. 3 as the L-1 bidder.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            8.
            <lb />
            In the present proceedings, the petitioner assails the shortlisting of
            <lb />
            the respondent No. 3 at the EOI stage and as well the selection of the
            <lb />
            respondent No. 3 in the RFP stage leading to issuance of the work order
            <lb />
            on two grounds.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            a) The petitioner assails the shortlisting of the respondent No. 3 at
            <lb />
            the EOI stage by review of the earlier order by the Authorities
            <lb />
            on the ground that review is a creature of the statute and in the
            <lb />
            context of the NIT when there is no specific power conferred
            <lb />
            upon the Authority/Tender Evaluation Committee in the NIT, it
            <lb />
            was impermissible for the Authority to review its earlier order
            <lb />
            and which was also uploaded in the website. It is contended
            <lb />
            that once an order is passed on the basis of the materials
            <lb />
            available before the Authority concerned, in the absence of any
            <lb />
            specific provision/power conferred under the various clauses of
            <lb />
            the NIT, the action of the Authority in qualifying the
            <lb />
            Respondent No. 3 vide their meeting held on 17.02.2021 is
            <lb />
            completely arbitrary inasmuch as by the earlier meeting held on
            <lb />
            25.01.2021. The Respondent No. 3 was considered to be
            <lb />
            &quot;technically not accepted&quot; as the experience details submitted
            <lb />
            by respondent No. 3 is a combination of experience of two (2)
            <lb />
            firms namely M/S Pashupati and M/s Samman Foundation. It is
            <lb />
            contended that the party does not meet the eligibility criteria
            <lb />
            3.2.1. It is contended that where the Authority has not been
            <lb />
            bestowed with any power to review its own order, a delegatee
            <lb />
            of the said Authority namely, the Tender Evaluation Committee,
            <lb />
            cannot review its earlier order passed. Such action adopted by
            <lb />
            the Tender Evaluation Committee not being specifically
            <lb />
            provided for in the NIT, the order of shortlisting the respondent
            <lb />
            No. 3 by the Tender Evaluation Committee vide its meeting held
            <lb />
            on 17.02.2021, by reviewing its earlier order dated 25.01.2021
            <lb />
            is arbitrary and colorable exercise of power and therefore, bad
            <lb />
            in law and needs to be suitably interfered with.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            b) The second contention of the petitioner is that on the facts it
            <lb />
            was not disputed that the experience projected by the
            <lb />
            Respondent No. 3, as required under the eligibility criteria of
            <lb />
            the NIT, was in respect of Ambulatory Services offered in the
            <lb />
            State of Bihar by the Respondent No. 3 in a joint venture with
            <lb />
            another organization i.e. M/S Samman Foundation. As such the
            <lb />
            experience gathered by a consortium cannot be individually
            <lb />
            claimed by a constituent of the consortium. It is contended that
            <lb />
            unless the respondent No. 3 can submit credentials for its
            <lb />
            experience in its individual capacity, any experience gathered as
            <lb />
            a constituent of the consortium cannot be claimed individually
            <lb />
            by a constituent i.e. namely the Respondent No. 3. As Clause
            <lb />
            3.2.1 specifically debars any consortium form participation and
            <lb />
            only permits single entity registered under appropriate laws in
            <lb />
            India, the action of the Authority in shortlisting the respondent
            <lb />
            No. 3 at the EOI stage for the purposes of issuance of the RFP
            <lb />
            by taking into consideration the experience gathered as a
            <lb />
            consortium, is in violation of the Clauses of the NIT and
            <lb />
            therefore, the action of the Authority in shortlisting the
            <lb />
            respondent No. 3 is arbitrary. Consequently, the actions of the
            <lb />
            Authority being arbitrary and colorable, the work order issued
            <lb />
            to respondent No. 3 should be interfered with, set aside and
            <lb />
            quashed and direction be issued to the respondents/Authorities
            <lb />
            to finalize the tender process in favour of the petitioner/society.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            9.
            <lb />
            In respect of the first contention Mr. U.K. Nair, learned Senior
            <lb />
            Counsel for the petitioner relying upon the Judgment of the Apex Court
            <lb />
            rendered in Patel Narshi Thakershi and Ors. Vs. Shri Pradyumansinghji ,
            <lb />
            reported in (1971) 3 SCC 844 submits that if the Authority is not
            <lb />
            empowered to review its own order then a delegatee of the said
            <lb />
            Authority namely the Tender Evaluation Committee cannot have the
            <lb />
            power to review its own order passed earlier.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            10. In respect of the second contention, the learned Senior counsel for
            <lb />
            the petitioner relies to the Judgment of the Apex Court in Municipal
            <lb />
            Corporation of India Ltd &amp; Anr Vs. B.G.V. India Ltd and Ors. reported in
            <lb />
            (2018) 5 SCC 462. The learned Senior counsel for the petitioner submits
            <lb />
            that the Apex Court in this Judgment has held that the bidder who
            <lb />
            submits a bid expressly declaring that it is submitting the same
            <lb />
            independently and without any partners, consortium or joint venture,
            <lb />
            cannot rely upon the technical qualifications of any third party for its
            <lb />
            qualification.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            11. The learned Advocate General appearing for the State respondent
            <lb />
            contested the allegations against them in the writ petition in its affidavit.
            <lb />
            It is submitted that there was absolute transparency in the process and
            <lb />
            the entire process for shortlisting the eligible bidder has been
            <lb />
            undertaken by the NHM in strict compliance of the tender conditions and
            <lb />
            as per the provisions of law applicable. It is submitted that the
            <lb />
            allegations of the petitioner are completely unfounded and the actions of
            <lb />
            the Authority being administrative in nature, the ratio laid down in the
            <lb />
            Judgment of Patel Narshi Thakershi and Ors. Vs. Shri Pradyumansinghji
            <lb />
            reported in (1971) 3 SCC 844 is not applicable as the same is in respect
            <lb />
            of a Quasi Judicial function. It is submitted that as per the Clause of the
            <lb />
            EOI during the preliminary scrutiny, the Authority is permitted to seek
            <lb />
            further clarifications, explanations or information on any issue relating to
            <lb />
            the eligibility till such time the committee is fully convinced.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            12. The learned Advocate General relied on a catena of Judgments of
            <lb />
            the Apex Court and strenuously urged that in matters of commercial
            <lb />
            contracts and settlement of Government tenders, the scope of judicial
            <lb />
            review under Article 226 is extremely circumscribed. It is submitted that
            <lb />
            since public interest and public finance are involved, the Authority has to
            <lb />
            take every precaution to ensure that the most suitable bidder is
            <lb />
            shortlisted or selected for award of the contract. The Respondent No. 3
            <lb />
            was a lead partner of the consortium, which had rendered Ambulatory
            <lb />
            Services in the State of Bihar. The Government of Bihar has also
            <lb />
            certified by issuing necessary communication that the services rendered
            <lb />
            by the respondent No. 3 as the lead partner of the consortium is
            <lb />
            satisfactory. Referring to New Horizons Limited Vs. Union of India
            <lb />
            reported in (1995) 1 SCC 478 the learned Senior counsel submitted that
            <lb />
            the experience gathered as a member of a consortium can also be relied
            <lb />
            upon in matters where the components of the consortium participates
            <lb />
            individually. In the facts of the present case, the respondent No. 3 was a
            <lb />
            lead partner and it has submitted its necessary credentials to support its
            <lb />
            claim that it had executed similar Ambulatory Services in the State of
            <lb />
            Bihar. Referring to the communication received from the State of Bihar,
            <lb />
            in response to queries made by the NHM, Assam, the learned Advocate
            <lb />
            General submits that there has been no occasion for complaint in
            <lb />
            respect of similar Ambulatory Services offered by the respondent No. 3
            <lb />
            as a lead partner of the consortium in the State of Bihar. Under such
            <lb />
            circumstances, no fault can be attributed to the Authority in accepting
            <lb />
            the experience gathered by respondent No. 3 as a lead partner of the
            <lb />
            consortium in the State of Bihar to consider its eligibility in the present
            <lb />
            tender process. The law laid down by the Apex Court in New Horizons
            <lb />
            Limited (Supra) is still a good law and has not been overruled in
            <lb />
            subsequent Judgments.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            13. Mr. A.K. Bhattacharjee, learned Senior counsel assisted by Mr. S.
            <lb />
            Dutta contested the claims of the petitioner on behalf of shortlisted
            <lb />
            bidder namely M/S Pashupathinath Distributors Pvt. Limited which is
            <lb />
            arrayed as respondent No. 3 in the present proceedings. Mr.
            <lb />
            Bhattacharjee, learned Senior counsel strenuously urged that the offer
            <lb />
            of the respondent No. 3 is proper in all respects and that apart it was
            <lb />
            the lowest bidder. The learned Senior counsel urged that the contention
            <lb />
            of the petitioner that the shortlisting of the respondent No. 3 by the
            <lb />
            Authority vide the second meeting dated 25.01.2021 is impermissible in
            <lb />
            the absence of any specific provision for review under the Clause of the
            <lb />
            EOI and that such action of the Authority is completely unacceptable as
            <lb />
            the said proposition is alien in the realm of commercial contracts and
            <lb />
            administrative actions carried out by the State. Such an argument is
            <lb />
            totally misconceived and is based upon incorrect interpretation of law.
            <lb />
            The learned Senior counsel submits that if the proposition of there being
            <lb />
            no review available to an administrative authority while rendering its
            <lb />
            administrative functions, in the absence of any specific provisions, is to
            <lb />
            be accepted then it will lead to completely anomalous situation. The
            <lb />
            learned Senior counsel urged that the EOI is not a part of any statute. It
            <lb />
            is a tender floated by the Government and the terms and conditions
            <lb />
            mentioned in the tender clearly permits the Authority to pass any order
            <lb />
            in order to arrive at a just conclusion. The learned Senior counsel relies
            <lb />
            on the Judgments of the Apex Court in R.R. Verma &amp; Ors. Vs. Union of
            <lb />
            India &amp; Ors. reported in (1980) 3 SCC 402 and State of H.P &amp; Ors. Vs.
            <lb />
            Rajesh Chander Sood &amp; Ors. reported in (2016) 10 SCC 77. The learned
            <lb />
            Senior counsel further urged that in administrative functions, the bar of
            <lb />
            review unless prescribed as sought to be urged by the petitioner is
            <lb />
            completely not applicable. The learned Senior counsel urged that the
            <lb />
            writ petition at the behest of unsuccessful tenderer is not acceptable
            <lb />
            and the law in this regard has been consistent all throughout since the
            <lb />
            Raunaq International Ltd. Vs. I.V.R. Construction Ltd., reported in
            <lb />
            (1999) 1 SCC 492. The further contention of the learned Senior counsel
            <lb />
            is that the experience of the respondent No. 3 gathered as a constituent
            <lb />
            member of a consortium is available to be relied upon in respect of such
            <lb />
            a constituent member more particularly when the constituent was a lead
            <lb />
            partner of a consortium. Under such circumstances, there is no infirmity
            <lb />
            in the shortlisting of the respondent No. 3 for RFP and consequent
            <lb />
            issuance of work order by the Authority in favour of the respondent No.
            <lb />
            3 upon being declared as the L-1 bidder in respect of the present tender
            <lb />
            process. The learned Senior counsel further urged that besides there
            <lb />
            being no merit, the writ petition ought to be dismissed on the ground of
            <lb />
            delay and laches as the petitioner was well aware of the shortlisting of
            <lb />
            the Respondent No. 3 being shortlisted for issuance of RFP and its
            <lb />
            participates in the RFP process as far back as atleast 07.06.2021 but the
            <lb />
            petitioner chose to approach this writ Court only on 09.09.2021 after the
            <lb />
            issuance of the work order dated 31.08.2021 to respondent No. 3. The
            <lb />
            learned Senior counsel submits that pursuant to the work order issued
            <lb />
            the respondent No. 3 has undertaken substantial investments in order to
            <lb />
            mobilize men and materials for undertaking the &quot;Free Adarani Pick-up
            <lb />
            and Dropback Services&quot; contract of which is offered to the respondent
            <lb />
            No. 3. The learned Senior counsel, therefore, submits that the interim
            <lb />
            order dated 22.09.2021 passed by this Court has caused substantial
            <lb />
            losses to the respondent No. 3. Therefore, the interim order be vacated
            <lb />
            and the writ petition be dismissed and costs imposed on the petitioner.
            <lb />
            In support of its contentions, the learned Senior counsel refers to the
            <lb />
            Judgments of State of M.P Vs. Nandwal Jaiswal reported in (1986) 4 SCC
            <lb />
            566, Ascon (M/s) &amp; Anr Vs. State of Assam reported in 2017 (5) GLT
            <lb />
            875 and Maa Chandi Stone Crushing Vs. Chief Engineer reported in 2005
            <lb />
            SCC OnlineOri 1 to contend that the relief in writ proceedings is not
            <lb />
            available to a litigant on account of delay and creation of third party
            <lb />
            rights.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            14. I have heard the learned counsels for the parties and I have also
            <lb />
            carefully perused the pleadings on record and the case laws cited in
            <lb />
            support of their contentions. Records of the Tender Process which were
            <lb />
            called for have also been furnished for perusal of the Court.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            15.
            <lb />
            Before proceeding further, it would be necessary to refer to
            <lb />
            some of the relevant clauses of the EOI. By the Notice inviting EOI, the
            <lb />
            Mission Director, NHM, Assam invited eligible applicants/bidders for
            <lb />
            shortlisting to participate in the RFP process for the operation and
            <lb />
            management of &quot;Free Adarani Pick-up and Dropback Services&quot; in the
            <lb />
            State of Assam under JSSK. The key information provided are as under:
            <lb />
        </p>

        <table>
            S.No
            <lb />
            Key Information/ Events
            <lb />
            Time/Venue/Address
            <lb />
            1
            <lb />
            Date of issue of the EOI Document Date: 24/12/2020
            <lb />
            2
            <lb />
            Last date of download of EOI
            <lb />
            Document
            <lb />
            Date: 24/12/2020
            <lb />
            3
            <lb />
            Date of Pre-submission meeting
            <lb />
            Date: 04/01/2021
            <lb />
            4
            <lb />
            Due date and Time of submission
            <lb />
            (online&amp; Hard Copy)
            <lb />
            Date: 18/01/2021 (Subsequently extended till
            <lb />
            22.01.2021)
            <lb />
        </table>

        <p>
            16. The Objectives and Goals of the projects are provided under
            <lb />
            Clause 1.3. The relevant portion of which is extracted below:
        </p>
        <lb />
        <item>
            &quot;1.3.1 Creating better transportation facility in general to reduce the
            <lb />
            vulnerability of the New Mother and infants by providing accessibility
            <lb />
            at free of cost is the underlying principle of Adarani. It complements
            <lb />
            the Janani Shishu Suraksha Karyakram which provides cash
            <lb />
            incentives to women availing institutional delivery and the members
            <lb />
            supporting them in the process like ASHA.
        </item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            1.3.2 To operate the service from a centralized state of the art call
            <lb />
            centre (Control Room) with computer telephony integration,
            <lb />
            computer aided dispatch of vehicles and ability to log calls with GIS
            <lb />
            based GPRS integrated vehicle monitoring system for Adarani-Drop
            <lb />
            back and Pickup Service in the State of Assam.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            1.3.3 It would provide Dropback service to JSSK beneficiaries
            <lb />
            through Adarani Vehicles from 7am to 6 pm on 365 days in a year
            <lb />
            basis as per 12 hr shift operation due to the early sunrise and
            <lb />
            remoteness of rural areas prevailing in this North-eastern part of the
            <lb />
            country.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            1.3.4 It would provide pick up facility for postnatal check-ups of
            <lb />
            pregnant women from their homes to their nearest hospitals and
            <lb />
            return back to their homes.
            <lb />
            …………….&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            17. The Purpose of the EOI is provided under Clause 3.1. The
            <lb />
            relevant portion of which is extracted below:
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;Purpose of this EOI is to shortlist qualified Applicants as per the
            <lb />
            eligibility criteria given under para 1.2 (i.e. EOI Stage). Subsequent
            <lb />
            to the completion of the EOI process for shortlisting, the Authority
            <lb />
            shall issue RFP to the shortlisted applicants requesting them to
            <lb />
            submit a detailed proposal ( financial &amp; Technical) as per the FRP
            <lb />
            terms and conditions (i.e. RFP Stage). In the RFP stage, the most
            <lb />
            suitable Applicant shall be selected for award of contract based on
            <lb />
            the evaluation of the proposals submitted.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            18. The Eligibility Criteria is prescribed under Clause 3.2. The relevant
            <lb />
            portion of which is extracted below:
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;3.2.1 The Applicant (or the Firm intending to participate in the EOI
            <lb />
            process) must be a single entity (consortiums not allowed)
            <lb />
            registered under appropriate laws in India.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            3.2.2 The Applicant should have a minimum three years of business
            <lb />
            experience and out of which at least one (1) year in successfully
            <lb />
            handling similar JSSK services in public sector with a minimum of
            <lb />
            300 vehicles as of 30/11/2020.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            3.2.3 Satisfactory experience in call centre based vehicle
            <lb />
            management and operation with GIS based GPRS integrated vehicle
            <lb />
            monitoring system. The party has to produce supporting documents
            <lb />
            to this effect including certificate from the Client or the Authority
            <lb />
            valid for the above motioned period.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            3.2.4 Average Annual Turnover of the Applicant in the last three
            <lb />
            financial years i.e. 2017-18, 2018-19 and 2019-20 from similar
            <lb />
            activity should not be less than Rs. 1,000.00 Lakhs (Rupees ten
            <lb />
            crores only). The average annual turnover certificate as issued by
            <lb />
            the of Auditor/Chartered Accountant should be submitted in the
            <lb />
            format enclosed as Annexure 3 of this EOI document. The Certificate
            <lb />
            must be accompanied by attested copies of audited Statement of
            <lb />
            Accounts of last three financial years (i.e. 2017-18, 2018-19 and
            <lb />
            2019-20).
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            3.2.5 Entities blacklisted by the Inviting Authority or by any State
            <lb />
            Government or Central Government Organization shall not be
            <lb />
            allowed to participate in the process during the period of blacklisting.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            3.2.6. Registration: The Party should be registered under Income
            <lb />
            Tax , GST and relevant Labour Laws including Employees Provident
            <lb />
            Fund Organization, Employees State Insurance Corporation etc., as
            <lb />
            prescribed by law.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            19. The Evaluation and Shortlisting is prescribed under Clause 4. The
            <lb />
            relevant portion of which is extracted below:
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;4.1 Preliminary Scrutiny
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            4.1.1 All the applications (online &amp; hardcopy) received within due
            <lb />
            date and time shall only be considered by the Evaluation Committee.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            4.1.2 The evaluation committee shall first ensure that the
            <lb />
            applications are complete in all respect. Only those applications
            <lb />
            which are complete in all respect shall be considered for further
            <lb />
            scrutiny.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            4.1.3 Evaluation Committee reserves the right to seek further
            <lb />
            clarifications, explanation or information on any issue relating to the
            <lb />
            eligibility till such time the Committee is fully convinced.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            4.1.4 NHM shall finalize the list of the Applicants to be empaneled
            <lb />
            based on the evaluation and decision of the authority on the same
            <lb />
            shall be final and binding.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            4.1.5 Names of the Applicants shortlisted (for RFP process) as per
            <lb />
            the evaluation of the EOI Application will be hosted on our website
            <lb />
            on completion of all formalities. No correspondence on the above
            <lb />
            subject will be entertained.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            4.1.6 NHM, Assam reserves the right to reject any or all applications
            <lb />
            without assigning any reason(s) thereof.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            20. The issue of RFP for selection is prescribed under Clause 4.2. The
            <lb />
            relevant portion of which is extracted below:
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;2.2.1 Detailed Proposal shall be invited by NHM from the
            <lb />
            shortlisted Applicants (Parties) issuing RFP. In the RFP document all
            <lb />
            technical and operational details shall be furnished. At this stage the
            <lb />
            parties have to submit detailed technical and financial proposal for
            <lb />
            evaluation and selection of most suitable amongst them, as per the
            <lb />
            proposal submitted.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            2.2.2 The selection of the firm shall be strictly on the basis of most
            <lb />
            preferable bid received in response to the RFP, as per the terms and
            <lb />
            conditions and specifications mentioned therein.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            21. The Tender Committee in its meeting held on 25.01.2021, after
            <lb />
            examining the various EOIs submitted by the bidders, shortlisted three
            <lb />
            (3) bidders at the EOI stage, out of the five (5) bidders who submitted
            <lb />
            its bids. The petitioner was among the shortlisted bidders in the EOI
            <lb />
            process and the Respondent No. 3 and another bidder were declared as
            <lb />
            &quot;Technically not accepted&quot;. Details of which as provided in the Minutes
            <lb />
            dated 25.01.2021 is extracted below:
        </p>
        <lb />
        <table>
            Sl No
            <lb />
            Firm Name
            <lb />
            Deviation if any from the EOI terms and
            <lb />
            conditions
            <lb />
            Result
            <lb />
            1
            <lb />
            M/s
            <lb />
            Ziqitza
            <lb />
            Health
            <lb />
            Care
            <lb />
            Limited
            <lb />
            No deviation
            <lb />
            Technically accepted
            <lb />
            2
            <lb />
            M/s GVK EMRI
            <lb />
            No deviation
            <lb />
            Technically accepted
            <lb />
            3
            <lb />
            M/s Community
            <lb />
            Action through
            <lb />
            motivation
            <lb />
            Programme
            <lb />
            &quot;CAMP&quot;.
            <lb />
            No Deviation
            <lb />
            Technically accepted
            <lb />
            4
            <lb />
            M/s
            <lb />
            Pashupatinath
            <lb />
            Ltd
            <lb />
            The experience details submitted by M/s
            <lb />
            Pashupatinath Ltd is a combination of
            <lb />
            experience of 2 firms namely Pashupati and
            <lb />
            Samman Foundation. The party had not
            <lb />
            clarified the matter inspite seeking the same
            <lb />
            through email. Hence, it is understood, that
            <lb />
            the party does not meet the eligibility criteria
            <lb />
            3.2.1
            <lb />
            Technically
            <lb />
            not
            <lb />
            accepted
            <lb />
            5
            <lb />
            M/S Kria Health
            <lb />
            Care Pvt Ltd
            <lb />
            (i)The party does not have average annual
            <lb />
            turnover of Rs 10 crores. They have
            <lb />
            standalone turnover of Rs. 6.23 crores. They
            <lb />
            have consortium turnover of Rs 23.22 crores,
            <lb />
            which cannot be considered as per EOI terms
            <lb />
            and conditions. (ii)The party has not properly
            <lb />
            indicated the total no of vehicles operated by
            <lb />
            them as on 30.11.2020. Hence they deviate
            <lb />
            from the EOI clause 3.2.2
            <lb />
            Technically
            <lb />
            not
            <lb />
            accepted
            <lb />
        </table>

        <p>
            22. The shortlisted bidders were recommended for issuance of RFP for
            <lb />
            selection and award of the order for operation and management for
            <lb />
            &quot;Free Adarani Pick-up and Dropback Services&quot; in the State of Assam.
            <lb />
            The respondent No. 3 represented that there was no communication
            <lb />
            received either in writing or verbal from the Office of NHM regarding any
            <lb />
            clarifications sought for, as reflected in the Minutes dated 25.01.2021
            <lb />
            and therefore, they were not aware of such clarifications sought for. The
            <lb />
            Respondent No. 3, therefore, requested for re-consideration of their bid
            <lb />
            and any such clarifications as may be sought for by the NHM will
            <lb />
            accordingly be furnished by the respondent No. 3. Pursuant to the
            <lb />
            representation dated 15.02.2021 submitted by the respondent No. 3 to
            <lb />
            Mission Director, NHM, Assam requesting for recall or re-evaluation of
            <lb />
            the findings of the Bid Evaluation Committee meeting held on
            <lb />
            25.01.2021, the Authority took the views of the procurement expert who
            <lb />
            in turn advised that the experience of respondent No. 3 as a lead
            <lb />
            partner in the consortium can be considered. The committee thereafter
            <lb />
            reviewed it&apos;s earlier decision in its meeting held on 17.02.2021. In
            <lb />
            addition to the earlier shortlisted bidders including the petitioner, the
            <lb />
            NHM authority also recommended the respondent No. 3 for issuance of
            <lb />
            RFP documents. The Tender Committee thereafter, proceeded for
            <lb />
            Technical Evaluation of the RFP submitted by the bidders shortlisted
            <lb />
            pursuant to EOI stage including the petitioner and the respondent No. 3.
            <lb />
            This meeting was held on 12.03.2021. The Technical Evaluation was
            <lb />
            carried out in terms of the provision of Clause 1.10 of the RFP. As per
            <lb />
            the said Clause, the most preferred bidders must have a qualifying score
            <lb />
            of 60 marks in the technical evaluation as per the provisions of Clause
            <lb />
            1.10.5. All the four (4) shortlisted bidders were found to be &quot;technically
            <lb />
            qualified&quot; in terms of the criteria laid down as per Clause 1.10.5. The
            <lb />
            Authority thereafter proceeded for financial bid opening. The financial
            <lb />
            bids were opened on 31.03.2021. As per the comparative statement
            <lb />
            prepared by the Authority, the financial bid offered by the respondent
            <lb />
            No. 3 was considered to be the lowest and accordingly, the tender
            <lb />
            committee recommended the respondent No. 3. However, it was also
            <lb />
            recommended that a performance and feasibility report be called for
            <lb />
            from Bihar NHM to assess the feasibility and capability of the respondent
            <lb />
            No. 3 in running the &quot;Free Adarani Pick-up and Dropback Services&quot; The
            <lb />
            respondent No. 3 being the L-1 bidder, work order vide the order dated
            <lb />
            31.08.2021 was issued by the NHM Authority. The work order was
            <lb />
            issued to Respondent No. 3 after receipt of feedback from the Bihar,
            <lb />
            NHM, which was found to be satisfactory. The comparative statement
            <lb />
            prepared by the Authority as available in the Minutes of the financial bid
            <lb />
            opening are extracted below for convenience:
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            &quot;The Comparative Statement of the Financial Bid is given below (Annexure)
            <lb />
            a) Price officered by the technically qualified bidders for Adarani Drop Back and
            <lb />
            Pick Up Services:
        </p>
        <lb />
        <table>
            Sl No Name of the
            <lb />
            bidder
            <lb />
            Monthly
            <lb />
            Service
            <lb />
            Charges per
            <lb />
            vehicle per
            <lb />
            month in Rs.
            <lb />
            Quantity
            <lb />
            Total Monthly
            <lb />
            charges per
            <lb />
            vehicle/month
            <lb />
            for Adarani
            <lb />
            Drop Back and
            <lb />
            Pick up
            <lb />
            Services
            <lb />
            including GST
            <lb />
            In Rs.
            <lb />
            Awarded
            <lb />
            1
            <lb />
            Pashupati
            <lb />
            Distributors
            <lb />
            Pvt Ltd
            <lb />
            54921.00
            <lb />
            373
            <lb />
            20485533.00
            <lb />
            L1
            <lb />
            2
            <lb />
            Community
            <lb />
            Action
            <lb />
            Through
            <lb />
            Motivation
            <lb />
            Programme
            <lb />
            &quot;Camp&quot;
            <lb />
            79200.00
            <lb />
            373
            <lb />
            29541600.00
            <lb />
            L2
            <lb />
            3.
            <lb />
            GVK-
            <lb />
            Emergency
            <lb />
            Management
            <lb />
            and Research
            <lb />
            Institute
            <lb />
            88110.00
            <lb />
            373
            <lb />
            32865030.00
            <lb />
            L3
            <lb />
            4
            <lb />
            Ziqitza Health
            <lb />
            Care Limited
            <lb />
            88900.00
            <lb />
            373
            <lb />
            33159700.00
            <lb />
            L4
        </table>
        <lb />
        <item>
            Out of the four nos of bidders, the Tender Evaluation Committee
            <lb />
            that Pashupati Distributors Pvt Limited has quoted the lowest price
            <lb />
            (L1) for Operation and Management of Adarani Pick Up and Drop Back
            <lb />
            Services.
        </item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            The Committee recommended that Pashupati Distributors Pvt Limited has
            <lb />
            participated for the first time in Adarani Tender in Assam. They are presently
            <lb />
            running the ambulatory services in Bihar, so a performance report of Pashupati
            <lb />
            Distributors Pvt Limited may be obtained from NHM, Bihar to access the
            <lb />
            feasibility and capability of Pashupati Distributors Pvt Limited to run the Adarani
            <lb />
            Drop Back Services in Assam.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            Sd/-
            <lb />
            Sd/-
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            BME
            <lb />
            Programme Executive
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            Sd/-
            <lb />
            Sd/-
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            Director Finance &amp; Accounts
            <lb />
            AMD AMSCL&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            23. From a perusal of the Tender Notice, it is seen that the Notice
            <lb />
            inviting EOI has three (3) stages of evaluation. The bids offered by the
            <lb />
            intending bidders were initially scrutinized and evaluated under the said
            <lb />
            tender process as specified under Clause 4. The eligibility criteria for
            <lb />
            such an evaluation is prescribed under Clause 3.2. It is only upon the
            <lb />
            said preliminary scrutiny and evaluation that the Authority will choose to
            <lb />
            recommend the bidders from whom the RFP will be sought for. In terms
            <lb />
            of the said Clause, during the process of preliminary evaluation, the
            <lb />
            Evaluation
            <lb />
            Committee
            <lb />
            is
            <lb />
            empowered
            <lb />
            to
            <lb />
            seek
            <lb />
            clarifications/explanations/information of any issue relating to the
            <lb />
            eligibility till such time, the committee is fully convinced. Upon the
            <lb />
            preliminary scrutiny, the Authority will recommend the intending bidders
            <lb />
            from whom the RFP will be sought for. Thereafter, the RFP submitted by
            <lb />
            the bidders, will be subject to technical evaluation as provided for under
            <lb />
            Clause 1.10.5. Upon being technically qualified, the financial bids of the
            <lb />
            technically qualified bidders will be opened and evaluated as per Clause
            <lb />
            1.10.6. Upon due perusal of the various Clauses in the EOI and the RFP,
            <lb />
            it is seen that the evaluation of the tender involves three (3) different
            <lb />
            stages of scrutiny and evaluation. As is evident from the affidavit-in-
            <lb />
            opposition filed on behalf of NHM, upon the results of the preliminary
            <lb />
            scrutiny being uploaded in the website, the respondent No. 3
            <lb />
            represented before the department with a request for re-evaluation of
            <lb />
            its decision dated 25.01.2021 wherein the respondent No. 3 was shown
            <lb />
            to be &quot;technically not accepted&quot;. The re-evaluation was sought for
            <lb />
            primarily on the ground that in the details of the Minutes of the meeting
            <lb />
            held on 25.01.2021 uploaded in the website of the NHM, in respect of
            <lb />
            respondent No. 3 whose name appeared in the Sl. No. 4 of the Chart, it
            <lb />
            was mentioned that &quot;the experience details submitted by the M/S
            <lb />
            Pashupatinath Ltd is a combination of experience of 2 firms namely
            <lb />
            pashupati and Samman Foundation. The party had not clarified the
            <lb />
            matter inspite of seeking the same through email. Hence, it is
            <lb />
            understood, that the party does not meet the eligibility criteria 3.2.1.&quot;
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            24. The respondent No. 3 by its representation dated 15.02.2021
            <lb />
            represented as under:
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;Ref.: PDPL/
            <lb />
            Date…………
            <lb />
            BY E-MAIL / SPEED POST
            <lb />
            NHM-001/2021
            <lb />
            15 th February, 2021
        </item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            To,
            <lb />
            The Mission Director,
            <lb />
            National Health Mission, Assam.
            <lb />
            Saikia Commercial Complex, Shrinagar Path.
            <lb />
            Christian Basti, G S Road,
            <lb />
            Guwahati-781005, Assam
            <lb />
            Email-misnrhm.assam@gmail.com
            <lb />
        </item>
        <item>
            Ref: i) Etender-nic@nic.in email dated 11.02.2021 for the Bid 102308;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            ii) Record Note of discussion held on. 25.01.2021 relating to EOI
            <lb />
            Transport-NHM/(Part-1)/24759 dated:24/12/20 For
            <lb />
            and Management of &quot;Free Adarani Pick-Up &amp; Dropback Services&quot; to
            <lb />
            Mother and Neonates as part of Janani Sishu Surakhsha Karayakaram (JSSK) in
            <lb />
            the State of Assam.
        </item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            Dear Sir/s.
            <lb />
            We refer to the Bid Evaluation Committee meeting held on 25.01.2021
            <lb />
            (hereinafter referred to as the &quot;Meeting&quot;) in presence of the Members (Tender
            <lb />
            Committee) and in particular the deliberations, observations, reasons and
            <lb />
            directions given for not accepting the technical bid of our company (hereinafter
            <lb />
            referred to as the &quot;PDPL&quot;) i.e. PDPL (Sl no.4 of Annexure A of the Record Note of
            <lb />
            discussion held on 25.01.2021 relating to EOI No.NHM/24011/8/2018-Referal
            <lb />
            Transport-NHM/(Part-1)/24759)
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            a) At the outset, it is submitted that our &quot;company has not received any verbal or
            <lb />
            written clarification email/letter/communication from National Health Mission,
            <lb />
            Assam, its representatives or from the website of assamtenders.gov.in or anyone
            <lb />
            as mentioned in the Meeting of 25.01.2021. It is pertinent to note that the
            <lb />
            experience details submitted by PDPL is technically correct and qualify the
            <lb />
            eligibility criteria under 3.2.1 of the EOI for the following reasons;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            i)
            <lb />
            PDPL is a company registered under the laws India and has applied for
            <lb />
            the above mentioned bid as a single entity and not as consortium;
            <lb />
            therefore it meets the requirements of 3.2.1 of the EOI.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            ii)
            <lb />
            PDPL meets the eligibility criteria of Business experience (3.2.2 of the
            <lb />
            EOI), experience in call centre based vehicle management and
            <lb />
            operation with GIS based GPRS integrated vehicle monitoring system
            <lb />
            (3.2.3 of the EOI, Average Annual Turnover (3.2.4 of the EOI) along
            <lb />
            with the clause 3.2.5 and 3.2.6 of the EOI. The supporting documents
            <lb />
            for the above are already on record with NHM, which was submitted
            <lb />
            physically to and accepted by NHM on 22.01.2021.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            iii)
            <lb />
            PDPL or its representatives have not received any clarification
            <lb />
            email/letter/communication from National Health Mission, Assam, its
            <lb />
            representatives or from the website of assamtenders.gov.in or anyone
            <lb />
            to seek clarification on the &quot;experience&quot; of PDPL.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            iv)
            <lb />
            It is germane to note that Consortium of PDPL &amp; Samman foundation
            <lb />
            is a different entity from PDPL. To obviate the confusion, it is
            <lb />
            submitted that PDPL for one of the business transactions in the same
            <lb />
            sector formed a Consortium with Samman Foundation naming &quot;PDPL &amp;
            <lb />
            Samman foundation&quot;. Please note that &quot;PDPL &amp; Samman foundation&quot;
            <lb />
            have not applied for the present EOI bid No.NHM/24011/8/2018-
            <lb />
            Transport-NHM/(Part-1)/24759 dated: 24/12/20, rather only
            <lb />
            PDPL as a separate entity has applied for the abovementioned bid.
        </item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            That in the interest of the project, the most suitable Applicant shall be selected
            <lb />
            for award of contract based on the evaluation of the proposal submitted. Keeping
            <lb />
            into the consideration the prominence, credentials, professionalism and
            <lb />
            experience, we request that PDPL should get fair chance to represent itself on
            <lb />
            account of any queries or clarifications required by the Bid Evaluation Committee
            <lb />
            or any NHM representatives before rejecting its technical bids.
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            c) In light of the above facts, it is only in the Interest of justice, besides being
            <lb />
            absolutely necessary for the protection of the interest PDPL to:
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            i)
            <lb />
            Stay and recall the directions, observation and reasoning of the Bid
            <lb />
            Evaluation Committee meeting held on 25.01.2021;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            ii)
            <lb />
            Stay the Bid Evaluation Committee recommendations dated 25.01.2021
            <lb />
            for the empanelment of the agencies namely M/s Ziqtizaa Health care,
            <lb />
            M/s GVK EMRI and M/s Community Action through motivation
            <lb />
            Programme &quot;CAMP&quot; and seeking detailed RFP from them for the further
            <lb />
            process in the bid of Janani Sishu Surakhsha Karayakaram (JSSK).
            <lb />
        </item>

        <item>
            iii)
            <lb />
            re-evaluate the technical bid presented by the bidders after tak
        </item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            iv)
            <lb />
            ing due clarifications if needed by proper email or communications.
        </item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            We request the respected committee to take on record our submissions, while
            <lb />
            passing any further directions as it deems fit and proper. We further submit that if
            <lb />
            need arises we are available to give presentation, for the said purpose before the
            <lb />
            committee and shall be allowed to submit more documents if necessary as per the
            <lb />
            committee instructions.
        </item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            Please note that we received the information of our technical bid being rejected
            <lb />
            by etender-nic@nic.in email of 11.02.2021 and is submitting our objection against
            <lb />
            the directions of the Bid Evaluation Committee meeting held on 25.01.2021 within time.
        </item>
        <lb />
        <item>
            Yours faithfully,
            <lb />
            For PashupatiNath Distributor Private Limited (PDPL)
            <lb />
            For PASHUPATINATH DISTRIBUTORS PRIVATE LTD.
            <lb />
            Sd/-
            <lb />
            Director
            <lb />
            (RAJEEV RANJAN)&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            25. On the basis of the representation that the respondent No. 3 has
            <lb />
            submitted in its individual capacity as a separate entity and not as a
            <lb />
            consortium, the Tender Evaluation Committee in its meeting held on
            <lb />
            17.02.2021 reviewed its earlier decision on 25.01.2021 and
            <lb />
            recommended the respondent No. 3 along with the other three (3)
            <lb />
            shortlisted bidders for issuance of RFP scheme.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            26. The question before this Court is whether in the absence of any
            <lb />
            specific clauses/prescription in the EOI can the tender evaluation
            <lb />
            committee review it&apos;s earlier decision taken?
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            27. The further question which arises for a decision is that admittedly
            <lb />
            the experience details furnished by the respondent No. 3 in support of
            <lb />
            its eligibility to participate in the tender process, relates to work
            <lb />
            executed by the respondent No. 3 as a component of a consortium
            <lb />
            offering Ambulatory Services in the State of Bihar. Can the experience
            <lb />
            gathered by the consortium be individually claimed by a Constituent of
            <lb />
            the Consortium?
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            28. The third issue which arises for a decision is that in the facts of
            <lb />
            the case, the eligibility of the respondent No. 3 for participating in the
            <lb />
            technical evaluation of the RFP was known to the petitioner at least as
            <lb />
            far back as on 12.03.2021 i.e. the date of technical evaluation on which
            <lb />
            date all the four (4) shortlisted bidders were held to be technically
            <lb />
            accepted. That apart, by the meeting held on 31.03.2021, the financial
            <lb />
            bids were opened and the respondent No. 3 was recommended as L-1.
            <lb />
            Inspite of the knowledge of the participation of the respondent No. 3,
            <lb />
            the writ petitioner approached this Court only in the month of
            <lb />
            September, 2021. Pursuant to the recommendation of the Tender
            <lb />
            Committee recommending the respondent No. 3 as L-1, the work order
            <lb />
            was issued to respondent No. 3 on 31.08.2021. In view of the work
            <lb />
            order being issued to respondent No. 3 and in view of the statements
            <lb />
            made at the bar that the respondent No. 3 has incurred substantial
            <lb />
            investment towards mobilization of manpower and machine towards
            <lb />
            implementation of the &quot;Free Adarani Pick-up and Dropback Services&quot; in
            <lb />
            the State of Assam. Pursuant to the work order dated 31.08.2021 being
            <lb />
            issued, third party rights have been created in the meanwhile. Under the
            <lb />
            circumstances whether the writ petitioner can be granted any relief at
            <lb />
            the stage.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            29. In so far as the first issue is concerned, the Judgment relied upon
            <lb />
            by the petitioner which is pressed into service to rely on the contentions
            <lb />
            of the petitioner was rendered in the context of orders being passed by
            <lb />
            the Administrative Officers. The question which was before the Apex
            <lb />
            Court is whether the then Commissioner of Rajkot had competence to
            <lb />
            quash the order made by the Saurashtra Government on 22.10.1956.
            <lb />
            The then Commissioner was acting as a delegatee of the State
            <lb />
            Government and in that context the Apex Court held that the order
            <lb />
            passed by the then Commissioner amounted to review of the order
            <lb />
            made by the Saurashtra Government and the Apex Court, therefore,
            <lb />
            held that the power of review is not an inherent power and it must be
            <lb />
            conferred by law either specifically or by necessary implications. If the
            <lb />
            Government had no power to review its own order, it is obvious that its
            <lb />
            delegatee would not have power to review its order.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            30. In the context of the present proceedings, the issue before this
            <lb />
            Court is whether the Tender Evaluation Committee could have reviewed
            <lb />
            its earlier order.
        </p>
        <lb />
        <p>
            In the scheme of the EOI, the powers for evaluation by the Tender
            <lb />
            Evaluation Committee are prescribed in the EOI/RFP unlike in the case
            <lb />
            of Patel Narshi Thakershi (Supra), where the Supreme Court held that
            <lb />
            power of review is not inherent and a delegatee cannot have the power
            <lb />
            of review unless prescribed. The facts involved in the present
            <lb />
            proceedings are different from the facts in the case of Patel Thakershi
            <lb />
            (Supra). The said Judgment of the Apex Court came to be considered in
            <lb />
            a subsequent Judgment before the Apex Court in R.R. Verma (supra).
            <lb />
            The Apex Court therein had held that where the Government was
            <lb />
            exercising quasi judicial powers vested by a statute, the power of review
            <lb />
            must be conferred by a statute specifically or by a necessary
            <lb />
            implications. However, the said principle is not applicable to decisions
            <lb />
            purely of administrative nature. The Apex Court held that to extend this
            <lb />
            principle to purely administrative decisions would lead to untoward and
            <lb />
            startling results. The Government must be free to alter its policy or its
            <lb />
            decision in administrative matters. The relevant paragraph of the
            <lb />
            Judgment is extracted below:
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;5. The last point raised by Shri Garg was that the Central Government
            <lb />
            had no power to review its earlier orders as the rules do not vest the
            <lb />
            government with any such power. Shri Garg relied on certain decisions
            <lb />
            of this Court in support of his submission: Patel Narshi
            <lb />
            Thakershi v. Pradyumansinghji Arjunsinghji [(1971) 3 SCC 844 : AIR
            <lb />
            1970 SC 1273] ; D.N. Roy v. State of Bihar [(1971) 3 SCC 844 : (1971) 3
            <lb />
            SCC 844 : (1971) 2 SCR 522] and State of Assam v. J.N. Roy
            <lb />
            Biswas [(1976) 1 SCC 234 : 1976 SCC (L&amp;S) 10 : AIR 1975 SC 2277 :
            <lb />
            (1976) 2 SCR 128] . All the cases cited by Shri Garg are cases where the
            <lb />
            government was exercising quasi-judicial power vested in them by
            <lb />
            statute. We do not think that the principle that the power to review must
            <lb />
            be conferred by statute either specifically or by necessary implication is
            <lb />
            applicable to decisions purely of an administrative nature. To extend the
            <lb />
            principle to pure administrative decisions would indeed lead to untoward
            <lb />
            and startling results. Surely, any government must be free to alter its
            <lb />
            policy or its decision in administrative matters. If they are to carry on
            <lb />
            their daily administration they cannot be hidebound by the rules and
            <lb />
            restrictions of judicial procedure though of course they are bound to
            <lb />
            all statutory requirements and also observe the principles of
            <lb />
            natural justice where rights of parties may be affected. Here again, we
            <lb />
            emphasise that if administrative decisions are reviewed, the decisions
            <lb />
            after review are subject to judicial review on all grounds on which
            <lb />
            an administrative decision may be questioned in a court. We see no
            <lb />
            force in this submission of the learned Counsel. The appeal is, therefore,
            <lb />
            dismissed.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            31. The Judgment rendered in the Apex Court in R.R. Verma(supra) is
            <lb />
            also followed in a recent Judgments of the Apex Court rendered in
            <lb />
            Rajesh Chander Sood (Supra). In this Judgment the Apex Court held
            <lb />
            that the power of Administrative Review can be exercised for good and
            <lb />
            valid justifications.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            32. Accordingly, in view of the law laid down by the Apex Court, it is
            <lb />
            held that in administrative actions, administrative Authority is
            <lb />
            empowered to revisit or review its orders for justifiable reasons. That
            <lb />
            power is inherent in the Government or an instrumentality of the State,
            <lb />
            but for good and justifiable reasons. To restrict any administrative
            <lb />
            authority to review or revisit any order or policy, supported by justifiable
            <lb />
            reasons, where required, will certainly lead to an anomalous and
            <lb />
            unworkable situation. Accordingly, the first contention of the writ
            <lb />
            petitioner that the Tender Evaluation Committee by its Second order
            <lb />
            dated 17.02.2021 could not have reviewed its earlier order and the
            <lb />
            same is therefore arbitrary, cannot be accepted and the same is
            <lb />
            therefore rejected.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            33. In respect of the second question, the Apex Court in New Horizons
            <lb />
            Limited and Anr. Vs. Union of India and Anr. reported in (1995) 1 SCC
            <lb />
            478 has clearly upheld that the experiences gathered as a constituent
            <lb />
            of a consortium can also be relied upon for evaluating the experience in
            <lb />
            respect of the said entity when it participates as a single entity. The
            <lb />
            Apex Court in New Horizon Limited (Supra) held that earlier experiences
            <lb />
            as one of the partners of a firm cannot be discounted. Similarly, when a
            <lb />
            company having past experiences undergoes re-organization as a result
            <lb />
            of merger or amalgamation with another company having no such past
            <lb />
            experiences, the tender submitted in the name of the re-organized
            <lb />
            company, cannot be rejected. Alternatively, in case of a split in a
            <lb />
            company, the new company though having persons with experience in
            <lb />
            the field may not have experience in its name while the original
            <lb />
            company having experience in its name lacks persons with experience.
            <lb />
            It was held that while considering the requirement regarding experience
            <lb />
            it has to be born in mind that the said requirement is contained in a
            <lb />
            document inviting offer for commercial transaction and the terms and
            <lb />
            conditions of such document have to be construed from the standpoint
            <lb />
            of a prudent businessman. Such credentials are to be examined from a
            <lb />
            commercial point of view which means that if the contract is to be
            <lb />
            entered with a company he will look into the background of the
            <lb />
            company and the persons who are in control of the same and their
            <lb />
            capacity to execute the work. He would go not by the name of the
            <lb />
            company but by the persons behind the company. The relevant
            <lb />
            paragraph of the said Judgment is extracted below:
            <lb />
        </p>

        <item>
            &quot;23. Even if it be assumed that the requirement regarding experience
            <lb />
            as set out in the advertisement dated 22-4-1993 inviting tenders is a
            <lb />
            condition about eligibility for consideration of the tender, though we
            <lb />
            find no basis for the same, the said requirement regarding experience
            <lb />
            cannot be construed to mean that the said experience should be of
            <lb />
            the tenderer in his name only. It is possible to visualise a situation
            <lb />
            a person having past experience has entered into a partnership
            <lb />
            and the tender has been submitted in the name of the partnership
            <lb />
            firm which may not have any past experience in its own name. That
            <lb />
            not mean that the earlier experience of one of the partners of
            <lb />
            the firm cannot be taken into consideration. Similarly, a company
            <lb />
            incorporated under the Companies Act having past experience may
            <lb />
            undergo reorganisation as a result of merger or amalgamation with
            <lb />
            another company which may have no such past experience and the
            <lb />
            tender is submitted in the name of the reorganised company. It could
            <lb />
            not be the purport of the requirement about experience that the
            <lb />
            experience of the company which has merged into the reorganised
            <lb />
            company cannot be taken into consideration because the tender has
            <lb />
            not been submitted in its name and has been submitted in the name
            <lb />
            of the reorganised company which does not have experience in its
            <lb />
            name. Conversely there may be a split in a company and persons
            <lb />
            looking after a particular field of the business of the company form a
            <lb />
            new company after leaving it. The new company, though having
            <lb />
            persons with experience in the field, has no experience in its name
            <lb />
            while the original company having experience in its name lacks
            <lb />
            persons with experience. The requirement regarding experience does
            <lb />
            mean that the offer of the original company must be considered
            <lb />
            because it has experience in its name though it does not have
            <lb />
            experienced persons with it and ignore the offer of the new company
            <lb />
            because it does not have experience in its name though it has
            <lb />
            persons having experience in the field. While considering the
            <lb />
            requirement regarding experience it has to be borne in mind that the
            <lb />
            said requirement is contained in a document inviting offers for a
            <lb />
            commercial transaction. The terms and conditions of such a document
            <lb />
            have to be construed from the standpoint of a prudent businessman.
            <lb />
            When a businessman enters into a contract whereunder some work is
            <lb />
            to be performed he seeks to assure himself about the credentials of
            <lb />
            the person who is to be entrusted with the performance of the work.
            <lb />
            Such credentials are to be examined from a commercial point of view
            <lb />
            which means that if the contract is to be entered with a company he
            <lb />
            will look into the background of the company and the persons who
            <lb />
            are in control of the same and their capacity to execute the work. He
            <lb />
            would go not by the name of the company but by the persons behind
            <lb />
            the company. While keeping in view the past experience he would
            <lb />
            also take note of the present state of affairs and the equipment and
            <lb />
            resources at the disposal of the company. The same has to be the
            <lb />
            approach of the authorities while considering a tender received in
            <lb />
            response to the advertisement issued on 22-4-1993. This would
            <lb />
            require that first the terms of the offer must be examined and if they
            <lb />
            are found satisfactory the next step would be to consider the
            <lb />
            credentials of the tenderer and his ability to perform the work to be
            <lb />
            For judging the credentials past experience will have to be
            <lb />
            considered along with the present state of equipment and resources
            <lb />
            available with the tenderer. Past experience may not be of much help
            <lb />
            if the machinery and equipment is outdated. Conversely lack of
            <lb />
            experience may be made good by improved technology and better
            <lb />
            equipment. The advertisement dated 22-4-1993 when read with the
            <lb />
            notice for inviting tenders dated 26-4-1993 does not preclude
            <lb />
            adoption of this course of action. If the Tender Evaluation Committee
            <lb />
            had adopted this approach and had examined the tender of NHL in
            <lb />
            this perspective it would have found that NHL, being a joint venture,
            <lb />
            has access to the benefit of the resources and strength of its
            <lb />
            companies as well as to the experience in database
            <lb />
            management, sales and publishing of its parent group companies
            <lb />
            because after reorganisation of the Company in 1992 60% of the
            <lb />
            share capital of NHL is owned by Indian group of companies namely,
            <lb />
            TPI, LMI, WML, etc. and Mr Aroon Purie and 40% of the share capital
            <lb />
            is owned by IIPL a wholly-owned subsidiary of Singapore Telecom
            <lb />
            which was established in 1967 and is having long experience in
            <lb />
            publishing the Singapore telephone directory with yellow pages and
            <lb />
            other directories. Moreover in the tender it was specifically stated that
            <lb />
            IIPL will be providing its unique integrated directory management
            <lb />
            system along with the expertise of its managers and that the
            <lb />
            managers will be actively involved in the project both out of
            <lb />
            Singapore and resident in India.&quot;
            <lb />
        </item>

        <p>
            34. In the facts of the case in BVG India Pvt Ltd. (Supra), it
            <lb />
            necessary in terms of the tender Clauses thereunder to set out details of
            <lb />
            any other company/firms involved as a consortium member. The said
            <lb />
            company in response to the said Clause replied in negative, which was
            <lb />
            construed to mean that no other company or firm was involved as a
            <lb />
            consortium member in BVG India Limited. The bid was submitted by
            <lb />
            BVG India Limited (Supra) on its own, unaccompanied by any
            <lb />
            consortium member. Despite the same BVG India Limited furnished
            <lb />
            experience certificate of its consortium namely BVG Kshitij Waste
            <lb />
            Management Services Pvt. Ltd. In the Bid papers, no information
            <lb />
            whatsoever was given of the relationship/linkage of the BVG Kshitij
            <lb />
            Management Services Pvt. Ltd. and the respondent/BVG India
            <lb />
            Limited. Under these circumstances, the Apex Court held that on the
            <lb />
            purported experience certificate issued in the name of BVG Kshitij Waste
            <lb />
            Management Services Pvt Ltd. cannot come to the help of BVG India Ltd
            <lb />
            so show its work experience. The said certificate relied upon by BVG
            <lb />
            India Limited, neither showed three years experience of BVG India Ltd
            <lb />
            nor did it specify that BVG India Ltd was carrying out garbage/waste
            <lb />
            collections or more than 300 MT per day. Further before the Apex Court,
            <lb />
            no material was produced to show that M/S BVG Kshitij Waste
            <lb />
            Management Services Pvt. Ltd is the same as the BVG India Ltd or that
            <lb />
            is a consortium member. It is on these facts, the Apex Court held that
            <lb />
            the experience certificate issued in favour of BVG Kshitij Waste
            <lb />
            Management Services Pvt. Ltd. cannot be relied upon to fulfill the
            <lb />
            eligibility criteria of BVG India Ltd. The facts involved in BVG India
            <lb />
            Ltd(Supra) are clearly distinguishable on the facts involved in the
            <lb />
            present proceedings. In the present proceedings, there was no
            <lb />
            declaration sought for from the respondent No. 3 as to whether it was
            <lb />
            involved in any consortium. The criteria prescribed in the Notice inviting
            <lb />
            EOI is that the intending bidders must submit their bids in individual
            <lb />
            capacity. No consortiums were permitted to apply.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            35. It is evident from the pleadings as well as from the submissions
            <lb />
            made at the bar that there is no quarrel that the respondent No. 3 had
            <lb />
            submitted its bid in its individual entity. The only question was whether
            <lb />
            the experience it had gathered as a lead partner of the consortium
            <lb />
            Samman Foundation can be relied upon to satisfy the requirement of
            <lb />
            experience for the purposes of eligibility. The law in this regard has been
            <lb />
            explained elaborately by the Apex Court in New Horizons Ltd (Supra).
            <lb />
            Even in BVG India Limited (Supra), the earlier decision of the Apex Court
            <lb />
            in New Horizons Ltd. (Supra) has not been distinguished or differed
            <lb />
            with. The law laid down by the Apex Court in New Horizons Ltd (Supra)
            <lb />
            is still a good law and no Judgments have been pressed into service by
            <lb />
            the petitioner to submit that subsequent Judgments of the Apex Court
            <lb />
            had differed with the view and the law laid down in New Horizons Ltd
            <lb />
            (Supra).
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            36. On the contrary in a recent Judgment rendered by the Apex Court
            <lb />
            in Maa Nabadurga Construction Vs. Saroj Kumar Jena &amp; Ors reported in
            <lb />
            MANU/SC/1279/2015. The Apex Court relied upon the law laid down in
            <lb />
            New Horizons Ltd. (Supra). Coming to the facts of the case, the records
            <lb />
            which were produced before the Court pertaining to the instant tender
            <lb />
            process also contains the tender papers submitted by the selected
            <lb />
            tenderers. Perusal of the tender papers submitted by the respondent No.
            <lb />
            3 reveals that the bid documents have been submitted as per the criteria
            <lb />
            prescribed in the EOI/RFP. Further, in terms of the clarifications sought
            <lb />
            for by the NHM authority, the appropriate Authority in the State of Bihar
            <lb />
            has duly certified that the respondent No. 3 had satisfactorily executed
            <lb />
            Ambulatory Services in the State of Bihar as a lead partner of the
            <lb />
            consortium Samman Foundation. In view of the principle culled out by
            <lb />
            the Apex Court in New Horizons Ltd. (supra), it has to be held that the
            <lb />
            experience gathered by the respondent No. 3 as a lead partner of the
            <lb />
            consortium Samman cannot be discredited. The tender issuing authority
            <lb />
            upon perusal of the relevant documents and papers relating to the bid
            <lb />
            submitted has arrived at a satisfaction that the respondent No. 3 fulfills
            <lb />
            the criteria and has the experience necessary for being shortlisted at the
            <lb />
            EOI stage for issuance of RFP.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            37. Accordingly, in view of the law laid down by the Apex Court, the
            <lb />
            contention of the petitioner that the experience gathered by constituent
            <lb />
            of a consortium cannot be taken into account when the constituent
            <lb />
            participates in a tender process in its individual capacity, being contrary
            <lb />
            to the law laid down by the Apex Court in New Horizons Ltd (Supra) is
            <lb />
            therefore rejected.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            38. The Judgment of the Apex Court in BVG India Ltd. (Supra) pressed
            <lb />
            into service by the petitioner, on the facts of the present proceedings is
            <lb />
            clearly distinguishable from the facts of the present case and therefore
            <lb />
            does not come to the aid of the petitioner.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            39. There is no specific challenge to the tender evaluation process in
            <lb />
            the RFP stage, either during technical evaluation or in the financial
            <lb />
            evaluation. The sheet anchor of the petitioner is that the experience of
            <lb />
            the consortium cannot be availed of by the respondent No. 3 as a
            <lb />
            constituent in its individual capacity and the respondent No. 3 being
            <lb />
            already rejected by the Tender Evaluation Committee and there being
            <lb />
            no power of review conferred specifically in the NIT Clauses, the Tender
            <lb />
            Evaluation Committee could not have reviewed its earlier decision to
            <lb />
            make the respondent No. 3 eligible for the issuance of RFP.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            40. The entire gamut of the challenge made by the respondent No. 3
            <lb />
            is directed towards the evaluation/re-evaluation conducted at the EOI
            <lb />
            stage. The process of evaluation at the EOI stage came to be concluded
            <lb />
            on 17.02.2021. From the pleadings available on record, it is evident that
            <lb />
            the petitioner was aware of this evaluation/re-evaluation made atleast
            <lb />
            as far back as 12.03.2021 when the technical evaluation of the
            <lb />
            shortlisted tenderers took place. Although representations were
            <lb />
            addressed to the tendering authority, the challenge in the present
            <lb />
            proceedings came to be made only by filing the writ petition in the
            <lb />
            month of September, 2021 that to after issuance of the work order
            <lb />
            dated 31.08.2021, although the petitioner claimed that it was unaware
            <lb />
            about the issuance of work order to the Respondent No. 3, when the
            <lb />
            first Writ Petition being W.P(C) No. 4543/2021 was filed. Under such
            <lb />
            circumstances what fell for consideration before this Court is the process
            <lb />
            of evaluation only at the EOI stage. There being no specific challenge
            <lb />
            made nor pleadings available in respect of infraction of the tender
            <lb />
            conditions during the technical and financial evaluation, or any other
            <lb />
            ground other than the grounds relied upon to assail the shortlisting of
            <lb />
            respondent No. 3 at the EOI stage, there is no necessity for this Court to
            <lb />
            venture into the evaluation process resorted to by the tender issuing
            <lb />
            Authority in the technical evaluation as well as the financial evaluation.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            41. No malice/Bias/Ulterior motives have been alleged or attributed to
            <lb />
            the NHM Authorities or the respondent No. 3. It is also no the pleaded
            <lb />
            case that the actions of the NHM Authority/State was exercised for
            <lb />
            purposes foreign to the purposes intended and thereby it amounted to
            <lb />
            malice-in-law. From a perusal of the records presented to the Court, it is
            <lb />
            seen that the NHM Authority has followed the tender conditions and
            <lb />
            criteria specified while arriving at it&apos;s decision of awarding the contract
            <lb />
            to the L-1 bidder namely the Respondent No. 3. There is no malice-in-
            <lb />
            law that can be attributed to the respondent authorities on the given
            <lb />
            facts and circumstances of this case.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            42. In any view of the matter, the scope of judicial review under
            <lb />
            Article 226 of the Constitution of India matters relating to commercial
            <lb />
            contracts is well laid down by the Apex Court. The various
            <lb />
            pronouncements of the Apex Court relating to scope of Judicial review in
            <lb />
            exercise of Article 226 of the Constitution of India in contractual matters
            <lb />
            are relevant for the purposes of the present proceedings.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            43. In Raunaq International Ltd. Vs. I.V.R. Construction Ltd, reported
            <lb />
            in (1999) 1 SCC 492, the Apex Court held that superior Courts should
            <lb />
            not interfere with in matters of tenders unless substantial public interest
            <lb />
            was involved or the transaction was malafide.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            44. In Air India Ltd. Vs. Cochin International Airport Ltd. reported in
            <lb />
            (2000) 2 SCC 617, the Apex Court held that Courts must proceed with
            <lb />
            great caution while exercising their discretionary powers and should
            <lb />
            exercise such power only in furtherance of public interest and not
            <lb />
            merely on making out a legal point.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            45. In Master Marine Services (P) Ltd. Vs. Metcalfe &amp; Hodgkinson (P)
            <lb />
            Ltd. reported in (2005) 6 SCC 138, it was held that the Court should
            <lb />
            primarily concerned itself with the question as to whether there was any
            <lb />
            infirmity in the decision making process.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            46. In Jagdish Mandal Vs. State of Orissa, reported in (2007) 14 SCC
            <lb />
            517, the Apex Court held that a contract is a commercial contract.
            <lb />
            Evaluation of tenders and awarding of contracts are essentially
            <lb />
            commercial functions. Principles of equity and natural justice stay at a
            <lb />
            distance in such matters. If the decision relating to award of contract is
            <lb />
            bona fide and is in public interest, Courts will not interfere in exercise of
            <lb />
            power of judicial review, even if a procedural aberration or error in
            <lb />
            assessment or prejudice to a tenderer, is made out.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            47. In B.S.N. Joshi &amp; Sons Ltd. Vs. Nair Coal Services Ltd., reported in
            <lb />
            (2006) 11 SCC 548, the Apex Court held that the Court&apos;s interference in
            <lb />
            contractual matters should be minimal. The High Court&apos;s jurisdiction in
            <lb />
            such matters is limited and it should exercise judicial restraint unless
            <lb />
            illegality or arbitrariness on the part of the employer is apparent on the
            <lb />
            face of the record.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            48. In Michigan Rubber (India) Ltd. Vs. State of Karnataka, reported in
            <lb />
            (2012) 8 SCC 216, it was held that if the State or its instrumentalities
            <lb />
            acted reasonably and fairly in public interest in awarding contract,
            <lb />
            interference would be very restrictive since no person can claim
            <lb />
            fundamental right to carry on business with the Government. Therefore,
            <lb />
            Court would not normally interfere in policy decisions and in matters
            <lb />
            challenging award of contract by the State or public authorities.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            49. In Afcons Infracture Ltd. Vs. Nagpur Metro Rail Corpn Ltd.,
            <lb />
            reported in (2016) 16 SCC 818, it was held that a mere disagreement
            <lb />
            with the decision making process or with the decision of the authority
            <lb />
            cannot be a reason for a constitutional Court to interfere. The threshold
            <lb />
            of mala fides, intention to favour someone or arbitrariness, irrationality
            <lb />
            or perversity must be met before the Constitutional Court interferes with
            <lb />
            decision making process or the decision.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            50. In Montecarlo Ltd. Vs. NTPC, reported in AIR 2016 SC 4946, it was
            <lb />
            held that where the decision is taken is manifestly in consonance with
            <lb />
            the language of the tender document or subserves the purpose for
            <lb />
            which the tender is floated, the Court should follow the principle of
            <lb />
            restraint. Technical evaluation or comparison by the Court would be
            <lb />
            impermissible.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            51. In Silppi Constructions Contractors Vs. Union of India and Anr.,
            <lb />
            reported in (2020) 16 SCC 489, the Apex Court after considering catena
            <lb />
            of Judgments held that that the essence of law laid down by the Apex
            <lb />
            Court, in the settled Judgments, is in the exercise of restraint and
            <lb />
            cautioned; the need for overwhelming public interest to justify judicial
            <lb />
            intervention in matters of contract involving the State instrumentalities.
            <lb />
            Unless there is total arbitrariness or unreasonableness in the decision
            <lb />
            making process, the Court&apos;s should give way to the experts. The Court is
            <lb />
            not to sit like a Court of appeal over the appropriate authority, the
            <lb />
            authority floating the tender is the best judge of its requirements and as
            <lb />
            to how the documents are to be interpreted. If two interpretations are
            <lb />
            possible then the interpretation of the author must be accepted.
            <lb />
            Therefore, the Court&apos;s interference in tender matters should be minimal.
            <lb />
            It shall only interfere to prevent arbitrariness, irrationality, bias, mala
            <lb />
            fides or perversity.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            52. In the above conspectus, the present case will have to be
            <lb />
            examined. The scope of work in the contact is with regard to providing
            <lb />
            Ambulatory Services for new born babies along with their mothers for
            <lb />
            pick up and drop facilities from their residents. The vehicles and the
            <lb />
            manpower are to be provided by the service provider. The service
            <lb />
            provider is to put up a mechanism to ensure that the requirements of
            <lb />
            the scope of work are fulfilled to the desire extent. There is no dispute
            <lb />
            that the Respondent No. 3 had submitted along with its bid papers
            <lb />
            where it had stated that it had offered such ambulatory services as a
            <lb />
            lead partner of a consortium. It is not the pleaded case of the petitioner
            <lb />
            that such services were not at all rendered at all by the respondent No.
            <lb />
            3 or that the services rendered in the State of Bihar and the scope of
            <lb />
            work pertaining to the present tender process are completely different.
            <lb />
            The only ground on which the shortlisting of the respondent No. 3 has
            <lb />
            been challenged is the benefit of experience claimed by the respondent
            <lb />
            No. 3 as a lead partner of the consortium while rendering Ambulatory
            <lb />
            Services in the State of Bihar as necessary experience in the present
            <lb />
            tender process, where the respondent No. 3 has participated in its
            <lb />
            individual capacity. That apart, the petitioner was well aware that the
            <lb />
            respondent No. 3 being permitted to participate after being initially
            <lb />
            declared as &quot;technically not accepted&quot;. It is apparent that the petitioner
            <lb />
            took every opportunity to participate in the bid process along with other
            <lb />
            intending bidders including the respondent No. 3 without raising any
            <lb />
            objections to the tender process initiated by the authority concerned. It
            <lb />
            is only upon the event of the petitioner not being shortlisted as L-1 that
            <lb />
            he ap0roached this Court by filing the present writ petition.
        </p>
        <lb />
        <p>
            As discussed above, no mala fides have been attributed against
            <lb />
            the authority concerned. In the given facts and circumstances, the
            <lb />
            authority concerned having proceeded in terms of the NIT published,
            <lb />
            no case for arbitrariness or bias is made out.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            53. The law culled out in respect of commercial contracts as extracted
            <lb />
            above is very clear The scope of judicial review under Article 226 is
            <lb />
            extremely limited and the same is available only when the decision
            <lb />
            making process is illegal, irregular, arbitrary or opposed to public policy.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            54. As discussed above, since the writ petition is directed against the
            <lb />
            decision taken by the Tender Evaluation Committee reviewing its earlier
            <lb />
            decision to permit the respondent No. 3 to be shortlisted for issuance of
            <lb />
            RFP and no other grounds have been urged in this proceedings to assail
            <lb />
            the decision of technical evaluation, financial evaluation and the
            <lb />
            consequential issuance of work order, in view of what has been held
            <lb />
            above as well as in view of the law pertaining to scope of judicial review
            <lb />
            under Article 226, the challenge made by the writ petitioner cannot be
            <lb />
            sustained and the same is therefore rejected.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            55. That apart besides the representation issued by the petitioner
            <lb />
            pursuant to technical and financial evaluation, there are no pleadings as
            <lb />
            to why the writ petitioner continued to participate in the tender process
            <lb />
            and came before this Court only after being rejected in the financial
            <lb />
            evaluation. It is evident that the grievance of the petitioner as regards
            <lb />
            the respondent No. 3 being shortlisted in the EOI stage for issuance of
            <lb />
            RFP, appears to have germinated only after the financial evaluation
            <lb />
            wherein the petitioner was declared as L-2 and the respondent No. 3
            <lb />
            was declared L-1.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            56. The facts pleaded reveal that the petitioner took every opportunity
            <lb />
            to participate in the tender process to take its chance for being selected
            <lb />
            as the L-1 bidder. It appears that it is only after the petitioner has been
            <lb />
            evaluated as L-2 bidder that the present proceedings have been initiated
            <lb />
            to question the scrutiny and selection of the respondent No. 3 at the
            <lb />
            EOI stage. As submitted at the bar that the respondent No. 3 in the
            <lb />
            meantime has stated to have made substantial investments for
            <lb />
            mobilization of manpower and materials towards effective
            <lb />
            implementation of the &quot;Free Adarani Pick-up and Dropback Services&quot; in
            <lb />
            the State of Assam. The writ Court being a Court of equity cannot come
            <lb />
            to the aid of a person or an entity who is not able to sufficiently explain
            <lb />
            the delay and laches while approaching this Court to ventilate its
            <lb />
            grievances and more so were third party rights have been allowed to be
            <lb />
            created. Interference by the Writ Court is completely unwarranted in the
            <lb />
            facts of present case, more particularly in the absence of specific
            <lb />
            pleadings attributing any malice against the State/NHM Authority or the
            <lb />
            respondent No. 3.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            57. Reference in this context to be made in the cases of State of M.P
            <lb />
            Vs. Nandwal Jaiswal reported in (1986) 4 SCC 566, Ascon (M/s) &amp; Anr
            <lb />
            Vs. State of Assam reported in 2017 (5) GLT 875 and Maa Chandi Stone
            <lb />
            Crushing Vs. Chief Engineer reported in 2005 SCC OnlineOri 1.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            58. In view of the above, the writ petition is found to devoid of any
            <lb />
            merit and the same is therefore dismissed. No order as to costs.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            59. The interim order dated 22.09.2021 is hereby stands vacated.
            <lb />
        </p>

        <p>
            60. Records produced before the Court are returned to Mr. B. Gogoi,
            <lb />
            learned Standing Counsel for the respondent No. 2.
        </p>
        <p>
            <lb />
            JUDGE
            <lb />
            Comparing Assistant
        </p>


    </text>
</tei>