<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<p>
			1. Whether the Reporters of local papers may
			<lb />
			be allowed to see the judgment?
			<lb />
			Yes
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			2. To be referred to Reporter or not?
			<lb />
			Yes
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			3. Whether the judgment should be reported
			<lb />
			Yes
			<lb />
			in the Digest?
			<lb />
		</p>

		<head>
			MANMOHAN SINGH, J.
			<lb />
		</head>

		<p>
			1.
			<lb />
			By this order, I shall dispose of the following applications:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			a)
			<lb />
			IA No.15781/2008 under Order 39 Rule 1 &amp; 2 the
			<lb />
			Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (hereinafter referred
			<lb />
			to as the CPC).
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			b)
			<lb />
			IA No.3085/2009 under Order 39 Rule 4 CPC.
			<lb />
			IA Nos.15781/2008 &amp; 3085/2009 in CS(OS) No. 2682/2008
			<lb />
			Page No.2 of 132
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			2.
			<lb />
			The Plaintiff has filed the instant suit for restraining
			<lb />
			infringement of copyright, damages etc. The plaintiff claims to be the
			<lb />
			owner of the copyright in the repertoire of songs, cinematograph films,
			<lb />
			sound recordings etc. The plaintiff claims to have over 20000 Hindi Non
			<lb />
			film songs and around 50000 songs in regional languages.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			3.
			<lb />
			The plaintiff further states that the business of the plaintiff
			<lb />
			which is film producing, music distribution etc is largely dependant upon
			<lb />
			the exploitation of its copyright. The said copyright exploitation enables
			<lb />
			the plaintiff to sustain its creative activities thereby giving opportunities
			<lb />
			to many talents including composers, artists, singers, etc. The plaintiff
			<lb />
			states that the monetary gains arising from copyright exploitation further
			<lb />
			empowers it with financial strength to carry on its business of film
			<lb />
			making. The infringements of such works of the plaintiff, thus, causes
			<lb />
			royalty losses to the plaintiff and are responsible for the loss in the
			<lb />
			business of the plaintiff.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			4.
			<lb />
			The plaintiff claims that the copyright exploitation of the
			<lb />
			works is done by the licensing system whereby the plaintiff gives public
			<lb />
			performance licences to the parties who in turn give the plaintiff the
			<lb />
			necessary royalty. The plaintiff has filed the catalogue in which the
			<lb />
			plaintiff has claimed copyright and also filed the documents to the effect
			<lb />
			of showing its licencing scheme.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			5.
			<lb />
			The defendant No. 1 is stated to be a social networking and
			<lb />
			entertainment website which offers a variety of entertainment
			<lb />
			applications including sharing, viewing of music, images, cinematograph
			<lb />
			works having its base in the United States of America. The defendant
			<lb />
			No. 2 is the owner of the defendant No. 1 which is stated to be a division
			<lb />
			of News Corporation, Fox Interactive media which is offering, border
			<lb />
			free online network that caters to consumers by giving them platform or
			<lb />
			tools.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			6.
			<lb />
			As per the plaintiff, the defendant No.1 describes the website
			<lb />
			as a place for friends and projects its website as a place to upload
			<lb />
			pictures and videos. The said website myspace.com provides country
			<lb />
			specific content and is one of the most popular social networking and
			<lb />
			content sharing website in the world. The plaintiff contends that the
			<lb />
			defendants&quot; basic point of attraction in running this website is to make
			<lb />
			available the multimedia content including songs, pictures, clips which
			<lb />
			can be seen and shared by the user over the internet space. The said
			<lb />
			website of defendant No. 1 not only includes recently released infringing
			<lb />
			material but also the material which has not yet been released or is
			<lb />
			authorized for broadcast through the authorized distribution channels.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			7.
			<lb />
			The features of the website are being described as that the
			<lb />
			user or visitor need not subscribe to the website in order to enable him to
			<lb />
			search and view the video on the same. But for the purposes of uploading
			<lb />
			a video on to the website, the user is required to subscribe and create a
			<lb />
			user profile. It is also pointed out in the plaint that when a user in India
			<lb />
			visits the said website the said user is immediately forwarded to India
			<lb />
			centric version of the website namely in.myspace.com which is catering
			<lb />
			to the Indian community.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			8.
			<lb />
			The plaintiff states that the website of the defendants contains
			<lb />
			the additional features and instructions which encourages the users and
			<lb />
			enables them to learn how to share videos. These additional functions
			<lb />
			create additional unauthorized copying, electronically store, transmit the
			<lb />
			content that infringes the rights of the others including the plaintiff.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			9.
			<lb />
			The website of the defendants is stated to also generate
			<lb />
			revenue by offering of this illegal content/ infringing works. The said
			<lb />
			revenue is made through the medium of advertisements being displayed
			<lb />
			on each webpage. The whole business of the defendant No. 1 is
			<lb />
			specifically depends upon authorizing free uploading and then
			<lb />
			distributing the content through downloading or streaming content to end
			<lb />
			users.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			10.
			<lb />
			The complaint of the plaintiff emerges from the kind of
			<lb />
			business model adopted by the defendants wherein it states that the
			<lb />
			songs, cinematograph works including the ones which are for new movies
			<lb />
			or upcoming movies distributing which the plaintiff earns its revenue and
			<lb />
			completes its cost of film making gets deprived due to illegal
			<lb />
			IA Nos.15781/2008 &amp; 3085/2009 in CS(OS) No. 2682/2008
			<lb />
			Page No.5 of 132
			<lb />
			dissemination of the songs, cinematographs works by the defendants on
			<lb />
			internet whereby the defendants encourages and authorizes the users to
			<lb />
			share these contents and the end users are benefitted with the said songs
			<lb />
			and films free of charge by in turn distribution by the defendants to the
			<lb />
			public at large.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			11.
			<lb />
			The plaintiff has also explained the operation of the website of
			<lb />
			the defendants in the following manner:
		</p>
		<lb />
		<table>
			User
			<lb />
			
			<lb />
			
			<lb />
			MySpace sends the streaming
			<lb />
			video and audio content from
			<lb />
			MySpace&quot;s servers to the user&quot;s
			<lb />
			computer or other device where it
			<lb />
			can be seen and heard.
			<lb />
			Simultaneously, a copy of the
			<lb />
			chosen video and/or sound
			<lb />
			recording is downloaded from
			<lb />
			the MySpace website to the
			<lb />
			user&quot;s computer.
			<lb />
			
			<lb />
			
			<lb />
			User clicks on preferred search result.
			<lb />
			
			<lb />
			MySpace provides for users a search and indexing function which
			<lb />
			allows users to search for the video/sound recording and provides a
			<lb />
			list of thumbnails search results in response to the search.
			<lb />
			
			<lb />
			MySpace makes a copy of the uploaded video or sound recording
			<lb />
			in its own software format, and stores it on its own servers.
			<lb />
			
			<lb />
			Subscriber uploads video recording (cinematograph film) or sound
			<lb />
			recording on MySpace website using facility provided by
			<lb />
			MySpace.
			<lb />
		</table>
		<p>
			12.
			<lb />
			The plaintiff has stated that in the year 2007 a non disclosure
			<lb />
			agreement was signed between the plaintiff and the defendants and
			<lb />
			thereafter there were in talks with the defendants whereby the defendants
			<lb />
			were called upon to take the licences from the plaintiff. But, the talks
			<lb />
			broke down and the defendants rather offered the plaintiff to go for
			<lb />
			registration of rights management tool programme by way of email dated
			<lb />
			January 18, 2008. However, the plaintiff then gave a legal notice on
			<lb />
			20.2.2008 informing the defendants about its rights. The reply to the
			<lb />
			notice of the plaintiff by the defendants was issued on 12.3.2008 wherein
			<lb />
			the defendants assumed that the content of the plaintiff copyright has
			<lb />
			been taken down and also that the same shall not be made available on
			<lb />
			the website in future.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			13.
			<lb />
			However, in December 2008, it was realized by the plaintiff
			<lb />
			that the defendants have not removed the said infringing material from the
			<lb />
			website. The said infringing material despite the assurance of the
			<lb />
			defendants was still available on the website of the defendants. The
			<lb />
			plaintiff has enumerated the infringing material as on December 2008 in
			<lb />
			the plaint which can be outlined as under:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<table>
			<p>LANGUAGE</p>
			<lb />
			<p>SUB-GENRE</p>
			<lb />
			<p>TITLE</p>
			<lb />
			<p>SINGER/ARTIS</p>
			<lb />
			<p>EXPECTED</p>
			<lb />
			<p>RELEASE</p>
			<lb />
			<p>DATE</p>
			<lb />
			<p>PUNJABI</p>
			<lb />
			<p>ALBUM</p>
			<p>Punjaban</p>
			<lb />
			<p>Pammi Bai</p>
			<lb />
			<p>17th Dec 2008</p>
			<lb />
			<p>PUNJABI</p>
			<lb />
			<p>ALBUM</p>
			<lb />
			<p>As Kudiye</p>
			<lb />
			<p>Labh Janjua,</p>
			<lb />
			<p>Kuldeep Sandhu,</p>
			<lb />
			<p>Karan Mahi,</p>
			<lb />
			<p>Onkar Onki, Vicky</p>
			<lb />
			<p>Bhoi</p>
			<lb />
			<p>and</p>
			<lb />
			<p>Kulwinder Singh</p>
			<lb />
			<p>17th Dec 2008</p>
			<lb />
			<p>HINDI</p>
			<lb />
			<p>ALBUM</p>
			<lb />
			<p>Hari Om</p>
			<lb />
			<p>Hari Haran</p>
			<lb />
			<p>18th Dec 2008</p>
			<lb />
			<p>PUNJABI</p>
			<lb />
			<p>ALBUM</p>
			<lb />
			<p>Bottle Wargi</p>
			<lb />
			<p>Ravinder Grewal</p>
			<lb />
			<p>18th Dec 2008</p>
			<lb />
			<p>PUNJABI</p>
			<lb />
			<p>ALBUM</p>
			<lb />
			<p>Don't Mind</p>
			<lb />
			<p>Aman Riar</p>
			<lb />
			<p>24th Dec 2008</p>
			<lb />
			<p>HINDI</p>
			<lb />
			<p>FILM</p>
			<lb />
			<p>JAANE TU YA</p>
			<lb />
			<p>JAANE NA</p>
			<lb />
			<p>IMRAN KHAN,</p>
			<lb />
			<p>GENELIA</p>
			<lb />
			<p>D'SOURZA,</p>
			<lb />
			<p>MANDHRI</p>
			<lb />
			<p>PADHNIS,</p>
			<lb />
			<p>AIYAZ KHAN &amp;</p>
			<lb />
			<p>OTHERS</p>
			<lb />
			<p>12.12.08</p>
			<lb />
			<p>HINDI</p>
			<lb />
			<p>COMPILATION</p>
			<lb />
			<p>2008</p>
			<lb />
			<p>IT'S</p>
			<lb />
			<p>ROCKING (SET)</p>
			<lb />
			<p>OF TWO CD,</p>
			<lb />
			<p>MC-SINGLE)</p>
			<lb />
			<lb />
			<p>12.12.08</p>
			<lb />
			<p>HARYANVI</p>
			<lb />
			<p>RAJA</p>
			<lb />
			<p>HARISHCHAND</p>
			<lb />
			<p>RA</p>
			<lb />
			<p>NARENDRA</p>
			<lb />
			<p>KAUSHIK,</p>
			<lb />
			<p>MEENAKSHI</p>
			<lb />
			<p>PANCHAL</p>
			<lb />
			<p>16.12.08</p>
			<lb />
			<p>PUNJABI</p>
			<lb />
			<p>ALBUM</p>
			<lb />
			<p>DEEWANA</p>
			<lb />
			<p>TERA</p>
			<lb />
			<p>SANDEEP</p>
			<lb />
			<p>SANDHU</p>
			<lb />
			<p>18.12.08</p>
			<lb />
			<p>PUNJABI</p>
			<lb />
			<p>ALBUM</p>
			<lb />
			<p>SARDAR</p>
			<lb />
			<p>GARY HOTHI</p>
			<lb />
			<p>22.12.08</p>
			<lb />
			<p>BHOJPURI</p>
			<lb />
			<p>FILM</p>
			<lb />
			<p>SWARG</p>
			<lb />
			<p>JAISAN</p>
			<lb />
			<p>GHAR SANSAR</p>
			<lb />
			<p>PART 1 &amp; 2</p>
			<lb />
			<p>DHEERAJ</p>
			<lb />
			<p>PANDIT, MILI</p>
			<lb />
			<p>PRIYA,</p>
			<lb />
			<p>SUBHASH</p>
			<lb />
			<p>BHARGAV,</p>
			<lb />
			<p>VANDANA,</p>
			<lb />
			<p>KSHITIJ</p>
			<lb />
			<p>PRAKASH,</p>
			<lb />
			<p>RENU MISHRA,</p>
			<lb />
			<p>VIJAI RAI</p>
			<lb />
		</table>
		<p>
			14.
			<lb />
			Thereafter, the plaintiff filed the present suit feeling
			<lb />
			dissatisfied with the assurances of the defendants and sought the interim
			<lb />
			reliefs from this court to the following terms:
			<lb />
		</p>
		<item>
			“(i)
			<lb />
			grant an order of permanent injunction
			<lb />
			restraining the defendants, their officers,
			<lb />
			employees, agents, servants and representatives and
			<lb />
			all others acting on their behalf and in active
			<lb />
			concert or participation with them or any of them
			<lb />
			from
			<lb />
			reproducing,
			<lb />
			adapting,
			<lb />
			distributing,
			<lb />
			communicating, transmitting, disseminating or
			<lb />
			displaying on their website www.myspace.com,
			<lb />
			www.in.myspace.com or any sub-domain thereof or
			<lb />
			otherwise infringing in any manner the
			<lb />
			cinematograph films, sound recordings and/or the
			<lb />
			underlying literary or musical works in which the
			<lb />
			plaintiff owns exclusive, valid and subsisting
			<lb />
			copyright(s);
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(ii)
			<lb />
			grant an order of permanent injunction
			<lb />
			restraining the defendants, their officers,
			<lb />
			employees, agents, servants and representatives and
			<lb />
			all others acting on their behalf and in active
			<lb />
			concert or participation with them or any of them
			<lb />
			from causing, contributing to, inducing, enabling,
			<lb />
			facilitating or participating in the infringement of
			<lb />
			the cinematograph films, sound recordings and/or
			<lb />
			the underlying literary or musical works in which
			<lb />
			the plaintiff owns exclusive, valid and subsisting
			<lb />
			copyright(s) on their website www.myspace.com,
			<lb />
			www.in.myspace.com or any sub-domain thereof or
			<lb />
			otherwise; and
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(iii)
			<lb />
			grant an order of rendition of accounts by
			<lb />
			the defendants to the plaintiff;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(iv)
			<lb />
			grant an order requiring the defendants
			<lb />
			jointly and severally to pay damages as stated
			<lb />
			hereinabove to the plaintiff;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(v)
			<lb />
			grant costs of the instant suit to the
			<lb />
			plaintiff; and
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(vi)
			<lb />
			pass any other such order(s) in favour of
			<lb />
			the plaintiff and against the defendants as may be
			<lb />
			deemed fit and proper by this Hon&quot;ble Court in the
			<lb />
			interest of justice and equity.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			15.
			<lb />
			The matter was first listed before this court on 19.12.2008
			<lb />
			when the defendants also appeared as caveators and this court was
			<lb />
			passed the following order :
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;I.A. No.15781/2008 (u/O 39 R 1 and 2 CPC)
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			…..Notice. Counsel for the defendants accepts
			<lb />
			notice. He seeks and is granted four weeks&quot; time to
			<lb />
			file a reply to the application, with an advance copy
			<lb />
			to the other side, who may file a rejoinder thereto,
			<lb />
			if any, before the next date of hearing.
		</item>
		<lb />
		<item>
			In the meantime, as an interim measure and without
			<lb />
			prejudice to the rights and contentions of the
			<lb />
			respective parties, the Plaintiff agrees as a gesture
			<lb />
			of goodwill, to handover the copies of the albums
			<lb />
			mentioned in para 47 of the plaint to the
			<lb />
			defendants, for the defendants to ensure that the
			<lb />
			copyright of the Plaintiff in any of the aforesaid
			<lb />
			audio visual, songs, sound recordings and literary
			<lb />
			and musical works is not communicated to the
			<lb />
			public through/on/via the website of the Plaintiff
			<lb />
			www.myspace.com.
		</item>
		<lb />
		<item>
			The Plaintiff shall also furnish an updated catalogue
			<lb />
			of its works in which it has a copyright, to the
			<lb />
			defendants.
			<lb />
			The defendants shall make an
			<lb />
			endeavor to ensure removal of the infringing
			<lb />
			contents in which the Plaintiff have a copyright,
			<lb />
			from its aforesaid website and file an affidavit of
			<lb />
			compliance in this regard before the next date of
			<lb />
			hearing……..&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			16.
			<lb />
			The said order was challenged before the Hon&quot;ble Division
			<lb />
			Bench, wherein the Hon&quot;ble Division Bench passed the following order
			<lb />
			with the observation that the said order is an interim measure and will not
			<lb />
			come in the way of the Learned Single Judge in deciding the interim
			<lb />
			IA Nos.15781/2008 &amp; 3085/2009 in CS(OS) No. 2682/2008
			<lb />
			Page No.10 of 132
			<lb />
			applications. The said order of Learned Division Bench is reproduced
			<lb />
			hereinafter:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;In our view the prayer in the respondent&quot;s plaint is
			<lb />
			general in nature. It does not refer to specific titles
			<lb />
			in respect of which infringement has taken place.
			<lb />
			The catalogue when printed out gives the name and
			<lb />
			title of songs and films in which the Plaintiff claims
			<lb />
			copyright. The plaint does not state that all of the
			<lb />
			songs/films have been uploaded on the appellant&quot;s
			<lb />
			web-site. However, the scope and nature of the
			<lb />
			plaint is left to be determined in the suit. In light of
			<lb />
			this fact, we are of the view that as and when the
			<lb />
			respondent provides details of its songs and films
			<lb />
			which have been uploaded on the web-site of the
			<lb />
			appellant, the appellant shall immediately take
			<lb />
			remedial measures to remove the same from its
			<lb />
			website not later than one week from the date of
			<lb />
			such communication. In our view, if such
			<lb />
			requisitions of the respondent are complied with
			<lb />
			within a week by the appellant, it would constitute
			<lb />
			sufficient protection of the respondent&quot;s rights as an
			<lb />
			interim measure, and would demonstrate the
			<lb />
			endeavour of the appellant to comply with the
			<lb />
			Order dated 19 th December, 2008. We, however,
			<lb />
			make it clear that nothing said in this order would
			<lb />
			come in the way of the decision of the learned
			<lb />
			Single Judge.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			17.
			<lb />
			The defendants have filed its written statement and replied to
			<lb />
			the application seeking interim injunction. The defendants have also filed
			<lb />
			an application under Order 39 Rule 4 seeking modification of the order
			<lb />
			passed on 19.12.2008. The defendants have also amended the written
			<lb />
			statement and in the amended written statement they have raised the
			<lb />
			following defences :
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			a)
			<lb />
			This court does not have territorial jurisdiction to entertain and try
			<lb />
			the present proceedings on the grounds:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			 The defendant No.1 is a foreign national and is carrying on
			<lb />
			business outside the jurisdiction of this court in US.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			 No part of cause of action has occurred with in the territorial
			<lb />
			jurisdiction of this court.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			 The defendant No.1 is not amenable personally to jurisdiction
			<lb />
			of this court and therefore cannot be compelled to be under
			<lb />
			the jurisdiction of this court.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			 The website of defendants cannot close the jurisdiction to this
			<lb />
			court as it does not pass the tests laid down in the case of
			<lb />
			Banyan Tree Vs. A. Murali Krishna Reddy &amp; Anr, 2010
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(42) PTC 361 (Del).
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			 The exercise of jurisdiction by this court would mean that the
			<lb />
			court is giving extraterritorial effect.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			b)
			<lb />
			That the suit is not maintainable as the prayers made in the suit are
			<lb />
			non specific and if granted it will impose impossible burden upon
			<lb />
			the defendant No. 1. The plaintiff has failed to specify in respect of
			<lb />
			which works, it is seeking injunction order and thus the suit is not
			<lb />
			maintainable.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			c)
			<lb />
			The prayers made in the suit are open ended and the blanket
			<lb />
			injunction of the kind cannot be granted by the court. No qua timet
			<lb />
			action is maintainable in suit for copyright infringements
			<lb />
			d)
			<lb />
			The plaintiff has made certain misrepresentations about the facts
			<lb />
			which according to the defendants were not mentioned in the legal
			<lb />
			notice in the year 2008 and the defendants have clarified all the
			<lb />
			aspect work wise.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			e)
			<lb />
			The acts of defendants are those of intermediatory providing free
			<lb />
			of cost platform to the users without any actual or direct
			<lb />
			knowledge of the content being uploaded and has no role in
			<lb />
			selection of the content so uploaded. The defendants have no
			<lb />
			control over the said content being uploaded as the portal of the
			<lb />
			defendants is such where it cannot exercise any such control.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			f)
			<lb />
			The acts of the defendants are those of intermediatory and are
			<lb />
			protected under the provisions of Section 79 of Information
			<lb />
			Technology Act, 2000. The said provision will act as safe harbor
			<lb />
			provisions of US Digital Millennium Copyright Act (&quot;DMCA&quot;)
			<lb />
			whereby the liability of the defendants shall be exempted by
			<lb />
			operation of Section 79 of IT Act, 2000.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			g)
			<lb />
			The agreements or the assignments which are placed on record by
			<lb />
			the plaintiff are defective. The said agreement reveals that the
			<lb />
			rights of the movies vest with the producers and they have retained
			<lb />
			the said rights including internet rights. Thus, the rights which are
			<lb />
			asserted by the plaintiff actually do not belong to the plaintiff.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			h)
			<lb />
			The defendants only provides a means for file sharing where the
			<lb />
			acts which are performed may or may not be infringing and thus
			<lb />
			mere providing of means is no infringement under the eyes of the
			<lb />
			law.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			i)
			<lb />
			The acts of the defendants are protected under the provisions of
			<lb />
			Digital Millennium Copyright Act (&quot;DMCA&quot;) of United States.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			j)
			<lb />
			The defendants have provided the term of use agreement with
			<lb />
			users which reads as under:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;8. Content / Activity prohibited. The following
			<lb />
			are examples of the kind of Content that is illegal or
			<lb />
			prohibited to post on or through the MySpace
			<lb />
			Services. MySpace reserves the right to investigate
			<lb />
			and take appropriate legal action against anyone
			<lb />
			who, in MySpace&quot;s sole discretion, violates this
			<lb />
			provision, including without limitation, removing
			<lb />
			the offending content from the MySpace Services
			<lb />
			and terminating the Membership of such violators.
			<lb />
			Prohibited Content includes, but is not limited to
			<lb />
			Content that, in the sole discretion of MySpace:
			<lb />
			…….
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			8.8. constitutes or promotes an illegal or
			<lb />
			unauthorized copy of another person&quot;s copyrighted
			<lb />
			work, such as providing pirated computer programs
			<lb />
			or links to them, providing information to
			<lb />
			circumvent manufacturer-installed copy-protect
			<lb />
			devices, or providing pirated music or links to
			<lb />
			pirated music files.
			<lb />
			……
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			8.16 Violates the privacy rights, publicity rights,
			<lb />
			copyrights, trademark rights, contract rights or any
			<lb />
			other rights of any person&quot;
		</item>
		<lb />
		<p>
			Thus, the defendants themselves require their users to respect
			<lb />
			the copyright of the others and have all intention to remove the infringing
			<lb />
			content whatsoever from its website.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			k)
			<lb />
			The defendants do not derive the monetary gains against the
			<lb />
			advertisement in the user generated content. The advertisements
			<lb />
			may exist on the same page as on User Generated Content but they
			<lb />
			are not really against the user generated content but against the
			<lb />
			licensed content.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			l)
			<lb />
			The defendant No. 1 acts as merely a licensee of the user wherein
			<lb />
			it takes a limited license from the user to add, delete or modify the
			<lb />
			content so that the same is befitting to its website to make it
			<lb />
			viewable. But the said defendant does not have any other license to
			<lb />
			sell those works or make it public outside its services.
			<lb />
			Vide clause 6.1 of the User Agreement, the said defendant
			<lb />
			binds its users to grant it a limited license to use, modify, delete from,
			<lb />
			add to, publicly perform, publicly display, reproduce and distribute such
			<lb />
			UGC solely for the purposes of the website.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			The said clause reads as under:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;6.1
			<lb />
			MySpace does not claim any ownership rights in
			<lb />
			the text, files, images, photos, video, sounds, musical works,
			<lb />
			works of authorship, applications, or any other materials
			<lb />
			(collectively, &quot;Content&quot;) that you post on or through the
			<lb />
			MySpace Services. After posting your Content to the
			<lb />
			MySpace Services, you continue to retain any such rights
			<lb />
			that you may have in your Content, subject to the limited
			<lb />
			license herein. By displaying or publishing (&quot;posting&quot;)
			<lb />
			any Content on or through the MySpace Services, you
			<lb />
			hereby grant to MySpace a limited license to use,
			<lb />
			modify, delete from, add to, publicly perform, publicly
			<lb />
			display, reproduce, and distribute such Content solely on
			<lb />
			or through the MySpace Services, including without
			<lb />
			limitation distributing part or all of the MySpace
			<lb />
			Website in any media formats and through any media
			<lb />
			channels, except Content marked &quot;private&quot; will not be
			<lb />
			distributed outside the MySpace Website. This limited
			<lb />
			license does not grant MySpace the right to sell or otherwise
			<lb />
			distribute your Content outside of the MySpace Services.
			<lb />
			After you remove your Content from the MySpace Website
			<lb />
			we will cease distribution as soon as practicable, and at such
			<lb />
			time when distribution ceases, the license will terminate. If
			<lb />
			after we have distributed your Content outside the MySpace
			<lb />
			Website you change the Content&quot;s privacy setting to
			<lb />
			&quot;private,&quot; we will cease distribution of such &quot;private&quot;
			<lb />
			Content outside the MySpace Website as soon as
			<lb />
			practicable after you make the change.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			m)
			<lb />
			The uploaded content can be identified only by way of URL
			<lb />
			(Uniform Resource locator) as an address and the defendants
			<lb />
			cannot thus segregate the infringing or non infringing works.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			n)
			<lb />
			The defendants have installed a notice and take down procedure in
			<lb />
			compliance of Digital Millennium Copyright Act (&quot;DMCA&quot;) of
			<lb />
			US same as earlier one wherein, any proprietor who has a reason
			<lb />
			to believe that the copyrighted content has been posted on the
			<lb />
			website, can issue notice and ask to take down the request and the
			<lb />
			IA Nos.15781/2008 &amp; 3085/2009 in CS(OS) No. 2682/2008
			<lb />
			Page No.16 of 132
			<lb />
			defendants will immediately take the corrective measures to take
			<lb />
			down and remove the said content.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			o)
			<lb />
			The defendants have also provided three safeguards on its own:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			 The Hash Block Filter
			<lb />
			 Take Down stay Down
			<lb />
			 Rights management tool
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			The Hash Block filters prevents the deleted content from
			<lb />
			being reposted by taking finger print of the content.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			The Take Down stay down contents also prevents the
			<lb />
			repetitive reposting of the file containing identical content. Thus,
			<lb />
			the said filter is also a useful identifier for preventing repetitive
			<lb />
			infringement.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			The third tool has been explained by the defendants in detail
			<lb />
			which is as under:
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			The most powerful filtering tool that defendant No.1 makes
			<lb />
			available to copyright owners is the free RMT Copyright Filter.
			<lb />
			The defendant No.1 allows any copyright owner to register for and
			<lb />
			use this tool at no charge subject to a single registration agreement.
			<lb />
			A copy of the standard RMT Registration Agreement applicable in
			<lb />
			this behalf has been filed along with the list of documents. To take
			<lb />
			advantage of the RMT, all that the copyright owner needs to do is,
			<lb />
			register with the defendant No.1 and then create &quot;fingerprints&quot; of
			<lb />
			its audio or audio visual content (using the free software that the
			<lb />
			said defendant makes available through its filtering vendor called
			<lb />
			Audible Magic). The copyright owner submits the fingerprints to
			<lb />
			the defendant&quot;s filtering vendor with associated business rules,
			<lb />
			e.g., the copyright owner can decide to block all of its content or
			<lb />
			rather allow users to post certain pieces of content that it is trying
			<lb />
			to promote.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			Thereafter, if the copyright owner instructs that all of its
			<lb />
			content should be blocked, the defendant No.1&quot;s RMT Copyright
			<lb />
			Filter will be set to block all content uploaded by users that
			<lb />
			matches the copyright owner&quot;s content. This means if any piece of
			<lb />
			content is uploaded that matches any 30 seconds of the copyright
			<lb />
			owner&quot;s content, it would be blocked (the 30 seconds of matched
			<lb />
			content is the technical limit for the filtering technology). If the
			<lb />
			copyright owner, therefore, submits fingerprints to the RMT
			<lb />
			Copyright Filter, it can avail themselves of extremely broad
			<lb />
			copyright protection on its website. Upon signing up for the RMT
			<lb />
			(as well as signing Audible Magic&quot;s own short agreement
			<lb />
			regarding the use of its signature generation software), the content
			<lb />
			owner need not ever part with its content to receive the benefits of
			<lb />
			filtering. Rather, the content owner need only itself create the
			<lb />
			fingerprints of its content, by using Audible Magic&quot;s free software,
			<lb />
			and then send such fingerprints to Audible Magic with appropriate
			<lb />
			usage instructions (i.e., &quot;block&quot; or &quot;allow&quot;). The defendant No.1
			<lb />
			also periodically runs the filter retroactively over its website, again
			<lb />
			at its own cost, over all the content that has already been posted on
			<lb />
			its website. Accordingly, if content was uploaded by a user before
			<lb />
			a copyright owner was able to add it to Audible Magic&quot;s reference
			<lb />
			database of fingerprints, the filter will catch such previously
			<lb />
			uploaded content and remove it.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			Thus, as per the defendants all these measures are nothing but
			<lb />
			safeguards to prevent infringement and sufficiently demonstrates
			<lb />
			their bonafides and non involvement in the infringing acts.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			p)
			<lb />
			The defendants have launched their India operations in December
			<lb />
			2007 and immediately informed all the music companies about its
			<lb />
			right management tool so that the infringement can be minimized
			<lb />
			and the plaintiff cannot blame the defendants for its own reluctance
			<lb />
			to subscribe to such facility and for the resulting infringements due
			<lb />
			to its non subscription.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			q)
			<lb />
			That the interim arrangement recorded in the Hon&quot;ble Division
			<lb />
			Bench&quot;s Order dated March 6, 2009 embraces the &quot;notice and take
			<lb />
			down&quot; protocol set forth as a legal norm in the laws across the
			<lb />
			world including the laws of India to deal with the issues of on-line
			<lb />
			liability. Consequently, the said interim order represents the only
			<lb />
			feasible answer to the grievance of the Plaintiff, if found to be well
			<lb />
			founded in law and fact.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			r)
			<lb />
			The Plaintiff has made misrepresentation of facts that the
			<lb />
			defendants do not have any control over the content posted on their
			<lb />
			website by the users. Further, the defendants do not target Indian
			<lb />
			customers. The advertisements that may appear along with the
			<lb />
			thumbnails are a result of an automated process carried out by a
			<lb />
			search engine, which is term centric and not content centric.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			18.
			<lb />
			The applications came up for hearing from time to time and
			<lb />
			clarifications were also sought from the parties after reserving the matter
			<lb />
			for orders.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			19.
			<lb />
			Learned counsel Mr. Amit Sibal appearing on behalf of the
			<lb />
			plaintiff has made his submissions which can be enunciated as under:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			a)
			<lb />
			Firstly, learned counsel Mr Sibal has submitted that the acts of the
			<lb />
			defendants wherein the defendants have used the copyrighted
			<lb />
			works of the plaintiff without licence or any authority, amounts to
			<lb />
			primary acts of infringement. Learned counsel has placed reliance
			<lb />
			on the provisions of Section 51 (a) (i) of the Copyright Act, 1957
			<lb />
			(herein after referred as to as &quot;Act&quot;) and argued that the defendants
			<lb />
			are communicating the works of the plaintiff to the public without
			<lb />
			authority or licence and thus causing royalty losses in addition to
			<lb />
			making the work available to the public which only owner of the
			<lb />
			work is entitled to do. Therefore, the present case is a squarely a
			<lb />
			case of primary act of infringement as provided under Section 51
			<lb />
			(a)(i) of the Act.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			b)
			<lb />
			Secondly, learned counsel Mr Sibal has argued that the present
			<lb />
			case comes within the purview of Section 51 (a) (ii) of the Act as
			<lb />
			the defendants by providing a space to the users and enabling them
			<lb />
			to communicate the work to the public for the defendants&quot; own
			<lb />
			profit are actually permitting the place for infringement for their
			<lb />
			profit which is an infringement prescribed under Section 51 (a) (ii)
			<lb />
			of the Act. Mr. Sibal argued that providing webspace to the user is
			<lb />
			amounting to permitting the place. The expression &quot;place&quot; has to
			<lb />
			be interpreted to subsume not merely physical place or space but
			<lb />
			also space at the virtual world of internet. It is also pointed by the
			<lb />
			learned counsel that the defendants has not, in the pleadings,
			<lb />
			contested that MySpace website is a &quot;place&quot; within the meaning of
			<lb />
			Section 51 (a) (ii) of the Act.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			c)
			<lb />
			Further it is explained by Mr Sibal that the defendants have not
			<lb />
			disclosed to the court that the defendants&quot; acts are not totally
			<lb />
			without consideration in providing the space to the users. But,
			<lb />
			actually the defendants have purely and largely have commercial
			<lb />
			interest in operating this kind of arrangement. As per Mr Sibal, it
			<lb />
			would not be unapt to call this as purely a commercial model as the
			<lb />
			defendants are reaping profits from all the advertisers by putting
			<lb />
			the advertisements along side the sound recordings and the
			<lb />
			cinematographs works of the plaintiff. By doing all this, the
			<lb />
			defendants are permitting a place to be used for infringement for
			<lb />
			profit. The same is an act of infringement under Section 51 (a) (ii)
			<lb />
			of the Act.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			In order to support his contention Mr. Sibal relied upon the
			<lb />
			following judgments:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			 Satyam Infoway Ltd. v. Sifynet Solutions Pvt. Ltd.
			<lb />
			(AIR 2004 SC 3540)
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			 Super Cassette Industries Ltd. v. Nirulas Corner
			<lb />
			House (P) Ltd.148 (2008) DLT 487 is relied upon to
			<lb />
			contend that the similar argument like in the present case
			<lb />
			that the defendant business in the website includes the
			<lb />
			usage of space for infringing as well as non infringing
			<lb />
			purposes by the various users, was raised in that case
			<lb />
			wherein the court was concerned with usage of the
			<lb />
			infringing works by the Hotels/ the defendants therein who
			<lb />
			took the stand that the hotel anyways charge the customers
			<lb />
			for viewing the television whether it is an infringing work
			<lb />
			or otherwise, thus the defendants therein sought to justify
			<lb />
			that the said acts does not come within the purview of
			<lb />
			Section 51 (a) (ii) which is permitting the place for profit
			<lb />
			for infringement purposes. The court as per the learned
			<lb />
			counsel for the plaintiff has rejected the said argument in
			<lb />
			the following words:
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			&quot;22. The plaintiff has been able to show that the
			<lb />
			defendants are using cable connection and extending
			<lb />
			facilities of television to their patrons in the hotel
			<lb />
			rooms, for payments are received. In this view, prima
			<lb />
			facie, the content of songs and videos broadcast are
			<lb />
			communications to the public……..&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			d)
			<lb />
			Learned counsel Mr. Sibal submitted that the case of the
			<lb />
			defendants do not fall within the exception provided under Section
			<lb />
			51 (a) (ii) of the Act as the defendants are doing the infringement
			<lb />
			with knowledge and also they have a reason to believe that such
			<lb />
			acts would amount to infringement of copyright.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			Mr. Sibal has provided following reasons whereby it can be
			<lb />
			said that the defendants&quot; acts of communicating the work are
			<lb />
			coupled with knowledge:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			 Clause 9 of The Terms of Use Agreement of MySpace
			<lb />
			with the user itself makes it evident that MySpace itself
			<lb />
			reminds its users not to upload content which can infringe
			<lb />
			anyone&quot;s copyright on MySpace.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			 In paragraph 29 of the Written statement the defendant No.
			<lb />
			1 itself has listed various tools that it is supplying to
			<lb />
			copyright owners to deal with the infringement taking
			<lb />
			place on the MySpace&quot;s website.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			e)
			<lb />
			Learned Counsel Mr. Sibal submitted that the argument of the
			<lb />
			primary infringement can be strengthened by looking at Section 14
			<lb />
			of the Act wherein copyright means right to do or authorize the
			<lb />
			doing of the act. Thus, the said acts are the acts of the owner and
			<lb />
			the defendants while providing a space at the internet is
			<lb />
			authorizing the communication of the work to the public by which
			<lb />
			large segment of public is able to hear, listen and watch the
			<lb />
			cinematograph and musical works of the plaintiff without its
			<lb />
			authorization. Thus, the defendants&quot; acts amounts to authorizing
			<lb />
			the infringement which itself is a separate infringement by way
			<lb />
			conjoint reading of Section 14 read with Section 51.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			Mr. Sibal has referred to extensive English case laws
			<lb />
			included the ones decided in Australia on the subject of authorizing
			<lb />
			the infringement which can be enlisted as under:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			 University of New South Wales v. Moorhouse (1975)
			<lb />
			CLR 1
		</item>
		<lb />
		<item>
			 Universal Music Australia Pty Ltd. and Ors. v.
			<lb />
			Sharman License Holdings Ltd. and Ors
		</item>
		<lb />
		<item>
			 Australasian Performing Right Association v. Jain,
			<lb />
			(1990)18IPR663
		</item>
		<lb />
		<item>
			 Roadshow Films Pty. Ltd v iiNet Limited, [2010] FCA
			<lb />
			24
		</item>
		<lb />
		<item>
			 Arista Records, Inc. v. Flea World, Inc. 2006 WL
			<lb />
			842883 (D.N.J.).
		</item>
		<lb />
		<p>
			Thus, it is the submission of Mr. Sibal that the defendants&quot;
			<lb />
			acts are nothing less than providing means to an infringement for
			<lb />
			profit which is equally considered to be an infringement. The said
			<lb />
			infringement also gets established when the defendants&quot; exercises
			<lb />
			full control over and above the user generated content and other
			<lb />
			determinative factors which are well settled by the new line of
			<lb />
			decisions as mentioned above.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			f)
			<lb />
			Learned counsel Mr. Sibal vehemently argued that the &quot;notice and
			<lb />
			take down&quot; alternative which has been suggested by the
			<lb />
			defendants do not mitigate the wrongs of the defendants and is not
			<lb />
			a sufficient safeguard for an infringement which occurs on day to
			<lb />
			day basis.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			This has been explained by Mr. Sibal by informing that the
			<lb />
			new musical and cinematograph works are made from time to time,
			<lb />
			as and when there are promotions of new movies. The availability
			<lb />
			of the said trailors or musical works on internet would mean
			<lb />
			sharing the same with public at large. Notice and turn down
			<lb />
			provisions which provides the aggrieved party to get the
			<lb />
			defendants to notice the already occurring infringement and
			<lb />
			thereafter the defendants remove the contents on internet. The said
			<lb />
			procedure is inappropriate and does not remedy the infringement,
			<lb />
			as by the time notice to turn down is given by the plaintiff to the
			<lb />
			defendants, infringement is already caused whereby the works of
			<lb />
			the plaintiff are already circulated to the public at large.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			Thus, the procedure suggested by the defendants to first
			<lb />
			make the infringing work available and then to delete on request is
			<lb />
			bad and puts to the plaintiff into irretrievable harm by causing
			<lb />
			infringement of each and every new work of the plaintiff and
			<lb />
			enough damage is already done prior to making such turn down
			<lb />
			request. As per Mr. Sibal, the question has to be seen from the
			<lb />
			perspective as why the defendants should be at all allowed to
			<lb />
			cause infringement of the plaintiff works at the first place and more
			<lb />
			so when the said acts are the conscious acts where the defendants
			<lb />
			are also getting benefitted.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			g)
			<lb />
			It is also the contention of Mr. Sibal that the defendants, refuge
			<lb />
			under the safe harbor provisions of the law will not be applicable
			<lb />
			to the present case. The present case is to be decided upon the
			<lb />
			existing legal position and the law of the land and not as per the
			<lb />
			US Digital Millenium Copyright Act. The said act and provisions
			<lb />
			under the said act does not extend to India and neither there is any
			<lb />
			provision under the existing laws which provides such safe harbor
			<lb />
			provisions and in the absence of the same, the discussion relating
			<lb />
			to the same in relation to infringement of the plaintiff&quot;s works in
			<lb />
			India becomes irrelevant. In short, the Digital Millennium
			<lb />
			Copyright Act (&quot;DMCA&quot;) is not applicable to the present dispute.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			By making the above submissions, Mr. Sibal argued that the
			<lb />
			plaintiff has prima facie case as there is no denial to the title of the
			<lb />
			works owned by the plaintiff and there are infringing activities
			<lb />
			being carried on the internet without authorization of the plaintiff.
			<lb />
			Further, the defendants are doing the same deliberately and causing
			<lb />
			the plaintiff royalty losses. The balance of convenience also lies in
			<lb />
			favour of the plaintiff and they are more inconvenient in the event
			<lb />
			of non grant of injunction as their works are continuing to be
			<lb />
			infringed on internet. On the other hand, the defendants can still
			<lb />
			continue their acts without displaying the works of the plaintiff&quot;s
			<lb />
			on the web.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			The plaintiff is put to irretrievable harm due to the illegal acts
			<lb />
			of the defendants and its extensive royalty losses due to the same
			<lb />
			and the defendants have nothing to loose, except, the illegal
			<lb />
			earnings arising out the infringing activities. Thus, as per the
			<lb />
			learned counsel Mr Sibal, the present case warrants the grant of
			<lb />
			injunction as per the prayers made in the injunction application and
			<lb />
			the order dated 19.12.2008 which has been modified by the
			<lb />
			Division bench further records that the same shall not come in the
			<lb />
			way of the learned single judge to decide the injunction application
			<lb />
			and thus this court can conveniently grant and extend the
			<lb />
			injunction in terms of the injunction application.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			20.
			<lb />
			Per contra, Mr. Rajinder Kumar, advocate, appearing on
			<lb />
			behalf of the defendants has resisted the injunction application and also
			<lb />
			submitted that the present case does not warrant the grant any injunction
			<lb />
			at all. Learned counsel Mr. Kumar has made the submissions which can
			<lb />
			be outlined in the following terms.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			a)
			<lb />
			Mr. Kumar firstly submitted that this court lacks necessary
			<lb />
			territorial and personal jurisdiction to entertain and try the
			<lb />
			proceedings against the defendants who are carrying on business,
			<lb />
			residing and personally works for gain in the United States of
			<lb />
			America. Mr. Kumar in order to buttress his submissions relied
			<lb />
			upon the following :
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			 The defendants are operating, carrying on its business,
			<lb />
			working for again outside the territories of India. The
			<lb />
			defendants are not personally amenable to the jurisdiction
			<lb />
			of this court.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			 This court can exercise jurisdiction only to the extent of
			<lb />
			the applicability of the law in India and not otherwise. This
			<lb />
			court cannot grant any orders which would have the effect
			<lb />
			to extending the same outside the territories of India.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			 The present case lacks territorial jurisdiction in view of the
			<lb />
			well settled law by this court in the case of Banyan Tree
			<lb />
			(Supra) wherein this court has extensively dealt with the
			<lb />
			subject of jurisdiction in the cases involving websites. The
			<lb />
			said case falls within the observations of Banyan Tree
			<lb />
			(Supra) and thus this court does not have territorial
			<lb />
			jurisdiction to entertain and try the present proceedings.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			 Even if the web-site of the defendants is interactive, the
			<lb />
			same by itself is not sufficient to clothe jurisdiction upon
			<lb />
			this court.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			 The defendants&quot; web-site, which is accessible and
			<lb />
			available to all and sundry from any part of the world, is
			<lb />
			not specifically targeted at users in India. The Plaintiff has
			<lb />
			not shown or pleaded prima facie that the defendant No.1
			<lb />
			&quot;purposefully availed&quot; itself of the jurisdiction of this
			<lb />
			Hon&quot;ble Court; that the nature of the activity indulged in
			<lb />
			by the defendants by the use of their web-site was with an
			<lb />
			intention to conclude a commercial transaction with the
			<lb />
			web-site user (since the defendant No.1&quot;s services are
			<lb />
			completely free of charge); and that the specific targeting
			<lb />
			of this forum state by the defendants have resulted in an
			<lb />
			injury or harm to the Plaintiff within this forum court.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			 The Plaintiff has pleaded that the defendants&quot; web-site is a
			<lb />
			highly interactive web-site which not only permits users to
			<lb />
			access the contents thereof but also to subscribe to the
			<lb />
			services provided by the defendants by &quot;signing up&quot; for
			<lb />
			such services, including, the uploading and downloading of
			<lb />
			videos available on the web-site. The plaint and the
			<lb />
			documents filed by the Plaintiff no-where show that the
			<lb />
			defendants&quot; use of its web-site is with an intention to
			<lb />
			conclude a commercial transaction with its users. On the
			<lb />
			contrary, the subscription to the services offered on
			<lb />
			defendants&quot; web-site is free and does not involve any
			<lb />
			future payment.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			 Even for the purposes of Section 20(c), CPC, in order to
			<lb />
			show that some part of the cause of action has arisen
			<lb />
			within the jurisdiction of this Hon&quot;ble Court by the
			<lb />
			defendants&quot; use of the internet, the Plaintiff must show and
			<lb />
			prove that not only the defendants&quot; specifically targeted
			<lb />
			viewers within the jurisdiction of this Hon&quot;ble Court but
			<lb />
			also that some commercial transaction using the web-site
			<lb />
			was entered into by the defendants with a user of its web-
			<lb />
			site within this forum resulting in an injury or harm to the
			<lb />
			Plaintiff within the jurisdiction of this Hon&quot;ble Court.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			 No such material has been placed on record by the Plaintiff
			<lb />
			that the defendants have entered into commercial
			<lb />
			transactions with the users of its web-site in Delhi or
			<lb />
			anywhere in India for that matter.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			 Further, the Plaintiff has sought to establish jurisdiction on
			<lb />
			the basis of certain print-outs from the defendants&quot; web-
			<lb />
			site to purportedly show availability of the Plaintiff&quot;s
			<lb />
			works on the said web-site for public performances,
			<lb />
			display and communication of the same to the public. No
			<lb />
			details of the users involved have been provided anywhere
			<lb />
			in the plaint. These print-outs seem to indicate that the
			<lb />
			Plaintiff has set-up its own people to access the
			<lb />
			defendants&quot; web-site and engineer the search results to
			<lb />
			suit its convenience. As held by the Hon&quot;ble Division
			<lb />
			Bench in the case of Banyan Tree (Supra), it would have
			<lb />
			to be a real commercial transaction that the defendants
			<lb />
			have with someone not set-up by the Plaintiff itself. The
			<lb />
			Banyan Tree (Supra), opinion further holds that if the
			<lb />
			only evidence is in the form of a series of trap transactions,
			<lb />
			they have to be shown as having been obtained using fair
			<lb />
			means. The Plaintiff in the present case has failed to aver
			<lb />
			in the plaint and place alongwith it any supporting material
			<lb />
			to
		</item>
		<lb />
		<p>
			Thus, as per Mr. Kumar, learned counsel for the defendants,
			<lb />
			this court lacks the territorial jurisdiction due to the above said
			<lb />
			reasons and this court should reject the plaint or return it to be
			<lb />
			presented before the appropriate forum.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			b) Mr. Kumar learned counsel for the defendants has argued by
			<lb />
			explaining the meaning of copyright in the cinematograph films
			<lb />
			that the copyright in any work can be infringed when the infringer
			<lb />
			actually indulge into the said act of infringement. The infringement
			<lb />
			cannot occur for the acts which the said defendants may indulge in
			<lb />
			future or which are not even entered into occurrence. It is the
			<lb />
			contention of learned counsel for the defendants that the plaintiff is
			<lb />
			seeking the general kind of injunction which is impermissible in
			<lb />
			law as there must be specific acts complained of for infringement
			<lb />
			to happen and the court to prevent those.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			Mr. Kumar has drawn analogy from Trade Marks Act, 1999
			<lb />
			wherein the language of provision under the chapter of
			<lb />
			infringement uses the wordings &quot;Likelihood of confusion&quot; which
			<lb />
			according to him means permitting the plaintiff to sue for future
			<lb />
			wrongs, however the as per the learned counsel no such language
			<lb />
			subsists in the Copyright Act and in that event of the matter, it is
			<lb />
			inappropriate for this court to consider the grant of injunction for
			<lb />
			the future wrongs.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			c)
			<lb />
			Learned counsel thereafter started explaining the working of the
			<lb />
			defendant&quot;s website by showing the technical background of the
			<lb />
			internet and how it emerged. Learned counsel has taken pains to
			<lb />
			explain the meaning of the word internet by citing some English
			<lb />
			judgments. Counsel has then submitted that the defendants&quot;
			<lb />
			website is premised on the newer and the latest version of web 2.0
			<lb />
			which permits interactive interface with the users using it which
			<lb />
			includes, media, games, songs, pictures and other multimedia.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			d)
			<lb />
			Learned counsel further argued that the there is a difference
			<lb />
			between the infringement of the copyright happening in the
			<lb />
			physical form or the tangible form and the acts which are done in
			<lb />
			the virtual world of the internet which are not available in the
			<lb />
			physical form. As per the learned counsel, that makes a lot of
			<lb />
			difference. As per the learned counsel, there is a world wide
			<lb />
			debate over the management of communication on the internet.
			<lb />
			There are two international covenants entered into by the countries
			<lb />
			who are members of World Intellectual property Organisation
			<lb />
			which are known as WIPO Copyright Treaty (WCT) and WIPO
			<lb />
			Performance and Phonograms Treaty (WPPT).
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			Learned counsel argued that the court should consider the
			<lb />
			provisions of these two treaties though India has not even ratified
			<lb />
			these conventions in order to consider the provisions relating to
			<lb />
			communications made over internet and its impact. Learned
			<lb />
			counsel in order to support his contention also relies upon the
			<lb />
			judgment passed by the Apex court in Entertainment Network
			<lb />
			(India) Ltd vs. Super Cassettes Industries, 2008 (9) SCALE 69
			<lb />
			wherein the apex court has expressed its opinion about the
			<lb />
			Application of International Conventions in India in the following
			<lb />
			words.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;79. It is for the aforementioned limited purpose, a
			<lb />
			visit to the provisions of International Conventions
			<lb />
			would be necessary.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			80. In interpreting the domestic/municipal laws, this
			<lb />
			Court has extensively made use of International law
			<lb />
			inter alia for the following purposes :
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(i)
			<lb />
			As a means of interpretation;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(ii)
			<lb />
			Justification or fortification of a stance
			<lb />
			taken;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(iii)
			<lb />
			To fulfill spirit of international obligation
			<lb />
			which India has entered into, when they are
			<lb />
			not in conflict with the existing domestic
			<lb />
			law;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(iv)
			<lb />
			To reflect international changes and reflect
			<lb />
			the wider civilization;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(v)
			<lb />
			To provide a relief contained in a covenant,
			<lb />
			but not in a national law;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(vi)
			<lb />
			To fill gaps in law. &quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			Mr. Kumar thus submitted that the Article 8 of the said
			<lb />
			convention may be read into by this court in order to find favour in
			<lb />
			the defendant&quot;s stand that the mere act of facilitating over internet
			<lb />
			does not amount to infringement.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			e)
			<lb />
			Learned counsel has argued that the defendants by providing
			<lb />
			online space to the subscribers enabling them to share media online
			<lb />
			is acting as an intermediary within the meaning of Section 79 of
			<lb />
			the Information Technology Act (as amended in the year 2009) and
			<lb />
			the acts of the defendants are thus saved by the Information
			<lb />
			Technology Act 2000 wherein its acts are without knowledge of
			<lb />
			the infringing nature of the communication.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			f)
			<lb />
			Learned counsel further argued that this court should interpret the
			<lb />
			provisions of the Copyright Act and information technology Act
			<lb />
			harmoniously wherein the IT Act will come into play in the same
			<lb />
			manner as that of the safe harbor provisions of US statute which
			<lb />
			saves the liability of the defendants. The argument which has been
			<lb />
			raised by the learned counsel for the defendants is that it cannot be
			<lb />
			said that on one hand the IT Act saves the intermediaries from the
			<lb />
			liability and on the other hand the same intermediaries are exposed
			<lb />
			to strict liability provisions of the Copyright Act. Both should
			<lb />
			operate simultaneously and the safeguard under IT Act, thus, must
			<lb />
			also shield the defendants from the liability under the Copyright
			<lb />
			Act as well which is no different from its operations on the
			<lb />
			internet.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			Learned counsel has further explained the preceding
			<lb />
			argument in detail by enumerating the working process of the
			<lb />
			defendants on the internet which establish that the defendants are
			<lb />
			no more than an intermediary who is doing this without knowledge
			<lb />
			and despite due diligence the content cannot be known to the
			<lb />
			defendants at the first instance. Learned counsel submitted that
			<lb />
			defendant No. 1 is predominantly a service provider/ intermediary,
			<lb />
			providing a free of cost platform to its users and offering an
			<lb />
			interactive user submitted network of friends, personal profiles,
			<lb />
			blogs, groups, photos, music, video, instant messaging services,
			<lb />
			mobile services and videos. It is further submitted that the said
			<lb />
			defendants do not directly upload any content on its website
			<lb />
			(except for content that it licenses and creates which constitutes a
			<lb />
			very small portion of the content on its website), but merely
			<lb />
			provides a platform to its users for uploading content under certain
			<lb />
			terms and conditions.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			Thus, as per the learned counsel for the defendants, the acts
			<lb />
			of the defendants are purely of the kinds of intermediary and the
			<lb />
			defendants are just facilitating the space and cannot be held to be
			<lb />
			within the knowledge of the content which is being uploaded by
			<lb />
			third party unless the right holder brings it to the notice of the
			<lb />
			defendants.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			g)
			<lb />
			Learned counsel further submitted that it is not merely without the
			<lb />
			knowledge of the defendants but also impossible to monitor each
			<lb />
			and every content which is being uploaded on the website. The
			<lb />
			same is, therefore, the compulsion of the defendants while
			<lb />
			operating on internet as the internet portal is open to world at large
			<lb />
			and due to the nature of the portal which is such that anyone can
			<lb />
			upload anything. The defendants being a facilitating entity cannot
			<lb />
			be held responsible due to its impossibility of monitoring each and
			<lb />
			every content over the internet unless the active participation of the
			<lb />
			defendants is established.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			h)
			<lb />
			Learned counsel for the defendants further submitted that the
			<lb />
			defendants are not gaining any monetary benefits arising out the
			<lb />
			user generated content. But rather the advertising as per the
			<lb />
			learned counsel for the defendants is no doubt a business model of
			<lb />
			the defendants but is against the licensed content.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			Further it has been argued that the advertisements may also
			<lb />
			appear automatically as the user types keywords and search for the
			<lb />
			same. This is usually a part of &quot;Adwords&quot; which are in the nature
			<lb />
			of hints or options given by the search engines as and when the
			<lb />
			user asks any query from search engine. The example of the same
			<lb />
			is given that supposingly if the user is typing Punjaban. The song
			<lb />
			may appear and along side the same some options of Punjabi
			<lb />
			matrimonial may appear automatically which happens due to the
			<lb />
			search engines exercise and not due to the acts of the defendants.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			j)
			<lb />
			Learned counsel submitted that indeed it is correct that the
			<lb />
			defendants takes the licence from the user to use, add, delete from
			<lb />
			or publicly perform or publicly display, publicly perform,
			<lb />
			reproduce and distribute the said content for the purposes of the
			<lb />
			website. However, the said licence is a precautionary step to avoid
			<lb />
			any objection from any users of the defendants. Learned counsel
			<lb />
			also states that the same does not mean that the defendants
			<lb />
			requires the licence for such reformatting.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			k)
			<lb />
			Learned counsel for the defendants further submitted that the
			<lb />
			defendants have already ensured that its website has measures to
			<lb />
			remove or prevent copyright infringements. The said measures are
			<lb />
			taken in consonance with the Digitial Millennium Copyright Act of
			<lb />
			USA. The said procedure is explained by the defendants below :
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;In pursuance of the above stated categories
			<lb />
			contemplated in the DMCA, the Defendant No.1
			<lb />
			has installed a &quot;notice and take down procedure&quot; as
			<lb />
			prescribed in the DMCA and offers the same free
			<lb />
			of cost to all copyright holders, who in their
			<lb />
			perception are likely to be affected by
			<lb />
			transmission/uploading of content by the users.
			<lb />
			Accordingly, if a copyright owner believes that his
			<lb />
			or her work has been copied and posted on the
			<lb />
			Defendant No.1&quot;s website in such a way that
			<lb />
			constitutes copyright infringement, the Defendant
			<lb />
			No.1 has provided information in the Frequently
			<lb />
			Asked Question (FAQ) section on its website to
			<lb />
			enable the copyright owner to file an infringement
			<lb />
			notice. Towards this end, the Defendant No.1 has
			<lb />
			provided details of its copyright agent in the User
			<lb />
			Agreement so that such copyright agent may be
			<lb />
			notified of the claim of infringement, consisting of
			<lb />
			the following information: (i) an electronic or
			<lb />
			physical signature of the person authorized to act
			<lb />
			on behalf of the owner of the copyright interest; (ii)
			<lb />
			a description of the copyrighted work that the
			<lb />
			copyright owner claims to have been infringed; (iii)
			<lb />
			a description of where the material that the
			<lb />
			copyright owner claims to have been infringed is
			<lb />
			located on the said Defendant&quot;s website [providing
			<lb />
			the URLs of the claimed infringing material]; (iv)
			<lb />
			the address, telephone number, and email address
			<lb />
			of the copyright owner; (v) a written statement by
			<lb />
			the copyright owner that he/she has a good faith
			<lb />
			belief that the disputed use is not authorized by the
			<lb />
			copyright owner, its agent, or the law; (vi) a
			<lb />
			statement by the copyright owner that the above
			<lb />
			information in its notice is accurate and, under
			<lb />
			penalty of perjury, that he /she is the copyright
			<lb />
			owner or authorized to act on the copyright owner&apos;s
			<lb />
			behalf.
		</item>
		<lb />
		<p>
			The defendant No.1 also automatically, and, at its own
			<lb />
			initiative and expense, takes two additional steps to hinder users
			<lb />
			from reposting that same content. The defendants records the
			<lb />
			&quot;hash&quot; of the file that has been removed which is a unique
			<lb />
			identifier for that file. The defendants also create a &quot;fingerprint&quot; of
			<lb />
			the content that has been removed, which is a unique identifier for
			<lb />
			the content. The defendant No.1 uses both the hash and the
			<lb />
			fingerprint to achieve the goal of preventing the same content that
			<lb />
			has been removed from being re-posted. After a copyright owner
			<lb />
			requests that user-posted content be removed from the defendant
			<lb />
			No.1&quot;s website, it automatically adds the hash to the Hash-Block
			<lb />
			filter and fingerprint to the Take Down Stay Down Filter.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			If any user tries to repost the same exact file, it should be
			<lb />
			blocked by the Hash-Block Filter, which will recognize the same
			<lb />
			file. If any user tries to repost the identical content (even if the file
			<lb />
			is different because the content comes from a different source), the
			<lb />
			Take Down Stay Down filter will recognize the identical content
			<lb />
			and block it from being reposted. These are both precise filters,
			<lb />
			because the goal is to take the copyright owner&quot;s specific take
			<lb />
			down request and apply it prospectively to all new content being
			<lb />
			posted. Copyright owners often have policies to allow users to post
			<lb />
			shorter pieces of content, but not the entire piece of content.
			<lb />
			Further, certain content may be protected under fair dealing
			<lb />
			protections or authorized by copyright owners themselves. In such
			<lb />
			situations, the defendant No.1 does not presume to know what the
			<lb />
			copyright owner might want done with different or shorter portions
			<lb />
			of the content. But, for content that the copyright owner has
			<lb />
			already removed, the Take Down Stay Down Filter will
			<lb />
			automatically block any new content that the filter recognizes as
			<lb />
			the identical content. The defendant No.1 employs these two filters
			<lb />
			automatically after receiving a take down request from a copyright
			<lb />
			owner, and the copyright owner need not take any action on its
			<lb />
			own to get the benefits of these two filters.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			The most powerful filtering tool that defendant No.1 makes
			<lb />
			available to copyright owners is the free RMT Copyright Filter.
			<lb />
			The defendant No.1 allows any copyright owner to register for and
			<lb />
			use this tool at no charge subject to a single registration agreement.
			<lb />
			A copy of the standard RMT Registration Agreement applicable in
			<lb />
			this behalf has been filed to take advantage of the RMT, all that
			<lb />
			the copyright owner needs to do is register with the defendant
			<lb />
			No.1, and then create &quot;fingerprints&quot; of its audio or audio visual
			<lb />
			content (using the free software that the said defendant makes
			<lb />
			available through its filtering vendor called Audible Magic). The
			<lb />
			copyright owner submits the fingerprints to the defendants&quot;
			<lb />
			filtering vendor with associated business rules-e.g., the copyright
			<lb />
			owner can decide to block all of its content or rather allow users to
			<lb />
			post certain pieces of content that it is trying to promote.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			Thereafter, if the copyright owner instructs that all of its
			<lb />
			content should be blocked, the defendant No.1&quot;s RMT Copyright
			<lb />
			Filter will be set to block all content uploaded by users that
			<lb />
			matches the copyright owner&quot;s content. This means, if any piece of
			<lb />
			content is uploaded that matches any 30 seconds of the copyright
			<lb />
			owner&quot;s content, it would be blocked (the 30 seconds of matched
			<lb />
			content is the technical limit for the filtering technology). If the
			<lb />
			copyright owner, therefore, submits fingerprints to the RMT
			<lb />
			Copyright Filter, it can avail itself of extremely broad copyright
			<lb />
			protection on its website. Upon signing up for the RMT (as well
			<lb />
			as signing Audible Magic&quot;s own short agreement regarding the use
			<lb />
			of its signature generation software), the content owner need not
			<lb />
			ever part with its content to receive the benefits of filtering.
			<lb />
			Rather, the content owner need only itself create the fingerprints of
			<lb />
			its content, by using Audible Magic&quot;s free software, and then send
			<lb />
			such fingerprints to Audible Magic with appropriate usage
			<lb />
			instructions (i.e., &quot;block&quot; or &quot;allow&quot;). The defendant No.1 also
			<lb />
			periodically runs the filter retroactively over its website, again at
			<lb />
			its own cost, over all content that has already been posted to its
			<lb />
			website. Accordingly, if content was uploaded by a user before a
			<lb />
			copyright owner was able to add it to Audible Magic&quot;s reference
			<lb />
			database of fingerprints, the filter will catch such previously
			<lb />
			uploaded content and remove it&quot;
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			21.
			<lb />
			Learned counsel states that once the defendants themselves
			<lb />
			vigilant about the right holders right and at their own expense are
			<lb />
			operating the measures to cure or filter the infringement. In these
			<lb />
			circumstances, the defendants cannot be said to be those who are
			<lb />
			indulging in the infringement when they have no connection whatsoever
			<lb />
			with the content of the works in question.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			22.
			<lb />
			By making these aforementioned submissions, Mr. Rajinder
			<lb />
			Kumar resisted the grant of injunction and also pressed for the vacation
			<lb />
			of the earlier order of Division bench by urging that the defences raised
			<lb />
			above prima facie establish that the defendants could not be held liable
			<lb />
			for any act of infringement of the copyright being an intermediary. The
			<lb />
			defendants already have a provision to remedy the grievance of the
			<lb />
			plaintiff which does not require any further orders as it is within the
			<lb />
			policy of operation of the defendants that it is required to delete the
			<lb />
			works which are infringing in nature. Further, the said acts are without
			<lb />
			knowledge sufficiently are not covered by the second part of the
			<lb />
			provision of Section 51(a) (ii) read with the provisions of IT Act and
			<lb />
			therefore no liability of infringement can be attributed against the
			<lb />
			defendants. Thus, the order passed by Division Bench is liable to vacated
			<lb />
			and injunction application filed by the plaintiff is to be dismissed.
			<lb />
			Although during the course of the arguments the defendants&quot; counsel
			<lb />
			admitted that the order passed by the division bench can be confirmed
			<lb />
			and the same is also stated to be the only answer in the written statement.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			23.
			<lb />
			I have gone through the plaint, written statement and records
			<lb />
			of the proceedings and also noted the submissions of the parties.
			<lb />
			However, before commenting upon the submissions of the parties, I deem
			<lb />
			it fit to first discuss the law on the subject.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<head>
			Law Relating To Copyright And Its Relation With Internet
			<lb />
			Computing
			<lb />
		</head>

		<p>
			24.
			<lb />
			Copyright is a bundle of rights which is meant to encourage
			<lb />
			creativity. The said rights are negative rights in as much as the same are
			<lb />
			prohibiting others from using the copyrighted works. The traditional
			<lb />
			concept of the copyright has undergone a drastic change as traditionally,
			<lb />
			the law relating to copyright was meant to encourage the original literary,
			<lb />
			books and also to help the poor authors. But, due to advent of the new
			<lb />
			technologies, its scope has extended manifolds. Now, the modern law of
			<lb />
			copyright encompasses musical works, cinematograph works, computer
			<lb />
			programs, performers rights, broadcasting rights.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			24.1
			<lb />
			The copyright has now become part of the business of the big
			<lb />
			organization more specifically in film industry where the major chunk of
			<lb />
			money is reaped out of the royalties arising out of the licensing and
			<lb />
			assignment of copyrights in the respective works. Rather, it would not be
			<lb />
			out of place to state that the royalties have become the backbone of the
			<lb />
			film making machinery. The companies like the plaintiff and other
			<lb />
			musical companies on one side earning royalities and thereon investing
			<lb />
			the same funds in making the films.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			24.2
			<lb />
			One more stage of complexity has been attained by the
			<lb />
			copyright law due to emergence of the virtual world of internet. The
			<lb />
			internet computing has also brought many changes in our lives in stages.
			<lb />
			The era in 1990s saw the beginning of the computing internet, wherein,
			<lb />
			the TCPIP internet and windows interface which was so user friendly due
			<lb />
			to which we became conversant with the emails and network navigation.
			<lb />
			Thereafter, in the year 2000 and later the type of computing changed and
			<lb />
			it has been refined and set the benchmarks, there has been a sudden rise
			<lb />
			in the markets of software be it accounting, designing, photo printing,
			<lb />
			office using like notepads, gaming, chatting, user to user protocol, music
			<lb />
			sharing programs like napster, kazaa etc.. All these software development
			<lb />
			have further taught us that there is much more than emails and typing on
			<lb />
			the computer and internet is very vast by which one can navigate in
			<lb />
			several spheres of subjects and can share the data with other users.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			24.3
			<lb />
			The third and more advance stage of computing which we are
			<lb />
			witnessing at this stage is the one wherein the level of internet computing
			<lb />
			is established and there is a tendency to conduct business online. There is
			<lb />
			a large segment of business models which are growing over the internet
			<lb />
			wherein the users are participating actively and thereon the companies
			<lb />
			are earning solely on the basis of the internet services by facilitating users
			<lb />
			to share their contents which are attractive (which includes pictures,
			<lb />
			motion pictures, films, songs, graphics, trailors, private communications
			<lb />
			amongst the eminent personalities, scam disclosures etc) so as to make it
			<lb />
			common to all and enabling them to view it easily by sitting at home. The
			<lb />
			more prominent examples of this advance stage is utube, myspace,
			<lb />
			facebook etc. This is really an advance stage and there is no hesitation in
			<lb />
			saying that it is a remarkable development wherein one can see motion
			<lb />
			pictures with high quality graphics on internet which includes filming and
			<lb />
			other mode of entertainment .
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			24.4
			<lb />
			While facilitating the said sharing process over the internet,
			<lb />
			the companies like the defendants are gaining business in the nature of
			<lb />
			advertising, sponsorships, other like businesses which makes them
			<lb />
			popular and run their show. This can be said to be one more way of
			<lb />
			conducting business which is comparatively new in its field. The problem
			<lb />
			however crept in when the content which is a subject matter of sharing on
			<lb />
			the website operated by the companies are someone else&quot;s copyright or
			<lb />
			proprietary material and not owned by the person or the user supplying
			<lb />
			them. The question then arises, as to whether the said company by
			<lb />
			providing the medium of sharing to the users and also gaining
			<lb />
			commercially alongside the same can be said to have infringed the
			<lb />
			copyright of the right holder. This court is faced with the similar kind of
			<lb />
			situation wherein the defendants&quot; said website operator and the plaintiff
			<lb />
			is the right holder and the court is called upon to answer the said question
			<lb />
			by applying the copyright law accordingly to this another mode of doing
			<lb />
			business which has been innovated by the defendants in the virtual world
			<lb />
			of internet.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			25.
			<lb />
			Copyright and its meaning has been provided under Section
			<lb />
			13 and 14 of the Act. The infringement of the copyright has been defined
			<lb />
			under Section 51 of the Act. The said provisions are reproduced
			<lb />
			hereinafter for the ease of reference:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;13. Works in which copyright subsists-(1)
			<lb />
			Subject to the provisions of this section and the
			<lb />
			other provisions of this Act, copyright shall subsist
			<lb />
			throughout India in the following classes of works,
			<lb />
			that is to say -
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(a) Original, literary, dramatic, musical and artistic
			<lb />
			works,
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(b) cinematograph films, and
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(c) [sound recordings]
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(2)
			<lb />
			Copyright shall not subsist in any work
			<lb />
			specified in sub section (1), other than a work to
			<lb />
			which the provisions of Section 40 or Section 41
			<lb />
			apply, unless-
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(i) In the case of published work, the work is
			<lb />
			first published in India, or where the work is
			<lb />
			first published outside India, the author is at
			<lb />
			the date of such publication, or in a case
			<lb />
			where the author was dead at that date, was
			<lb />
			at the time of his death, a citizen of India,
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(ii) In the case of an unpublished work other
			<lb />
			than [work of architecture], the author is at
			<lb />
			the date of the making of the work a citizen
			<lb />
			of India or domiciled in India; and
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(iii) In the case of [work of architecture], the
			<lb />
			work is located in India
			<lb />
			Explanation-In the case of a work of joint
			<lb />
			authorship, the conditions conferring copyright
			<lb />
			specified in this sub section shall be satisfied by all
			<lb />
			the authors of the work.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(3)
			<lb />
			Copyright shall not subsist-
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(a) In any cinematograph film if a substantial part
			<lb />
			of the film is an infringement of the copyright in
			<lb />
			any other work;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(b) In any [sound recording] made in respect of a
			<lb />
			literary, dramatic or musical work, it in making
			<lb />
			the [sound recording], copyright in such work
			<lb />
			has been infringed.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(4)
			<lb />
			The copyright in a cinematograph film or
			<lb />
			a [sound recording] shall not affect the separate
			<lb />
			copyright in any work in respect of which a
			<lb />
			substantial part of which, the film, or as the case
			<lb />
			may be, the [sound recording] is made.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(5)
			<lb />
			In the case of a work or architecture,
			<lb />
			copyright shall subsist only in the artistic character
			<lb />
			and design and shall not extend to processes or
			<lb />
			methods or construction.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			&quot;14. Meaning of copyright-For the purposes of
			<lb />
			this Act, &quot;copyright&quot; means the exclusive right
			<lb />
			subject to the provisions of this Act, to do or
			<lb />
			authorise the doing of any of the following acts in
			<lb />
			respect of a work or any substantial part thereof,
			<lb />
			namely :-
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(a)
			<lb />
			In the case of a literary, dramatic or
			<lb />
			musical work not being a computer programme,-
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(i)
			<lb />
			to reproduce the work in any material form
			<lb />
			including the storing of it in any medium by
			<lb />
			electronic means;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(ii)
			<lb />
			to issue copies of the work to the public not
			<lb />
			being copies already in circulation;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(iii) to perform the work in public, or
			<lb />
			communicate it to the public;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(iv)
			<lb />
			to make any cinematograph film or sound
			<lb />
			recording in respect of the work;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(v)
			<lb />
			to make any translation of the work;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(vi)
			<lb />
			to make any adaptation of the work;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(vii) to do, in relation to a translation or an
			<lb />
			adaptation of the work, any of the acts
			<lb />
			specified in relation to the work in sub
			<lb />
			clauses (I) to (vi)
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(b)
			<lb />
			In the case of a computer programme,-
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(i)
			<lb />
			to do any of the acts specified in clause (a)
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(ii)
			<lb />
			to sell or give on commercial rental or offer
			<lb />
			for sale or for commercial rental any copy of
			<lb />
			the computer programme
			<lb />
			Provided that such commercial rental does not apply
			<lb />
			in respect of computer programmes where the
			<lb />
			programme itself is not the essential object of the
			<lb />
			rental.]
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(c)
			<lb />
			In the case of an artistic work,-
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(i)
			<lb />
			to reproduce the work in any material form
			<lb />
			including depiction in three dimensions of a
			<lb />
			two dimensional work or in two dimensions
			<lb />
			of a three dimensional work;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(ii)
			<lb />
			to communicate the work to the public;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(iii) to issue copies of the work to the public not
			<lb />
			being copies already in circulation;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(iv)
			<lb />
			to include the work in any cinematograph
			<lb />
			film;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(v)
			<lb />
			to make any adaptation of the work;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(vi)
			<lb />
			to do in relation to an adaptation of the work
			<lb />
			any of the acts specified in relation to the
			<lb />
			work in sub clauses (i) to (iv);
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(d)
			<lb />
			In the case of a cinematograph film-
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(i)
			<lb />
			to make a copy of the film, including a
			<lb />
			photograph of any image forming part
			<lb />
			thereof;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(ii)
			<lb />
			to sell or give on hire, or offer for sale or
			<lb />
			hire, any copy of the film, regardless of
			<lb />
			whether such copy has been sold or given on
			<lb />
			hire on earlier occasions;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(iii) to communicate the film to the public
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(e)
			<lb />
			In the case of a sound recording-
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(i)
			<lb />
			to make any other sound recording
			<lb />
			embodying it;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(ii) to sell or give on hire, or offer for sale or
			<lb />
			hire, any copy of the sound recording
			<lb />
			regardless of whether such copy has been
			<lb />
			sold or given on hire on earlier occasions;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(iii) to communicate the sound recording to the
			<lb />
			public
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			Explanation -For the purposes of this section, a
			<lb />
			copy which has been sold once shall be deemed to
			<lb />
			be a copy already in circulation.]&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			&quot;51. When copyright infringed -Copyright in a
			<lb />
			work shall be deemed to be infringed -
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(a)
			<lb />
			When any person, without a licence
			<lb />
			granted by the owner of the Copyright or the
			<lb />
			Registrar of Copyrights under this Act or in
			<lb />
			contravention of the conditions of a licence so
			<lb />
			granted or of any conditions imposed by a
			<lb />
			competent authority under this Act-
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(i) does anything, the exclusive right to do
			<lb />
			which is by this Act conferred upon the
			<lb />
			owner of the copyright, or
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(ii) permits for profit any place to be used for the
			<lb />
			communication of the work to the public
			<lb />
			where such communication constitutes an
			<lb />
			infringement of the copyright in the work,
			<lb />
			unless he was not aware and had no
			<lb />
			reasonable ground for believing that such
			<lb />
			communication to the public would be an
			<lb />
			infringement of copyright, or]
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(b)
			<lb />
			When any person -
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(i) makes for sale on hire, or sells or lets for
			<lb />
			hire, or by way of trade displays or offers for
			<lb />
			sale or hire, or
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(ii) Distributes either for the purposes of trade or
			<lb />
			to such an extent as to affect prejudicially the
			<lb />
			owner of the copyright, or
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(iii) By way of trade exhibits in public, or
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(iv)
			<lb />
			Imports [***] into India, any infringing
			<lb />
			copies of the work:
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			[Provided that nothing in sub-clause (iv) shall apply
			<lb />
			to the import of one copy of any work, for the
			<lb />
			private and domestic use of the importer.]
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			Explanation -For the purposes of this section, the
			<lb />
			reproduction of a literary, dramatic, musical or
			<lb />
			artistic work in the form of a cinematograph film
			<lb />
			shall be deemed to be an &quot;infringing copy&quot;.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			26.
			<lb />
			From the bare reading of the Section 51, it becomes apparent
			<lb />
			that the infringement is, doing of any act by a person who is not
			<lb />
			authorized by the owner, which the owner is conferred to do under the
			<lb />
			provisions of the Act or permitting any place for profit for infringement of
			<lb />
			the copyright is also an infringement under the Act. The said two
			<lb />
			provisions are disjunctive in as much as that there shall be an
			<lb />
			infringement even if the acts are done which are of the owner or in the
			<lb />
			alternative the acts of permitting any place for profit.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			27.
			<lb />
			At this stage, it becomes relevant also to examine that the
			<lb />
			wordings of Section 51 (a) (ii) which provide permitting &quot;any place&quot; for
			<lb />
			profit. The use of the words &quot;any place&quot; would include common public
			<lb />
			place or library or any other kind of place. The wordings do not put any
			<lb />
			embargo of the kind of the place which is required to be permitted for
			<lb />
			profit in order to establish an infringement. But rather the wordings used
			<lb />
			in the sub section are &quot;any place&quot; so as to subsume physical place or
			<lb />
			place at the internet or webspace. The reference is invited to the
			<lb />
			provisions of UK Copyright Act, 1956 which are similar in nature to
			<lb />
			Indian Copyright Act in this respect which brings more clarity on this
			<lb />
			aspect. The said provisions are reproduced hereinafter:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;Section 5 (5) The copyright in a literary, dramatic or
			<lb />
			musical work is also infringed by any person who permits a
			<lb />
			place of public entertainment to be used for a performance
			<lb />
			in public of the work, where the performance constitutes an
			<lb />
			infringement of copyright in the work :
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			Provided that this sub section shall not apply in a case where
			<lb />
			the person permitting the place to be so used -
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			a) was not aware, and had no reasonable grounds for
			<lb />
			suspecting, that the performance would be an
			<lb />
			infringement of copyright, or
			<lb />
			b) gave the permission gratuitously or for a
			<lb />
			consideration which was only nominal or (if more
			<lb />
			than nominal) did not exceed reasonable estimate of
			<lb />
			expenses to be incurred by him in consequence of the
			<lb />
			use of the place for the performance.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(6)
			<lb />
			In this section &quot;place of public entertainment&quot;
			<lb />
			includes any premises which are occupied mainly for other
			<lb />
			purposes, but are from time to time made available for hire
			<lb />
			to such persons as may desire to hire them for purposes of
			<lb />
			public entertainment&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			28.
			<lb />
			I am also comparing the provisions of UK Copyright Act,
			<lb />
			1988 (CDPA) which has been passed in the year 1988 repealing the
			<lb />
			earlier law. The said provisions are:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;Section 25 : Secondary Infringement:
			<lb />
			permitting use of premises for infringing
			<lb />
			performance.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(1)
			<lb />
			Where the copyright in a literary,
			<lb />
			dramatic or musical work is infringed by a
			<lb />
			performance at a place of public entertainment, any
			<lb />
			person who gave permission for that place to be
			<lb />
			used for the performance is also liable for the
			<lb />
			infringement unless when he gave permission he
			<lb />
			believed on reasonable grounds that the
			<lb />
			performance would not infringe copyright.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(2)
			<lb />
			In this section &quot;place of public
			<lb />
			entertainment&quot; includes premises which are
			<lb />
			occupied mainly for other purposes but are from
			<lb />
			time to time made available for hire for the
			<lb />
			purposes of public entertainment.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			Section 26 : Secondary Infringement: provision
			<lb />
			of apparatus for infringing performance, etc
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(1)
			<lb />
			Where copyright in a work is infringed by
			<lb />
			a public performance of the work, or by the playing
			<lb />
			or showing of the work in public, by means of
			<lb />
			apparatus for -
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(a) playing sound recordings,
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(b) showing films, or
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(c) receiving visual images or sounds
			<lb />
			conveyed by electronic means, the
			<lb />
			following persons are also liable for
			<lb />
			the infringement.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(2)
			<lb />
			A person who supplied the apparatus, or any
			<lb />
			substantial part of it, is liable for the infringement if when he
			<lb />
			supplied the apparatus or part-
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			a)
			<lb />
			he knew or had reason to believe that the
			<lb />
			apparatus was likely to be so used as to
			<lb />
			infringe copyright, or
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			b)
			<lb />
			in the case of apparatus whose normal use
			<lb />
			involves a public performance, playing or
			<lb />
			showing, he did not believe on reasonable
			<lb />
			grounds that it would not be so used as to
			<lb />
			infringe copyright.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(3)
			<lb />
			An occupier of premises who gave permission for
			<lb />
			the apparatus to be brought onto the premises is liable for
			<lb />
			the infringement if when he gave permission he knew or had
			<lb />
			reason to believe that the apparatus was likely to be so used
			<lb />
			as to infringe copyright.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(4)
			<lb />
			A person who supplied a copy of sound recording
			<lb />
			or film used to infringe copyright is liable for the
			<lb />
			infringement if when he supplied it he knew or had reason to
			<lb />
			believe that what he supplied, or a copy made directly or
			<lb />
			indirectly from it, was likely to be so used as to infringe
			<lb />
			copyright.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			29.
			<lb />
			By comparing the situation as exists in 1956 Act of UK and
			<lb />
			1957 Act of India in the provisions, it becomes amply clear that the
			<lb />
			wordings used in the Section of UK Act are &quot;place of public
			<lb />
			entertainment&quot; but in Indian Act, the wordings used are &quot;any place&quot;
			<lb />
			which reflects the intention of the legislature which is to provide a
			<lb />
			provision for permissive infringement wherein it is not merely a place of
			<lb />
			public entertainment which is included but any place wherein the
			<lb />
			infringement is facilitated would be covered by the provision of the
			<lb />
			Indian Copyright Act, 1957.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			30.
			<lb />
			The situation becomes more clear as one further sees carefully
			<lb />
			the later enactment of same nature in the UK CDPA Act of 1988 which
			<lb />
			provides two kinds of infringements separately which are that the &quot;place
			<lb />
			of public entertainment&quot; and &quot;infringement caused by use of an
			<lb />
			apparatus&quot;. This fine distinction which is present in the later Act of UK is
			<lb />
			not present in the Indian Act. This would demonstrate that UK legislature
			<lb />
			was conscious about the kinds of the infringement which are going to be
			<lb />
			caused in the light of the development in the technology and mere
			<lb />
			provision of facilitating the infringement at public place of entertainment
			<lb />
			would not sufficiently cover the protection and the apparatus
			<lb />
			infringement must be provided separately under the separate head.
			<lb />
			Therefore, in the light of the same, the provision relating to providing
			<lb />
			means by way of apparatus is further introduced in addition to the already
			<lb />
			existing provision which relates to infringement relates to place of public
			<lb />
			entertainment in the 1988 Act.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			31.
			<lb />
			In the sharp contrast, our Indian Act which has been amended
			<lb />
			number of times i.e. in 1984, 1994, 1999 which although provided for
			<lb />
			several crucial amendments including computer programmes as a subject
			<lb />
			of copyright under the head of literary work but has not provided any
			<lb />
			separate infringement by way of an apparatus under the separate head or
			<lb />
			separately and the provision relates to the facilitating infringement is the
			<lb />
			same as it stood in the 1957 Act. In absence of such amendment in the
			<lb />
			Indian Act and in view of the loosely worded provision which is &quot;any
			<lb />
			place&quot;, the same can be given a wider connotation so as to include the
			<lb />
			place on the internet not confining it to place of entertainment but to
			<lb />
			extend it to other places also.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			32.
			<lb />
			It is now well settled that when there are new technological
			<lb />
			inventions or change in circumstances which was not in contemplation at
			<lb />
			the time when the statute was enacted, the said invention or technological
			<lb />
			advancement may be included in the same enactment if they are falling
			<lb />
			within the same genus provided in the existing enactment.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			33.
			<lb />
			The reference in this respect is invited to the decision of
			<lb />
			House of Lords in Comdel Commodities Ltd vs. Siporex Trade SA,
			<lb />
			(1990) 2 All ER 552, wherein Lord Bridge has said &quot;When a change in
			<lb />
			social conditions produces a novel situation which was not in
			<lb />
			contemplation at the time when a statute is first enacted, there can be no
			<lb />
			a priori assumption that the enactment does not apply to the new
			<lb />
			circumstances. If the language of the enactment is wide enough to extend
			<lb />
			to those circumstances, there is no reason why it should not apply.&quot;
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			On the same principles, general words are construed as to
			<lb />
			include new inventions and technological advances not known at the time
			<lb />
			when the act was passed. The Photograph copy is held to be a copy
			<lb />
			under the Engraving Copyright Act, 1734 in the case of Gambart v. Ball
			<lb />
			(1863) 32 LJCP 166. Similarly telephone was not invented in 1869, even
			<lb />
			then the telephone was held to be a telegraph under the provisions of
			<lb />
			Telegraphs Act 1863 in the case of A.G. vs. Edison Telephone Co of
			<lb />
			London (1880) 6 QBD 244 referred in The Senior Electric Inspector
			<lb />
			vs. Laxminarayan Chopra &amp; Ors., AIR 1962 SC 159.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			34.
			<lb />
			More Recently Hon&quot;ble Supreme Court in State of
			<lb />
			Maharashtra vs. Praful B Desai (Dr.), (2003) 4 SCC 601, has
			<lb />
			accepted the evidence by way of video conferencing as a valid one where
			<lb />
			the person being tried will satisfy the requirement of Section 273 of Code
			<lb />
			of Criminal Procedure, 1973 when the technique of video conferencing
			<lb />
			was not even developed.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			35.
			<lb />
			In view of the same and also the fact that the provision
			<lb />
			provides for permitting &quot;any place&quot; which itself is loosely worded and is
			<lb />
			unfettered by any qualification, the said words &quot;any place&quot; have to be
			<lb />
			construed widely so as to include the place at the webspace or internet in
			<lb />
			order to give effect to the provision to be operative in cases of newer
			<lb />
			kind of the infringements being caused at the webspace.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			36.
			<lb />
			This is more so, in the absence of the specific provision
			<lb />
			relating to infringement by way of apparatus, the law in that situation
			<lb />
			cannot remain static witnessing the infringements which can be otherwise
			<lb />
			covered under the Act. The provisions which can conveniently cover the
			<lb />
			said acts must also be interpreted to include those new acts to make the
			<lb />
			provision workable for the newer kinds of infringement to the extent the
			<lb />
			wordings permit so. Therefore, the wordings &quot;any place&quot; under Section
			<lb />
			51 (a) (ii) of the Act includes the place at the webspace in order to cover
			<lb />
			the infringements or the wrongs caused at the webspace.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			37.
			<lb />
			The proposition which emerges from the above discussion is
			<lb />
			that there is an express provision under the Act which prohibits a person
			<lb />
			from permitting any place including webspace for profit unless the said
			<lb />
			person is having no knowledge or reason to believe that the
			<lb />
			communication of the work is infringing in nature.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			38.
			<lb />
			There is, however, another way of approaching the similar
			<lb />
			kind of proposition which is popularly known as infringement by way of
			<lb />
			authorization. This is done by interpreting Section 51 (a) (i) read with
			<lb />
			Section 14 of the Act. The said Sections are reproduced hereinafter:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;51. When copyright infringed -Copyright in a
			<lb />
			work shall be deemed to be infringed -
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(a) When any person, without a licence granted by
			<lb />
			the owner of the Copyright or the Registrar of
			<lb />
			Copyrights under this Act or in contravention of the
			<lb />
			conditions of a licence so granted or of any
			<lb />
			conditions imposed by a competent authority under
			<lb />
			this Act-
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(i) does anything, the exclusive right to do which is
			<lb />
			by this Act conferred upon the owner of the
			<lb />
			copyright, or……..&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			&quot;14. Meaning of copyright-For the purposes of this
			<lb />
			Act, &quot;copyright&quot; means the exclusive right subject
			<lb />
			to the provisions of this Act, to do or authorise the
			<lb />
			doing of any of the following acts in respect of a
			<lb />
			work or any substantial part thereof, namely :-
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(a) In the case of a literary, dramatic or musical
			<lb />
			work not being a computer programme,-……&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			39.
			<lb />
			By reading these provisions together, it can be seen doing the
			<lb />
			acts of owner of copyright without permission or licence amounts to
			<lb />
			infringement. The acts of owner are defined under Section 14 which
			<lb />
			include doing or authorize doing the acts. Thus, by virtue of conjoint
			<lb />
			reading one can say that the infringement of copyright can also be in the
			<lb />
			cases where there are acts of authorizing the infringement by anyone
			<lb />
			without permission.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			40.
			<lb />
			The said concept of authorizing the infringement has been
			<lb />
			succinctly discussed by Copinger &amp; Skone James on Copyright
			<lb />
			(Fourteenth Edition by Kevin Garnett M.A., Jonathan R. James, MA.
			<lb />
			LLB, Gillian Davies, Ph.D., 1999 Edition, London, Sweet &amp; Maxwell),
			<lb />
			who is an authority on the subject in the following words:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;7-151 Meaning of &quot;authorize&quot;, Authorization
			<lb />
			means the grant or purported grant which may be
			<lb />
			express or implied, of the right to do the act
			<lb />
			complained of, whether the intention is that the
			<lb />
			grantee should do the act on his own account or
			<lb />
			only on account of the grantor. An expression
			<lb />
			which has been often used as equivalent to the
			<lb />
			word &quot;authorize&quot; is &quot;sanction, approve, or
			<lb />
			countenance&quot; but this must be treated with caution
			<lb />
			particularly in so far as the word &quot;countenance&quot; is
			<lb />
			equivalent to the word &quot;condone&quot;. Thus, in general
			<lb />
			an authorization &quot;can only come from someone
			<lb />
			having or purporting to have authority and an act is
			<lb />
			not authorized by someone who merely enables or
			<lb />
			possibly assists or even encourages another to do
			<lb />
			that act, but does not purport to have any authority
			<lb />
			which he can grant to justify the doing of the act.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			41.
			<lb />
			It is noteworthy to mention that the said concept of
			<lb />
			authorizing the infringement although looks akin to Section 51 (a) (ii) of
			<lb />
			the Act but the said authorization does not coincide with the permitting
			<lb />
			the place for profit. The concept of authorizing the infringement is rather
			<lb />
			bigger and cannot be equated with merely facilitating the place for profit
			<lb />
			which is the express provision of the law, which may be said to be one its
			<lb />
			facets. The act of authorizing is something more than merely providing
			<lb />
			means with knowledge and require further active participation of the
			<lb />
			person than that of the permitting the place for infringement. This is due
			<lb />
			to the reason that the grant of means to an infringement is different than
			<lb />
			the granting the right to do the act of infringement.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			41.1
			<lb />
			Sometimes the infringement is not done directly but is done
			<lb />
			indirectly by the authority of some person for instance where a person
			<lb />
			handovers a pirated CD to a friend and also asks him to make number of
			<lb />
			copies and sell them to the public on behalf of the former. In that
			<lb />
			situation, the former is authorizing infringement which he is doing
			<lb />
			through another person. Both are parties to an infringement due to their
			<lb />
			direct or active involvement. In this example, the person retains his
			<lb />
			control where he can say to his friend to do or not to do the same on his
			<lb />
			behalf. Besides that, the former person also has knowledge about the
			<lb />
			pirated nature of the CD which is also relevant. Thus, it is an
			<lb />
			authorization and it is not merely providing a means for infringement but
			<lb />
			rather more than the same which is doing the infringement along with the
			<lb />
			co infringer or under the authority of a person.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			41.2
			<lb />
			The act of authorizing infringement is premised on the
			<lb />
			concept of joint tort feasors wherein the person is held liable for
			<lb />
			commission of equal wrong when there is apparent clear establishment of
			<lb />
			his involvement in the wrong along with the other person committing the
			<lb />
			same. The active participation, inducement, approval or countenance, are
			<lb />
			thus necessary ingredients of authorization may not be sine qua non for
			<lb />
			the establishment of permission of place for profit. The knowledge of the
			<lb />
			fact that the acts are going to be infringing is again different from the
			<lb />
			active participation or any kind of inducement.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			41.3
			<lb />
			The knowledge is the starting point for authorization which is
			<lb />
			going to be established unless the clear active participation or reasonable
			<lb />
			degree of control is proved besides knowledge. But on the other hand the
			<lb />
			same may not be true with permitting the place for profit wherein there is
			<lb />
			only knowledge which is sufficient and the further state of affairs may
			<lb />
			remain irrelevant. Therefore, the onus of proof for establishing the
			<lb />
			authorization is more onerous than that of the establishing facilitation for
			<lb />
			profit.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			41.4
			<lb />
			This distinction between the two concepts is necessary in
			<lb />
			order to better comprehend the subject which will make the evaluation of
			<lb />
			arguments raised by the parties easier.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			42.
			<lb />
			Now, I shall deal with the contentions of the parties raised by
			<lb />
			them relating to the authorization and the applicability of Section 51 (a)
			<lb />
			(ii) of the Act.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			43.
			<lb />
			It is the contention of learned counsel for the plaintiff that the
			<lb />
			acts of providing the space over the internet and thereafter continuously
			<lb />
			doing the same ever after coming to know about the plaintiff&quot;s
			<lb />
			proprietary interests amounts to authorization as the defendants are aware
			<lb />
			that the said space is going to be used for infringement purposes. As per
			<lb />
			the learned counsel, the said acts become authorization as the defendants
			<lb />
			retain the control and power to further distribute or communicate the
			<lb />
			work to the public. The said thing is done by the defendants with
			<lb />
			knowledge coupled with that of its own participation wherein it is
			<lb />
			offering the works of the plaintiff to the public at large by enlisting the
			<lb />
			works of the defendants in their search engine in such a way that when
			<lb />
			someone types the name of a song or a movie, the same is easily
			<lb />
			available on the search results. Mr. Sibal has narrated the factors by
			<lb />
			which the defendants are authorizing the infringement which can be
			<lb />
			enumerated as under:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			a)
			<lb />
			The defendants provide a search facility which enables anyone
			<lb />
			who visits its website to locate audio-visual or audio files
			<lb />
			amongst those uploaded by other users, which files are copied
			<lb />
			by the defendants and stored on their servers.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			b)
			<lb />
			The defendants prescribe the terms of use which must
			<lb />
			necessarily be subscribed to by a User for becoming a
			<lb />
			defendants&quot; User.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			c)
			<lb />
			A person has to necessarily be a registered User with the
			<lb />
			defendant/MySpace to use the uploading facility (which
			<lb />
			ultimately leads to infringement).
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			d)
			<lb />
			MySpace /defendant can without anybody&quot;s approval reject,
			<lb />
			refuse to post or delete any content for any or no reason
			<lb />
			uploaded on its website.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			e)
			<lb />
			Defendants take license from the User for the content
			<lb />
			uploaded and can modify, delete from and add to the said
			<lb />
			content.
			<lb />
			All these factors as per Mr. Sibal are evidence of the degree
			<lb />
			of control which the defendants can exercise and thus, the authorization
			<lb />
			gets established once the defendants are found to be controlling the
			<lb />
			infringing activities and has its say in preventing them or controlling
			<lb />
			them.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			44.
			<lb />
			Mr. Sibal has also made submissions that the said acts
			<lb />
			amounts to infringement as per the provision of Section 51 (a) (ii) of the
			<lb />
			Act due to aforesaid reasons.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			45.
			<lb />
			On the other hand, Mr. Kumar resisted the same by stating
			<lb />
			that neither the said acts are authorization and nor the same are falling
			<lb />
			under Section 51 (a) (ii) due to the following reasons:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			a)
			<lb />
			The defendants are having no control over the works which are
			<lb />
			uploaded on the websites everyday and thus they are no privy to
			<lb />
			any such works which are infringing in nature.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			b)
			<lb />
			The defendants are not having any knowledge about which are the
			<lb />
			works which are infringing or non infringing. It is only subsequent
			<lb />
			to uploading and thereafter when the proprietor brings it to their
			<lb />
			notice, it becomes clear that the works are infringing in nature.
			<lb />
			Therefore, once it is without knowledge coupled by no control
			<lb />
			over the works, the defendants cannot be held liable for
			<lb />
			infringement.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			c)
			<lb />
			The defendants have cited the safe harbor provisions of US law
			<lb />
			and lot of cases decided under English law (which has been
			<lb />
			commented on later in the judgment as at this stage, the issue of
			<lb />
			infringement is decided).
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			d)
			<lb />
			It is well established, that merely providing means for doing the
			<lb />
			acts which may be infringing, the person cannot be held liable for
			<lb />
			authorization and therefore, the defendants in the absence of clear
			<lb />
			establishment of its role in doing or promoting the infringement
			<lb />
			cannot be held liable for infringement.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			e)
			<lb />
			There are several measures or safeguards like notice and turn
			<lb />
			down and many more are already undertaken by the defendants
			<lb />
			and therefore, the defendants are not infringers.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			46.
			<lb />
			I have examined the submissions of the parties carefully and
			<lb />
			have gone through the plaint, written statement and documents filed by
			<lb />
			the parties and after doing so, I am of the opinion that the acts of
			<lb />
			defendants of providing the space on internet or webspace for profit are
			<lb />
			prima facie infringing in nature. The reasons for my prima facie
			<lb />
			observations can be discussed as follows:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			a)
			<lb />
			Firstly, it would be wise to reiterate three proposition which I have
			<lb />
			already discussed earlier.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			 The provision of Section 51 (a) (i) and Section 51 (a) (ii)
			<lb />
			of the Act are disjunctive in nature in as much as the word
			<lb />
			&quot;or&quot; between the two makes it clear that even on
			<lb />
			satisfaction of one provision, there would be an
			<lb />
			infringement of copyright.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			 The infringement by way of authorization would fall within
			<lb />
			Section 51 (a) (1) read with Section 14 of the Act as
			<lb />
			against the act of permitting the place for profit which is
			<lb />
			separately provided under Section 51(a) (ii) of the Act.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			 There is a distinction between the concept of authorization
			<lb />
			as well as the concept of permitting the place for profit and
			<lb />
			the essential ingredients for establishing the same are also
			<lb />
			different.
			<lb />
			Keeping these three propositions in mind, I have no hesitation to
			<lb />
			state that the acts of the defendants whereby they are offering the space
			<lb />
			over the internet, getting the works uploaded through users, thereafter
			<lb />
			saving in their own database with the limited licence to add, amend, or
			<lb />
			delete the content and thereafter communicating the said work to the
			<lb />
			public by providing some advertisements alongside the work or in the
			<lb />
			alternative gaining advertisements or sponsorships on the said basis
			<lb />
			thereafter would prima facie tantamounts to permitting the place for profit
			<lb />
			for infringement as envisaged under Section 51 (a) (ii) of the Act.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			b)
			<lb />
			The said acts of the defendants are certainly falling within the
			<lb />
			realm of an infringement under Section 51(a) (ii) of the Act. This is
			<lb />
			due to the reason that the defendants are permitting the place
			<lb />
			which is place at webspace to the users at large. The said place is
			<lb />
			not for the profit of the users only but also for the private profits or
			<lb />
			gains of the defendants. The defendants do not dispute that they
			<lb />
			are running the advertisement but their stand is that some
			<lb />
			advertisements are automatically appearing due to the search
			<lb />
			engines or key words which are typed by the users. The defendants
			<lb />
			although state that they are not advertising anything or earning
			<lb />
			anything due to the same. But, I am afraid that it is not the truth,
			<lb />
			the advertisements which are attached to movie clips or are
			<lb />
			displayed prior to the starting of the clip or after the movie clip is
			<lb />
			ended, are not the user provided or automatically emerging ones
			<lb />
			but are sponsored. There are third kind of advertisements which
			<lb />
			are displayed till the time work is being downloaded on the
			<lb />
			website and is ready to play, the said advertisements keep the user
			<lb />
			busy uptil the user reaches the definite target which is intended
			<lb />
			movie song or movie clips. All this happens only when the
			<lb />
			defendants permit this to happen and to the advantage of the
			<lb />
			defendants. Thus, the defendants are certainly earning profits or
			<lb />
			gains and not doing anything mistakenly or bonafidely without
			<lb />
			notice as contended by them. There is certainly complete element
			<lb />
			of commerce attached to it to increase the bandwidth of the
			<lb />
			users/customers and sponsorship and/or adds. Thus, the defendants
			<lb />
			are permitting the place for profit.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			47.
			<lb />
			Now, the submission of the defendants that their acts are
			<lb />
			without knowledge or no reasonable belief of infringement are, therefore,
			<lb />
			would not fall within the Section 51 (a) (ii) but would be protected by the
			<lb />
			later part of the Section is also meritless. It is also not difficult now to
			<lb />
			answer the question of knowledge or reasonable belief which can be
			<lb />
			immediately discerned due to following factual situations:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			 Firstly, the defendants are themselves providing the
			<lb />
			safeguards in the event of the infringing activities being
			<lb />
			carried upon their website which means that the
			<lb />
			defendants have atleast reasonable apprehension or belief
			<lb />
			that the acts which are being carried on the website may
			<lb />
			infringe someone else&quot;s copyright including the plaintiff.
		</item>
		<lb />
		<item>
			The defendants could immediately turn and say
			<lb />
			that the said provisions are made to prevent the
			<lb />
			infringement as per the international laws more
			<lb />
			specifically Digital Millennium Copyright Act (&quot;DMCA&quot;)
			<lb />
			of US. However, the said fact does not preclude this court
			<lb />
			from drawing any inference as to the reasonable belief of
			<lb />
			the defendants that the activities upon their website are
			<lb />
			infringing in nature. Perhaps the legislature in US is more
			<lb />
			conscious of these frequent infringements on the internet
			<lb />
			and that is the reason it has enacted the special Act for
			<lb />
			these purposes for providing curative measures and
			<lb />
			thereby giving such acts a legitimate effect by balancing
			<lb />
			the two interests one of internet infringer and another of
			<lb />
			the proprietor by providing that the post infringement
			<lb />
			curative measures as sufficient safeguards for the
			<lb />
			purposes of infringement and protecting any such
			<lb />
			infringement liability . But the same may not be legal in
			<lb />
			the Indian scenario absenting such situation. Therefore,
			<lb />
			this Court can infer the reasonable amount of knowledge
			<lb />
			by the defendants about the infringing nature of the acts
			<lb />
			which are going to be carried on the defendants&quot; website
			<lb />
			when the defendants on their own provide with these
			<lb />
			measures. Certainly, there is a reasonable belief by the
			<lb />
			defendants that the acts are infringing in nature.
		</item>
		<lb />
		<item>
			 Secondly, the reasonable belief or knowledge specifically
			<lb />
			to that of the plaintiff works is also present in this case.
			<lb />
			This is due to the reason that the plaintiff has already
			<lb />
			notified its company name and lists of the titles owned by
			<lb />
			it. The defendants have also been dealing with the
			<lb />
			plaintiff prior to the institution of the suit. Thus, the
			<lb />
			defendants cannot be said to be totally oblivious to the
			<lb />
			fact that the Bollywood songs which are going to be
			<lb />
			IA Nos.15781/2008 &amp; 3085/2009 in CS(OS) No. 2682/2008
			<lb />
			Page No.69 of 132
			<lb />
			uploaded on their website may not belong to the plaintiff.
			<lb />
			Rather the defendants on its own states that while
			<lb />
			launching India centric operations, the defendants have
			<lb />
			informed all the music companies about their tools.
			<lb />
			Furthermore, when the defendants have been notified
			<lb />
			time and again by the plaintiff about updated works and
			<lb />
			the defendants are hard pressed to remove those contents.
			<lb />
			In these circumstances, the defendants&quot; stand at this stage
			<lb />
			that they are totally unaware of the situation is not
			<lb />
			correct. There is complete knowledge to the defendants
			<lb />
			of the infringing nature of acts which are going to be
			<lb />
			carried on their website and rather it would not be out of
			<lb />
			place to say that the defendants are also aware that the
			<lb />
			plaintiff&quot;s works are available on the website which are
			<lb />
			infringing in nature.
		</item>
		<lb />
		<item>
			 Thirdly, the knowledge and reasonable belief for
			<lb />
			infringement to the defendants can be seen when one
			<lb />
			examines the mechanism of working of the defendants.
			<lb />
			The defendants take the limited licence to amend or
			<lb />
			delete or modify the works suitably from the user. This
			<lb />
			itself makes it evident that before uploading on the
			<lb />
			website or making it available on the website, the works
			<lb />
			in question go into the servers or the computers of the
			<lb />
			defendants where the programmers modify the said
			<lb />
			contents or amend the said contents suitably. Rather the
			<lb />
			said modification also goes to the extent of adding
			<lb />
			advertisements prior to the clips or after the clips
			<lb />
			embellishing them, adding logos of the companies.
		</item>
		<lb />
		<item>
			All this is nothing but knowledge about the content
			<lb />
			what the defendants are displaying, showing, exhibiting.
			<lb />
			Thus, the defendants&quot; stand that they are totally unaware
			<lb />
			at the time of uploading what is going on and they should
			<lb />
			be protected being unconnected with anyone is also ex-
			<lb />
			facie bad. On the contrary at the time of uploading and
			<lb />
			till the time the said work is made available to the public
			<lb />
			on search engine form by the defendants, there are
			<lb />
			sufficient steps including modification (which has a
			<lb />
			major role) wherein the knowledge of the defendants can
			<lb />
			be seen.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			 Fourthly, the knowledge and reasonable belief of
			<lb />
			infringement is also apparent on behalf of the defendants
			<lb />
			when the defendants&quot;
			<lb />
			indulge into India centric
			<lb />
			operation as contended by the plaintiff. It is also stated
			<lb />
			that the defendants have whole office dedicated to Indian
			<lb />
			works which caters the Indian consumers. The
			<lb />
			modifications of the works, India centric offices or
			<lb />
			operations, adding advertisements of the same language,
			<lb />
			seeking licences from users to modify or alter the works,
			<lb />
			informing the major copyright owners about its tool
			<lb />
			anticipating actions by them or preventing need for
			<lb />
			licences, all these makes the knowledge more apparent
			<lb />
			on the face of the record.
		</item>
		<lb />
		<item>
			Thus, clearly due to complete satisfaction of the
			<lb />
			provision of Section 51 (a) (ii), the acts of defendants are
			<lb />
			prima facie infringing in nature, which are violative of
			<lb />
			Section 51 (a) (ii) of the Act.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			48.
			<lb />
			So far as the act of authorization is concerned, The said act
			<lb />
			requires sanction, approval or countenance which are the wordings used
			<lb />
			in English Judgments which are more than the mere act of knowledge. I
			<lb />
			have already distinguished the authorization which would fall within
			<lb />
			Section 51 (a) (i) from that Section 51 (a) (ii) of the Act which expressly
			<lb />
			provides knowledge or reasonable belief as only tests for satisfaction. I
			<lb />
			shall now examine and test the acts of defendants on the principles of
			<lb />
			authorization.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			The principles for satisfaction of authorization are laid down
			<lb />
			in various cases which are cited at bar. However, for the sake of brevity
			<lb />
			the same can be culled out as follows:
		</p>
		<lb />
		<item>
			1. The authorization requires countenance or sanction or
			<lb />
			approval from that of the person authorizing the said act.
			<lb />
			This means that the said action of sanction or approval
			<lb />
			requires more to be shown than mere knowledge ( Kindly
			<lb />
			see C.B.S. Inc. &amp; C.B.S. United Kingdom v. Ames
			<lb />
			Records &amp; Tapes Limited; (1981) RPC 407 (decided on
			<lb />
			13 th February, 1981) where court used sanction and
			<lb />
			approval as the test).
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			2. The authorization has to be targeted to the identified
			<lb />
			persons so that the clear case is made out. (Although
			<lb />
			Copinger(Supra) differs from this view).
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			3. The authorization requires that the person must have the
			<lb />
			authority to permit the infringement in as much as the
			<lb />
			person giving the authorization must retain a control over
			<lb />
			the subject matter in order to call it as authorization.
			<lb />
			(Kindly see C.B.S. Songs Limited &amp; Others vs. Amstrad
			<lb />
			Consumer Electronics Plc. &amp; Another (House of Lords),
			<lb />
			(1988) RPC 567)
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			4. Merely providing means for infringement does not
			<lb />
			establish control and therefore the person cannot be said to
			<lb />
			have approved or countenanced such act.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			49.
			<lb />
			Broadly English Courts have tested all the cases on these very
			<lb />
			principles while attributing the liability over the infringers or in
			<lb />
			alternative rejecting the case of infringement. Mostly, in cases relating to
			<lb />
			newer means like tape recorder or in the cases of jukebox which are mere
			<lb />
			means for providing recordings of songs, the courts in England or
			<lb />
			common law have rejected the claims of infringement on the ground that
			<lb />
			these are merely new means for recording and nothing more unless the
			<lb />
			participation of providing the means must be shown towards the
			<lb />
			infringement. Let me now examine the acts of the defendants on these
			<lb />
			principles.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			50.
			<lb />
			It was the contention of the defendants that no clear
			<lb />
			establishment of their involvement is made out as the portal of the
			<lb />
			defendants is such wherein every day there is much of data which is
			<lb />
			being uploaded and thus the defendants could not be held liable for
			<lb />
			authorization.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			Further, it has been said on behalf of the defendants that the
			<lb />
			defendants are themselves cautious by putting notices on the internet by
			<lb />
			calling upon to users not to upload infringing contents. It is also said that
			<lb />
			the defendants are providing notice and turn down features which shows
			<lb />
			that the said acts are not emanating from the defendants. It is not the
			<lb />
			defendants who are promoting those acts.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			51.
			<lb />
			I have gone through the rival submissions of the parties.
			<lb />
			While testing the acts of the defendants on the threshold principles
			<lb />
			available under the common law, the doubts can be expressed at the
			<lb />
			prima facie stage whether the plaintiff has completely discharged its onus
			<lb />
			of proving as to whether the acts of communicating the musical works,
			<lb />
			sound recordings are actuated by the countenance, approval or not. Mr.
			<lb />
			Sibal has taken pains to inform this court that there is an element of
			<lb />
			control which has been exercised by the defendants. However, I am not
			<lb />
			fully satisfied whether the said factors enumerated by the Mr. Sibal
			<lb />
			would sufficiently establish at this prima facie stage such degree of
			<lb />
			control by the defendants which can also be called as approval or
			<lb />
			countenance or sanctioning. No doubt, I have arrived at the prima facie
			<lb />
			view that there is knowledge which is clearly present at this stage
			<lb />
			wherein the defendants are aware what they are communicating. But the
			<lb />
			act of approval or sanction requires, the defendants&quot; participation,
			<lb />
			exercise of control besides knowledge which I feel is a question which
			<lb />
			can determined only at the time of trial as at this stage it is not clearly
			<lb />
			emerging from the documents as to the state of affairs after the
			<lb />
			knowledge which may be relevant for establishing the authorization .
			<lb />
			This is also more so because the approval or sanction is required to be
			<lb />
			established particularly towards the present acts of infringement which is
			<lb />
			difficult to comment upon at this stage.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			52.
			<lb />
			In addition to the above, one more thing which needs to be
			<lb />
			considered is that the defendants plead that the acts of the defendants are
			<lb />
			not authorization, to which I have already answered the same at this
			<lb />
			stage. However, once the plaintiff informs about the works owned by it
			<lb />
			to the defendants, the said defendants thereafter attain knowledge not
			<lb />
			only of the means to be used for infringement but also the knowledge
			<lb />
			about the rights of the plaintiff. The necessary consequence which
			<lb />
			follows from the same is that once the defendants are put to notice about
			<lb />
			the rights of the plaintiff in relation to the particular works, thereafter the
			<lb />
			defendants cannot continue to do the said acts in relation to the works for
			<lb />
			which the details have been provided without the permission of the
			<lb />
			plaintiff. In that event, the defendants after putting to notice immediately
			<lb />
			steps into the shoes of the ordinary infringer under Section 51 (a) (i) of
			<lb />
			the Act who is aware of the rights of the plaintiff (copyright owner) and
			<lb />
			then the question of authorization becomes irrelevant and the acts are to
			<lb />
			be adjudged from the standpoint of ordinary infringement.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			53.
			<lb />
			The defendants have already stated in the written statement
			<lb />
			that the arrangement done by the Division Bench is the possible solution
			<lb />
			to this proposition arising in the present case. The defendants&quot; counsel
			<lb />
			has also stated that he would have no objection if the order passed by the
			<lb />
			Division Bench is continued. Thus, the defendant&quot;s acts are infringing in
			<lb />
			violation of Section 51 (a) (i) of the Act once the defendants are put to
			<lb />
			notice about the plaintiff rights in the respective works and in the event
			<lb />
			the defendants do not turn down the same or allow the repetition to
			<lb />
			happen.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			54.
			<lb />
			In these circumstances, I am of the view that though the acts
			<lb />
			of the defendants are prima facie infringing in view of the satisfaction of
			<lb />
			provision of Section 51 (a) (ii) of the Act but the question of the
			<lb />
			authorization requires further proof of participation which has to be
			<lb />
			tested at the time of trial. Nevertheless, the defendants are infringing the
			<lb />
			plaintiff&quot;s work as their acts are falling within the alternative or
			<lb />
			disjunctive requirement for infringement under Section 51 (a) (ii) of the
			<lb />
			Act. Further, the defendants&quot; act may become infringing if the defendants
			<lb />
			do not turn down or allow the repeated uploads to happen after put to the
			<lb />
			notice about the plaintiff&quot;s rights in the said works.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<head>
			Re: Jurisdiction
			<lb />
		</head>

		<p>
			55.
			<lb />
			Now I shall deal with other submissions of the parties point
			<lb />
			wise including the issue relating to jurisdiction. At the threshold, I would
			<lb />
			like to state that I have held that this court has the jurisdiction and
			<lb />
			therefore proceeded to decide the aspect of copyright infringement first. I
			<lb />
			shall now discuss the reasons for arriving at the conclusion that this Court
			<lb />
			has necessary territorial jurisdiction which are as under:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			55.1
			<lb />
			Firstly, the present case relates to infringement of copyright
			<lb />
			wherein the remedies are conferred under the special statute. The said
			<lb />
			suit for infringement of copyright can be filed and initiated at the place
			<lb />
			wherein the plaintiff carries on business, or personally works for gain etc.
			<lb />
			This is by virtue of non obstante clause provided under Section 62 (2) of
			<lb />
			the Act which reads as under:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;62. Jurisdiction of court over matters arising under
			<lb />
			this Chapter. (1) Every suit or other civil
			<lb />
			proceeding arising under this Chapter in respect of
			<lb />
			the infringement of copyright in any work or the
			<lb />
			infringement of any other right conferred by this
			<lb />
			Act shall be instituted in the district court having
			<lb />
			jurisdiction.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(2) For the purpose of sub-section (1), a &quot;district
			<lb />
			court having jurisdiction&quot; shall notwithstanding
			<lb />
			anything contained in the Code of Civil Procedure,
			<lb />
			1908 (5 of 1908), or any other law for the time
			<lb />
			being in force, include a district court within the
			<lb />
			local limits of whose jurisdiction, at the time of the
			<lb />
			institution of the suit or other proceeding, the
			<lb />
			person instituting the suit or other proceeding or,
			<lb />
			where there are more than one such persons, any of
			<lb />
			them actually and voluntarily resides or carries on
			<lb />
			business or personal works for gain.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			55.2
			<lb />
			By mere reading of the provision of Section 62(2) of the Act,
			<lb />
			it becomes amply clear that the suit for infringement can be filed at the
			<lb />
			forum where the plaintiff resides or carries on business. The opening
			<lb />
			words of the provision provides &quot;Notwithstanding anything contained in
			<lb />
			the code of civil procedure&quot; which means that the said provision will
			<lb />
			operate in addition to what has be provided in the Code of Civil
			<lb />
			procedure. Thus, the said provision enables the suit to be filed at the
			<lb />
			place of the plaintiff which is the additional ground for attracting the
			<lb />
			jurisdiction of the court.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			55.3
			<lb />
			This question is no longer res integra and put to rest by the
			<lb />
			Supreme Court while examining the said provision in the case of Exphar
			<lb />
			SA &amp; Anr vs Eupharma Laboratories Ltd. &amp; Anr, (2004) 3 SCC 688
			<lb />
			wherein the Hon&quot;ble Court observed.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;It is, therefore, clear that the object and reason for
			<lb />
			the introduction of sub-section (2) of Section 62
			<lb />
			was not to restrict the owners of the copyright to
			<lb />
			exercise their rights but to remove any impediment
			<lb />
			from their doing so. Section 62(2) cannot be read as
			<lb />
			limiting the jurisdiction of the District Court only to
			<lb />
			cases where the person instituting the suit or other
			<lb />
			proceeding, or where there are more than one such
			<lb />
			persons, any of them actually and voluntarily
			<lb />
			resides or carries on business or presently works
			<lb />
			for gain. It prescribes an additional ground for
			<lb />
			attracting the jurisdiction of a Court over and above
			<lb />
			the &apos;normal&apos; grounds as laid down in Section 20 of
			<lb />
			the Code.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			Therefore, the plaintiff while it has initiated the said suit at the
			<lb />
			forum where it is carrying on business has rightly initiated the suit in
			<lb />
			compliance of the provision of Section 62(2) of the Act which is the
			<lb />
			additional ground for attracting the jurisdiction. In these circumstances,
			<lb />
			by operation of non-obstance clause, the principles relating to defendants
			<lb />
			carrying on business or part of cause of action or subject matter becomes
			<lb />
			irrelevant as the present case falls under the special provisions prescribed
			<lb />
			in the special statute. The said provisions under Section 62 are in addition
			<lb />
			to and not in derogation or conflict with the general law as envisaged in
			<lb />
			the Code of Civil Procedure. Thus, the recourse of the defendants&quot;
			<lb />
			counsel in relation to the principles of general law is misplaced.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			55.4
			<lb />
			The personal amenability of the defendants are therefore, not
			<lb />
			relevant in case of suit for infringement wherein the jurisdiction is sought
			<lb />
			to be invoked by way of provisions of the special enactment when it
			<lb />
			provides for non obstante clause. The said non obstante clause thus
			<lb />
			operate to its full extent and it cannot be said that there is a separate
			<lb />
			question of personal amenability of the defendants to be in the forum
			<lb />
			state which is still to be considered.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			55.5
			<lb />
			It is true that that to sue a foreign defendant in this country,
			<lb />
			the foreigner either must be resident and or carry on business within the
			<lb />
			jurisdiction of forum court. These are the principles applicable in private
			<lb />
			International law. The only exception is if such party submits to the
			<lb />
			jurisdiction. However the operation of this rule is not absolute but is
			<lb />
			subject to the municipal law.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			55.6
			<lb />
			It is now well settled that when the municipal law provides
			<lb />
			otherwise or overrides the private international law, then the municipal
			<lb />
			law prevails over and above the principles of private international law.
			<lb />
			The said principle has been comprehensively decided by Karnataka High
			<lb />
			Court in Airbus Industries Vs. Laura Howell Linton, ILR 1994 KAR
			<lb />
			1370 wherein the Court has stated that even the provisions of Section 20
			<lb />
			(c) of the Code of Civil Procedure which provides cause of action wholly
			<lb />
			or in part overrides the private international law.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			The Madras High Court in Swaminathan v. Somasundaram
			<lb />
			AIR 1938 Mad 731 in considering whether the Indian Courts have
			<lb />
			jurisdiction over non-resident foreigners, it was held that even with
			<lb />
			respect to non-resident foreigners, the Courts in British India have
			<lb />
			jurisdiction in personam in suits based upon a cause of action arising in
			<lb />
			British India.)
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			55.7
			<lb />
			Thus, in the present case also even assuming that the rules of
			<lb />
			private international law may have any role to play, the same stands
			<lb />
			overridden by the express provision of the special act which is Copyright
			<lb />
			Act, 1957 which speaks otherwise and entitles the plaintiff to sue at the
			<lb />
			place of its own forum.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			55.8
			<lb />
			Secondly, the argument was advanced by the defendants
			<lb />
			about the commission of torts outside India. The said argument is also
			<lb />
			rejected as meritless. The commission of tort in the present case is in
			<lb />
			India. The website of the defendants is one which is engaged in the
			<lb />
			online business of providing and exhibiting the songs and cinematograph
			<lb />
			films worldwide including India. The said website is usually accessed by
			<lb />
			Indians for downloading the songs of upcoming movies from the website
			<lb />
			of the defendants. The plaintiff has substantiated the cause of action by
			<lb />
			showing some instances of infringements which has been caused in
			<lb />
			relation to the specific works. Thus, the said commission of the tort has
			<lb />
			occurred or occurs in India wherein the Indian user goes to the website,
			<lb />
			the defendants through its search engine exhibits the said works and the
			<lb />
			work is communicated to the public by sending the work to him and
			<lb />
			facilitating downloading or reaching to the computer of Indian user.
			<lb />
			Similarly, conversely, when the Indian user shares the infringing work
			<lb />
			with the defendants&quot; website which goes into the servers of the
			<lb />
			defendants and saved there after the uploading. The said actions are
			<lb />
			sufficient to constitute part of cause of action under Section 20 (c) of the
			<lb />
			Code of Civil Procedure.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			55.9
			<lb />
			In the first case, the tort or civil wrong is caused in India as
			<lb />
			the aspect of downloading to the computer has been occurred in India
			<lb />
			when the said work is communicated to Indian users without the
			<lb />
			permission of the plaintiff. In the second case too, the initiation of the tort
			<lb />
			or part of the same has occurred in India as the infringing work without
			<lb />
			the authority of the plaintiff is communicated to the defendants with a
			<lb />
			limited licence to further modify and communicate further. The said
			<lb />
			commission of the acts or the part of the overt acts constitutes the part of
			<lb />
			cause of action within the meaning of Section 20 (c) of the Code of Civil
			<lb />
			Procedure.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			55.10
			<lb />
			Section 20 (c) of the Code confers jurisdiction where the
			<lb />
			cause of action wholly or in part arises. Thus, the court where the part of
			<lb />
			cause of action will arise would have the jurisdiction to entertain and try
			<lb />
			the proceeding like in the present case. So seeing from any standpoint be
			<lb />
			from special act or general code of civil procedure, this court has
			<lb />
			necessary territorial jurisdiction to entertain and try the proceedings.
			<lb />
			However, the discussion to Section 20 (c) of the Code becomes merely
			<lb />
			academic as the special act itself confers jurisdiction on this court by
			<lb />
			operation of non obstante clause. Still, I have deemed it fit to discuss the
			<lb />
			same in view of the categorical objections raised by the defendants on
			<lb />
			jurisdiction.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			55.11
			<lb />
			Thirdly, the reliance of the judgment of the Division Bench in
			<lb />
			Banyan Tree (Supra) is equally misplaced by the defendants and thus
			<lb />
			does not aid the case of the defendants at all.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			55.12
			<lb />
			It is a well settled principles the judgment is an authority of
			<lb />
			what it decides and not for the proposition which can be logically
			<lb />
			deduced therefrom. [The said proposition has been laid down by the
			<lb />
			Supreme Court in Bharat Forge Co. Ltd. v. Utam Manohar Nakate
			<lb />
			(2005) I LLJ 738 SC ; M.P. Gopalakrishnan Nair and Anr. vs. State
			<lb />
			of Kerala &amp; Ors.: AIR 2005 SC2053]
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			55.13.
			<lb />
			In Banyan Tree (Supra), the Hon&quot;ble Division Bench has
			<lb />
			rightly reframed the issue in the following manner:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;For the purposes of a passing-off action, or an
			<lb />
			infringement action where the plaintiff is not
			<lb />
			carrying on business within the jurisdiction of a
			<lb />
			court, in what circumstances can it be said that the
			<lb />
			hosting of a universally accessible web-site by the
			<lb />
			defendants lends jurisdiction to such court where
			<lb />
			such suit is filed (&quot;the forum state&quot;)?
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			56.
			<lb />
			By mere reading of the question answered by the Hon&quot;ble
			<lb />
			Division Bench, it becomes patently clear that the Hon&quot;ble Division
			<lb />
			Bench was concerned with the question wherein a passing off action,
			<lb />
			whether the jurisdiction of the court can be conferred by way of website
			<lb />
			operation of the defendants or not, or the case of infringement where the
			<lb />
			plaintiff is not carrying on business within the territorial jurisdiction of
			<lb />
			the court. The apparent distinguishing features which make Banyan tree
			<lb />
			case inapposite to the present case are outlined as under:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			a)
			<lb />
			Firstly, the case of Banyan Tree (Supra) was a case of passing off,
			<lb />
			however, the present case is a case of infringement wherein
			<lb />
			plaintiff invokes the jurisdiction on the basis of carrying on his
			<lb />
			business at the forum court. It needs no further mention that it is
			<lb />
			now well settled that the tests of conferring jurisdiction on the
			<lb />
			court in the case of the passing off and the infringement are totally
			<lb />
			different. Whereas, the jurisdiction in infringement cases is
			<lb />
			governed by the provisions of special act like Section 62(2) of the
			<lb />
			Copyright Act. On the other hand, in the passing off cases, it is
			<lb />
			governed by the ordinary law of civil procedure. Thus, the case of
			<lb />
			plaintiff carrying on business or working for gain which is a
			<lb />
			relevant and significant consideration in the present case in view of
			<lb />
			operation of special statute was absent in the case of Banyan Tree
			<lb />
			(Supra) and that was the sole reason the court had difficulty in
			<lb />
			assuming the jurisdiction in Banyan Tree (Supra) which lead to
			<lb />
			referral to division Bench for the question to be answered.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			b)
			<lb />
			Secondly, The Division Bench in Banyan Tree (Supra) also
			<lb />
			observed that if the case of Banyan Tree (Supra) would have been
			<lb />
			of infringement, then the court would have had jurisdiction and the
			<lb />
			special provisions of Section 62(2) of Copyright Act, 1957 as well
			<lb />
			as Section 134(2) of the Trade Marks Act are those of the kinds of
			<lb />
			the long arm provisions in the limited sense. The relevant excerpt
			<lb />
			from the Banyan Tree (Supra) dicta is reproduced hereinafter:
		</p>
		<lb />
		<item>
			&quot;8. At the outset it needs to be noted that the present
			<lb />
			suit is not one for infringement by the defendants of the
			<lb />
			Plaintiff&quot;s trademark and the Plaintiff carries on
			<lb />
			business within the jurisdiction of the court. If it were,
			<lb />
			then in terms of Section 134 (2) of the Trademarks Act
			<lb />
			1999 (TM Act) this court would have jurisdiction to
			<lb />
			entertain the suit although the defendants do not reside
			<lb />
			or carry on business within its jurisdiction. Section 134
			<lb />
			(2) of the TM Act (like and Section 62 (2) of the
			<lb />
			Copyright Act, 1957) is therefore a &quot;long arm&quot;
			<lb />
			provision in a limited sense, confined to infringement
			<lb />
			actions by Plaintiffs carrying on business within the
			<lb />
			jurisdiction of the forum court. The present suit is an
			<lb />
			action for passing off in which neither the Plaintiff nor
			<lb />
			any of the defendants voluntarily resides or carries on
			<lb />
			business within the local limits of Delhi. Consequently,
			<lb />
			neither Section 20 (a) nor Section 20(b) CPC applies.
			<lb />
			The Plaintiff seeks to find the territorial jurisdiction of
			<lb />
			this Court in terms of Section 20(c) CPC. In other
			<lb />
			words, according to the Plaintiff the cause of action,
			<lb />
			wholly or in part, arises within the jurisdiction of this
			<lb />
			Court. This, according to the Plaintiff is on account of
			<lb />
			two factors. One, that the website of the defendants is
			<lb />
			accessible in Delhi; it is not a passive website but used
			<lb />
			for soliciting business in Delhi. Second, that there was
			<lb />
			at least one instance of the defendants&quot; brochure being
			<lb />
			sent to a Delhi resident for the purposes of sale of
			<lb />
			property.&quot;
		</item>
		<lb />
		<p>
			Thus, the said distinction and the caveat expressed by the
			<lb />
			Division Bench itself is sufficient to exclude the present case from
			<lb />
			that of the operation of Banyan Tree Judgment as it stands a good
			<lb />
			law which it decides and cannot be extended to infringement cases
			<lb />
			which are governed by special provisions.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			c)
			<lb />
			Thirdly, assuming that the judgment of Banyan Tree (Supra) may
			<lb />
			be applied to the present case, even then the difference in the
			<lb />
			factual matrix further takes out the present case from the
			<lb />
			application of the said dicta. This is due to the reason in Banyan
			<lb />
			Tree&apos;s case (supra), the court was concerned with the hotel
			<lb />
			services wherein there was tendency of booking online in the hotel
			<lb />
			from every place and thus the mere act of booking cannot be held
			<lb />
			to clothe jurisdiction on this court unless it forms a part of cause of
			<lb />
			action in the case whereas in the present case concerns with the
			<lb />
			activities of the defendants which are primarily web based which
			<lb />
			are interactive due to media presence, downloading, uploading and
			<lb />
			nothing else. The court propounded doctrine of purposeful
			<lb />
			availment in Banyan Tree&apos;s case (supra) to show the nexus of the
			<lb />
			transaction with cause of action in the suit. In the sharp
			<lb />
			contradistinction to the same, the defendants in the present case
			<lb />
			are offering to show and communicating the Indian works to the
			<lb />
			Indian public with the interactive media inside and the user is able
			<lb />
			to view the same online, download it and use it and further
			<lb />
			communicate to public. The plaintiff has also substantiated the
			<lb />
			same by providing download of the sample infringement which are
			<lb />
			also forming part of cause of action. Thus, there is sufficient
			<lb />
			interactivity in the website which is aiming at the Indian users and
			<lb />
			shows nexus with the complaint with the suit where the plaintiff is
			<lb />
			directly aggrieved. The present case would be therefore, different
			<lb />
			from the case of Trade Mark infringement wherein some online
			<lb />
			transaction or a trap order is shown to clothe cause of action for
			<lb />
			the purposes of invoking jurisdiction.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			The present case relates to complaints arising directly out of
			<lb />
			the online acts and thus cannot be rejected on the counts of
			<lb />
			unconnected cause of action. Therefore, the Banyan Tree&apos;s case
			<lb />
			(supra) is inapplicable in the present case and rather if the tests laid
			<lb />
			down in the same are applied, the present case sufficiently
			<lb />
			qualifies the tests of Banyan Tree (Supra).
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			57.
			<lb />
			Hence, for all these aforesaid reasons, this court will have
			<lb />
			jurisdiction to entertain and try the proceeding.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			58.
			<lb />
			The related argument as to jurisdiction was also raised by the
			<lb />
			learned counsel for the defendants that this Court cannot exercise the
			<lb />
			extra territorial jurisdiction as assuming jurisdiction would in this case
			<lb />
			would mean exercising extra territorial jurisdiction. The said argument is
			<lb />
			rejected as baseless and the reasons for variance are outlined as under:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			a)
			<lb />
			Firstly, this Court has already arrived at the finding that the court
			<lb />
			has assumed the jurisdiction on the basis of the part of cause of
			<lb />
			action which has arisen in India and the infringement is being
			<lb />
			caused in India. Thus, this court would have jurisdiction to
			<lb />
			entertain and try the proceedings for infringements which has been
			<lb />
			caused in India.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			b) Secondly it is merely the apprehension of the defendants that there
			<lb />
			will be some effect of extra territorial for which this court is not
			<lb />
			concerned, it is neither the case of the plaintiff to give this as an
			<lb />
			extra territorial effect and nor this court is giving any such effect as
			<lb />
			contended by the defendants. Rather, the court is exercising the
			<lb />
			jurisdiction on the basis of the law of the land which is Copyright
			<lb />
			Act of India, 1957.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			c)
			<lb />
			Thirdly, it has already been observed that the commission of tort of
			<lb />
			infringement has occurred in India which is prima facie infringing
			<lb />
			in nature, the said acts are prohibited under the Copyright Act and
			<lb />
			thus this court is proceeding to do what is permissible under the
			<lb />
			law. This court is not concerned with any incidental effects which
			<lb />
			the defendants are apprehensive of due to the exercise of the
			<lb />
			jurisdiction of the Court and that cannot come in the way of
			<lb />
			exercise of jurisdiction of this Court.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			d)
			<lb />
			There are lots of cases cited on Article 245 of the Indian
			<lb />
			Constitution wherein it has been observed about the parliamentary
			<lb />
			power to enact the extra territorial laws. The said reliance of
			<lb />
			judgments is equally misplaced as in the present case, this court is
			<lb />
			not concerned with the legislative competence of the any extra
			<lb />
			territorial laws. The said judgments are not applicable to the
			<lb />
			present case as the court is exercising the jurisdiction on the basis
			<lb />
			of Indian law having force in India and thus the concerns are mere
			<lb />
			apprehensions of the defendants which this court cannot take care
			<lb />
			of.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<head>
			PROBABLE EFFECT OF AMENDMENTS UNDER THE IT ACT
			<lb />
			2000 (AS AMENDED ON 2009) ON THE REMEDIES
			<lb />
			PRESCRIBED UNDER COPYRIGHT ACT 1957.
			<lb />
		</head>

		<p>
			59.
			<lb />
			Now I shall discuss another aspect of impact of the amended
			<lb />
			provisions of Information Technology Act 2000 on the provisions of the
			<lb />
			Copyright Act inturn on the present case as it is the defendants&quot;
			<lb />
			contention that the provisions of IT Act relates to internet related wrongs
			<lb />
			and thus their acts are protected under the IT laws of India.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			60.
			<lb />
			The submission has been advanced by the defendants that the
			<lb />
			amendments made in 2009 in the IT Act, 2000 will have great impact on
			<lb />
			the satisfaction of this Court for the purposes of grant or non grant of the
			<lb />
			injunction against the defendants. The relevant sections of amended Act
			<lb />
			relied upon by the defendants which according to the defendants will
			<lb />
			enable the defendants to escape the liability of infringement are
			<lb />
			reproduced hereinafter:
		</p>
		<lb />
		<item>
			&quot;Section 79 of IT Act, 2000 reads as under :
		</item>
		<lb />
		<item>
			&quot;Exemption from liability of intermediary in
			<lb />
			certain cases -
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(1) Notwithstanding anything contained in any law
			<lb />
			for the time being in force but subject to the
			<lb />
			provisions of sub-sections (2) and (3), an
			<lb />
			intermediary shall not be liable for any third party
			<lb />
			information, data, or communication link made
			<lb />
			available or hosted by him.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(2) The provisions of sub-section (1) shall apply
			<lb />
			if -
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(a) the function of the intermediary is limited to
			<lb />
			providing access to a communication system
			<lb />
			over which information made available by third
			<lb />
			parties is transmitted or temporarily stored or
			<lb />
			hosted; or
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(b) the intermediary does not -
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(i) initiate the transmission,
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(ii) select the receiver of the transmission, and
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(iii) select or modify the information contained
			<lb />
			in the transmission;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(c) The intermediary observes due diligence while
			<lb />
			discharging his duties under this Act and also
			<lb />
			observes such other guidelines as the Central
			<lb />
			Government may prescribe in this behalf.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(3) The provisions of sub-section (1) shall not apply
			<lb />
			if -
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(a) the intermediary has conspired or abetted or
			<lb />
			aided or induced, whether by threats or promise
			<lb />
			or otherwise in the commission of the unlawful
			<lb />
			act;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(b) upon receiving actual knowledge, or on being
			<lb />
			notified by the appropriate Government or its
			<lb />
			agency that any information, data or
			<lb />
			communication link residing in or connected to
			<lb />
			a computer resource, controlled by the
			<lb />
			intermediary is being used to commit the
			<lb />
			unlawful act, the intermediary fails to
			<lb />
			expeditiously remove or disable access to that
			<lb />
			material or that resource without vitiating the
			<lb />
			evidence in any manner.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			Explanation:
			<lb />
			For the purposes of this
			<lb />
			section, the expression &quot;third party information&quot;
			<lb />
			means any information dealt with by an
			<lb />
			intermediary in his capacity as an intermediary.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			Section 81 of IT Act, 2000 reads as under :
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			Act to have overriding effect.-The provisions of
			<lb />
			this Act shall have effect notwithstanding anything
			<lb />
			inconsistent therewith contained in any other law
			<lb />
			for the time being in force.
		</item>
		<lb />
		<item>
			[Provided that nothing contained in this Act shall
			<lb />
			restrict any person from exercising any right
			<lb />
			conferred under the Copyright Act, 1957 (14 of
			<lb />
			1957) or the Patents Act, 1970 (39 of 1970)].&quot;
		</item>
		<lb />
		<p>
			Section 2(w) of the IT Act defines intermediary as :
			<lb />
			&quot;Intermediary&quot; with respect to any particular electronic records, means
			<lb />
			any person who on behalf of another person receives, stores or transmits
			<lb />
			that record or provides any service with respect to that record and
			<lb />
			includes telecom service providers, network service providers, internet
			<lb />
			service providers, web hosting service providers, search engines, online
			<lb />
			payment sites, online-auction sites, online market places and cyber cafes.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			61.
			<lb />
			The submission advanced by the learned counsel for the
			<lb />
			defendants is that the acts of the defendants are protected under Section
			<lb />
			79 of the Act even if this court is not convinced by the argument of safe
			<lb />
			harbor provisions of the Digitial Millenium Act of US as the provision
			<lb />
			saves the liability of the intermediaries like the defendants. Thus, the
			<lb />
			defendant&quot;s acts of providing means of infringement and all other acts
			<lb />
			communicating the works to the public are mitigated by way of operation
			<lb />
			of Section 79 of Information Technology Act, 2000 ( as Amended on
			<lb />
			2009). The provision according to the defendants&quot; counsel is non
			<lb />
			obstante clause and thus will override the other acts.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			62.
			<lb />
			Per contra, learned counsel Mr. Sibal has advanced the
			<lb />
			argument that the provision of Section 79 of Information Technology Act,
			<lb />
			2000 cannot be read in isolation and has to be read along with Section 81
			<lb />
			which provides for the overriding effect of the Act. The said provisions
			<lb />
			also enacts the proviso which is also inserted by way of amendment
			<lb />
			which states that nothing contained in this Act shall restrict any person
			<lb />
			from exercising any right conferred under the Copyright Act, 1957 or the
			<lb />
			Patent Act, 1970. Thus, as per Mr. Sibal, the IT Act may override any
			<lb />
			other law, but by way of operation of the proviso to Section 81, the rights
			<lb />
			of the copyright owner cannot be curtailed by applying any other
			<lb />
			provision of the IT Act.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			63.
			<lb />
			I find that the provisions of Section 79 of the IT Act will have
			<lb />
			no bearing on the liability of infringement on the defendants due to the
			<lb />
			reasons entailed hereinafter:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			a)
			<lb />
			Firstly, I find merit in the submission of Mr. Sibal that conjoint
			<lb />
			reading of Section 79 and Section 81 makes it amply clear that the
			<lb />
			proviso to Section 81 prevents any provisions of IT Act to act as
			<lb />
			restriction on exercising of the rights by the copyright owner. This
			<lb />
			makes it clear when read the Section 81 which provides for the
			<lb />
			overriding effect of the IT act over other laws.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			The proviso appended to the said section provides that
			<lb />
			nothing contained in this act shall restrict the exercising of right by
			<lb />
			any person under the Copyright Act. The said proviso carves out
			<lb />
			an exception to the main enactment which is under the head of
			<lb />
			overriding effect of the IT Act.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			64.
			<lb />
			The scope and ambit of the proviso to the enactment has been
			<lb />
			succinctly discussed by the Apex Court in State of Rajasthan v. Leela
			<lb />
			Jain (1965) 1 SCR 276, wherein the Apex court has held :
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;So far as a general principle of construction of a
			<lb />
			proviso is concerned, it has been broadly stated that
			<lb />
			the function of a proviso is to limit the main part of
			<lb />
			the section and carve out something which but for
			<lb />
			the proviso would have been within the operative
			<lb />
			part.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			64.1
			<lb />
			In the case of Sales Tax Officer, Circle I, Jabalpur v.
			<lb />
			Hanuman Prasad : [1967]1SCR831 , Hon&quot;ble Bhargava, J. observed :
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;It is well-recognised that a proviso is added to a
			<lb />
			principal clause primarily with the object of taking
			<lb />
			out of the scope of that principal clause what is
			<lb />
			included in it and what the legislature desires
			<lb />
			should be excluded.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			64.2
			<lb />
			Thus, the combine effect of reading Section 81 and the
			<lb />
			proviso is that the provisions of IT act may override other laws for the
			<lb />
			time being in force but the cannot restrict the rights of the owner under
			<lb />
			the Copyright Act and the Patent Act. In other words, the rights of the
			<lb />
			owners under the Copyright Act, 1957 and/ or Patent Act, 1970 shall
			<lb />
			remain unfettered by any of the provisions of IT Act.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			64.3
			<lb />
			Accordingly, Section 79 cannot restrict the rights of the
			<lb />
			copyright owner by saving the liability of the defendants of the infringing
			<lb />
			acts caused under the provisions of Section 51 (a) (ii) of the Act by
			<lb />
			operation of proviso to Section 81 of the Act.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			b)
			<lb />
			Secondly, I am also doubtful that even if the provision of Section
			<lb />
			79 of the IT Act is applied to the present case, whether the
			<lb />
			defendants qualifies to get the benefit of the same under the IT Act.
			<lb />
			This is due to the reason that Section 79 although is a non obstante
			<lb />
			clause but is subject to Section 79 (2) and Section 79 (3) which
			<lb />
			provides the conditions of applicability and non applicability of the
			<lb />
			Section.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			The said Section 79 (2) (a) states that the Section will apply if
			<lb />
			the function of the intermediary is limited to providing access to a
			<lb />
			communication system over which information made available by
			<lb />
			third parties is transmitted or temporarily stored or hosted; or
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			(b) the intermediary does not -
			<lb />
			(i) initiate the transmission,
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			(ii) select the receiver of the transmission, and
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			(iii) select or modify the information contained in the
			<lb />
			transmission;
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			(c) The intermediary observes due diligence while
			<lb />
			discharging his duties under this Act and also
			<lb />
			observes such other guidelines as the Central
			<lb />
			Government may prescribe in this behalf.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			64.4
			<lb />
			The use of the wordings &quot;or&quot; between (a) and (b) makes them
			<lb />
			disjunctive, although (c) has to coexist with (a) or (b) whichever is
			<lb />
			applicable. In the present case, the provisions of Section 79 (2) (a) is not
			<lb />
			fulfilled as the function of the defendants is not confined to only provide
			<lb />
			an access to communication system where the third party information is
			<lb />
			stored, transmitted or hosted. But rather the defendants provides access
			<lb />
			only after a limited licence to add or modify the work and thereon by
			<lb />
			adding advertisements to the said works, modifying the works which
			<lb />
			means permitting the place for profit with knowledge. The said acts are
			<lb />
			thus of not those kinds prescribed under the provision of Section 79 (2)
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			(a) which are of a limited role of merely providing an access to system
			<lb />
			containing storage medium or transmission of the third party information.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			65.
			<lb />
			The acts of the defendants also may not fall with Section 79
			<lb />
			(2) (b) as the said situation prescribed in the provision has to be satisfied
			<lb />
			conjunctively or collectively as the word used between the (i), (ii), (iii) is
			<lb />
			&quot;and&quot; which means all the situations must be satisfied else, the said
			<lb />
			conditions in the provision are not met with. In the present case, the
			<lb />
			defendant&quot;s acts do not satisfy the criteria of modification of information.
			<lb />
			The defendants have attained the licence to modify the works provided
			<lb />
			by the users suitably. The complaint of the plaintiff is that adding the
			<lb />
			advertisement also infringes their rights. Thus, the act of modification of
			<lb />
			the works by the defendants also excludes the defendants from the
			<lb />
			purview of Section 79 (2) (b) of the Act.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			66.
			<lb />
			The third condition of due diligence is also doubtful as the due
			<lb />
			diligence is required while discharging his duties. Thus, if the defendants
			<lb />
			are put to notice about the rights of the plaintiff in certain works, the
			<lb />
			defendants should do preliminary check in all the cinematograph works
			<lb />
			relating Indian titles before communicating the works to the public rather
			<lb />
			than falling back on post infringement measures. The due diligence is
			<lb />
			also not satisfied when the defendants uploads the contents of the user on
			<lb />
			their server and then modify the same as per the limited licence to amend
			<lb />
			from users. This means that the defendants have the chances to keep a
			<lb />
			check on the works which defendants avoid so to the reasons best
			<lb />
			known to them. The due diligence is thus also doubtful although
			<lb />
			defendants contend for the satisfaction of due diligence.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			67.
			<lb />
			From the above, it is also clear that the applicability of
			<lb />
			Section 79 is also not satisfied although by operation of proviso to
			<lb />
			Section 81, the discussion on Section 79 is not really important. I do not
			<lb />
			also find my agreement with the submission of the defendants that there
			<lb />
			will be harmonious construction between Copyright Act and IT Act if the
			<lb />
			provision of Section 79 will save the liability of the copyright
			<lb />
			infringement of the intermediaries like the defendants. I think rather
			<lb />
			accepting the submission would lead to apparent disharmony or conflict
			<lb />
			between the provisions of two Acts. This can be explained as follows:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			68.
			<lb />
			Firstly it is well settled canon of construction that the court
			<lb />
			should adopt the mode of construction which upholds the provisions of
			<lb />
			the Act and make them workable and the interpretation which makes any
			<lb />
			provision of the Act otiose must be eschewed.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			68.1
			<lb />
			In High Court of Gujarat and Anr. v. Gujarat Kishan
			<lb />
			Mazdoor Panchayat and Ors. [2003] 2 SCR 799 , the Supreme Court
			<lb />
			held as under :
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;35. The Court while interpreting the provision of a
			<lb />
			statute, although, is not entitled to rewrite the
			<lb />
			statute itself, is not debarred from &quot;ironing out the
			<lb />
			creases&quot;. The court should always make an attempt
			<lb />
			to uphold the rules and interpret the same in such a
			<lb />
			manner which would make it workable.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			36. It is also a well-settled principle of law that an
			<lb />
			attempt should be made to give effect to each and
			<lb />
			every word employed in a statute and such
			<lb />
			interpretation which would render a particular
			<lb />
			provision redundant or otiose should be avoided.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			68.2
			<lb />
			If Section 79 of the IT Act is allowed to operate as an
			<lb />
			embargo or restriction upon the exercise of the right of right holder by
			<lb />
			saving the liability of the copyright infringement, the said interpretation
			<lb />
			will render proviso to Section 81 of the IT Act otiose or unworkable. The
			<lb />
			said interpretation thus leads the purpose of the proviso as redundant. On
			<lb />
			the contrary, if the gamut of the Section 79 is allowed to remain confined
			<lb />
			and subject to the proviso of Section 81 which is intended to be so by the
			<lb />
			legislature, both the provisions can stand and work in their respective
			<lb />
			fields.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			68.3
			<lb />
			Section 79 is, thus, meant for all other internet wrongs
			<lb />
			wherein intermediaries may be involved including auctioning, networking
			<lb />
			servicing, news dissemination, uploading of pornographic content but not
			<lb />
			certainly relating to the copyright infringement or patent infringement
			<lb />
			which has been specifically excluded by way of proviso to Section 81.
			<lb />
			This can be only possible harmonious construction between the two Acts
			<lb />
			which makes both the Acts workable.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			68.4
			<lb />
			Secondly, besides making proviso to Section 81 otiose, the
			<lb />
			interpretation canvassed by the defendants lead to conflict between two
			<lb />
			acts and also leads to absurd results. This is due to the reason that the
			<lb />
			Copyright Act, 1957 itself provides for an infringement as well as the
			<lb />
			exceptions of the infringement. Once the infringement is established, the
			<lb />
			remedies to the same are prescribed by Section 55. In that situation and
			<lb />
			given the fact that there is an express proviso excluding the copyright
			<lb />
			infringement from the purview of IT Act if not applied leads to
			<lb />
			unnecessary adding further restrictions on the copyright infringements
			<lb />
			which is impermissible and therefore leads to absurd results negating the
			<lb />
			statutorily prescribed remedies for copyright infringement.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			68.5
			<lb />
			Further the provisions of authorization or permitting the place
			<lb />
			for profit requires knowledge or reasonable belief and other common law
			<lb />
			requirements for establishing the infringement as discussed above. Thus,
			<lb />
			the said act of authorization and/or permitting the place for profit itself
			<lb />
			requires knowledge and reasonable belief of infringement which are
			<lb />
			inbuilt exception to the infringement, The operation of Section 79 to
			<lb />
			exempt the liability of the intermediary except in cases of knowledge is
			<lb />
			rather repetition of the same provision and if the same is allowed to
			<lb />
			operate in the way of infringement which itself requires knowledge and
			<lb />
			reasonable belief or countenance or approval in respective cases would
			<lb />
			lead to anomalous situations and would lead to absurd results.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			68.6
			<lb />
			Thirdly, there is no legislative disharmony by operation of the
			<lb />
			proviso to Section 81 and rather adding of proviso to Section 81 by way
			<lb />
			of amendment put the unrest into an end. If Section 79 would have
			<lb />
			application to the copyright infringement which saves absolutely the
			<lb />
			liability of the intermediary without insertion of the proviso by the
			<lb />
			legislature under Section 81, then there would have been apparent
			<lb />
			conflict between the acts of infringement by way of permitting the place
			<lb />
			for profit provided under Section 51 (a) (ii) and Section 79 which saves
			<lb />
			the liability of the intermediary. Thus, without insertion of the proviso to
			<lb />
			Section 81, there would have been two laws, one, providing the acts of
			<lb />
			intermediary or facilitator as infringement and another saving the liability.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			68.7
			<lb />
			In Dwarka Prasad v. Dwarka Das Saraf [1976] 1 SCR 277.
			<lb />
			Hon&quot;ble Krishan Iyer, J. speaking for the Court observed thus:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			There is some validity in this submission but if, on a
			<lb />
			fair construction, the principal provision is clear, a
			<lb />
			proviso cannot expand or limit it. Sometimes a
			<lb />
			proviso is engrafted by an apprehensive draftsman
			<lb />
			to remove possible doubts, to make matters plain,
			<lb />
			to light up ambiguous edges. Here, such is the
			<lb />
			case....&quot;
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			68.8
			<lb />
			The adding of proviso is rather not only exclusionary but also
			<lb />
			clarificatory in nature which clarifies that the provisions of IT Act may
			<lb />
			not restrict the rights under Copyright Act or Patent Act as its tries to
			<lb />
			create and confer harmony between two laws and enactments so that they
			<lb />
			can operate in their respective fields. Thus, there is harmony by adopting
			<lb />
			the proviso rather than negating it.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			69.
			<lb />
			In view of the above discussion, I find that there is no impact
			<lb />
			of provisions of Section 79 of IT Act (as amended on 2009) on the
			<lb />
			copyright infringements relating to internet wrongs where intermediaries
			<lb />
			are involved and the said provision cannot curtail the rights of the
			<lb />
			copyright owner by operation of proviso of Section 81 which carves out
			<lb />
			an exception cases relating to copyright or patent infringement.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<head>
			IMPACT OF PROVISIONS OF DIGITAL MILLENIUM ACT OF
			<lb />
			US AND OTHER ENGLISH LAW
			<lb />
		</head>

		<p>
			70.
			<lb />
			Now I shall deal with the possible impact of Digital
			<lb />
			Millennium Copyright Act (&quot;DMCA&quot;) of US and the other English
			<lb />
			judgments cited by the parties.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			71.
			<lb />
			The great stress has been laid on the judgments passed by US
			<lb />
			courts in following cases which are passed on analyzing the provisions
			<lb />
			of Digital Millennium Copyright Act (&quot;DMCA&quot;):
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			(i) IO Group, Inc v. VEOH Networks (Case 5:06-cv-03926
			<lb />
			HRL)
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(ii) UMG Recordings v. VEOH Networks (Case 2:07-cv-
			<lb />
			05744-AHM-AJW)
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(iii) Viacom Inc. v. Youtube, Inc &amp; ors (07 Civ. 2103 LLS)
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			72.
			<lb />
			I have gone through the decisions passed by US Courts under
			<lb />
			the US Digital Millennium Copyright Act (&quot;DMCA&quot;) and I am of the
			<lb />
			firm view, that there is no corresponding law which is in pari materia to
			<lb />
			that of Digital Millennium Copyright Act (&quot;DMCA&quot;). The said Act
			<lb />
			specifically addresses the issues relating internet related wrongs, however
			<lb />
			our existing law of Copyright Act, 1957 does not provide any such safe
			<lb />
			harbor provisions and rather the later enactment of IT Act, 2000 and its
			<lb />
			new amendment in 2009 speaks otherwise which I have already
			<lb />
			examined Section 81 of IT Act (as amended in 2009), proviso to which
			<lb />
			excludes the operation of the IT law in cases of copyright infringement.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			73.
			<lb />
			It is trite that the court cannot re legislate or add words into
			<lb />
			the statute. this has been followed in Association for Development vs.
			<lb />
			Union of India &amp; Others, 2010 (115) DRJ 277 wherein this court
			<lb />
			approved the literal rule and observed that -it is not the duty of the court
			<lb />
			to enlarge the scope of the legislation when the language of the provision
			<lb />
			is plain and unambiguous. The court cannot recast or reframe the
			<lb />
			legislation for the very reason it has no power to legislate. The court
			<lb />
			cannot add words to a statute or reads words into it which are not there&quot;.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			74.
			<lb />
			It is also well settled that the laws and the provisions which
			<lb />
			are not pari materia cannot be compared. This has been followed in the
			<lb />
			decision of the Apex Court in the case of Babu Khan vs. Nazim Khan
			<lb />
			(2001) 5 SCC 375). The following conclusion of Their Lordships is
			<lb />
			relevant: (para 5)
		</p>
		<lb />
		<item>
			&quot;5......It is true that the courts while construing a
			<lb />
			provision of an enactment often follow the
			<lb />
			decisions by the courts construing similar provision
			<lb />
			of an enactment in pari materia. The object behind
			<lb />
			the application of the said rule of construction is to
			<lb />
			avoid contradiction between the two statutes
			<lb />
			dealing with the same subject. But in the present
			<lb />
			case, what we find is that the Madhya Bharat Land
			<lb />
			Revenue and Tenancy Act contains one integrated
			<lb />
			scheme providing for remedy to a pucca tenant
			<lb />
			claiming restoration of possession under Section 91
			<lb />
			and 93 of the Act. The Madhya Bharat Land
			<lb />
			Revenue and Tenancy Act was repealed by the
			<lb />
			M.P. Land Revenue Code. In the repealing Act i.e.
			<lb />
			M.P. Land Revenue Code we do not find any
			<lb />
			provision like Section 93 of the Act. We are,
			<lb />
			therefore, of the view that Sections 9 1, 92 and 93
			<lb />
			of the Act are not in pari materia with the provision
			<lb />
			of Section 250 of the M.P. Code. It is not a sound
			<lb />
			principle of construction to interpret a provision
			<lb />
			of an enactment following the decisions rendered
			<lb />
			on a similar provision of an enactment when two
			<lb />
			statutes are not in pari materia&quot;
			<lb />
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			75.
			<lb />
			The adoption and drawing aid from the said provisions in the
			<lb />
			present scenario would thus mean adding provisions into the statute when
			<lb />
			the existing law says otherwise. Thus, in absence of any such law similar
			<lb />
			to Digital Millennium Copyright Act (&quot;DMCA&quot;), the reliance of the
			<lb />
			provisions and judgments passed under the said law is of no avail to the
			<lb />
			defendants and this court under existing law cannot be convinced by the
			<lb />
			reliance of the provisions of Digital Millennium Copyright Act
			<lb />
			(&quot;DMCA&quot;) of US.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			76.
			<lb />
			The same view was taken by constitutional bench of Supreme
			<lb />
			Court in R.L. Arora vs. State of UP, [1962] Supp(2) SCR 149 while
			<lb />
			rejecting the reading of American constitution 5 th Amendment due to
			<lb />
			inconsistent provisions wherein the court observed as under:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;20. It seems that there has been controversy in
			<lb />
			America as to the meaning of the words &quot;public
			<lb />
			use&quot; used in the above amendment and there are
			<lb />
			two views prevalent. The older view was, and it is
			<lb />
			still held in some States, that &quot;public use&quot; means
			<lb />
			&quot;use by the public -that is, public employment -
			<lb />
			and consequently that to make a use public, a duty
			<lb />
			must devolve on the person or corporation holding
			<lb />
			property appropriated by the right of eminent
			<lb />
			domain to furnish the public with the use intended,
			<lb />
			and that there must be a right on the part of the
			<lb />
			public, or some portion of it, or some public or
			<lb />
			quasi-public agency on behalf of the public, to use
			<lb />
			the property after it is condemned&quot;. The later view
			<lb />
			is that &quot;public use&quot; means &quot;public advantage,
			<lb />
			convenience, or benefit, and that anything which
			<lb />
			tends to enlarge the resources, increase the
			<lb />
			industrial energies, and promote the productive
			<lb />
			power of any considerable number of the
			<lb />
			inhabitants of a section of the State, or which leads
			<lb />
			to the growth of towns and the creation of new
			<lb />
			resources for the employment of capital and labour
			<lb />
			contributes to the general welfare and the
			<lb />
			prosperity of the whole community and giving the
			<lb />
			Constitution a broad and comprehensive
			<lb />
			interpretation, constitutes a public use&quot; (see
			<lb />
			American Jurisprudence. Vol. 18. pp. 661-62). In
			<lb />
			one State, where the older view is still held, the
			<lb />
			court pointed out that &quot;if public use were construed
			<lb />
			to mean that the public would be benefited in the
			<lb />
			sense that the enterprise or improvement for the use
			<lb />
			of which the property was taken might contribute to
			<lb />
			the comfort or convenience of the public, or a
			<lb />
			portion thereof, or be esteemed necessary for their
			<lb />
			enjoyment, there would be absolutely no limit to the
			<lb />
			right to take private property, that it would not be
			<lb />
			difficult to show that a factory, hotel, etc., the
			<lb />
			erection of which was contemplated, would result
			<lb />
			in benefit to the public, and that, under this power,
			<lb />
			the property of the citizen would never be safe from
			<lb />
			an invasion.&quot; (see ibid. p. 664) It is the later view
			<lb />
			prevalent in some States in America for which the
			<lb />
			respondents are contending, and the result of that
			<lb />
			would be the same as pointed out above. But we do
			<lb />
			not think it necessary to examine the American
			<lb />
			cases cited before us because the words in our
			<lb />
			statute are not pari materia with the words used
			<lb />
			in the fifth amendment to the American
			<lb />
			Constitution.&quot; (Emphasis Supplied)
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			77.
			<lb />
			Likewise, the defendants as well as the plaintiff in order to
			<lb />
			support the arguments on authorization have placed reliance on the
			<lb />
			number of cases which are decided by the UK Courts and the other
			<lb />
			courts of common law jurisdiction some granting the injunction and some
			<lb />
			refusing the same depending upon the facts and circumstances of the
			<lb />
			case. The said cases are enlisted as under:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			 C.B.S. Inc. &amp; C.B.S. United Kingdom v. Ames
			<lb />
			Records &amp; Tapes Limited (decided on 13 th
			<lb />
			February, 1981) (1981) RPC 407.
		</item>
		<lb />
		<item>
			 C.B.S. Songs Limited &amp; Others vs. Amstrad
			<lb />
			Consumer Electronics Plc. &amp; Another (House of
			<lb />
			Lords), (1988) RPC 567)
		</item>
		<lb />
		<item>
			 Ong Seow Pheng &amp; Ors. v. Lotus Development
			<lb />
			Corp. &amp; Another [1997] 3 SLR.( Singapore Court)
		</item>
		<lb />
		<item>
			 CCH Canadian Ltd vs. Law Society of Upper
			<lb />
			Canada (2004 SCC 13) [Supreme Court of Canada]
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			78.
			<lb />
			No doubt the judgments passed by the UK Courts and in other
			<lb />
			common law jurisdictions are relevant to take into consideration on the
			<lb />
			tests laid down by the courts in order to arrive at the conclusion as to
			<lb />
			whether the acts of the defendants amount to authorization or not. I have
			<lb />
			already paraphrased the said tests while examining the aspect of
			<lb />
			authorization in the preceding paragraphs. Beyond that, I feel the
			<lb />
			conclusions set out in each of all those cases are of less value due to the
			<lb />
			following reasons:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			a) The provisions of UK Act of 1956 and Indian Act 1957 and also
			<lb />
			further CDPA Act 1988 are not same. The wordings in the
			<lb />
			Sections are although similar with variations but are not identical.
			<lb />
			Like in UK Act of 1956, permitting the place of public
			<lb />
			entertainment for profit is an infringement while in Indian Act of
			<lb />
			1957, permitting any place for profit are the wordings under
			<lb />
			Section 51 which has made the differences in the interpretation as
			<lb />
			discussed above.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			Similarly, in UK CDPA Act of 1988, there are separate
			<lb />
			infringements provided for place for public entertainment for profit
			<lb />
			in the form Section 25 and infringement by way of apparatus in the
			<lb />
			form of Section 26. Further in UK Act of 1988 there are statutory
			<lb />
			indicators which excludes the liability of the persons under certain
			<lb />
			circumstances in cases of infringement by way of Appratus.
			<lb />
			However, Indian Act of 1957 remains the same with no such
			<lb />
			provisions.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			Thus, there is difference in provisions and the wordings
			<lb />
			which may ascribe difference meaning. This is also the reason for
			<lb />
			the English court to rely more on the concept of authorization. In
			<lb />
			the absence of pari materia provisions, the complete reliance on
			<lb />
			these decisions may not be useful.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			b) I have not based my conclusion regarding infringement on
			<lb />
			authorization (although I have analysed the tests relating to the
			<lb />
			same) as I have found that the same may require active
			<lb />
			participation besides knowledge which is a matter of trial and I
			<lb />
			have found that still the acts of the defendants are hit by the
			<lb />
			provisions of Section 51 (a) (ii) of the Act. In these circumstances,
			<lb />
			the decisions on authorization may become of less aid as the acts
			<lb />
			of the defendants are squarely covered under the express
			<lb />
			legislative provision.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			Accordingly, principally, I accept the decisions rendered on
			<lb />
			authorization and tests laid down in the same and the same can be taken
			<lb />
			into consideration for the purposes of deciding the acts of authorization
			<lb />
			but may not be helpful in the cases involving the permitting the place for
			<lb />
			profit which is a statutorily prescribed infringement.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<head>
			RELIANCE ON INTERNATIONAL COVENANTS
			<lb />
		</head>
		<p>
			79.
			<lb />
			Now, I shall be dealing with the submissions advanced by the
			<lb />
			learned counsel for the defendants on the reading of International
			<lb />
			covenants and adopting the same in interpreting the copyright law and
			<lb />
			especially the internet related wrongs which is The WIPO Copyright
			<lb />
			Treaty and its Article 8.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			It is also equally well settled that the international law and
			<lb />
			covenants can be taken recourse of in the municipal law to the extent
			<lb />
			they are not inconsistent with the municipal law and to fill the gaps in the
			<lb />
			existing law. {This has been accepted by Supreme Court in Visakha &amp;
			<lb />
			Ors. vs. State of Rajasthan, (1997) 6 SCC 241)}
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			80.
			<lb />
			In the present case, the defendants themselves have informed
			<lb />
			the Court that India has not even ratified the said convention. Thus, the
			<lb />
			reliance on the said convention into Indian law is thus misplaced. Further,
			<lb />
			The answer to this can be traced if one reads the judgment of
			<lb />
			Entertainment Network (Supra) more carefully wherein the court
			<lb />
			discusses the extent to which the international covenants can be read into
			<lb />
			the national law. The relevant paragraphs of the judgment are
			<lb />
			reproduced hereinafter:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;While India is a signatory to the International
			<lb />
			Covenants, the law should have been amended in
			<lb />
			terms thereof. Only because laws have not been
			<lb />
			amended, the same would not by itself mean that
			<lb />
			the purport and object of the Act would be allowed
			<lb />
			to be defeated. If the ground realities changed, the
			<lb />
			interpretation should also change. Ground realities
			<lb />
			would not only depend upon the new situations and
			<lb />
			changes in the societal conditions vis-a-vis the use
			<lb />
			of sound recording extensively by a large public,
			<lb />
			but also keeping in view of the fact that the
			<lb />
			Government with its eyes wide open have become a
			<lb />
			signatory to International Conventions.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			&quot;It is for the aforementioned limited purpose, a
			<lb />
			visit to the provisions of International Conventions
			<lb />
			would be necessary. In interpreting the
			<lb />
			domestic/municipal laws, this Court has
			<lb />
			extensively made use of International law inter alia
			<lb />
			for the following purposes:
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(i) As a means of interpretation;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(ii) Justification or fortification of a stance taken;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(iii) To fulfill spirit of international obligation which
			<lb />
			India has entered into, when they are not in conflict
			<lb />
			with the existing domestic law;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(iv) To reflect international changes and reflect the
			<lb />
			wider civilization;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(v) To provide a relief contained in a covenant, but
			<lb />
			not in a national law;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			(vi) To fill gaps in law.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			&quot;Beginning from the decision of this court in
			<lb />
			Kesavananda Bharati v. State of Kerala [(1973) 4
			<lb />
			SCC 225], there is indeed no dearth of case laws
			<lb />
			where this Court has applied the norms of
			<lb />
			international laws and in particular the international
			<lb />
			covenants to interpret domestic legislation. In all
			<lb />
			these cases, this court has categorically held that
			<lb />
			there would be no inconsistency in the use of
			<lb />
			international norms to the domestic legislation, if by
			<lb />
			reason thereof the tenor of domestic law is not
			<lb />
			breached and in case of any such inconsistency, the
			<lb />
			domestic legislation should prevail.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			&quot;However, applicability of the International
			<lb />
			Conventions and Covenants, as also the resolutions,
			<lb />
			etc. for the purpose of interpreting domestic statute
			<lb />
			will depend upon the acceptability of the
			<lb />
			Conventions in question. If the country is a
			<lb />
			signatory thereto subject of course to the provisions
			<lb />
			of the domestic law, the International Covenants
			<lb />
			can be utilized. Where International Conventions
			<lb />
			are framed upon undertaking a great deal of
			<lb />
			exercise upon giving an opportunity of hearing to
			<lb />
			both the parties and filtered at several levels as also
			<lb />
			upon taking into consideration the different societal
			<lb />
			conditions in different countries by laying down the
			<lb />
			minimum norm, as for example, the ILO
			<lb />
			Conventions, the court would freely avail the
			<lb />
			benefits thereof.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			&quot;Those Conventions to which India may not be a
			<lb />
			signatory but have been followed by way of
			<lb />
			enactment of new Parliamentary statute or
			<lb />
			amendment to the existing enactment, recourse to
			<lb />
			International Convention is permissible.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			81.
			<lb />
			From the reading of the aforesaid, it is clear that the
			<lb />
			international covenant wherein India is a signatory state can be utilized
			<lb />
			for limited purposes of bridging the gap between national law and
			<lb />
			international to the extent it is not repugnant with the national law. I am
			<lb />
			doubtful as to whether any of the tests laid down by Supreme Court are
			<lb />
			fulfilled in the present case in order to enable this court to consider the
			<lb />
			international covenant relied upon by the defendants. Firstly India has not
			<lb />
			ratified the said convention as per the defendants, thus there is no
			<lb />
			international obligation which is to be respected in the present case.
			<lb />
			Secondly, the defendants&quot; counsel wants this court to read into the
			<lb />
			following statement to their benefit:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;It is understood that the mere provision of physical
			<lb />
			facilities for enabling or making a communication
			<lb />
			does not in itself amount to communication within
			<lb />
			the meaning of this Treaty or the Berne Convention.
			<lb />
			It is further understood that nothing in Article 8
			<lb />
			precludes a contacting party from applying Article
			<lb />
			11 bis (2).&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			82.
			<lb />
			There is no disputing this proposition and I have in the
			<lb />
			preceding paragraphs of my judgment laid down this proposition that
			<lb />
			merely providing means does not amount to authorization. But this
			<lb />
			statement as such cannot be read into due to the non fulfillment of
			<lb />
			principles which enables this court to read into the international
			<lb />
			covenants.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			83
			<lb />
			This statement is neither bridging any gaps in the law and is
			<lb />
			rather part of the statute in India where permitting the place for profit is
			<lb />
			an infringement and not providing mere means. The reading of this
			<lb />
			statement itself may not aid the case of the defendants in any event and,
			<lb />
			thus, I am not convinced and also not sure as to what aid the defendants
			<lb />
			intend to draw from reading of this article from the convention. This also
			<lb />
			does not affect the invocation of the provision of Section 51 (a) (ii) of the
			<lb />
			Act basing upon which I have found prima facie view of the infringement.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			84.
			<lb />
			The submission has been made by the learned counsel for
			<lb />
			defendants that the defendants&quot; acts of providing the tools relating to
			<lb />
			notice and turn down provisions are sufficient safeguards and amounts to
			<lb />
			due diligence which should be considered to be a mitigating factor
			<lb />
			against the grant of the injunction as the defendants are taking curative
			<lb />
			measures against the possible infringement.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			85.
			<lb />
			I have gone through the submission advanced by the learned
			<lb />
			counsel for the defendants and I reject it being meritless. This is due to
			<lb />
			following reasons I find that the said post infringement measures may not
			<lb />
			be prima facie sufficient safeguards for the infringements:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			a) Firstly, I wish to again discuss Section 51 (a) (ii) of the Act read
			<lb />
			with Section 55 proviso, the wordings of which nowhere permits
			<lb />
			any room for due diligence to be exercised by the infringer and
			<lb />
			only provides an exemption for mistaken infringement on the count
			<lb />
			of lack of knowledge or the person was not aware of the said
			<lb />
			infringement. Under these circumstances, permitting this kind of
			<lb />
			due diligence post infringement would mean reading the words into
			<lb />
			the statute which would be impermissible under the canons of
			<lb />
			construction when the statute does not provides so.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			b) Secondly, I have already concluded separately that provisions of
			<lb />
			IT Act would not curtail the remedies under the Copyright Act and
			<lb />
			Patent Act by virtue of the proviso of IT Act. In these
			<lb />
			circumstances, the provisions of Section 79 cannot also allow to
			<lb />
			militate against the case of established infringement under Section
			<lb />
			51 and Section 55 of the Act.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			c) Thirdly, there are no safeguards provided under the Copyright Act
			<lb />
			for the infringement in the cases like the present one wherein there
			<lb />
			is a knowledge and exercise of due diligence post infringement.
			<lb />
			Rather, the conjoint reading of Section 51 of the Act and proviso
			<lb />
			to the Section 55 of the Act makes it clear that the knowledge or
			<lb />
			no notice of the infringement can only assist the defendants in
			<lb />
			resisting the damages and not the injunction. However, in some
			<lb />
			cases like the present one under Section 51 (a) (ii) of the Act, lack
			<lb />
			of knowledge can save the liability of infringement as the same is
			<lb />
			the ingredient of the Section. But certainly, there is no provision
			<lb />
			which can save the liability when there is an apparent knowledge
			<lb />
			and exercise of due diligence post infringement. I have already
			<lb />
			formed an opinion that the defendants are aware and has
			<lb />
			reasonable belief of infringement and thus the exercise of due
			<lb />
			diligence after the infringement cannot operate in favour of the
			<lb />
			defendants to escape the liability.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			d) Fourthly, if there is any due diligence which has to be exercised in
			<lb />
			the event of absence of any provision under the Act, the said due
			<lb />
			diligence must be present at the time of infringement and not when
			<lb />
			the infringement has already occurred so that the infringement can
			<lb />
			be prevented at the threshold and not when the same has already
			<lb />
			occurred. The post infringement measures like the ones informed
			<lb />
			by the defendants which are in compliances of US statute may hold
			<lb />
			good in US due to the legislative measure but the same are not
			<lb />
			operative in India. Such post due diligence on the ground of some
			<lb />
			inherent helplessness which the defendants are pleading only
			<lb />
			because they are sitting on internet or cyberspace may not be
			<lb />
			correct as the law does not exclude cyberspace from its purview to
			<lb />
			do infringements there. The defendants have sufficient means to
			<lb />
			modify the work by taking licenses from the users, adding
			<lb />
			advertisements to the works of the plaintiff. Consequently, the
			<lb />
			effective means for pre infringement enquires are also necessarily
			<lb />
			have to be performed by the defendants only. If the defendants
			<lb />
			state that there no means to do so due to some impossibilities, the
			<lb />
			defendants must take preliminary measures at the time of
			<lb />
			modification of the works and prior to making them available to
			<lb />
			the public so as to ensure that the same does not infringe any ones
			<lb />
			copyright.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			86.
			<lb />
			It gives me no hesitation to state that the compulsion which
			<lb />
			the defendants are pointing out of lack of corrective measures at the first
			<lb />
			instance due to multiplicity of the works or uploads and also the
			<lb />
			diversified business of the defendants is not only the plea taken by the
			<lb />
			defendants for the first time in any infringement action relating to
			<lb />
			copyright infringement. It is rather applicable to any case of infringement.
			<lb />
			Take for instance, the case of music library or shop selling movies for
			<lb />
			hire wherein the defendants take the plea that due to multiplicity of
			<lb />
			numbers or titles, one cannot identify the pirated ones from the originals.
			<lb />
			But this kind of argument or plea cannot preclude the labour or burden
			<lb />
			which the defendants ought to have exercised while taking into the
			<lb />
			possession the pirated titles by enquiring as to whether they are belonging
			<lb />
			to the owner or emanating from owner or not. The situation will become
			<lb />
			more complex when the same movie seller or person giving for hire will
			<lb />
			start keeping the international titles like Hindi Movies, English Movies,
			<lb />
			French Movies and Pakistani titles. The said labour then increases
			<lb />
			manifold and the said justification also gains more strength when he says
			<lb />
			that the due to several sources, it becomes virtually impossible to keep a
			<lb />
			hold of the each and every title whether original or duplicate. Even if the
			<lb />
			said person states that once it is brought to his notice by the customer or
			<lb />
			the owner that it is an infringement, he immediately removes the said title
			<lb />
			from the library or the shop. The said acts cannot save him from the
			<lb />
			liability of the infringement.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			87.
			<lb />
			Likewise in the present case, the labour or the due diligence is
			<lb />
			the enquiry by the defendants themselves to be exercised. The nature of
			<lb />
			portal due to which the defendants feels helpless is of less avail to
			<lb />
			mitigate the liability unless there is a statutory exemption to that effect
			<lb />
			(like in Digital Millennium Copyright Act (&quot;DMCA&quot;). The defendants
			<lb />
			can do many things to stop this, first that it can enquire at the stage when
			<lb />
			the defendants modify the works, at that time the defendants can enquire
			<lb />
			about the titles of the work and about ownership, secondly at the time of
			<lb />
			the uploading by the user, the content should not immediately made the
			<lb />
			available to the public, the defendants can put them to the halt subject to
			<lb />
			enquiries of the titles or authentication of the proprietor and thereafter
			<lb />
			make them available to the public.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			88.
			<lb />
			There is no reason to axiomatically make each and every
			<lb />
			work available to the public solely because user has supplied them unless
			<lb />
			the defendants are so sure that it is not infringement. If the defendants
			<lb />
			cannot exercise diligence of this nature, the necessary inferences can be
			<lb />
			drawn is that the defendants are making itself liable for infringement by
			<lb />
			its inactions to enquire about the source of the works at the appropriate
			<lb />
			stage.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			89.
			<lb />
			Thus, even if the post infringement measures which may be
			<lb />
			acceptable in certain legal systems due to the specific legislations may
			<lb />
			not be hold good in India when the statute in India does not culls out any
			<lb />
			such exception as mitigating factor.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			90.
			<lb />
			Now I shall be discussing the argument raised by the counsel
			<lb />
			for the parties on the reliefs. The extensive submissions have been made
			<lb />
			at the Bar about the nature of the relief.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			91.
			<lb />
			Mr. Sibal has submitted that the present case warrants
			<lb />
			complete interim injunction in terms of the prayers made in interim
			<lb />
			application wherein the defendants can be restrained from communicating
			<lb />
			the plaintiff&quot;s works to the public as the current arrangement as directed
			<lb />
			by Division Bench is not sufficiently protecting the rights of the plaintiff.
			<lb />
			Mr. Sibal states that the current arrangement enables the infringement to
			<lb />
			first happen and then comes corrective action which is belated in cases of
			<lb />
			internet wrongs therefore, the plaintiff seeks more directions from this
			<lb />
			Court so that the defendants do not infringe the works of the plaintiff.
			<lb />
			Mr. Sibal submits that even the order of Division Bench itself states that
			<lb />
			the same is tentative and cannot come in the way of deciding the
			<lb />
			injunction application.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			92.
			<lb />
			On the other hand, Mr. Kumar has submitted that the
			<lb />
			injunction in terms of the prayers made in the interim application cannot
			<lb />
			be granted due to following reasons:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			a) That there cannot be injunction of general nature wherein the
			<lb />
			plaintiff has not pointed out what are the specific infringements
			<lb />
			against which the plaintiff intended to secure protection and there
			<lb />
			can be injunction only to the extent of specific infringement and
			<lb />
			not in cases of infringements of future.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			b) That there cannot be any quia timet action in copyright
			<lb />
			infringement. This is as per the learned counsel due to difference in
			<lb />
			the language of the trade mark act and the Copyright Act wherein
			<lb />
			the trade mark law protects likelihood of confusion but the
			<lb />
			Copyright Act does not provide any such infringement. Thus, the
			<lb />
			principle of quia timet is not applicable in copyright infringement.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			c) That the injunction of general nature cannot be granted as the same
			<lb />
			is also barred under the provisions of Specific Relief Act, 1963
			<lb />
			wherein Section 14(1) (d) read with Section 41(e) prevents any
			<lb />
			such kind of injunction.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			d) That the term of the order granting an injunction should be such
			<lb />
			that it is quite plain what it presents and what it prohibits. An order
			<lb />
			which merely prohibits a man from doing what he has no authority
			<lb />
			to do, without showing him what the limits of his authority are, and
			<lb />
			leaves him to find what is forbidden and what is allowed, is
			<lb />
			irregular.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			e) That in the present matter, the relief of omnibus injunction as
			<lb />
			sought by the Plaintiff is not only impossible to comply with by the
			<lb />
			defendants due to the existing technological limitations, but this
			<lb />
			Hon&quot;ble Court will not be able to enforce the same unless the
			<lb />
			legitimate website of the defendant No.1 is shut down. Besides,
			<lb />
			this Hon&quot;ble Court would require continuous monitoring of the
			<lb />
			defendant No.1&quot;s website, which is neither feasible nor in the spirit
			<lb />
			of law.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			f) That the relief of the general injunction cannot be granted as the
			<lb />
			plaintiff has not shown the title on the copyright on each and every
			<lb />
			work. The defendants also dispute the assignments of the
			<lb />
			copyright being not in order. Further, the defendants allege that the
			<lb />
			assignment in every work pertains to several restrictions such as
			<lb />
			restriction as to terms, restriction as to home viewing etc. Thus, till
			<lb />
			the time the assignment deeds are examined. The plaintiff is not
			<lb />
			entitled to the relief of injunction much less the omnibus
			<lb />
			injunction.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			Thus, the defendants contend that the injunction of such
			<lb />
			nature is difficult to comply which necessitates non grant of such
			<lb />
			order which cannot be enforced.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			93.
			<lb />
			I have examined the submissions of the parties on the issue of
			<lb />
			grant of wider relief which has been mentioned in the Interim application.
			<lb />
			I am of the opinion that the court is not powerless to protect the interest
			<lb />
			of the party in cases involving civil wrongs when it involves recurring
			<lb />
			infringements or infractions. I shall now proceed to discuss the reasoning
			<lb />
			to this effect:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			93.1
			<lb />
			Firstly, the defendants&quot; concern that the plaintiff has not
			<lb />
			substantiated the cause of action by certainly providing the infringements
			<lb />
			against which it requires prohibitory relief. The said submission of the
			<lb />
			defendants do not aid their case as indeed the plaintiff has been able to
			<lb />
			procure the sample infringements which are entailed in the plaint out of
			<lb />
			the mass infringements which are occurring over the internet on day to
			<lb />
			day basis. It is the case of the plaintiff&quot;s that it is the owner of repertoire
			<lb />
			of the musical works and sound recordings. Out of this repertoire, if the
			<lb />
			plaintiff is able to show some sets of infringements and is also able to
			<lb />
			show that the defendant&quot;s acts are such which amounts to permitting the
			<lb />
			place for profit for infringement purposes and there is a complete
			<lb />
			certainty of future infringements. There is no reason why this court
			<lb />
			should continue to allow the defendants to use that place for profit of the
			<lb />
			defendants against the infringement of the plaintiff works which includes
			<lb />
			current works and future works of the plaintiff.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			93.2
			<lb />
			It would be wrong understanding of the law to state that the
			<lb />
			infringements can be prohibited only when the torts are perfected. The
			<lb />
			principle of quia timet is not only confined to the trade mark
			<lb />
			infringements as propounded by the learned counsel for the defendants.
			<lb />
			The said submission is also misplaced and rejected as meritless.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			93.3
			<lb />
			The principle of quia timet is applicable to any tortuous
			<lb />
			liability wherever there is an apprehension of infringement likely to
			<lb />
			happen. This can be seen even in the cases of trespass where the
			<lb />
			injunctions are sought even when there is threat of invasion in the
			<lb />
			property of someone. The principle of quia timet has been explained by
			<lb />
			John George Woodroffe in his book &quot;The Law Relating to Injunctions&quot;
			<lb />
			in the following words :
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;9.
			<lb />
			Relief. Whether it be given by the issue
			<lb />
			of an Injunction or the appointment of a Receiver,
			<lb />
			is granted general upon the principle quia timet;
			<lb />
			that is, the Court assists the party who seeks its
			<lb />
			aid, because he fears (quia timet) some future
			<lb />
			probable injury to his rights or interests, and not
			<lb />
			because an injury has already occurred, which
			<lb />
			requires any compensation or other relief. So the
			<lb />
			remedy by temporary Injunction being preventive
			<lb />
			in its nature, it is not necessary that a wrong should
			<lb />
			have been actually committed before the Court will
			<lb />
			interfere, since if this were required it would in
			<lb />
			most cases defeat the very purpose for which the
			<lb />
			relief is sought by allowing the commission of the
			<lb />
			act which the complainant seeks to restrain. And
			<lb />
			satisfactory proof that the defendants threaten the
			<lb />
			commission of a wrong (which is within their
			<lb />
			power) is sufficient ground to justify the relief.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			93.4
			<lb />
			Likewise, Hugh Laddie in his book titled as &quot;The Modern
			<lb />
			Law of Copyright&quot; by Laddie, Presscott &amp; Victoria at p. 405 observes
			<lb />
			about the nature of relief which can be sought in relation to infringements
			<lb />
			by way of authorization like in the present case in the following words:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;Relief can be sought in appropriate
			<lb />
			circumstances on quia timet basis even before the
			<lb />
			tort is perfected by the commission of the
			<lb />
			infringement authorized&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			93.5
			<lb />
			In Fletcher v Bealey, {1885] 28.Ch.D.688 the principles that
			<lb />
			should be followed by a Court when dealing with an application for an
			<lb />
			injunction quia timet when infringement of the plaintiff&apos;s rights is only
			<lb />
			apprehended were succinctly laid down by Pearson, J. who said as
			<lb />
			follows at page 698:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			&quot;I do not think, therefore, that I shall be very far
			<lb />
			wrong if I lay it down that there are at least two
			<lb />
			necessary ingredients for a quia timet action.
			<lb />
			There must, if no actual damage is proved, be
			<lb />
			proof of imminent danger, and there must also be
			<lb />
			proof that the apprehended damage will, if it
			<lb />
			comes, be very substantial. I should almost say it
			<lb />
			must be proved that it will be irreparable,
			<lb />
			because, if the danger is not proved to be so
			<lb />
			imminent that no one can doubt that, if the
			<lb />
			remedy is delayed, the damage will be suffered, I
			<lb />
			think it must be shown that, if the damage does
			<lb />
			occur at any time, it will come in such a way and
			<lb />
			under such circumstances that it will be
			<lb />
			impossible for the plaintiff to protect himself
			<lb />
			against it if relief is denied to him in a quia timet
			<lb />
			action.&quot;
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			93.6
			<lb />
			Thus, the submission that this court cannot prevent future
			<lb />
			wrongs on the basis of quia timet injunction is also not correct as it is
			<lb />
			equally applicable to infringement of copyright like in any other tortuous
			<lb />
			act. Accordingly, the plaintiff is entitled to relief on the basis of quia
			<lb />
			timet action as the defendant&quot;s nature of activities is such where the
			<lb />
			plaintiff&quot;s works is liable to infringe and more so when the defendants are
			<lb />
			notified about the plaintiff&quot;s several works. The said danger of
			<lb />
			infringement is imminent risk of substantial damages with certainty as
			<lb />
			the defendants have already done several infringements and will continue
			<lb />
			to do so in the light of the continuous acts of the defendants. The
			<lb />
			plaintiff&quot;s interest is also to be protected against such infractions which
			<lb />
			are possible by way of injunction and any court jurisdictionally
			<lb />
			competent can grant the relief prayed for quia timet action.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			93.7
			<lb />
			Secondly, the submission of the defendants that the injunction
			<lb />
			order of the nature wherein the defendants are restrained from infringing
			<lb />
			the plaintiff&quot;s works in general cannot be granted as the defendants must
			<lb />
			know for what the defendants are restrained is also not correct. If the
			<lb />
			defendants at this stage are already notified about the plaintiff&quot;s works
			<lb />
			for the purposes of notice and turn down provisions and is also conscious
			<lb />
			of the fact that the plaintiff owns most of Hindi movie titles and its
			<lb />
			copyright, there cannot be anything specific than stating that the
			<lb />
			defendants are restrained from using the works of the plaintiff.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			93.8
			<lb />
			It is only the apprehension of the defendants that they could
			<lb />
			not trace out the ownership of the plaintiff in each and every work.
			<lb />
			However, if one sees carefully the application of the notice and turn
			<lb />
			down facility provided by the defendants wherein the owners are chasing
			<lb />
			the infringers for turning their infringements down from the website as
			<lb />
			against the infringers chasing the owners, the problem of infringement
			<lb />
			can be resolved by applying the same conversely wherein infringers must
			<lb />
			legitimize the acts with the owners prior to committing any such
			<lb />
			infringements. This can be done only by the order of the court of
			<lb />
			prohibitory nature wherein the prior notice to the owners and steps to find
			<lb />
			ownership can be taken by the defendants by taking preventive actions
			<lb />
			prior to infringements.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			93.9
			<lb />
			These apprehensions of the defendants about inability of
			<lb />
			enforce or implement the order of this court are unfounded. Further, the
			<lb />
			concern of the defendants that their website hosts the acts which are
			<lb />
			infringing as well as non infringing and it is difficult to segregate all this
			<lb />
			and rather impossible is also unmeritorious. Such concerns are taken care
			<lb />
			by the courts while granting injunctions in copyright infringements.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			93.10
			<lb />
			In Garware Plastics and Polyester Ltd. and Ors. etc. v.
			<lb />
			Telelink and Ors. etc.; AIR 1989 Bom 331 wherein Hon&quot;ble Bombay
			<lb />
			High Court had examined this kind of concern wherein the court
			<lb />
			observed that it is true that there are certain places like hotels where there
			<lb />
			are private viewings as well as public viewings, some of which are
			<lb />
			infringement and some are not. But still, the court proceeded to grant the
			<lb />
			injunction against the defendants from infringing the plaintiff&quot;s works in
			<lb />
			respect of which the plaintiff is the owners and/or assignees of copyright
			<lb />
			without obtaining an assignment of the same from such owners and
			<lb />
			assignees or a licensee under the Copyright Act, 1957.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			93.11
			<lb />
			Similarly in the cases involving mass infringements like the
			<lb />
			cases instituted by Performing Rights Society, Phonographic Societies
			<lb />
			which not only espouse the cause of one copyright owner but is a
			<lb />
			collective action, the mere fact of non crystallization of all the
			<lb />
			infringements does not preclude the courts from granting the injunctions
			<lb />
			basing on the prima facie ownership of the plaintiff&quot;s works and sample
			<lb />
			infringements. All these injunctions are being granted by this court from
			<lb />
			time to time. Thus, this concern of the defendants has no meaning and the
			<lb />
			injunction of the nature asked by the plaintiff cannot be faulted with
			<lb />
			considering the acts of the defendants which are infringing in nature and
			<lb />
			the equal level of certainty with which the future infringement may arise.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			93.12
			<lb />
			Thirdly, the submission that this court cannot grant injunction
			<lb />
			in view of the Section 14 of the Specific Relief Act, 1963. I am of the
			<lb />
			opinion, that the Section 14 of the Act puts no embargo for the grant of
			<lb />
			the relief in the present case. This is due to the following reasons:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			 Firstly Section 14 read with Section 41(e) of the Act
			<lb />
			would lead to conclusion that the contracts which are not
			<lb />
			specifically enforceable, the injunction in negative
			<lb />
			enforcing those contracts cannot be granted. However,
			<lb />
			the present case does not fall within the purview of
			<lb />
			enforcing by way of injunction the contracts which cannot
			<lb />
			be enforced by way of operation of Section 14 of the Act.
			<lb />
			The present case rather relates to statutory injunction
			<lb />
			prescribed by the special law which is Copyright Act.
			<lb />
			The said injunction is sought under code of civil
			<lb />
			procedure by way of statutory remedy provided under the
			<lb />
			Act. Thus, the said analogy of enforcing the contract by
			<lb />
			way of injunction cannot be applicable to the present
			<lb />
			case.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			 The present dispute relates to remedy which is statutorily
			<lb />
			prescribed by the special law of Copyright. I have already
			<lb />
			stated that quia timet action can be maintained in the
			<lb />
			appropriate cases as permissible by the law. Thus, in the
			<lb />
			present case, the remedies prescribed by the special law
			<lb />
			will also operate over and above the remedies prescribed
			<lb />
			under the general law relating to contracts.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			 Section 14 (d) of the Act has been greatly stressed by the
			<lb />
			counsel for the defendants has also no applicability in the
			<lb />
			present case. However, in the present case, it would be
			<lb />
			incorrect to assume that the court cannot supervise the
			<lb />
			infringement of copyrights of the plaintiff&quot;s works in the
			<lb />
			event the court directs the defendants to take pre
			<lb />
			infringement measures to cut down infringement of the
			<lb />
			plaintiff&quot;s work. If the defendants are guilty of non
			<lb />
			performance or implementation of the order, the court can
			<lb />
			call for the records of the cache on the internet and
			<lb />
			downloads from the relevant sources whereby it can
			<lb />
			supervise whether the defendants have complied with the
			<lb />
			said order or not.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			94.
			<lb />
			More importantly, if the plaintiff files separate suits for
			<lb />
			number of infringements, the moot question is whether the said acts can
			<lb />
			be monitored in that case or not. The answer to my knowledge is in
			<lb />
			affirmative. If that is, so then it can be monitored now also by directing
			<lb />
			the defendants not to do the infringing acts. It would be rather futile
			<lb />
			exercise to relegate the plaintiff to file separate suits after perfection of
			<lb />
			infringements and allowing the defendants to continue to ride over the
			<lb />
			works of the plaintiff till that time.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			95.
			<lb />
			The challenge to the assignment deeds which has been made
			<lb />
			by the defendants are only confined to the defects in the respective
			<lb />
			assignment pointed by the defendants. The said defects in the
			<lb />
			assignments are disputed by the plaintiff by stating that the said
			<lb />
			assignments are proper and are in order which can be furnished before
			<lb />
			the court. All this is more of a question of trial at the time of evidence. At
			<lb />
			this stage, for the purposes of forming a prima facie opinion, the
			<lb />
			assignments filed with documents are taken as correct as no contrary or
			<lb />
			no cogent evidence to disprove the same has been placed on the record
			<lb />
			by the defendants. On the basis of the documents, it can be stated that the
			<lb />
			plaintiff is the owner of copyright, otherwise no one would have executed
			<lb />
			the assignment deeds. Therefore, the title of the ownership of the plaintiff
			<lb />
			is sufficient to form prima facie view.
		</p>
		<lb />
		<p>
			Accordingly, this court is not precluded from passing interim order
			<lb />
			in terms of the prayers made in IA No.15781/2008 whereby the
			<lb />
			defendants can be restrained from infringing the copyrighted works of the
			<lb />
			plaintiff online by permitting place for profit. No further submission
			<lb />
			remains unanswered.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			96.
			<lb />
			The principles for the grant of temporary injunction have been
			<lb />
			succinctly discussed in Dalpat Kumar &amp; Anr. vs. Prahlad Singh &amp;
			<lb />
			Ors.; AIR 1993 SC 276 wherein the apex court has stated that for the
			<lb />
			purposes of grant of temporary injunction, the court must test the case of
			<lb />
			the parties on threefold tests:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			a) Prima Facie Case
			<lb />
			b) Balance of Convenience
			<lb />
			c) Irreparable Damage
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			97.
			<lb />
			The plaintiff has been able to make out a prima facie case as
			<lb />
			the plaintiff is the owner of the copyright in the works enumerated in the
			<lb />
			plaint. The plaintiff has also been able to establish prima facie that the
			<lb />
			acts of the defendants are infringing in nature as the same are permitting
			<lb />
			the webspace or place on internet for profit. The prima facie case thus is
			<lb />
			in favour of the plaintiff. The balance of convenience lies in favour of the
			<lb />
			plaintiff as the defendants would be less inconvenienced if they are
			<lb />
			directed to not to infringe the plaintiff&quot;s works as it is their own case is
			<lb />
			that the defendants are doing business from multifarious jobs on internet
			<lb />
			and the works of the plaintiff is no means of profit. As against the same,
			<lb />
			the plaintiff is totally dependants upon its works for the purposes of
			<lb />
			royalties, reaping fruits of its copyright for further investments etc. thus,
			<lb />
			the plaintiff would be more inconvenienced if its works are continued to
			<lb />
			be exploited for profit without its permission. The irreparable loss would
			<lb />
			also ensue to plaintiff if the works of the plaintiff are allowed to be made
			<lb />
			public for permitting the place on internet for profit as against the
			<lb />
			defendants who will loose nothing more than users on internet which as
			<lb />
			per themselves are trivial part of their business model.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			98.
			<lb />
			Consequently, the present case warrants the grant of interim
			<lb />
			injunction for the purposes of prevention of infringement of the plaintiff&quot;s
			<lb />
			works. However, this court is not precluded from granting the interim
			<lb />
			relief in the moulded form so that the infringement can be prevented
			<lb />
			which is in fact the relief asked by the plaintiff in its interim application.
			<lb />
			Accordingly, the following interim directions and orders are passed:
			<lb />
		</p>

		<item>
			a)
			<lb />
			The defendants, their agents, representatives, servants, their
			<lb />
			officers or any person on their behalf are restrained from
			<lb />
			modifying the works (more specifically the works of the
			<lb />
			plaintiff), by adding advertisements to the said works of the
			<lb />
			plaintiff adding logos and/ or sponsorships to the works, or
			<lb />
			earning profit otherwise in any manner in relation to the said
			<lb />
			works consequent upon uploading to their website/webspace
			<lb />
			of www.myspace.com or in.myspace.com without making
			<lb />
			endeavours to enquire the ownership of the plaintiff (as at
			<lb />
			that stage of modification, the defendants have all means to
			<lb />
			enquire about the same) and thereby making them available
			<lb />
			to the public either by displaying (or playing or exhibition)
			<lb />
			of on the website or allowing the downloading from their
			<lb />
			website or otherwise of the said works in the modified form
			<lb />
			which will lead to permitting the place for profit within the
			<lb />
			meaning of Section 51 (a) (ii) of the Act and causes
			<lb />
			infringement of copyright of the plaintiff.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			b)
			<lb />
			In relation to the future works of the plaintiff to be uploaded
			<lb />
			by the users other than those which are mentioned in (a), it
			<lb />
			has been stated by defendants fairly in the written statement
			<lb />
			that the order passed by the division bench is only possible
			<lb />
			solution and have also during the course of the arguments
			<lb />
			agreed that the defendants would not be inconvenienced if
			<lb />
			the order passed by learned division bench is continued.
			<lb />
			Accordingly, the defendants shall delete the works of the
			<lb />
			plaintiff as and when the plaintiff provides the details of its
			<lb />
			songs and films which have been uploaded on the web-site
			<lb />
			of the defendants, the defendants shall immediately take
			<lb />
			remedial measures to remove the same from its website not
			<lb />
			later than one week from the date of such communication.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			c)
			<lb />
			Further the defendants are also directed to verify from the
			<lb />
			plaintiff independently without waiting the direction under
			<lb />
			(b) to be complied with by the plaintiff on their own by
			<lb />
			other means continuously or through its India centric
			<lb />
			operations about the ownership status or updations in the
			<lb />
			works of the plaintiff and shall do their honest endeavours
			<lb />
			on their own to remove the offending content or infringing
			<lb />
			works immediately after the gaining the said knowledge.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<item>
			d)
			<lb />
			In relation to the works of the plaintiff which are already
			<lb />
			turned down once by the defendants, the defendants are
			<lb />
			restrained from further allowing the continuation of the
			<lb />
			uploadings or its existence on its website of the same works
			<lb />
			which have already been turned down/ deleted by the
			<lb />
			defendants at the behest of the plaintiff request. This has
			<lb />
			been already stated by the defendants by explaining their
			<lb />
			various tools for preventing infringement wherein the
			<lb />
			defendants possess the necessary tools and the technology
			<lb />
			which identifies and prevents the repetitions in infringements
			<lb />
			after its first posting and deletion. Accordingly, the
			<lb />
			defendants are directed to ensure the deletions and the
			<lb />
			preventions of repetitions on their own after putting to notice
			<lb />
			by the plaintiff about the works by availing their own tools
			<lb />
			and not by the calling the plaintiff to do this by some
			<lb />
			subscription.
		</item>
		<lb />
		<item>
			In this way, the parties in the interim can prevent the
			<lb />
			infringements and its occurrence on the website of the defendants till the
			<lb />
			disposal of the suit. The orders passed in the interim applications are
			<lb />
			tentative in nature and does not come in the away of the court at the time
			<lb />
			of hearing of the matter after the completion of the trial.
			<lb />
		</item>

		<p>
			99.
			<lb />
			Consequently, the plaintiff&quot;s application being IA
			<lb />
			No.15781/2009 (U/o 39 R 1 &amp; 2 CPC) is allowed and defendants&quot;
			<lb />
			application being IA No.3085/2009 (U/o 39 R 4 CPC) is dismissed with
			<lb />
			cost of Rs.20,000/-.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			100.
			<lb />
			IA No.15781/2009 and IA No.3085/2009 are accordingly
			<lb />
			disposed of.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<head>
			CS (OS) No. 2682/2008</head>
		<lb />
		<p>
			List on 16 th August, 2011 for direction.
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>
			MANMOHAN SINGH, J
			<lb />
		</p>

		<p>JULY 29, 2011</p>


	</text>
</tei>