<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="10266771"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>

	1<lb/>
	<reference>IN THE HIGH COURT OF KARNATAKA AT BENGALURU<lb/> DATED THIS THE 19 TH DAY OF JANUARY, 2021 PRESENT<lb/> THE HON&apos;BLE MR. JUSTICE ARAVIND KUMAR<lb/> AND<lb/> THE HON&apos;BLE MR. JUSTICE B.A. PATIL<lb/> 28421/2019, 28900/2019, 29471/2019, 29604/2019,<lb/> 29668/2019, 30073/2019, 30187/2019, 31106/2019,<lb/> 31107/2019, 31322/2019, 31349/2019, 31350/2019,<lb/> 32184/2019, 33249/2019, 33262/2019, 34572/2019,<lb/> 35277/2019, 35575/2019, 35579/2019, 36127/2019,<lb/> 38110/2019, 38701/2019, 38895/2019, 40447/2019,<lb/> 40448/2019, 40450/2019, 41715/2019, 41716/2019,<lb/> 42273/2019, 45583/2019, 50244/2019, 50781/2019,<lb/> 50828/2019, 50955/2019, 50956/2019, 51043/2019,<lb/> 51101/2019, 51638/2019, 51710/2019, 51830/2019,<lb/> 51878/2019, 51879/2019, 51926/2019, 51941/2019,<lb/> 51944/2019, 51945/2019, 51961/2019, 52011/2019,<lb/> 52032/2019, 52134/2019, 52566/2019, 52609/2019,<lb/> 220/2020, 3190/2020, 9647/2020, 12647/2020<lb/></reference>

	(KLGP)<lb/> IN W.P.NO.47747/2017:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>SHRIRAM PROPERTIES PVT. LTD.,<lb/> A COMPANY REGISTERED UNDER THE<lb/> COMPANIES ACT, 1956<lb/> HAVING ITS REGISTERED OFFICE AT<lb/> NO.123, ANGAPPA NAICKAN STREET<lb/> CHENNAI AND ADMINISTRATIVE<lb/> OFFICE AT: 3RD FLOOR, MOOKAMIBA<lb/> COMPLEX, NO.4, LADY DESIKACHARY<lb/> ROAD, CHENNAI -560 004<lb/> REPRESENTED BY K. VAIDYANATHAN.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	AND BRANCH AT:<lb/>
	<reference>NO.40/43, NAGASHREE CHAMBERS<lb/> 4TH CROSS, 8TH MAIN, SADASHIVA<lb/> NAGAR, BANGALORE -560 090 4<lb/> REPRESENTED BY ITS<lb/> AUTHORIZED REPRESENTATIVE.<lb/> ...PETITIONER<lb/></reference>

	(BY SRI. AJESH KUMAR S, ADVOCATE)<lb/> AND:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>1 .<lb/> STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> REPRESENTED BY ITS SECRETARY<lb/> DEPARTMENT OF REVENUE<lb/> VIDHANA SOUDHA, AMBEDKAR<lb/> VEEDHI, BENGALURU -560 001.<lb/> 2 .<lb/> BENGALURU DEVELOPMENT AUTHORITY<lb/> REPRESENTED BY ITS COMMISSIONER<lb/> T. CHOWDAIAH ROAD<lb/> KUMAR PARK WEST<lb/> BENGALURU -560 020.<lb/> 3 .<lb/> BENGALURU BRUHAT MAHANAGARA PALIKE<lb/> BY ITS COMMISSIONER, N.R. CIRCLE<lb/> BANGALORE -560 002. …RESPONDENTS<lb/> (BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI. V. SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H.C, HCGP FOR R-1)<lb/> THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA<lb/> PRAYING TO STRIKE DOWN THE KARNATAKA LAND<lb/> GRABBING PROHIBITION ACT OF 2011 AS THE ACT IS<lb/> UNCONSTITUTIONAL<lb/> AS<lb/> IT<lb/> VIOLATES<lb/> THE<lb/> PETITIONER&apos;S RIGHT FOR A FREE AND FAIR TRIAL<lb/> GUARANTEED UNDER ARTICLE 21 OF CONSTITUTION<lb/> OF INDIA.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	IN W.P.NO.433/2017:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<reference>M/S SHAKTHI HILL RESORTS PVT. LTD.,<lb/> BEML LAYOUT, RAJARAJESHWARI 5<lb/></reference>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>NAGAR,OFF MYSORE ROAD<lb/> BENGALURU -560 098<lb/> REPRESENTED BY ITS CHAIRMAN<lb/> SRI. R. ARUNACHALAM<lb/> AGED ABOUT 64 YEARS.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>... PETITIONER<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	(BY SRI. J.M. RAJANNA SHETTY, ADVOCATE)<lb/> AND:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>1.<lb/> THE STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> REPRESENTED BY ITS REVENUE<lb/> COMMISSIONER, M.S. BUILDING<lb/> BENGALURU -560 001.<lb/> 2.<lb/> THE SPECIAL DEPUTY COMMISSIONER -II<lb/> BENGALURU URBAN DISTRICT<lb/> BEHIND KANDAYA BHAVAN<lb/> K.G. ROAD, BENGALURU -560 009.<lb/> 3.<lb/> THE TAHSILDAR<lb/> BANGALORE SOUTH TALUK<lb/> KANDAYA BHAVAN, K.G. ROAD<lb/> BENGALURU -560 009.<lb/> 4.<lb/> THE REGISTRAR<lb/> SPECIAL COURT UNDER<lb/> THE KARNATAKA LAND GRABBING<lb/> PROHIBITION ACT, 3 RD FLOOR<lb/> KANDAYA BHAVAN, K.G. ROAD<lb/> BENGALURU -560 009.<lb/> ... RESPONDENTS<lb/> (BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI. V. SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H.C, HCGP FOR R-1 TO R-4)<lb/> THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA<lb/> PRAYING TO DECLARE AND QUASH SECTION 11 OF<lb/> THE KARNATAKA ACT NO.38/2014 AS ULTRA VIRES<lb/> AND<lb/> UNCONSTITUTIONAL<lb/> VIDE<lb/> ANNEXURE-G<lb/> DATED:20.10.2014 PUBLISHED IN THE KARNATAKA<lb/> GAZETTE.</titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	6<lb/> IN W.P.NO.10728/2017:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>SYMBIOSIS SOCIETY<lb/> A SOCIETY REGISTERED UNDER<lb/> SOCIETIES REGISTRATION ACT, 1860<lb/> HAVING ITS REGISTERED OFFICE AT<lb/> SENAPATI BAPAT ROAD, PUNE<lb/> AND CAMPUS AND ADMINISTRATIVE<lb/> OFFICE AT:95/1, 95/2, ELECTRONIC CITY<lb/> PHASE-1, HOSUR ROAD BANGALORE -560 100<lb/> BY ITS AUTHORISED SIGNATORY<lb/> MR. T. SUNIL JACOB.<lb/> ... PETITIONER<lb/> (BY SRI. ASHOK HARNALLI, SR. COUNSEL FOR<lb/> SRI. MANMOHAN P.N, ADVOCATE)<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	AND:<lb/>
	<email>1.<lb/></email>

	<note type="funding">STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> DEPARTMENT OF REVENU<lb/> M.S. BUILDING<lb/> BANGALORE -560 001<lb/> REPRESENTED BY ITS SECRETARY.<lb/> 2.<lb/> THE TAHASILDAR<lb/> MEMBER, LAKE MAINTENANCE<lb/> ANEKAL TALUK, ANEKAL -560 100.<lb/> 3.<lb/> THE DEPUTY COMMISSIONER<lb/> ANEKAL TALUK, BENGALURU<lb/> RURAL DISTRICT<lb/> BENGALURU -560 100.<lb/> ... RESPONDENTS<lb/> (BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG<lb/> SRI. V. SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H.C, HCGP FOR R-1 TO R-3;<lb/> SRI. B.S. MANJUNATH, ADVOCATE<lb/> FOR IMPLEEDING APPLICANT ON I.A. 1/2018)<lb/> THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA 7<lb/> PRAYING TO DECLARE THE KARNATAKA LAND<lb/> GRABBING PROHIBITION ACT 2011 (KARNATAKA ACT<lb/> 38 OF 2014) AS ULTRA VIRES THE CONSTITUTION OF<lb/> INDIA VIDE ANNEX-Q AND/OR IN THE ALTERNATIVE.<lb/></note>

	IN W.P.NO.15532/2017:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>REMCO(BHEL) HOUSE BUILDING<lb/> CO-OPERATIVE SOCIETY LIMITED<lb/> NO.356, 5 TH MAIN, RPC (REMCO) LAYOUT<lb/> HAMPI NAGAR<lb/> BENGALURU -560 104<lb/> REPRESENTED BY ITS PRESINDENT<lb/> VIJAYAKUMAR<lb/> S/O LATE GOPALAKRISHNA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 55 YEARS.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>... PETITIONER<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	(BY SRI. D.R. RAVISHANKAR, ADVOCATE)<lb/> AND:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>1.<lb/> THE STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> BY ITS PRINCIPAL SECRETARY<lb/> REVENUE DEPARTMENT<lb/> M.S. BUILDING<lb/> BENGALURU -560 001.<lb/> 2.<lb/> LAND GRABBING PROHIBITION<lb/> SPECIAL COURT, 3 RD FLOOR<lb/> KANDYA BHAVANA, K.G. ROAD<lb/> BENGALURU -560 009<lb/> REPRESENTED BY ITS CHAIRMAN.<lb/> 3.<lb/> HEMANTH RAJU<lb/> S/O LATE MUNIRAJU<lb/> AGED ABOUT 40 YEARS<lb/> RESIDING AT NO.32, ESHWARA<lb/> TEMPLE ROAD, RAMOHALLI<lb/> KENGERI HOBLI<lb/> BEGALURU -560 074. 8<lb/> 4.<lb/> ASHOK S KULLI<lb/> S/O SHANKARAPPA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 56 YEARS<lb/> RESIDING AT NO.1, 4 TH MAIN ROAD<lb/> BYRAVESHWARANAGAR, NAGARABAVI<lb/> MAIN ROAD, BENGALURU -560 070.<lb/> 5.<lb/> M.A. PALANI<lb/> S/O LATE ANNIYAPPA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 61 YEARS<lb/> RESIDING AT NO.130, PMK NILAYAM<lb/> 1 ST MAIN, 2 ND STAGE, OKALIMPURA<lb/> BENGALURU -560 021.<lb/> ... RESPONDENTS<lb/> (BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI. V. SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H.C, HCGP FOR R-1 AND R-2;<lb/> SRI. SHANTHI BHUSHAN, ADVOCATE FOR R-3;<lb/> SRI. M. SHIVAPRAKASH, ADVOCATE FOR<lb/> C/R-4 &amp; ALSO FOR R-5)<lb/> THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA<lb/> PRAYING TO DECLARE THAT THE PROVISIONS OF THE<lb/> KARNATAKA LAND GRABBING PROHIBITION ACT IS<lb/> UNCONSTITUTIONAL AND ULTRA VIRES ARTICLE 14,<lb/> ARTICLE 19 AND 21 AND ARTICLE 300A OF THE<lb/> CONSTITUTION OF INDIA.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	IN W.P.NO.16281/2017:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>1.<lb/> SMT. B. LALITHAMMA<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	AGED ABOUT 50 YEARS<lb/> W/O LATE C.K. NARAYANA GOWDA.<lb/> 2.<lb/> SHRI. C.N. ASHOK<lb/> AGED ABOUT 55 YEARS.<lb/> 3.<lb/> SHRI. C.N. RAMESH<lb/> AGED ABOUT 52 YEARS 9<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">REPRESENTED BY GPA HOLDER<lb/> DR. C.N. PRAKASH.<lb/> 4.<lb/> SHRI. C.N. PRAKASH<lb/> AGED ABOUT 45 YEARS.<lb/> ALL SONS OF<lb/> LATE C.K. NARAYANA GOWDA<lb/> 1 TO 4 RESIDING AT<lb/> CHAMAREDDDIHALLI, ALANGUR<lb/> POST, MULBAGAL TALUK<lb/> KOLAR DISTRICT.<lb/> ... PETITIONERS<lb/></div>

	(BY SRI. AMARNATH B, ADVOCATE)<lb/> AND:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>1.<lb/> GOVERNMENT OF KARNATAKA<lb/> BY ITS PRINCIPAL SECRETARY<lb/> DEPARTMENT OF REVENUE<lb/> VIDHANA SOUDHA<lb/> AMBEDKAR VEEDI<lb/> BANGALORE -560 001<lb/> 2 .<lb/> SRI HEMANTHA RAJU<lb/> S/O LATE MUNI RAJU<lb/> R/A NO.32, ESHWAR TEMPLE ROAD<lb/> RAMOHALLI, KENGERI HOBLI<lb/> BANGALORE SOUTH TALUK<lb/> BANGALORE -560 074.<lb/> 3 .<lb/> SRI. M.K. AYYAPPA<lb/> COMMISSIONER, TRANSPORT<lb/> DEPARTMENT, TRANSPORT<lb/> BUILDING, SHANTI NAGAR<lb/> BANGALORE -560027.<lb/> 4 .<lb/> JAGADEESH<lb/> THAHASILDHAR<lb/> BANGALORE SOUTH TALUK<lb/> AGED ABOUT 45 YEARS<lb/> BANGALORE -560 009. 10<lb/> .<lb/> SHIVANNA<lb/> RTD. DEPUTY THAHSILDAR<lb/> AGED ABOUT 61 YEARS<lb/> BANGALORE SOUTH TALUK<lb/> KANDHAYA BHAVAN<lb/> BANGALORE.<lb/> .<lb/> CHANNEGOWDA<lb/> RTD. REVENUE INSPECTOR<lb/> NO.259, 7 TH MAIN, SARASWHATHI<lb/> NAGAR, BANGALORE -560 040.<lb/> .<lb/> M/S ASIAN FABTECH LTD<lb/> FLAT NO.15, 2 ND PHASE<lb/> PEENYA, BANGALORE -560 058<lb/> REP. BY MANAGING DIRECTOR<lb/> SRI. K.H. PUTTASHWAMI<lb/> S/O LATE HONNEGOWDA.<lb/> .<lb/> SMT. AKKAYYAMMA<lb/> D/O LATE SANJEEVAPPA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 60 YEARS<lb/> BEHIND YELLAMMA TEMPLE<lb/> TIGALARA ROAD, KENGERI VILALGE<lb/> KENGERI HOBLI.BANGALORE.<lb/> .<lb/> SMT. PADHMAMMA<lb/> D/O LATE SANJEEVAPPA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 58 YEARS<lb/> BEHIND YELLAMMA TEMPLE,<lb/> TIGALARA ROAD, KENGERI VILLAGE<lb/> KENGERI HOBLI, BANGALORE -59.<lb/> . SRI. YELLAPPA<lb/> D/O LATE SANJEEVAPPA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 56 YEARS<lb/> BEHIND YELLAMMA TEMPLE,<lb/> TIGALARA ROAD, KENGERI VILLAGE<lb/> KENGERI HOBLI, BANGALORE -59.</titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	11<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>. SMT. GOWRAMMA<lb/> D/O LATE SANJEEVAPPA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 54 YEARS<lb/> BEHIND YELLAMMA TEMPLE<lb/> TIGALARA ROAD, KENGERI VILLAGE<lb/> KENGERI HOBLI, BANGALORE -59.<lb/> . SRI. RAMESH<lb/> S/O LATE SANJEEVAPPA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 52 YEARS<lb/> BEHIND YELLAMMA TEMPLE<lb/> TIGALARA ROAD, KENGERI VILLAGE<lb/> KENGERI HOBLI, BANGALORE -59.<lb/> . SRI. SURESH<lb/> S/O LATE SANJEEVAPPA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 50 YEARS<lb/> BEHIND YELLAMMA TEMPLE<lb/> TIGALARA ROAD, KENGERI VILLAGE<lb/> KENGERI HOBLI, BANGALORE -59.<lb/> . SRI. LAKSHMAN<lb/> S/O SHAMANNA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 50 YEARS<lb/> BEHIND YELLAMMA TEMPLE<lb/> TIGALARA ROAD, KENGERI VILLAGE,<lb/> KENGERI HOBLI, BANGALORE -59.<lb/> . SMT. VIJAYALAKSHIMI<lb/> D/O SHAMANNA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 48 YEARS<lb/> BEHIND YELLAMMA TEMPLE<lb/> TIGALARA ROAD, KENGERI VILLAGE,<lb/> KENGERI HOBLI, BANGALORE -59.<lb/> . SMT. MUNILAKSHMAMMA<lb/> D/O SHAMANNA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 46 YEARS<lb/> BEHIND YELLAMMA TEMPLE<lb/> TIGALARA ROAD, KENGERI VILLAGE<lb/> KENGERI HOBLI, BANGALORE -59.</titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	12<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>. SMT. NEELAMMA<lb/> D/O SHAMANNA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 46 YEARS<lb/> BEHIND YELLAMMA TEMPLE<lb/> TIGALARA ROAD, KENGERI VILLAGE<lb/> KENGERI HOBLI, BANGALORE -59.<lb/> . SMT. BHAGYAMMA<lb/> D/O SHAMANNA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 44 YEARS<lb/> BEHIND YELLAMMA TEMPLE<lb/> TIGALARA ROAD, KENGERI VILLAGE<lb/> KENGERI HOBLI, BANGALORE -59.<lb/> . SMT. SHARADA<lb/> D/O SHAMANNA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 42 YEARS<lb/> BEHIND YELLAMMA TEMPLE<lb/> TIGALARA ROAD, KENGERI VILLAGE<lb/> KENGERI HOBLI, BANGALORE -59.<lb/> . SRIRAMA<lb/> S/O SHAMANNA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 45 YEARS<lb/> BEHING YELLAMMA TEMPLE<lb/> TIGALARA ROAD, KENGERI VILLAGE<lb/> KENGERI HOBLI, BANGALORE -59.<lb/> . SMT. DHANALAKSHMI<lb/> D/O SHAMANNA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 40 YEARS<lb/> BEHING YELLAMMA TEMPLE<lb/> TIGALARA ROAD, KENGERI VILLAGE<lb/> KENGERI HOBLI, BANGALORE -59.<lb/> . KANTHARAJU<lb/> S/O SHAMANNA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 40 YEARS<lb/> BEHING YELLAMMA TEMPLE<lb/> TIGALARA ROAD, KENGERI VILLAGE<lb/> KENGERI HOBLI, BANGALORE -59.</titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	13<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>. SMT. AKKAIYAMMA<lb/> D/O LATE YALLAPPA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 60 YEARS<lb/> BEHING YELLAMMA TEMPLE<lb/> TIGALARA ROAD, KENGERI VILLAGE<lb/> KENGERI HOBLI, BANGALORE -59.<lb/> . SMT. MANJULA<lb/> D/O LATE YALLAPPA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 48 YEARS<lb/> BEHING YELLAMMA TEMPLE<lb/> TIGALARA ROAD, KENGERI VILLAGE<lb/> KENGERI HOBLI, BANGALORE -59.<lb/> . SMT. ANUSOOYA<lb/> D/O LATE YALLAPPA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 46 YEARS<lb/> BEHING YELLAMMA TEMPLE<lb/> TIGALARA ROAD, KENGERI VILLAGE<lb/> KENGERI HOBLI, BANGALORE -59.<lb/> . RAJAPPA<lb/> S/O LATE YALLAPPA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 46 YEARS<lb/> BEHING YELLAMMA TEMPLE<lb/> TIGALARA ROAD, KENGERI VILLAGE<lb/> KENGERI HOBLI, BANGALORE -59.<lb/> . SRI. MUNIKRISHNA<lb/> S/O LATE YALLAPPA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 46 YEARS<lb/> BEHING YELLAMMA TEMPLE<lb/> TIGALARA ROAD, KENGERI VILLAGE,<lb/> KENGERI HOBLI, BANGALORE -59.<lb/> . SMT. SANJEEVAMMA<lb/> D/O LATE YALLAPPA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 46 YEARS<lb/> BEHING YELLAMMA TEMPLE<lb/> TIGALARA ROAD, KENGERI VILLAGE,<lb/> KENGERI HOBLI, BANGALORE -59. 14<lb/> 29 . SRI. K.V. VENKATARANGAIAH<lb/> S/O M. VENKATANARSIMHAIAH<lb/> AGED ABOUT 50 YEARS<lb/> DODDABELE VILLAGE<lb/> KENGERI HOBLI, BANGALORE -59.<lb/> 30 . SRI. P.K. CHANDRASHEKAR<lb/> S/O. P.V. KRISHNA MURTHY<lb/> AGED ABOUT 50 YEARS<lb/> NO.414, 2 ND STAGE,<lb/> INDIRANAGARA, BANGALORE -38.<lb/> 31 . SMT. SUJATHA<lb/> W/O LATE K.K. MAHADEVA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 50 YEARS<lb/> NO.4, NAGADEVANAHALLI<lb/> JNANABHARATHI POST<lb/> KENGERI UPANAGARA<lb/> BANGALORE -560 060.<lb/> 32 . SRI. H.B. JAYARAM<lb/> S/O LATE N. BORAIAH<lb/> AGED ABOUT 50 YEARS<lb/> NO.1519/2, 1 ST STAGE<lb/> 2 ND BLOCK, BANASHANKARI<lb/> BANGALORE -43.<lb/> 33 . C.S. VINAY KUMAR<lb/> AGED ABOUT 35 YEARS<lb/> NO.259, 7 TH MAIN<lb/> SARASHWATHINAGAR<lb/> BANGALORE -560 040.<lb/> 34 . SRI. K.V. VENUGOPAL<lb/> S/O VENKATANARASIMHAIAH<lb/> AGED ABOUT 50 YEARS<lb/> DODDABELE VILLAGE, KENGERI<lb/> HOBLI, BANGALORE -59. …RESPONDENTS<lb/> (BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI. V. SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H.C, HCGP FOR R-1; 15<lb/> SRI. K.N. PUTTEGOWDA, ADVOCATE FOR R-7;<lb/> SRI. H. SRIDHAR, ADVOCATE FOR R-30;<lb/> SRI. B.R. SATISH, ADVOCATE FOR R-33;<lb/> R-2, R-6, R-7 AND R-32 SERVED &amp; UNREPRESENTED<lb/> NOTICE DISPENSED WITH FOR R-3 TO R-5<lb/> R-8 TO R-29 &amp; R-31 &amp; R-34)<lb/> THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLE<lb/> 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA PRAYING TO<lb/> QUASH<lb/> THE<lb/> PROCEEDINGS<lb/> IN<lb/> CASE<lb/> NO.LGC(B)20/2017 ON THE FILE OF THE LAND<lb/> GRABBING, KANDAYA BHAVAN, BANGALORE, AS<lb/> AGAINST THE PETITIONERS HEREIN.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	IN W.P.NO.17180/2017:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>SRI. MUDDAVEERAPPA<lb/> S/O LATE MUDDAVEEREGOWDA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 82 YEARS<lb/> R/O BASAVESHWARANAGARA<lb/> 16 TH WARD, OLD SOAP FACTORY ROAD<lb/> KANAKAPURA TOWN<lb/> RAMANAGARA DISTRICT.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>... PETITIONER<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	(BY SRI. M.R. RAJAGOPAL, ADVOCATE)<lb/> AND:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>1.<lb/> THE STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> BY ITS SECRETARY<lb/> DEPARTMENT OF REVENUE<lb/> VIDHANA SOUDHA]<lb/> BENGALURU -560 001.<lb/> 2.<lb/> THE DEPUTY COMMISSIONER<lb/> RAMANAGARA DISTRICT<lb/> RAMANAGARA -571 511.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	3.<lb/> THE TAHSILDAR<lb/> KANAKAPURA TALUK 16<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>KANAKAPURA<lb/> RAMANAGARA DISTRICT -562 159.<lb/> 4.<lb/> SRI. BALE GOWDA<lb/> S/O LATE SHIVANE GOWDA<lb/> @GUNDE GOWDA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 57 TEARS<lb/> R/O CHIKKADEVARAHALLI<lb/> VILLAGE, T. HOSAHALLI POST<lb/> MARALAVADI HOBLI<lb/> KANAKAPURA TALUK<lb/> RAMANAGARA DISTRICT -562 117.<lb/> ... RESPONDENTS<lb/> (BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI. V. SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H.C, HCGP FOR R-1 TO R-3;<lb/> SRI. N. SUBBA SHASTRY, ADVOCATE FOR R-4)<lb/> THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA<lb/> PRAYING TO CALL FOR THE RECORDS FROM THE FILE<lb/> OF THE R-4 TAHSILDAR, KANAKAPURA TALUK,<lb/> KANAKAPURA IN RELATED TO THE LANDS BEARING SY.<lb/> NOS.28, 29 AND 31 OF KEERANAGERE VILLAGE,<lb/> MARALAVADI HOBLI, KANAKAPURA TALUK AND ALSO<lb/> THE RECORDS FROM THE FILE OF THE R-2 IN<lb/> RELATED TO CASE LGC(P) NO.34/2016 AND QUASH<lb/> THE ORDER DATED:23.02.2016 PASSED BY THE R-2<lb/> VIDE ANNEX-P.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	IN W.P. NO.21279/2017:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>SRI. OMKARA ASHRAMA<lb/> REPRESENTED BY ITS MANAGER<lb/> SRI. K. BHASKAR<lb/> SRINIVASPURA GRAMA<lb/> UTTARAHALLI MAIN ROAD<lb/> NEAR B.G.S. HOSPITAL<lb/> UTTARAHALLI HOBLI<lb/> BENGALURU -560 062.<lb/> ...PETITIONER 17<lb/> (BY SRI. SUNIL S RAO, ADVOCATE FOR<lb/> SRI. T. SESHAGIRI RAO, ADVOCATE)<lb/> AND:<lb/> 1 .<lb/> THE STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> REPRESENTED BY ITS<lb/> CHIEF SECRETARY<lb/> VIDHANA SOUDHA<lb/> BENGALURU -560 001.<lb/> 2 .<lb/> THE STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> DEPARTMENT OF REVENUE<lb/> REPRESENTED BY ITS SECRETARY<lb/> VIDHANA SOUDHA<lb/> BENGALURU -560 001.<lb/> 3 .<lb/> THE DEPUTY COMMISSIONER<lb/> BENGALURU URBAN DISTRICT<lb/> K.G. ROAD, BENGALURU -560 001.<lb/> 4 .<lb/> THE TAHSILDAR<lb/> BENGALURU SOUTH TALUK<lb/> KANDAYA BHAVAN BUILDING<lb/> K.G. ROAD, BENGALURU -560 001.<lb/> 5 .<lb/> THE REVENUE INSPECTOR<lb/> HEMMIGEPURA CIRCLE<lb/> KENGERI HOBLI<lb/> BENGALURU SOUTH TALUK.<lb/> 6 .<lb/> THE REGISTRAR<lb/> OFFICE OF THE SPECIAL COURT<lb/> FOR KARNATAKA LAND GRABBING<lb/> PROHIBITION, K.G. ROAD<lb/> BENGALURU -560 001. …RESPONDENTS<lb/> (BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI. V. SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H.C, HCGP)</titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	18<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA<lb/> PRAYING TO QUASH OF THE IMPUGNED ORDER DATED<lb/> 24.10.2016 IN CASE NO.LGC 17/2016 BY THE SPECIAL<lb/> COURT FOR KARNATAKA LAND GRABBING ACT, 2011<lb/> WHICH IS FOUND AT ANNEXURE-L TO THE W.P.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	IN W.P.NO.23095/2017:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>SRI. PRAKASHNATH<lb/> @SHEKARAPPA<lb/> S/O HONNEGOWDA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 50 YEARS<lb/> &quot;POOJARI ESTATE&quot;<lb/> SRINIVASAPURA CROSS<lb/> UTTARAHALLI MAIN ROAD<lb/> BANGALORE -560 060.<lb/> ...PETITIONER<lb/> (BY SRI. G. KRISHNAMURTHY, SR. COUNSEL FOR<lb/> MS. APARNA N, ADVOCATE)<lb/> AND:<lb/> 1 .<lb/> STATE BY SPECIAL PUBLIC PROSECUTOR<lb/> ATTACHED TO SPECIAL COUIRT FOR<lb/> LAND GRABBING PROHIBITION IN<lb/> KARNATAKA, 3RD FLOOR, KANDAYA<lb/> BHAVAN, K.G. ROAD<lb/> BENGALURU -560 001.<lb/> 2 .<lb/> SRI. HEMANTH RAJU<lb/> S/O MUNIRAJU<lb/> MAJOR<lb/> NO.32 ESHWARA TEMPLE ROAD<lb/> RAMOHALLI, KENGERI HOBLI<lb/> BANGALORE SOUTH TALUK<lb/> BENGALURU -560 074. …RESPONDENTS<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	(BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI. V. SREENIDHI, AGA AND 19<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>SMT. KAVITHA H.C, HCGP FOR R-1;<lb/> SRI. D. MALLIKARJUNA SWAMY,<lb/> ADVOCATE FOR R-12)<lb/> THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA READ<lb/> WITH SECTION 482 OF CODE OF CRIMINAL<lb/> PROCEDURE<lb/> 1973<lb/> PRAYING<lb/> TO<lb/> QUASH<lb/> THE<lb/> COMPLAINT NUMBERED AS LGC (P) 23/2017 DATED<lb/> 17.01.2017 VIDE ANNEX-A PENDING ON THE FILE OF<lb/> THE SPECIAL COURT KARNATAKA LAND GRABBING<lb/> AND PROHIBITION, KANDAYA BHAVAN, BANGALORE<lb/> AND CONSEQUENTLY QUASH THE ORDER DATED<lb/> 23.01.2017 VIDE ANNEX-B TAKING COGNIZANCE IN<lb/> LGC (P) 23/2017 UNDER SECTION 4 OF THE ACT AND<lb/> ENTIRE FURTHER PROCEEDINGS AGAINST THE<lb/> PETITIONER.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	IN W.P. NO.23800/2017:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>1 .<lb/> SMT UMA BALAGAVI<lb/> W/O MR. T.B. BALAGAVI<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	AGED ABOUT 55 YEARS<lb/> R/AT NO.120, MIG<lb/> K.H.B. COLONY<lb/> BASAVESHWARANAGAR<lb/> BENGALURU -560 079.<lb/> 2 .<lb/> SHRI. B.N. JAYARAM<lb/> S/O LATE NAGAPPA @<lb/> DODDANAGAPPA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 53 YEARS<lb/> R/AT BYRATHI VILLAGE<lb/> BIDARAHALLI HOBLI<lb/> BENGALURU EAST TALUK<lb/> BENGALURU -560 067.<lb/> ...PETITIONERS 20<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>(BY SRI. D.N. NANJUNDA REDDY, SR. COUNSEL FOR<lb/> SRI. PRAKASH T HEBBAR, ADVOCATE)<lb/> AND:<lb/> 1 .<lb/> STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> REVENUE DEPARTMENT<lb/> M.S. BUIDLING, 5TH FLOOR<lb/> DR. AMBEDKAR ROAD<lb/> BENGALURU -560 001<lb/> REPRESENTED BY ITS SECRETARY.<lb/> 2 .<lb/> SHRI. JUVANES C<lb/> S/O LATE Y. CHINNAPPA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 55 YEARS<lb/> R/AT A-1, 5TH FLOOR<lb/> SAI KRUPA APARTMENT<lb/> NEAR CHURCH<lb/> VISHWANATH NAGENAHALLI<lb/> BENGALURU -560 032.<lb/> 3 .<lb/> SHRI. B.A. BASAVARAJ<lb/> S/O ANJANAPPA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 48 YEARS<lb/> R/AT BYRATHI VILLAGE<lb/> BIDARAHALLI HOBLI<lb/> BENGALURU EAST TALUK<lb/> BENGALURU -560 067. …RESPONDENTS<lb/> (BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI. V. SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H.C, HCGP FOR R-1;<lb/> SRI. K. HANUMANTHRAYAPPA,<lb/> ADVOCATE FOR R-2;<lb/> R-3 SERVED AND )<lb/> THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA<lb/> PRAYING TO DECLARE THE KARNATAKA LAND<lb/> GRABBING PROHIBITION ACT 2011 (KARNATAKA ACT<lb/> 38/2014) AS ULTRA VIRES THE CONSTITUTION OF<lb/> INDIA BEING VIOLATIVE OF ARTICLES 14, 20, 21 AND<lb/> 300-A AND / OR IN THE ALTERNATIVE.</titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	21<lb/> IN W.P. NO.25219/2017:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>1 .<lb/> SMT. MOTAMMA<lb/> W/O VENKATARAMU<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	AGED ABOUT 66 YEARS.<lb/> 2 .<lb/> MR. GAUTHAM<lb/> S/O VENKATARAMU<lb/> AGED ABOUT 35 YEARS.<lb/> 3 .<lb/> MR. PREETHAM<lb/> S/O VENKATARAMU<lb/> AGED ABOUT 35 YEARS.<lb/> ALL THE PETITIONERS ARE<lb/> R/A D.NO.47, 4TH CROSS<lb/> 4TH MAIN, DOLLARS COLONY<lb/> MLA LAYOUT, RMV II STAGE<lb/> BANGALORE -560 094.<lb/> ...PETITIONERS<lb/> (BY SRI. SIDDHARTH B MUCHANDI, ADVOCATE)<lb/> AND:<lb/> 1 .<lb/> DEPUTY COMMISSIONER<lb/> CHIKKAMAGALURU DISTRICT<lb/> CHIKKAMAGALURU -577 101.<lb/> 2 .<lb/> ASSISTANT COMMISSIONER<lb/> CHIKKAMAGALURU DISTRICT<lb/> CHIKKAMAGALURU -577 101.<lb/> 3 .<lb/> TAHASILDHAR<lb/> MUDIGERE TALUK<lb/> CHIKKAMAGALURU -577 101. …RESPONDENTS<lb/> (BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI. V. SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H.C, HCGP) 22<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA PRAYING TO<lb/> QUASH THE ORDER DATED 14.03.2017 PASSED BY<lb/> THE KARNATAKA LAND GRABBING PROHIBITION<lb/> SPECIAL COURT AND ALL FURTHER PROCEEDINGS IN<lb/> LGC (S) 197/2017 VIDE ANNEX-A.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	IN W.P. NO.27437/2017:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>SHRI. MUNIRAJU<lb/> S/O LATE VENKATARAMANAPPA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 45 YEARS<lb/> R/AT SINGENA AGRAHARA VILLAGE<lb/> SARJAPURA HOBLI, ANEKAL TALUK<lb/> BENGALURU DISTRICT.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>...PETITIONER<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	(BY SRI. PRAKASH T HEBBAR, ADVOCATE)<lb/> AND:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>1 .<lb/> STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> REVENUE DEPARTMENT<lb/> M.S. BUILDING, 5TH FLOOR<lb/> DR. AMBEDKAR ROAD<lb/> BENGALURU -560 001<lb/> REPRESENTED BY ITS SECRETARY.<lb/> 2 .<lb/> THE TAHASILDAR<lb/> ANEKAL TALUK<lb/> TALUK OFFICE COMPOUND<lb/> ANEKAL, BENGALURU DISTRICT. …RESPONDENTS<lb/> (BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI. V. SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H.C, HCGP FOR R-1 &amp; R-2)<lb/> THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA 23<lb/> PRAYING TO DECLARE THAT THE KARNATAKA LAND<lb/> GRABBING PROHIBITION ACT 2011 (KARNATAKA ACT<lb/> 38 OF 2018) HAS NO APPLICATION TO THE FACTS AND<lb/> CIRCUMSTANCES OF THE PETITIONER&apos;S CASE IN CASE<lb/> LGC (S) NO.121/2016 BEFORE THE SPECIAL COURT<lb/> BENGALURU TILL APPLICATION IN FORM NO.523 IS<lb/> FINALLY DISPOSED OF AT ANNEX-B1.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	IN W.P. NO.27573/2017:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>1 .<lb/> MRS. ROSAMMA VARGHESE<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	W/O LATE T. VARGHESE VAREED<lb/> AGED ABOUT 80 YEARS.<lb/> 2 .<lb/> MR. GEORGE T VARGHESE<lb/> S/O LATE T VARGHESE VAREED<lb/> AGED ABOUT 59 YEARS.<lb/> BOTH ARE RESIDING AT<lb/> TEXLA FARMS, SURVEY NO.42/1<lb/> KANIMINIKE VILLAGE<lb/> KENGERI HOBLI<lb/> BENGALURU SOUTH TALUK<lb/> BENGALURU DISTRICT.<lb/> ...PETITIONERS<lb/> (BY SRI. KRISHNA B.R, ADVOCATE)<lb/> AND:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>1 .<lb/> THE STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> REVENUE DEPARTMENT<lb/> M.S. BUILDING, 5TH FLOOR<lb/> DR. AMBEDKAR ROAD<lb/> BENGALURU -560 001<lb/> REPRESENTED BY ITS<lb/> PRINCIPAL SECRETARY.<lb/> 2 .<lb/> THE THASILDAR<lb/> BENGALURU SOUTH TALUK<lb/> KANDAYA BHAVANA<lb/> K.G. ROAD, BENGALURU -560 001. …RESPONDENTS 24<lb/> (BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI. V. SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H.C, HCGP)<lb/> THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA<lb/> PRAYING TO DECLARE THE KARNATAKA LAND<lb/> GRABBING (PROHIBITION) ACT 2011 (KARNATAKA ACT<lb/> 30 OF 2014) AS ULTRA VIRUS TO THE CONSTITUTION<lb/> OF INDIA BEING VIOLATIVE OF ARTICLES 14, 20, 21<lb/> AND 300-A AND /OR IN THE ALTERNATIVE.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	IN W.P. NO.32134/2017:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>1 .<lb/> SRI. G.H. NAGARAJ<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	S/O LATE G. HANUMANTEGOWDA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 66 YEARS.<lb/> 2 .<lb/> SMT. HEMAVATI<lb/> W/O G.H. NAGARAJ<lb/> AGED ABOUT 57 YEARS.<lb/> 3 .<lb/> SMT. N. TEJASWINI @ JYOTHI<lb/> D/O G.H. NAGARAJ<lb/> AGED ABOUT 35 YEARS.<lb/> 4 .<lb/> SRI. VINAY @ SHAM<lb/> S/O G.H. NAGARAJ<lb/> AGED ABOUT 30 YEARS.<lb/>
	<div type="abstract">ALL (1TO 4) ARE RESIDENT OF<lb/> WARD NO.4, &apos;MATHRU NILYA&apos;<lb/> PRASHANTH NAGAR<lb/> CHICKBALLAPURA -562 101.<lb/> ...PETITIONERS<lb/></div>

	(BY SRI. R. DEVHADAS, SR. COUNSEL FOR<lb/> SRI. M. VEERABHADRAIAH, ADVOCATE) 25<lb/> AND:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>1 .<lb/> STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> REP. BY THE PRINCIPAL SECRETRY<lb/> DEPARTMENT OF REVENUE<lb/> M.S. BUILDING, 5TH FLOOR<lb/> DR. AMBEDKAR ROAD<lb/> BENGALURU -560 001.<lb/> 2 .<lb/> THE DEPUTY COMMISSIONER<lb/> &amp; DISTRICT MAGISTRATE<lb/> CHICKBALLAPURA DISTRICT<lb/> REVENUE BHAVAN<lb/> CHICKBALLAPURA TOWN<lb/> CHICKBALLAPURA -562 101.<lb/> 3 .<lb/> THE TAHASILDAR<lb/> CHICKBALLAPURA TALUK<lb/> REVENUE BHAVAN<lb/> CHICKBALLAPURA TOWN<lb/> CHICKBALLAPURA -562 101.<lb/> 4 .<lb/> THE COMMISSIONER<lb/> THE CHICKBALLAPURA MUNICIPAL<lb/> COUNCIL, CHICKBALLAPURA TOWN<lb/> CHICKBALLAPURA -562 101.<lb/> 5 .<lb/> SRI. AMEER MOHAMMED SADIQ<lb/> S/O LATE K AMMERJAN<lb/> AGED ABOUT 58 YEARS<lb/> DINNEHOSAHALLI ROAD<lb/> IDSMT LAYOUT, WARD NO.6<lb/> CHICKBALLAPURA -562 101.<lb/> 6 .<lb/> SRI. H. SRIRAM<lb/> S/O HANUMANTHAPPA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 55 YEARS<lb/> EX-MUNICIPAL PRESIDENT<lb/> WARD NO.30, CHAMARAJPET<lb/> SIDLAGATTA ROAD<lb/> CHICKBALLAPURA -562 101. 26<lb/> 7 .<lb/> SRI. RAVICHANDRA KUMAR<lb/> S/O LATE KRISHNAPPA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 45 YEARS<lb/> WARD NO.29, CHAMARAJPET<lb/> SIDLAGATTA ROAD<lb/> CHICKBALLAPURA -562 101. …RESPONDENTS<lb/> (BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI. V. SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H.C, HCGP FOR R-1 TO R-3;<lb/> SMT. PUSHPALATHA, ADVOCATE FOR R-4;<lb/> SRI. MANU KULKARNI, ADVOCATE A/W<lb/> SMT. SRUSHTI VIJ, ADVOCATE FOR R-5 TO R-7)<lb/> THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA<lb/> PRAYING TO DECLARE THAT KARNATAKA LAND<lb/> GRABBING PROHIBITION ACT, 2011 (KARNATAKA ACT,<lb/> 38/2014 AS ULTRA VIRES OF THE CONSTITUTION OF<lb/> INDIA BEING VIOLATIVE OF ARTICLES 14, 20, 21 &amp; 300-<lb/>A AS PER ANNEXURE-A.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	IN W.P. NO.32849/2017:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>1 .<lb/> DR. SITARAM SHETTY<lb/> AGED ABOOUT 60 YEARS<lb/> S/O LATE CHARMAKKI NARAYANA SHETTY<lb/> R/AT 4/10, MILLERS ROAD<lb/> OPPOSITE VIKRAM HOSPITRAL<lb/> BENGALURU -560 001.<lb/> 2 .<lb/> SUMITRA R SHETTY<lb/> AGED ABOUT 61 YEARS<lb/> DAUGHTER OF LATE CHARMAKKI<lb/> NARAYANA SHETTY<lb/> RESIDING AT 65, LAVELLE ROAD<lb/> 4TH CROSS, BENGALURU -560 001.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>...PETITIONERS<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	(BY SRI. SHRISHAIL NAVALGUND, ADVOCATE) 27<lb/> AND:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>1 .<lb/> STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> THROUGH ITS CHIEF SECRETARY<lb/> VIDHANA SOUDHA<lb/> AMBEDKAR VEEDHI<lb/> BENGALURU -560 001.<lb/> 2 .<lb/> DEPUTY CONSERVATOR OF<lb/> FORESTS, KOPPA DIVISION<lb/> CHIKKAMAGALURU -577 101. …RESPONDENTS<lb/> (BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI. V. SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H.C, HCGP FOR R-1 &amp; R-2)<lb/> THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLE<lb/> 226 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA, 1950 PRAYING<lb/> TO STRIKE DOWN THE KARNATAKA LAND GRABBING<lb/> PROHIBITION ACT, 2011 (KARNATAKA ACT NO.38 OF<lb/> 2014) ANNEXURE-A AS BEING VIOLATIVE OF ARTICLES<lb/> 14 (EQUALITY BEFORE LAW) 20 (PROTECTION IN<lb/> RESPECT OF CONVICTION FOR OFFENCES) AND 21<lb/> (PROTECTION OF LIFE AND PERSONAL OF LIBERTY) OF<lb/> THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA, 1950 AND/OR AS BEING<lb/> OUTSIDE THE COMPETENCE OF THE LEGISLATURE OF<lb/> THE STATE OF KARNATAKA.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	IN W.P. NO.33085/2017:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>SRI. A.C. ANANTHA SWAMY<lb/> AGED ABOUT 75 YEARS<lb/> S/O LATE PATEL CHIKKAHANUMAIAH<lb/> RESIDING AT AVALAHALLI,<lb/> KENGERI HOBLI<lb/> BANGALORE SOUTH TALUK<lb/> BENGALURU -560 026.<lb/> ...PETITIONER<lb/> (BY SRI. BHADRINATH R, ADVOCATE) 28<lb/> AND:<lb/> 1 .<lb/> THE STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> REPESENTED BY ITS SECRETARY<lb/> REVENUE DEPARTMENT<lb/> M.S. BUILDING, VIDHANA SOUDHA<lb/> DR. AMBEDKAR VEEDHI<lb/> BENGALURU -560 001.<lb/> 2 .<lb/> THE TAHASILDAR<lb/> BENGALURU SOUTH TALUK<lb/> BENGALURU -560 009. …RESPONDENTS<lb/> (BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI. V. SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H.C, HCGP)<lb/> THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA<lb/> PRAYING TO QUASH THE PROCEEDINGS PENDING ON<lb/> THE FILE OF THE HON&apos;BLE SPECIAL COURT FOR<lb/> PROHIBITION OF LAND GRABBING, KANDAYA BHAVAN,<lb/> BANGALORE, AS AGAINST THE PETITIONER VIDE<lb/> ANNEX-S.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	IN W.P. NO.34202/2017:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>DR. B. RAMANA RAO<lb/> S/O LATE B.S. RAMA RAO<lb/> AGED ABOUT 65 YEARS<lb/> NO.94/H, 9TH CROSS<lb/> 13TH MAIN, RAJMAHAL VILAS<lb/> EXTENSION, BENGALURU -560 080.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>...PETITIONER<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	(BY SRI. S.G. BHAGAVAN, ADVOCATE) 29<lb/> AND:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>1 .<lb/> THE STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> BY THE PRINCIPAL SECRETARY<lb/> DEPARTMENT OF REVENUE<lb/> M.S. BUILDING, DR. AMBEDKAR ROAD<lb/> BENGALURU -560 001.<lb/> 2 .<lb/> NARAYANASWAMY<lb/> S/O LATE HANUMANTHAIAH<lb/> R/O NO.MARUTHI NAGARA<lb/> NEAR ANJINEYA SWAMY TEMPLE<lb/> MADANAYAKANAHALLI -560 042<lb/> BENGALURU NORTH TALUK. …RESPONDENTS<lb/> (BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI. V. SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H.C, HCGP FOR R-1;<lb/> SRI. CHOKKA REDDY, ADVOCATE FOR R-2)<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<note type="funding">THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA<lb/> PRAYING TO QUASH THE KARNATAKA LAND GRABBING<lb/> PROHIBITION ACT, 2011, THE ACT. AND QUASH THE<lb/> PROCEEDINGS IN L.G.C. (P) NO.234 OF 2017 IN<lb/> KARNATAKA LAND GRABBING, SPECIAL COURT,<lb/> KANDAYA BHAVANA, THE SPECIAL COURT, KANDAYA<lb/> BHAVAN, THE SPECIAL COURT&apos; DATED 03.04.2017 AS<lb/> PER ANNEX-D IN SO FAR AS THE PETITIONER IS<lb/> CONCERNED AND TO AWARD COSTS OF THE PETITION.<lb/></note>

	IN W.P. NO.35384/2017:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>MR. IRFAN RAZACK<lb/> S/O LATE SRI. S. RAZACK<lb/> AGED ABOUT 63 YEARS<lb/> MANAGING DIRECTOR OF<lb/> M/S PRESTIGE ESTATES 30<lb/> PROJECTS LTD.,<lb/> OFFICE AT: THE FALCON HOUSE<lb/> NO.1, MAIN GUARD CROSS ROAD<lb/> BANGALORE -560 001.<lb/> ...PETITIONER<lb/> (BY SRI. UDAY HOLLA, SR. COUNSEL FOR<lb/> SRI. MOHUMED SADIQ B.A, ADVOATE)<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	AND:<lb/>
	<note type="copyright">1 .<lb/> THE STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> VIDHANA SOUDHA<lb/> REVENUE DEPARTMENT<lb/> BANGALORE, REPRESENTED BY ITS<lb/> SECRETARY.<lb/></note>

	2 .<lb/> DEPUTY COMMISSIONER<lb/> BANGALORE NORTH TALUK<lb/> KANDAYA BHAVAN<lb/> K.G. ROAD, BANGALORE -560 009.<lb/> 3 .<lb/> THE ASSISTANT COMMISSIONER<lb/> BANGALORE NORTH TALUK<lb/> KANDAYA BHAVAN<lb/> K.G. ROAD, BANGALORE -560 009.<lb/> 4 .<lb/> THE TAHSILDAR<lb/> BANGALORE NORTH TALUK<lb/> MINIVIDHANA SOUDHA<lb/> BANGALORE-560 064. …RESPONDENTS<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>(BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI. V. SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H.C, HCGP)<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<note type="funding">THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA<lb/> PRAYING TO DECLARE THAT THE KARNATAKA LAND<lb/> GRABBING PROHIBITION ACT, 2011 (PUBLISHED IN<lb/> THE OFFICIAL GAZETTE ON 09.10.2014) IS ILLEGAL<lb/> AND ULTRA VIRES THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA 31<lb/></note>

	(ANNEXURE-A) AND CONSEQUENTLY STRIKE DOWN<lb/>
	<byline>
	<affiliation>THE KARNATAKA LAND GRABBING PROHIBITION ACT,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>2011.<lb/></address>

	IN W.P. NO.36324/2017:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<reference>SMT. V. KRISHNAMMA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 61 YEARS<lb/> W/O LATE GOVINDARAJU<lb/> NO.7, MARAPPA THOTA<lb/> 2ND CROSS, P.G. ROAD<lb/> J.C. NAGAR, BANGALORE -560 006.<lb/> ...PETITIONER<lb/> (BY SRI. NARAYANA SWAMY P.M, ADVOCATE)<lb/></reference>

	AND:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>1 .<lb/> THE STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> REVENUE DEPARTMENT<lb/> M.S. BUILDING, 5TH FLOOR<lb/> DR. AMBEDKAR ROAD<lb/> BENGALURU -560 001<lb/> REP BY ITS SECRETARY.<lb/> 2 .<lb/> THE COMMISSIONER<lb/> BRUHATH BANGALORE MAHANAGARA<lb/> PALIKE, J.C. ROAD<lb/> BANGALORE -560 002.<lb/> 3 .<lb/> THE CHIEF ENGINEER<lb/> BRUHATH BANGALORE MAHANAGARA<lb/> PALIKE, 9TH FLOOR<lb/> JAYANAGAR COMMERCIAL COMPLEX<lb/> JAYANAGAR, BANGALORE -560 011. …RESPONDENTS<lb/> (BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI. V. SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H.C, HCGP FOR R-1;<lb/> SRI. KEMPANNA, ADVOCATE FOR R-2 &amp; R-3) 32<lb/> THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA<lb/> PRAYING TO DECLARE THE KARNATAKA LAND<lb/> GRABBING PROHIBITION ACT 2011 (KARNATAKA ACT<lb/> 38/2014) AS ULTRA VIRUS THE CONSTITUTION OF<lb/> INIDA BEING VOLATILE OF THE ARTICLES 14, 20, 21<lb/> AND 300-A AND OR IN THE ALTERNATIVE.<lb/> IN W.P. NO.36610/2017:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/> 1 .<lb/> SRI. S. SOMASHEKARA REDDY<lb/> AGED ABOUT 58 YEARS<lb/> PRESIDENT<lb/> BENGALURU AIRPORT CITY<lb/> LIONS SERVICE TRUST<lb/> MUNNEKOLALU VILLAGE<lb/> MARATHALLI POST<lb/> BENGALURU -560 037.<lb/> 2 .<lb/> SRI. LINGA REDDY K<lb/> AGED ABOUT 58 YEARS<lb/> VICE PRESIDENT<lb/> BENGALURU AIRPORT CITY LIONS<lb/> SERVICE TRUST, MUNNEKOLALU<lb/> VILLAGE MARATHALLI POST<lb/> BENGALURU -560 037.<lb/> 3 .<lb/> SRI. KRISHNA REDDY G<lb/> AGED ABOUT 47 YEARS<lb/> TREASURER<lb/> BENGALURU AIRPORT CITY LIONS<lb/> SERVICE TRUST, MUNNEKOLALU<lb/> VILLAGE MARATHALLI POST<lb/> BENGALURU -560 037.<lb/> ...PETITIONERS<lb/> (BY SRI. HARISH H.V, ADVOCATE)<lb/> AND:<lb/> 1 .<lb/> STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> REPRESENTED BY CHIEF SECRETARY<lb/> VIDHANA SOUDHA 33<lb/> VIDHANA VEEDHI ROAD<lb/> BENGALURU -560 001.<lb/> 2 .<lb/> DEPARTMENT OF REVENUE<lb/> REPRESENTED BY ITS<lb/> PRINCIPAL SECRETARY<lb/> VIKAS SOUDHA<lb/> VIDHANA VEEDHI ROAD<lb/> BENGALURU -560 001. …RESPONDENTS<lb/> (BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI. V. SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H.C, HCGP)<lb/> THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA<lb/> PRAYING TO QUASH THE ENTIRE SUO-MOTU<lb/> PROCEEDINGS IN LGC (S) 238/2016 ON THE FILE OF<lb/> KARNATAKA LAND GRABBING PROHIBITION SPECIAL<lb/> COURT AT BENGALURU AT ANNEX-A AS ULTRA VIRUS<lb/> THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	IN W.P. NO.36640/2017:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>SRI. S. ANNEYAPPA<lb/> S/O LATE SONNELLAPPA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 75 YEARS<lb/> R/AT THIGALACHOWDADENAHALLI<lb/> VILLAGE, SARJAPURA HOBLI<lb/> ANEKAL TLAUK -562 125.<lb/> ...PETITIONER<lb/> (BY SRI. KUMAR J.C, ADVOCATE)<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	AND:<lb/>
	<email>1 .<lb/></email>

	STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> REVENUE DEPARTMENT<lb/> M.S. BUILDING<lb/> 5TH FLOOR, DR. AMBEDKAR ROAD 34<lb/> BENGALURU -560 001<lb/> REP BY ITS PRINCIPAL SECRETARY.<lb/> 2 .<lb/> THE TAHSILDAR<lb/> ANEKAL TALUK, ANEKAL<lb/> BENGALURU DISTRICT -562 106. …RESPONDENTS<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>(BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI. V. SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H.C, HCGP)<lb/> THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA<lb/> PRAYING TO DECLARE THE KARNATAKA LAND<lb/> GRABBING PROHIBITION ACT, 2011 (KARNATAKA ACT<lb/> 38/2014) AS ULTRA VIRES THE CONSTITUTION OF<lb/> INDIA BEING VIOLATIVE OF ARTICLES 14, 20, 21 AND<lb/> 300-A.<lb/> IN W.P. NO.36690/2017:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/> 1 .<lb/> RATHEESH NAMBIAR<lb/> S/O LATE C.R. NAMBIAR<lb/> AGED ABOUT 42 YEARS<lb/> R/AT NO./RFA A64<lb/> PURAVA RIVER, MARTHAHALLI<lb/> BANGALORE -560 037.<lb/> 2 .<lb/> VISHWANATH REDDY<lb/> S/O LATE NARAYANA REDDY<lb/> AGED ABOUT 61 YEARS<lb/> R/AT NAZRAYANAGHATTA VILLAGE<lb/> SARJAPURA HOBLI, ANEKAL TALUK<lb/> BANGALORE -562 106.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>3 .<lb/> N.K. HARISH<lb/> S/O LATE N KRISHNA REDDY<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	AGED ABOUT 49 YEARS<lb/> NARAYANAGHATTA VILLAGE 35<lb/> SARJAPURA HOBLI, ANEKAL TALUK<lb/> BANGALORE -562 106.<lb/> 4 .<lb/> K. SRINIVAS REDDY<lb/> S/O LATE N. KRISHNA REDDY<lb/> AGED ABOUT 44 YEARS<lb/> NARAYANAGHATTA VILLAGE<lb/> SARJAPURA HOBLI, ANEKAL TALUK<lb/> BANGALORE -562 106.<lb/> ...PETITIONERS<lb/> (BY SRI. D.R. RAVISHANKAR, ADVOCATE)<lb/> AND:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>1 .<lb/> STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> BY LAW AND PARLIMENTARY AFFAIRS<lb/> VIDHANA SOUDHA<lb/> BANGALORE -560 001<lb/> REP BY CHIEF SECRETARY.<lb/> 2 .<lb/> STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> BY SECRETARY TO GOVT.,<lb/> DEPARTMENT OF REVENUE<lb/> M.S. BUILDING<lb/> BANGALORE -560 001.<lb/> 3 .<lb/> TAHSILDAR<lb/> ANEKAL TALUK<lb/> BANGALORE SOUTH DIVISION<lb/> BANGALORE -562 106. …RESPONDENTS<lb/> (BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI. V. SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H.C, HCGP)<lb/> THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA<lb/> PRAYING TO DECLARE THE KARNATAKA LAND<lb/> GRABBING PROHIBITION ACT 2011 (KARNATAKA ACT<lb/> 38 OF 2014) ANNEX-C) AS ULTRA VIRES THE<lb/> CONSTITUTION OF INDIA BEING VIOLATIVE OF 36<lb/> ARTICLES 14, 20, 21 AND 300-A AND/OR IN THE<lb/> ALTERNATIVE.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	IN W.P. NO.36760/2017:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>SRI. ARUACHALAM<lb/> S/O LATE SRI. RANGASWAMY MUDALIAR<lb/> AGED ABOUT 62 YEARS<lb/> CHAIRMAN<lb/> M/S SHAKTHI HILL RESORTS<lb/> PRIVATE LIMITED, HAVING ITS<lb/> OFFICE AT BEML LAYOUT<lb/> RAJARAJESWARINAGAR<lb/> BENGALURU -560 039.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>...PETITIONER<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	(BY SRI. J.M. RAJANNA SETTY, ADVOCATE)<lb/> AND:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>1 .<lb/> THE STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> REPRESENTED BY ITS<lb/> HOME DEPARTMENT<lb/> HOME COMMISSIONER<lb/> M.S. BUILDING<lb/> BENGALURU -560 001.<lb/> 2 .<lb/> B.M.T.F. POLICE STATION<lb/> CORPORATION BUILDING<lb/> J.C. ROAD, BENGALURU -560 002<lb/> REPRESENTED BY<lb/> THE DEPUTY SUPERINTENDENT<lb/> OF POLICE. …RESPONDENTS<lb/> (BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI. V. SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H.C, HCGP) 37<lb/> THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA<lb/> PRAYING TO QUASH THE IMPUGNED NOTICE AT<lb/> ANNEX-C DATED 24.07.2017 ISSUED BY THE<lb/> KARNATAKA LAND GRABBING PROHIBITION SPECIAL<lb/> COURT AS DEVOID OF THE AUTHORITY OF LAW.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	IN W.P. NO.37713/2017:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>SMT. SUMITHRA<lb/> W/O G.T. VENKATESH<lb/> AGED ABOUT 37 YEARS<lb/> KASABA HOBLI, RURAL GUDIBANDE<lb/> &amp; GUDIBANDE TALUK<lb/> CHIKKABALLAPURA -561 207.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>...PETITIONER<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	(BY SRI. M. SHIVAPRAKASH, ADVOCATE)<lb/> AND:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>1 .<lb/> PRINCIPAL SECRETARY<lb/> DEPARTMENT OF REVENUE<lb/> STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> VIDHANA SOUDHA<lb/> BANGALORE -560 001.<lb/> 2 .<lb/> THE KARNATAKA LAND GRABBING<lb/> PROHIBITION SPECIAL COURT<lb/> KANDAYA BHAVAN, K.G. ROAD<lb/> BANGALORE -560 001<lb/> REPRESENT BY REGISTER.<lb/> 3 .<lb/> THE DEPUTY COMMISSIONER<lb/> GOVERNMENT OF KARNATAKA<lb/> CHIKKABALLAPURA DISTRICT<lb/> CHIKKABALLAPURA -561 207.<lb/> 4 .<lb/> THE ASSISTANT COMMISIONER<lb/> GOVERNMENT OF KARNATAKA<lb/> CHIKKABALLAPURA SUB DIVISION<lb/> CHIKKABALLAPURA -561 207 38<lb/> 5 .<lb/> THE TAHSILDAR<lb/> GUDIBANDE TALUK OFFICE<lb/> GUDIBANDE TALUK<lb/> GUDIBANDE, CHIKKABALLAPURA<lb/> DISTRICT -561 207.<lb/> 6 .<lb/> SRI. NANJAPPA<lb/> S/O VENKATARANAPPA<lb/> TAHSILDAR, GUDIBANDE TALUK<lb/> CHIKKABALLAPURA -561 207.<lb/> 7 .<lb/> MAHAMMED ELIYAS<lb/> S/O LATE SHAIK FAKRUDDIN<lb/> R/AT UPPARAHALLI VILLAGE<lb/> KASABA HOBLI, GUDIBANDE TALUK<lb/> CHIKKABALLAPURA -561 207. …RESPONDENTS<lb/> (BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI. V. SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H.C, HCGP R-1 TO R-5;<lb/> SRI. CHETHAN KUMAR H, ADVOCATE FOR R-6;<lb/> SRI. SHARATH S GOWDA, ADVOCATE FOR R-7)<lb/> THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA<lb/> PRAYING TO QUASH THE IMPUGNED ORDER PASSED<lb/> DATED 01.08.2017 BY THE R-2 AT ANNEXURE-M AND<lb/> QUASH THE IMPUGNED ORDER PASSED DATED<lb/> 20.022017 AT ANNEXURE-J PASSED BY THE R-4 AND<lb/> CONSEQUENTLY TO DIRECT HT ER-3 TO ADJUDICATE<lb/> AND<lb/> CONCLUDE<lb/> THE<lb/> PROCEEDINGS<lb/> IN<lb/> R.A.NO.25/2015-16 ON MERITS.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	IN W.P. NO.40597/2017:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>NARAYANA MURTHY<lb/> MANAGING TRUSTEE OF HANUMAGIRI<lb/> PRIVATE TRUST, RESIDING AT # 81<lb/> BALAJI NILAYA, 4TH MAIN 39<lb/> POORNA PRAJNA NAGAR<lb/> 5TH STAGE, BASK BANGALORE -560 061.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>...PETITIONER<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	(BY SRI. AJIT P.B, ADVOCATE)<lb/> AND:<lb/>
	<email>1 .<lb/></email>

	<note type="funding">THE STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> REPRESENTED BY THE<lb/> REVENUE DEPARTMENT<lb/> M.S. BUILDING, 5TH FLOOR<lb/> DR. AMBEDKAR ROAD<lb/> BANGALORE -560 001<lb/> REPRESENTED BY ITS<lb/> PRINCIPAL SECRETARY.<lb/> 2 .<lb/> THE TAHSILDAR<lb/> BANGALORE SOUTH TALUK<lb/> KANDAYA BHAVAN<lb/> BANGALORE -560 001. …RESPONDENTS<lb/> (BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI. V. SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H.C, HCGP)<lb/> THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA<lb/> PRAYING TO DECLARE THAT THE KARNATAKA LAND<lb/> GRABBING PROHIBITION ACT, 2011 (KARNATAKA ACT<lb/> 38/2014) IS ULTRA VIRES THE CONSTITUTION OF<lb/> INDIA AS IT VIOLATES ARTICLES 14, 20, 21 AND 300-A<lb/> OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA.<lb/></note>

	IN W.P. NO.41593/2017:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>MR. IRFAN RAZACK<lb/> AGED ABOUT 63 YEARS<lb/> S/O LATE SRI. S. RAZAK<lb/> MANAGING DIRECTOR OF 40<lb/> M/S PRESTIGE ESTATES<lb/> PROJECTS LTD<lb/> A REGISTERED COMPANY REGISTERED<lb/> UNDER THE COMPANIES ACT 1956<lb/> OFFICE AT:THE FALCON HOUSE&quot;<lb/> NO.1, MAIN GUARD CROSS ROAD<lb/> BANGALORE -560 001.<lb/> ...PETITIONER<lb/> (BY SRI. UDAY HOLLA, SR. COUNSEL FOR<lb/> SRI. MOHUMED SADIQ B.A, ADVOCATE)<lb/> AND:<lb/> 1 .<lb/> THE STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> VIDHANA SOUDHA<lb/> REVENUE DEPARTMENT<lb/> BANGALORE -560 001<lb/> REPRESENTED BY ITS SECRETARY.<lb/> 2 .<lb/> DEPUTY COMMISSIONER<lb/> BANGALORE EAST TALUK<lb/> KANDAYA BHAVAN<lb/> K.G. ROAD, BANGALORE -560 009.<lb/> 3 .<lb/> THE ASSISTANT COMMISSIONER<lb/> BANGALOPRE EAST TALUK<lb/> KANDAYA BHAVAN<lb/> K.G. ROAD, BANGALORE -560 009.<lb/> 4 .<lb/> THE TAHSILDAR<lb/> BANGALORE EAST TALUK<lb/> K.R. PURAM, BANGALORE -560 036. …RESPONDENTS<lb/> (BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI. V. SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H.C, HCGP)<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<note type="funding">THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA<lb/> PRAYING TO DECLARE THAT THE KARNATAKA LAND<lb/> GRABBING ACT, 2011 (PUBLISHED IN THE OFFICIAL<lb/> GAZETTE ON 09.10.2014) IS ILLEGAL AND ULTRA VIRES<lb/> THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA (ANNEXURE-A) AND 41<lb/> CONSEQUENTLY STRIKE DOWN THE KARNATAKA LAND<lb/> GRABBING PROHIBITION ACT, 2011.<lb/></note>

	IN W.P. NO.42959/2017:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>1 .<lb/> M/S SRI. NAKODA CONSTRUCTION LTD<lb/> OFFICE AT NO.133/1<lb/> THE RESIDENCY 10TH FLOOR<lb/> RESIDENCY ROAD<lb/> BENGALURU -560 025<lb/> REPT. BY ITS DIRECTOR<lb/> SRI. MAHAVEER GULECHA<lb/> S/O TEJRAJ GULECHA.<lb/> 2 .<lb/> SRI. MAHAVEER GULECHA<lb/> S/O TEJRAJ GULECHAR<lb/> NO.40/A, CLASSIC ORCHARDS<lb/> BANNERGHATTA ROAD<lb/> BEHIND MEENAKSHI TEMPLE<lb/> KOTHANUR BENGALURU -560 076.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>...PETITIONERS<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	(BY SRI. B.S. RADHANANDAN, ADVOCATE)<lb/> AND:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>1 .<lb/> THE STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> REVENUE DEPARTMENT<lb/> M.S. BUILDING<lb/> BENGALURU -560 001<lb/> SECERTARY TO THE GOVERNMENT.<lb/> 2 .<lb/> STATE BY SPECIAL PUBLIC<lb/> PROSECUTOR, ATTACHED TO<lb/> SPECIAL COURT OF LAND<lb/> GRABBING PROHIBITION IN KARNATAKA. …RESPONDENTS<lb/> (BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI. V. SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H.C, HCGP) 42<lb/> THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA<lb/> PRAYING TO DECLARE THAT THE PROVISIONS OF THE<lb/> SECTION 9 OF THE KARNATAKA LAND GRABBING<lb/> PROHIBITION ACT, IS UNCONSTITUTIONAL AND ULTRA<lb/> VIRES THE ARTICLE 14, ARTICLE 19 AD ARTICLE 21<lb/> AND ARTICLE 300A OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	IN W.P. NO.43059/2017:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>SRI. BABU R<lb/> S/O RAMACHANDRAPPA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 39 YEARS<lb/> R/AT # 323, RAGHVANAPALYA<lb/> UTTARAPALYA HOBLI<lb/> BANGALORE SOUTH TALUK -560 078.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>...PETITIONER<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	(BY SRI. SURESH DESAI K, ADVOCATE)<lb/> AND:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>1 .<lb/> STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> REVENUE DEPARTMENT<lb/> M.S. BUILDING, 5TH FLOOR<lb/> DR.AMBEDKAR ROAD<lb/> BENGALURU -560 001<lb/> REPRESENTED BY ITS<lb/> PRINCIPAL SECRETARY.<lb/> 2 .<lb/> THE DEPUTY COMMISSIONER<lb/> BANGALORE URBAN DISTRICT<lb/> K.G.ROAD, BANGALORE -560 009.<lb/> 3 .<lb/> THE TAHSILDAR<lb/> BENGALURU SOUTH TALUK<lb/> BENGALURU<lb/> BENGALURU DISTRICT -560 009.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>4 .<lb/> N. NAGARAJ</docAuthor>
	</byline>

	43<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>S/O H NARAYANAPPA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 60 YEARS<lb/> R/AT VASANTHPURA<lb/> SUBRAMANYA PURA POST<lb/> BENGALURU -560 061. …RESPONDENTS<lb/> (BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI. V. SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H.C, HCGP FOR R-1 TO R-3;<lb/> SRI. ANIL KUMAR J, ADVOCATE FOR R-4)<lb/> THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA<lb/> PRAYING TO DECLARE THE KARNATAKA LAND<lb/> GRABBING PROHIBITION ACT, 2011 (KARNATAKA ACT<lb/> 38/2014) AS ULTRA VIRES THE CONSTITUTION OF<lb/> INDIA BEING VIOLATIVE OF ARTICLES 14, 20, 21 AND<lb/> 30-A AND OR/IN THE ALTERNATIVE.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	IN W.P. NO.43227/2017:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>M/S SALARPURIA ROPPY<lb/> REALTORS PVT LTD.,<lb/> A COMPANY INCORPORATED<lb/> UNDER THE COMPANIES ACT 1956<lb/> HAVING ITS REGISTERED OFFICE AT<lb/> # 3, 4TH FLOOR SALARPURIA WINDSOR<lb/> ULSOOR ROAD, BENGALURU<lb/> KARNATAKA -560 042<lb/> REPRESENTED BY ITS<lb/> AUTHORISED SIGNATORY<lb/> MR. ASHWIN SANCHETI.<lb/> ...PETITIONER<lb/> (BY SRI. BADRI VISHAL, ADVOCATE)<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	AND:<lb/>
	<email>1 .<lb/></email>

	<note type="funding">STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> REVENUE DEPARTMENT<lb/> M.S. BUILDING, 5TH FLOOR</note>

	44<lb/> DR. AMBEDKAR ROAD<lb/> BENGALURU -560 001<lb/> REPRESENTED BY ITS SECRETARY.<lb/> 2 .<lb/> TAHASILDAR<lb/> BANGALORE SOUTH TALUK<lb/> KANDAYA BHAVAN GROUND FLOOR<lb/> K.G. ROAD, BANGALORE -560 009. …RESPONDENTS<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>(BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI. V. SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H.C, HCGP)<lb/> THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA<lb/> PRAYING TO DECLARE THE KARNATKA LAND<lb/> GRABBING PROHIBITION ACT 2011 (KARNATAKA ACT<lb/> 38 OF 2014) AS ULTRA VIRES THE CONSTITUTION OF<lb/> INDIA BEING VIOLATIVE OF ARTICLES 14, 20, 21 AND<lb/> 300-A.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	IN W.P. NO.44273/2017:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/> 1 .<lb/> T.V. VENKATESH<lb/> S/O LATE THALLAM VISHWANATH<lb/> SKPT ROAD, C-BLOCK<lb/> Y.N. HOSAKOTE TOWN AND HOBLI<lb/> PAVAGADA TALUK<lb/> TUMKUR DISTRICT -572 141.<lb/> 2 .<lb/> N.S. MANJUNATHA<lb/> S/O LATE N.V. SHANKARATHNAM<lb/> SHETTY, R/AT C-BLOCK<lb/> Y.N. HOSAKOTE TOWN AND HOBLI<lb/> PAVAGADA TALUK<lb/> TUMKUR DISTRICT -572 141.<lb/> 3 .<lb/> N.R. ASHWATHKUMAR 45<lb/> S/O N.V. RAJAGOPA SHETTY<lb/> RESIDING AT Y.N. HOSAKOTE<lb/> PAVAGADA TALUK<lb/> TUMKUR DISTRICT -560 042.<lb/> ...PETITIONERS<lb/> (BY SRI. H SRINIVAS RAO, ADVOCATE)<lb/> AND:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>1 .<lb/> STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> REVENUE DEPARTMENT<lb/> M.S. BUILDING, 5TH FLOOR<lb/> DR. AMBEDKAR ROAD<lb/> BENGALURU -560 001<lb/> REPRESENTED BY ITS SECRETARY.<lb/> 2 .<lb/> SRI. KOTESHWARA TEMPLE SEVA<lb/> AND DEVELOPMENT TRUST (REGD)<lb/> Y.N. HOSAKOTE TOWN AND HOBLI<lb/> PAVAGADA TALUK, TUMKUR -572 141<lb/> REP. BY ITS PRESIDENT<lb/> H.P. BALARAM NAYAK. …RESPONDENTS<lb/> (BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI. V. SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H.C, HCGP FOR R-1;<lb/> SRI. R. NATARAJ, ADVOCATE FOR R-2)<lb/> THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA<lb/> PRAYING TO DECLARE THE KARNATKA LAND<lb/> GRABBING PROHIBITION ACT 2011 (KARNATAKA ACT<lb/> 38 OF 2014) AS ULTRA VIRES THE CONSTITUTION OF<lb/> INDIA BEING VIOLATIVE OF ARTICLES 14, 20, 21 AND<lb/> 300-A.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	IN W.P. NO.44687/2017:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<email>1 .<lb/></email>

	SRI. TEJRAJ GULECHA 46<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>S/O SRI. PUKARAJ<lb/> AGED ABOUT 62 YEARS<lb/> R/ATNO.40/A, CLASSICAL<lb/> ORCHARDS, BEHIND MEENAKSHI<lb/> TEMPLE, BANNERGHATTA ROAD<lb/> BENGALURU -560 076.<lb/> 2 .<lb/> SRI. REDDY VEERANNA<lb/> S/O LATE SANJEEVAPPA<lb/> R/AT 9/1, CLASIC COURT<lb/> RICHMOND ROAD<lb/> BENGALURU -560 025.<lb/> ..PETITIONERS<lb/> (BY SRI.: GANAPATHY BHAT VAJRALLI, ADVOCATE)<lb/> AND:<lb/> 1 .<lb/> THE STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> REVENUE DEPARTMENT<lb/> M.S. BUILDING, BENGALURU -560 001<lb/> REPRESENTED BY ITS SECRETARY.<lb/> 2 .<lb/> THE STATE BY SPECIAL PUBLIC<lb/> PROSECUTOR, ATTACHED TO SPECIAL<lb/> COURT OF LAND GRABBING<lb/> PROHIBITION IN KARNATAKA<lb/> BENGALURU -560 009.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	3 .<lb/> THE EXCUTIVE ENGINEER<lb/>
	<reference>B.B.M.P. BYTARAYANAPURA<lb/> YELAHANKA, BANGALORE -64<lb/> AMNEDED V.C.O. DATED 05.02.2018. …RESPONDENTS<lb/></reference>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>(BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI. V. SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H.C, HCGP)<lb/> THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA<lb/> PRAYING TO DECLARE THAT THE PROVISION OF<lb/> SECTION-9 OF THE KARNATAKA LAND GRABBING<lb/> PROHIBITION ACT IS UNCONSTITUTIONAL AND ULTRA 47<lb/> VIRUS THE ARTICLE 14, ARTICLE 19 AND ARTICLE 21<lb/> AND ARTICLE 3-A OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	IN W.P. NO.45114/2017:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>SMT. R. VASANTHAMMA<lb/> W/O K.P. REVANNA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 80 YEARS<lb/> BYCHENAHLLI VILLAGE<lb/> KUSHALANAGARA HOBLI<lb/> SOMAWARPETE TALUK<lb/> KODAGU DISTRICT -571 234.<lb/> ...PETITIONER<lb/> (BY SRI. T. SESHAGIRI RAO, ADVOCATE)<lb/> AND:<lb/> 1 .<lb/> THE STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> DEPARTMENT OF REVENUE<lb/> VIDHANA SOUDHA<lb/> BENGALURU -560 001<lb/> REP. BY ITS SECRETARY.<lb/> 2 .<lb/> THE DISTRICT COMMISSIONER<lb/> KODAGU DISTRICT<lb/> MADIKERI -571 234.<lb/> 3 .<lb/> THE TAHSILDAR<lb/> SOMARPETE TALUK<lb/> MADIKERI -571 234.<lb/> 4 .<lb/> THE CHIEF OFFICER<lb/> TOWN MUNICIPALITY<lb/> KUSHALANAGARA -571 234.<lb/> 5 .<lb/> MR. K.S. DEVAPPA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 70 YEARS<lb/> BYCHENAHALLI<lb/> KUSHALANAGARA -571 234.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>6 .<lb/> SRI. M.E. MOHIDDIN<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	AGED ABOUT 65 YEARS 48<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>VICE PRESIDENT<lb/> KARNATAKA STATE SCIENCE PARISHAT<lb/> KODAGU DISTRICT UNIT<lb/> KODAGU -571 234.<lb/> .<lb/> DR. B.S. RADHAKIRSHNA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 75 YEARS<lb/> RATHABEEDHI<lb/> KUSHALANAGARA -571 234.<lb/> .<lb/> SRI. K.C. GANAPATHI<lb/> AGED ABOUT 55 YEARS<lb/> KUSHALANAGARA-571 234<lb/> BYCHENAHALLI.<lb/> .<lb/> SRI. POUL D&apos;SOUZA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 55 YEARS<lb/> BYCHENAHALLI<lb/> KUSHALANAGAR -571 234.<lb/> . SRI. M.S. BIDDAPPA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 48 YEARS<lb/> BYCHENAHALLI<lb/> KUSHALANAGARA -571 234.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>. SMT. M.B. INDIRA<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	AGED ABOUT 50 YEARS<lb/> BYCHENAHALLI<lb/> KUSHALANAGARA -571 234.<lb/> . SRI. B.S. LOKESH SAGAR<lb/> AGED ABOUT 50 YEARS<lb/> BYCHENAHALLI<lb/> KUSHALANAGARA -571 234.<lb/> . SRI. BOPAIAH<lb/> AGED ABOUT 60 YEARS<lb/> KUSHALANAGARA -571 234.<lb/> . DR. MOTAIAH<lb/> AGED ABOUT 60 YEARS<lb/>
	<idno>BYCHENAHALLI<lb/> KUSHALANAGARA -571 234. 49<lb/></idno>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>15 . SRI. SHIVAKUMARA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 4 YEARS<lb/> BYCHENAHALLI<lb/> KUSHALANAGARA -571 234. …RESPONDENTS<lb/> (BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI. V. SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H.C, HCGP FOR R-1 TO R-3;<lb/> SRI. B.S. BASAVARAJU, ADVOCATE FOR R-6;<lb/> R-5, R-7, R-10 &amp; R-11, R-14 &amp; R-15 ARE SERVED<lb/> AND )<lb/> THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA<lb/> PRAYING TO QUASH THE IMPUGNED NOTICE/ORDER<lb/> DATED 16.08.2017 INITIATED BY THE KARNATAKA<lb/> LAND GRABBING PROHIBITION SPECIAL COURT,<lb/> BENGALURU VIDE ANNEX-A IN SO FAR AS THE<lb/> PETITIONER IS CONCERNED.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	IN W.P. NO.47887/2017:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>SMT. SMITHA UDAY KUMAR<lb/> W/O UDAY KUMAR<lb/> SMITHA VILAS<lb/> ALVAS HOSPITAL ROAD<lb/> MARPADY VILLAGE<lb/> MOODABIDRI -574 227.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>...PETITIONER<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	(BY SRI. DHANANJAY KUMAR, ADVOCATE)<lb/> AND:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>1 .<lb/> STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> REVENUE DEPARTMENT<lb/> MS BUILDING, 5TH FLOOR<lb/> DR.AMBEDKAR ROAD<lb/> BENGALURU -560 001<lb/> REPRESENTED BY ITS SECRETARY. 50<lb/> 2 .<lb/> TAHASILDAR<lb/> MOODABIDRI<lb/> MANGALORE TALUK<lb/> D.K. DISTRICT -574 227.<lb/> 3 .<lb/> SUB INSPECTOR OF POLICE<lb/> MOODABIDRI POLICE STATION<lb/> MANGALORE TALUK,<lb/> D.K. DISTRICT -574 227. …RESPONDENTS<lb/> (BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI. V. SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H.C, HCGP)<lb/> THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA<lb/> PRAYING TO DECLARE THE KARNATAKA LAND<lb/> GRABBING PROHIBITION ACT 2011 (KARNATAKA ACT<lb/> 38/2014) AS ULTRA -VIRES THE CONSTITUTION OF<lb/> INDIA BEING VIOLATIVE OF ARTICLES 14, 20, 21 AND<lb/> 300-A.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	IN W.P. NO.50674/2017:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>SMT. B.V. SHYLAJA<lb/> W/O N. NAGARAJU<lb/> AGED ABOUT 48 YEARS<lb/> R/AT NO.88, VASANTHAPURA<lb/> UTTARAHALLI HOBLI<lb/> SUBRAMANAYAPURA POST<lb/> BANGALORE -560 061.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>...PETITIONER<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	(BY SRI. V VISWANATH SETTY, ADVOCATE)<lb/> AND:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>1 .<lb/> STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> REVENUE DEPARTMENT 51<lb/> M.S. BUILDING, AMBEDKAR<lb/> VEEDHI, BANGALORE -560 001<lb/> REPRESENTED BY THE SECRETARY.<lb/> 2 .<lb/> SHRI. AJITH KUMAR R<lb/> S/O R.M. RAMACHANDRA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 34 YEARS<lb/> R/AT. NO.272, RAGHAVANAPALYA<lb/> J.P. NAGAR, 9TH PHASE<lb/> BENGALURU -560 083.<lb/> 3 .<lb/> SHRI. N. SRINIVASA<lb/> S/O NARAYANAPPA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 54 YEARS<lb/> R.AT NO.700, VASANTHAPURA<lb/> KALYANINAGAR UTTARAHALLI<lb/> HOBLI, SUBRAMANYAPURA<lb/> POST BANGALORE -560 061. …RESPONDENTS<lb/> (BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI. V. SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H.C, HCGP FOR R-1;<lb/> SRI. K. SURESH DESAI, ADVOCATE FOR R-2;<lb/> SRI. P. MAHADEVASWAMY, ADVOCATE FOR R-3)<lb/> THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA<lb/> PRAYING TO QUASH THE ORDER PASSED BY THE<lb/> KARNATAKA LAND GRABBING PROHIBITION SPECIAL<lb/> COURT, BANGALORE DATED 24.10.2017 BY TAKING<lb/> COGNIZANCE AGAINST THE PETITIONER AND R-3 FOR<lb/> THE ALLEGED OFFENCES PUNISHABLE UNDER<lb/> SECTION 4(3) OF KARNATAKA LAND GRABBING ACT,<lb/> 2011 ON THE BASIS OF FALSE COMPLAINT FILED BY<lb/> THE R-2 AGAINST THE PETITIONER AND THE R-2<lb/> UNDER SECTION 9(1) OF KARNATAKA LAND GRABBING<lb/> ACT, VIDE ANNEX-K. 52<lb/> IN W.P. NO.51160/2017:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/> 1 .<lb/> S.B. JAGADEESH<lb/> AGED ABOUT 52 YEARS<lb/> S/O BYREGOWDA<lb/> RESIDING AT RAMESHWARA<lb/> BADAVANE, CHANNARAYAPATNA<lb/> TOWN, CHANNARAYAPATNA TALUK<lb/> HASSAN DISTRICT-577 230.<lb/> 2 .<lb/> RATHNAMMA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 55 YEARS<lb/> W/O VENKATARAMU<lb/> R/AT RAMARISHNA LAYOUT<lb/> GANDHI CIRCLE<lb/> CHANNARAYAPATNA TALUK<lb/> HASSAN DISTRICT -577 230.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>3 .<lb/> H.K. VISHVESHWARA<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	AGED ABOUR<lb/> S/O KUMARASWAMY<lb/> R/AT H. HOSAHALLI VILLAGE<lb/> SHRAVANABELAGOLA HOBLI<lb/> CHANNARAYAPATNA TALUK<lb/> HASSAN DISTRICT -577 230.<lb/> ...PETITIONERS<lb/> (BY SRI. SAHUL HAMEED, ADVOCATE)<lb/> AND:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>1 .<lb/> STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> REVENUE DEPARTMENT<lb/> M.S. BUILDING, 5TH FLOOR<lb/> DR. AMBEDKAR ROAD<lb/> BENGALURU -560 001<lb/> REPRESENTED BY ITS SECRETARY.<lb/> 2 .<lb/> SHRI. RAMAMURTHY GOWDA<lb/> S/O HANUMANTHRAYAPPA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 47 YEARS 53<lb/> R/AT NO.98, 8TH MAIN ROAD<lb/> GYANAGANGANAGAR<lb/> ULLAL MAIN ROAD<lb/> BANGALORE -560 056. …RESPONDENTS<lb/> (BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI. V. SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H.C, HCGP FOR R-1;<lb/> SRI. C.R. GOPALSWAMY FOR R-2)<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<note type="funding">THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLE<lb/> 226 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA PRAYING TO<lb/> DECLARE<lb/> THE<lb/> KARNATAKA<lb/> LAND<lb/> GRABBING<lb/> PROHIBITION ACT 2011 (KARNATAKA ACT 38 OF 2014)<lb/> AS ULTRA VIRES THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA BEING<lb/> VIOLATIVE OF ARTICLES 14, 20 21 AND 300-1 AND/OR<lb/> IN THE ALTERNATIVE.<lb/> IN W.P. NO.52972/2017:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/> 1 .<lb/> BHANDARKAR&apos;S ARTS AND<lb/> SCIENCE COLLEGE , TRUST<lb/> SPONSORED BY THE ACADEMY<lb/> OF GENERAL EDUCATION<lb/> MANIPAL, SITUATED AT<lb/> KUNDAPUR -576 201<lb/> UDUPI DISTRICT, REP. BY ITS PRINCIPAL<lb/> SRI. N.P. NARAYANA SHETTY.<lb/> 2 .<lb/> THE ACADEMY OF GENERAL<lb/> EDUCATION, UNIVERSITY BUILDING<lb/> MADHAVANAGAR, MANIPAL -576 104<lb/> REP.</note>

	BY ITS ADMINISTRATIVE<lb/> OFFICER, DR. H. SHANTHARAM.<lb/> ...PETITIONERS<lb/> (BY SRI. N. RAVINDRANATH KAMATH, ADVOCATE)<lb/> AND:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>1 .<lb/> THE STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> REVENUE DEPARTMENT,<lb/> 5TH FLOOR, M.S.BUILDING,<lb/> DR.AMBEDKAR ROAD,<lb/> BENGALURU-01<lb/> REP BY ITS SECRETARY<lb/> 2 .<lb/> THE TAHSILDAR<lb/> KUNDAPUR TALUK<lb/> KUNDAPUR -576 201<lb/> UDUPI DISTRICT.<lb/> 3 .<lb/> THE ASSISTANT COMMISSIONER<lb/> KUNDAPUR -576 201<lb/> UDUPI DISTRICT.<lb/> 4 .<lb/> THE DEPUTY COMMISSIONER<lb/> UDUPI DISTRICT<lb/> MANIPAL -576 104<lb/> UDUPI DISTRICT.<lb/> 5 .<lb/> THE TOWN MUNICIPAL COUNCIL<lb/> KUNDAPUR -576 201<lb/> UDUPI DISTRICT<lb/> BY ITS CHIEF OFFICER.<lb/> 6 .<lb/> SR. GANESH SHETTY<lb/> FATHERS NAME NOT KNOWN<lb/> TO PETITIONERS<lb/> GADDEMANE, LIC ROAD<lb/> VADERA HOBLI VILLAGE<lb/> KUNDAPUR TALUK.<lb/> 7 .<lb/> SRI. SHARATHCHANDRA HEGDE<lb/> S/O LATE B. SADANANDA HEGDE<lb/> RESIDING AT SADANANDA<lb/> SATWADY, POST MOODLAKATTE<lb/> KUNDAPURA TALUK<lb/> UDUPI DISTRICT -576 217. …RESPONDENTS<lb/> (BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI. V. SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H.C, HCGP FOR R-1 TO R-4; 55<lb/> SRI. H. JAYAKAR SHETTY, ADVOCATE<lb/> FOR R-6 &amp; R-7; R-5 SERVED)<lb/> THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA<lb/> PRAYING TO DECLARE THE KARNATAKA LAND<lb/> GRABBING PROHIBITION ACT, 2011 (KARNATAKA ACT<lb/> 38/2014) AT ANNEX-C AS ULTRA VIRES THE<lb/> CONSTITUTION OF INDIA BEING VIOLATIOVE OF<lb/> ARTICLES 14, 2021 AND 300-A AND / OR IN THE<lb/> ALTERNATIVE.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	IN W.P. NO.53008/2017:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>SMT. SMITHA UDAY KUMAR<lb/> W/O UDAY KUMAR<lb/> SMITHA VILAS<lb/> ALVAS HOSPITAL ROAD<lb/> MARPADY VILLAGE<lb/> MOODABIDRI -574 227.<lb/> ...PETITIONER<lb/> (BY SRI. DHANANJAY KUMAR, ADVOCATE)<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	AND:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>1 .<lb/> STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> REVENUE DEPARTMENT<lb/> M.S. BUILDING, 5TH FLOOR<lb/> DR. AMBEDKAR ROAD<lb/> BENGALURU -560 001<lb/> REPRESENTED BY ITS SECRETARY.<lb/> 2 .<lb/> TAHASILDAR<lb/> MOODABIDRI<lb/> MANGALORE TALUK<lb/> D.K. DISTRICT -574 227. …RESPONDENTS<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	(BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI. V. SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H.C, HCGP) 56<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA<lb/> PRAYING TO DECLARE THE KARNATAKA LAND<lb/> GRABBING PROHIBITION ACT 2011 (KARNATAKA ACT<lb/> 38 OF 2014) AS ULTRA VIRES THE CONSTITUTION OF<lb/> INDIA BEING VIOLATIVE OF ARTICLES 14, 20, 21 AND<lb/> 300-A.<lb/> IN W.P. NO.54035/2017: BETWEEN<lb/> ARUN S<lb/> S/O. LATE SHRI. V. G. SURENDRAN<lb/> AGED ABOUT 53 YEARS<lb/> R/AT NO. 29, 2ND FLOOR<lb/> J.V.R. PLAZA, BELLARY MAIN<lb/> ROAD, HEBBAL, BENGALURU -24<lb/> MANAGING DIRECTOR<lb/> MONITO BUILDERS PVT. LTD.,<lb/> A REGISTERED PARTNERSHIP FIRM<lb/> HAVING ITS OFFICE AT NO.29<lb/> 2ND FLOOR, GVR PLAZ,<lb/> BELLARY MAIN ROAD<lb/> HEBBAL, BANGALORE -560 024.<lb/> ...PETITIONER<lb/> (BY SRI. K. SHASHIKIRAN SHETTY, SR. COUNSEL FOR<lb/> SMT. LATHA S SHETTY, ADVOCATE)<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	AND:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>1 .<lb/> THE STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> REPRESENTED BY ITS<lb/> CHIEF SECRETARY<lb/> REVENUE DEPARTMENT<lb/> M.S. BUILDING<lb/> BENGALURU -560 001.<lb/> 2 .<lb/> JOINT COMMISSIONER (NORTH)<lb/> TOWN PLANNING DEPARTMENT<lb/> BBMP, YALAHANKA ZONE<lb/> BANGALORE -560 092. 57<lb/> 3 .<lb/> ASSISTANT DIRECTOR<lb/> TOWN PLANNING DEPARTMENT<lb/> BBMP, YALAHANKA ZONE<lb/> BANGALORE -560 092.<lb/> 4 .<lb/> DEPUTY COMMISSIONER<lb/> BENGALURU URBAN DISTRICT<lb/> FOURTH FLOOR, DC OFFICE<lb/> BUILDING, REVENUE COMPLEX<lb/> K.G. ROAD, BANGALORE -560 009.<lb/> 5 .<lb/> EXECUTIVE ENGINEER<lb/> MAJOR RAIN WATER DRAIN<lb/> (YELAHANKA), BBMP YELAHANKA<lb/> ZONE, BANGALORE-560 092. …RESPONDENTS<lb/> (BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI. V. SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H.C, HCGP, FOR R-1 &amp; R-4;<lb/> SRI. ASHWIN S HALADY, ADVOCATE FOR R-2, 3 &amp; 5)<lb/> THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA<lb/> PRAYING TO DECLARE THAT THE PROVISIONS OF THE<lb/> KARNATAKA LAND GRABBING PROHIBITION ACT, IS<lb/> UNCONSTITUTIONAL AND ULTRA VIRES ARTICLE 14, 19<lb/> AND 21 AND 300-A OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA<lb/> (ANNEXURE-A).<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	IN W.P. NO.54081/2017:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>SRI. V.G. SIDDHARTHA<lb/> S/O SRI. S.V. GANGAIAH HEGDE<lb/> AGED ABOUT 57 YEARS<lb/> MANAGING PARTNER<lb/> &apos;SHABAN RAMZAN&apos;<lb/> HALASUR ESTATE NR PURA TALUK 58<lb/> CHIKMAGALUR DISTRICT<lb/> CHIKMAGALUR -577 101.<lb/> ...PETITIONER<lb/> (BY SRI. K. SHASHIKIRAN SHETTY, SR. COUNSEL FOR<lb/> SMT. LATHA S SHETTY, ADVOCATE)<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	AND:<lb/>
	<email>1 .<lb/></email>

	<note type="funding">THE STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> REPRESENTED BY ITS CHIEF SECRETARY<lb/> REVENUE DEPARTMENT,<lb/> M.S.BUIDLING<lb/> BENGALURU-560 001<lb/> 2 .<lb/> THE RANGE FOREST OFFICER<lb/> BALEHONNUR ANGE<lb/> N.R. PURA TALUK, CHIKMAGALUR<lb/> CHIKMAGALUR -577 101.<lb/> 3 .<lb/> ASSISTANT CONSERVATOR OF FOREST<lb/> N R PURA TALUK<lb/> CHIKMAGALUR DISTRICT<lb/> CHIKMAGALUR-577101<lb/> 4 .<lb/> DEPUTY CONSERVATOR OF FOREST<lb/> KOPPA KOPPA<lb/> CHIKMAGALUR-577101. …RESPONDENTS<lb/> (BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI. V. SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H.C, HCGP)<lb/> THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA<lb/> PRAYING TO DECLARE THAT THE PROVISIONS OF THE<lb/> KARNATAKA LAND GRABBING PROHIBITION ACT, IS<lb/> CONSTITUTIONAL AND ULTRA VIRES ARTICLE 14, 19<lb/> AND 21 AND 300-A OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA<lb/> (ANNEXURE-A).</note>

	59<lb/> IN W.P. NO.54082/2017:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>SRI. V.G. SIDDHARTHA HEGDE<lb/> S/O SRI. S.V. GANGAIAH HEGDE<lb/> AGED ABOUT 57 YEARS<lb/> PROPRIETOR<lb/> &apos;DEVADARSHINI ESTATE&apos;<lb/> KOPPA TALUK<lb/> CHIKMAGALUR DISTRICT<lb/> CHIKMAGALUR-577101.<lb/> ...PETITIONER<lb/> (BY SRI. K. SHASHIKIRAN SHETTY, SR. COUNSEL FOR<lb/> SMT. LATHA S SHETTY, ADVOCATE)<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	AND:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>1 .<lb/> THE STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> REPRESENTED BY ITS CHIEF SECRETARY<lb/> REVENUE DEPARTMENT,<lb/> M.S.BUIDLING<lb/> BENGALURU-560 001<lb/> 2 .<lb/> THE RANGE FOREST OFFICER<lb/> KOPALA TALUK<lb/> CHIKMAGALUR DISTRICT<lb/> CHIKMAGALUR -577 104.<lb/> 3 .<lb/> ASSISTANT CONSERVATOR OF FOREST<lb/> KOPALA TALUK<lb/> CHIKMAGALUR DISTRICT<lb/> CHIKMAGALUR-577 101.<lb/> 4 .<lb/> DEPUTY CONSERVATOR OF FOREST<lb/> KOPPA, CHIKMAGALUR-577 101. …RESPONDENTS<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	(BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI. V. SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H.C, HCGP, FOR R-1 &amp; R-4) 60<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA<lb/> PRAYING TO QUASH THE CRIMINAL PROCEEDINGS<lb/> PENDING BEFORE THE LAND GRABBING SPECIAL<lb/> COURT IN PROCEEDINGS NO.LGC (S) NO.887/2017<lb/> AGAINST THE PETITIONER FOR OFFENCE PUNISHABLE<lb/> UNDER SECTION 4(3) OF THE KARNATAKA LAND<lb/> GRABBING PROHIBITION ACT, 2011(ANNEXURE-B)<lb/> IN W.P. NO.55683/2017:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/> 1 .<lb/> KARNATAKA REDDY JANANSANGA<lb/> BEING A REGISTED SOCIETY<lb/> UNDER MYSORE SOCIETIES ACT 1904<lb/> HAVING ITS OFFICE AT CA SITE NO.1<lb/> MAHAYOGI VEMANA RPAD<lb/> 16TH MAIN, 3RD BLOCK<lb/> KORAMANGALA, BANGALORE-560 034<lb/> REPTD. BY ITS SECRETARY<lb/> SRI. MUNINAGAPPA.<lb/> 2 .<lb/> SRI. MUNINAGAPPA<lb/> GENERAL SECRETARY<lb/> KARNATAKA REDDY JANA SANGHA,<lb/> NO.1, 100 FEET ROAD, MAHAYOGI<lb/> VEMANA ROAD, 16TH MAIN<lb/> KORAMANGALA 3RD BLOCK<lb/> BENGALURU-560 034.<lb/> ...PETITIONERS<lb/> (BY SRI.: MALLA REDDY B.V, ADVOCATE)<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	AND:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>1 .<lb/> STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> REVENUE DEPARTMENT<lb/> M.S.BUILDING, 5TH FLOOR<lb/> DR.AMBEDKAR ROAD<lb/> BENGALURU-560 001<lb/> REPTD. BY ITS SECRETARY. 61<lb/> 2 .<lb/> RICKY EAPEN<lb/> FATHERS NAME NOT KNOWN TO THE<lb/> PETITIONER, MAJOR<lb/> R/AT NO.570/571, 3RD BLOCK<lb/> 16TH A&quot; MAIN, KORAMANGALA<lb/> BANGALORE-560 034. …RESPONDENTS<lb/> (BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI. V. SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H.C, HCGP, FOR R-1;<lb/> SRI. K.B.S. MANIAN, ADVOCATE FOR R-2)<lb/> THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA<lb/> PRAYING TO QUASH THE IMPUGNED ORDER DATED<lb/> 24.03.2017 ANNX-A ISSUED BY THE SPECIAL COURT<lb/> CONSTITUTED UNDER KARNATAKA LAND GRABBING<lb/> PROHIBITION ACT 2011 IN CASE NO. LGC (P) 224/2017<lb/> AND THE PROCEEDING SIN LGC (P). 886/2017 VIDE<lb/> ANNX-A.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	IN W.P. NO.56296/2017:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>DR. A.C. GANAPATHY<lb/> S/O A.B.CHINNAPPA,<lb/> AGED ABOUT 72 YEARS<lb/> RESIDING AT CHENNAGI VILLAGE<lb/> CHENNAKOTE POST, POLLIBETTA<lb/> KODAGU-571 215.<lb/> ...PETITIONER<lb/> (BY SRI. C.M. POONACHA, ADVOCATE)<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	AND:<lb/>
	<note type="copyright">1 .<lb/> THE STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> REPRESENTED BY ITS<lb/> PRINCIPAL SECRETARY<lb/> REVENUE DEPARTMENT 62<lb/></note>

	<reference>M.S. BUILDING<lb/> BENGALURU-560 001.<lb/></reference>

	2 .<lb/> THE TASHILDAR<lb/> VIRAJPET TALUK,<lb/> KODAGU DISTRICT-571 218. …RESPONDENTS<lb/> (BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI. V. SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H.C, HCGP)<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA<lb/> PRAYING TO QUASH THE SUMMONS DATED 17.11.2017<lb/> IN PROCEEDING SNO. LGC (G) NO.1932/2017 PENDING<lb/> ON THE FILE OF COURT HALL-01, THE KARNATAKA<lb/> LAND GRABBING PROHIBITION SPECIAL COURT, AS<lb/> AGAINST THE PETITIONER FOR OFFENCE PUNISHABLE<lb/> UNDER<lb/> THE<lb/> KARNATAKA<lb/> LAND<lb/> GRABBING<lb/> PROHIBITION ACT 2011 VIDE ANNX-A ISSUED BY<lb/> REGISTRAR<lb/> KARNATAKA<lb/> LAND<lb/> GRABBING<lb/> PROHIBITION SPECIAL COURT.<lb/> IN W.P. NO. 235/2018:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>MR. C.V.MANJUNATHA<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<note type="funding">AGED ABOUT 63 YEARS,<lb/> THE AUTHORIZED DIRECTOR,<lb/> TELECOM EMPLOYEES CO-OPERATIVE<lb/> HOUSING SOCIETY LTD.,<lb/> REGISTERED OFFICE AT NO.23, I FLOOR,<lb/> NEHRUNAGAR MAIN ROAD,<lb/> BEHIND REDDY PETROL BUNK,<lb/> SHESHADRIPURAM,<lb/> BENGALURU-560020. …PETITIONER<lb/></note>

	(BY SRI. AJIT KALYAN, ADVOCATE)<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>DR. B.R.AMBEDKAR VEEDHI,<lb/> BENGALURU-560001.<lb/> (REPRESENTED BY ITS<lb/> PRINCIPAL SECRETARY)<lb/> 2.<lb/> THE TAHASILDAR<lb/> BENGALURU NORTH (A) TALUK,<lb/> 3 RD FLOOR, HOTEL SHARAVATHI<lb/> BUILDING, YELAHANKA NEW TOWN<lb/> OPP. TO CANARA BANK,<lb/> BENGALURU-560064.<lb/> 3.<lb/> MR. CHANDRASHEKAR<lb/> S/O. LATE HANUMANTHARAYAPPA,<lb/> AGED ABOUT 53 YEARS,<lb/> RESIDING AT KOLIPURA VILLAGE,<lb/> JALA HOBLI, B.K.HALLI POST,<lb/> BENGALURU NORTH (A) TALUK,<lb/> BENGALURU-562149.<lb/> 4.<lb/> MR. Y.G.ASHWATH<lb/> S/O. LATE GOVINDAPPA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 58 YEARS,<lb/> RESIDING AT NO.358, &quot;A&quot; SECTOR,<lb/> KHB COLONY, YELAHANKA NEW TOWN,<lb/> BENGALURU-560064.<lb/> …RESPONDENTS<lb/> (BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI. V. SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H.C, HCGP, FOR R-1 &amp; R-2;<lb/> SRI. B.S. ANIL KUMAR, ADOVATE FOR R-3;<lb/> R-4 SERVED AND )<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<note type="funding">THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA PRAYING<lb/> TO QUASH THE NOTICE DATED 01.06.2017 ANNEXURE-<lb/>A AND FURTHER QUASH THE ENTIRE PROCEEDINGS 73<lb/> 2.<lb/> THE TAHASILDAR,<lb/> VIRAJPET TALUK,<lb/> KODAGU DISTRICT-571218.<lb/> …RESPONDENTS<lb/> (BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI. V. SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H.C, HCGP)<lb/> THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA AND<lb/> SECTION 482 OF THE CODE OF CRIMINAL PROCEDURE<lb/> PRAYING TO QUASH THE KARNATAKA LAND GRABBING<lb/> PROHIBITION ACT, 2011, QUASH THE PROCEEDINGS IN<lb/> L.G.C.(G)<lb/> NO.1942/2017<lb/> IN<lb/> KARNATAKA<lb/> LAND<lb/> GRABBING, SPECIAL COURT</note>

	<reference>, 3 RD FLOOR, KANDAYA<lb/> BHAVANA, KEMPEGOWDA ROAD, BENGALURU, COURT<lb/> HALL NO.1 DATED 31.10.2017 VIDE ANNEXURE-B AND<lb/> ETC.<lb/> IN W.P. NO.5390/2018:<lb/></reference>

	BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>H.B.SRINIVASAMURTHY,<lb/> S/O. LATE BHIMAIYA,<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	65 YEARS,<lb/> HOSURU VILLAGE AND POST,<lb/> AMMATTI HOBLI,<lb/> VIRAJPET TALUK-571211<lb/> KODAGU DISTRICT.<lb/> …PETITIONER<lb/> (BY SRI. S.G. BHAGAVAN, ADVOCATE) AND<lb/> 1.<lb/>
	<note type="copyright">THE STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> BY THE PRINCIPAL SECRETARY,<lb/> DEPARTMENT OF REVENUE,<lb/></note>

	M.S.BUILDING, DR. AMBEDKAR ROAD, 74<lb/> BENGALURU-560001.<lb/> 2.<lb/> THE TAHASILDAR,<lb/> VIRAJPET TALUK,<lb/> KODAGU DISTRICT-571218.<lb/> …RESPONDENTS<lb/> (BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI. V. SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H.C, HCGP)<lb/>
	<note type="funding">THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA AND<lb/> SECTION 482 OF THE CODE OF CRIMINAL PROCEDURE<lb/> PRAYING TO QUASH THE KARNATAKA LAND GRABBING<lb/> PROHIBITION ACT, 2011, QUASH THE PROCEEDINGS IN<lb/> L.G.C.(G)<lb/> NO.1945/2017<lb/> IN<lb/> KARNATAKA<lb/> LAND<lb/> GRABBING, SPECIAL COURT, 3 RD FLOOR, KANDAYA<lb/> BHAVANA, KEMPEGOWDA ROAD, BENGALURU, COURT<lb/> HALL NO.1 DATED 07.11.2017 AS PER ANNEXURE-B<lb/> AND ETC.<lb/> IN W.P. NO.5391/2018:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/> BALASUBRAMANYA<lb/> S/O. GOPAL BHAT,<lb/> 61 YEARS,<lb/> HOSURU VILLAGE AND POST,<lb/> AMMATTI HOBLI,<lb/> VIRAJPET TALUK-571211<lb/> KODAGU DISTRICT.<lb/> …PETITIONER<lb/> (BY SRI. S.G. BHAGAVAN, ADVOCATE) AND<lb/> 1.<lb/> THE STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> BY THE PRINCIPAL SECRETARY,<lb/> DEPARTMENT OF REVENUE,<lb/> M.S.BUILDING, DR. AMBEDKAR ROAD, 75<lb/> BENGALURU-560001.<lb/> 2.<lb/> THE TAHASILDAR,<lb/> VIRAJPET TALUK,<lb/> KODAGU DISTRICT-571218.<lb/> …RESPONDENTS<lb/> (BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI. V. SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H.C, HCGP)<lb/> THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA AND<lb/> SECTION 482 OF THE CODE OF CRIMINAL PROCEDURE<lb/> PRAYING TO QUASH THE KARNATAKA LAND GRABBING<lb/> PROHIBITION ACT, 2011, QUASH THE PROCEEDINGS IN<lb/> L.G.C.(G)<lb/> NO.1946/2017<lb/> IN<lb/> KARNATAKA<lb/> LAND<lb/> GRABBING, SPECIAL COURT, 3 RD FLOOR, KANDAYA<lb/> BHAVANA, KEMPEGOWDA ROAD, BENGALURU, COURT<lb/> HALL NO.1 DATED 07.11.2017 AS PER ANNEXURE-B<lb/> AND ETC.<lb/> IN W.P. NO.5704/2018:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/> NAGARAJU<lb/> S/O. GANGADHARAIAH<lb/> AGED ABOUT 47 YEARS,<lb/> RESIDING AT NO.416<lb/> TAVAREKERE VILLAGE,<lb/> MADAGI ROAD, TAVAREKERE POST<lb/> BENGALURU SOUTH TALUK.<lb/> …PETITIONER<lb/> (BY SRI. S. SUDHARSHAN, ADVOCATE) AND<lb/> 1.<lb/> HEMANTHARAJU<lb/> S/O. LATE MANIRAJU<lb/> AGED ABOUT 46 YEARS,<lb/> SOCIAL WORKER 76<lb/> C/O. YUDDA BHOOMI HORATA SENE<lb/> NO.32, ESHWARA TEMPLE ROAD,<lb/> RAMOHALLI, KENGERI HOBLI,<lb/> BENGALURU SOUTH TALUK<lb/> BENGALURU-560074.<lb/> 2.<lb/> THE TAHSILDAR<lb/> BENGALURU SOUTH TALUK<lb/> KHANDAYA BHAWAN<lb/> KEMPEGOWDA ROAD,<lb/> BENGALURU-560009.<lb/> …RESPONDENTS<lb/> (BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI. V. SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H.C, HCGP, FOR R-2;<lb/> R-1 SERVED AND )<lb/> THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA AND<lb/> SECTION 482 OF THE CODE OF CRIMINAL PROCEDURE,<lb/> 1973 PRAYING TO DECLARE THAT THE PROCEEDING<lb/> ON THE RECORD OF THE SPECIAL COURT OF THE<lb/> TRIAL OF OFFENCES UNDER THE KARNATAKA LAND<lb/> GRABBING (PROHIBISION) ACT, 2011 IN PETITION<lb/> NO.LGC 43 OF 2016 IS ANNEXURE-G AT PAGE NO.227-<lb/>270 DATED 08.01.2018 IN VIOLATION OF THE<lb/> UNDERLYING STATUTE, IN GROSS VIOLATION OF<lb/> ARTICLE 21 OF THE CONSTITUTION, OPPOSED TO<lb/> EXTABLISHED LAWS AND IN CONTRAVENTION OF<lb/> OTHER STATUTES AND HAS LED TO A GRAVE FAILURE<lb/> AND MISCARRIAGE OF JUSTICE AND TO QUASH IT,<lb/> ACCORDINGLY, IN EXERCISE OF THE CONSITUENT AND<lb/> INHERENT POWER OF THIS HON&apos;BLE COURT.<lb/></note>

	IN W.P.NO.6061/2018:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>MR. CHANNAMUNIYAPPA<lb/> S/O MUTHAIAH<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	AGED ABOUT 40 YEARS 77<lb/>
	<reference>PEDDAMAPALYA VILLAGE,<lb/> TAWAREKERE HOBLI,<lb/> BENGALURU SOUTH<lb/> BENGALURU 562 130.<lb/> ...PETITIONER<lb/> (BY SRI. K. SHASHIKIRAN SHETTY, SR. COUSEL FOR<lb/> SMT. LATHA S SHETTY, ADVOCATE)<lb/></reference>

	AND:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>1.<lb/> THE STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> REPRESENTED BY ITS CHIEF SECRETARY<lb/> REVENUE DEPARTMENT,<lb/> M.S. BUILDING,<lb/> BENGALURU -560 001.<lb/> 2.<lb/> SHRI. HANUMANTHARAJU<lb/> S/O LATE MUNIRAJU<lb/> SOCIAL WORKER,<lb/> C/O YUDDA BHOOMI HORATA SENE<lb/> NO.32, ESWARA EMPLE ROAD,<lb/> RAMOHALLI, KENGERI, HOBLI,<lb/> BANGALORE SOUTH TALUK,<lb/> BENGALURU -560 074.<lb/> 3.<lb/> THE TAHSILDAR<lb/> BANGALORE SOUTH TALUK,<lb/> KANDAYA BHAVAN,<lb/> KEMPEGOWDA ROAD,<lb/> BENGALURU -560 009.<lb/> …RESPONDENTS<lb/> (BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI. V. SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H.C, HCGP, FOR R-1 &amp; R-3:<lb/> R-2 SERVED)<lb/> THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLE<lb/> 226 &amp; 227 OF CONSTITUTION OF INDIA PRAYING TO<lb/> DECLARE THAT THE PROVISIONS OF THE KARNATAKA<lb/> LAND<lb/> GRABBING<lb/> PROHIBITION<lb/> ACT,<lb/> IS<lb/> UNCONSTITUTIONAL AND ULTRA VIRES ARTICLE 14,<lb/> IN W.P.NO.7868/2018:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/> N KAMALASAMBASIVA<lb/> @ SAMBASIVAMURTHY SWAMIJI,<lb/> S/O LATE NARASIMHAIAH,<lb/> AGED ABOUT 73 YEARS,<lb/> DHARMADHIKARI SRI. KOTILINGASWAMY TEMPLE,<lb/> R/AT KAMMASANDRA VILLAGE,<lb/> BETHAMANGALA HOBLI,<lb/> BANGARPET TALUK-563 121.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>...PETITIONER<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	(BY SRI. RAHUL S REDDY, ADVOCATE)<lb/> AND:<lb/>
	<email>1.<lb/></email>

	<note type="funding">THE STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> REPRESENTED BY ITS SECRETARY,<lb/> DEPARTMENT OF REVENUE,<lb/> VIDHANA SOUDHA,<lb/> BENGALURU-560 001.<lb/> 2.<lb/> THE TAHSILDAR<lb/> BANGARPET TALUK,<lb/> BANGARPET-563 114. …RESPONDENTS<lb/> (BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI. V. SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H.C, HCGP)<lb/> THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLE<lb/> 226 &amp; 227 OF CONSTITUTION OF INDIA PRAYING TO<lb/> DECLARE<lb/> THE<lb/> KARNATAKA<lb/> LAND<lb/> GRABBING<lb/> PROHIBITION ACT 2011 (KARNATAKA ACT 38/2014) AS<lb/> ULTRA VIRES THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA BEING<lb/> VIOLATIVE OF ARTICLES 14, 20, 21 AND 300A AND<lb/> ETC.</note>

	84<lb/> IN W.P.NO.8035/2018:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>DAADYS DEVELOPERS AND BUILDERS<lb/> REPRESENTED BY BOBY SEBASTIAN<lb/> S/O LATE K. T. SABASTIAN<lb/> AGED ABOUT 42 YEARS<lb/> R/A NO.383, 9 TH MAIN<lb/> 7 TH SECTOR, H S R LAYOUT<lb/> BENGALURU -560 102.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>...PETITIONER<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	(
	<reference>BY SRI. D.R. RAVISHANKAR, ADVOCATE FOR<lb/> SRI. N. SHIVAKUMAR, ADVOCATE)<lb/></reference>

	AND:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>1.<lb/> STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> BY LAW AND PARLIAMENTARY AFFAIRS<lb/> VIDHANA SOUDHA<lb/> BENGALURU -560 001.<lb/> 2.<lb/> STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> BY SECRETARY TO GOVT.,<lb/> DEPARTMENT OF REVENUE<lb/> M S BUILDING<lb/> BENGALURU -560 001.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	3.<lb/> TAHASILDAR<lb/> ANEKAL TALUK<lb/> BANGALORE SOUTH DIVISIOON<lb/> BENGALURU -562 106. …RESPONDENTS<lb/> (BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI. V. SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H.C, HCGP)<lb/>
	<note type="funding">THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLE<lb/> 226 &amp; 227 OF CONSTITUTION OF INDIA PRAYING TO<lb/> DECLARE<lb/> THE<lb/> KARNATAKA<lb/> LAND<lb/> GRABBING<lb/> PROHIBITION ACT 2011 (KARNATAKA ACT 38/2014) AS 85<lb/> ULTRA VIRES THE CONSITUTION OF INDIA BEING<lb/> VIOLATIVE ARTICLES 14, 20, 21 AND 300-1 IN THE<lb/> ALTERNATIVE.<lb/></note>

	IN W.P.NO.8186/2018:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>MVC HANUMANTHAIAH<lb/> SON OF VENKATARAMANAPPA<lb/> AGED 70 YEARS<lb/> RESIDING AT NO 2,<lb/> WEST PARK ROAD,<lb/> MALLESHWARAM<lb/> BENGALURU -560 003.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>...PETITIONER<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	(BY SRI. SHAKAR SHETTY, ADVOCATE)<lb/> AND:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> REP. BY ITS REVENUE SECRETARY<lb/> VIDHANA SOUDHA<lb/> DR. AMBEDKAR VEEDHI<lb/> BENGALURU -560 001.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>…..RESPONDENT<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	(BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI. V. SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H.C, HCGP)<lb/>
	<note type="funding">THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLE<lb/> 226 &amp; 227 OF CONSTITUTION OF INDIA PRAYING TO<lb/> QUASH THE ORDER DATED 21.12.2017 IN LGC(S)<lb/> No.500 OF 2017 ON THE FILE OF THE KARNATAKA<lb/> LAND GRABBING PROHIBITION SPECIAL COURT,<lb/> BENGALURU,<lb/> (CH-1)<lb/> AS<lb/> PER<lb/> ANNEXURE-G,<lb/> ACCORDING TO LAW.<lb/></note>

	AND:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> REP. BY ITS REVENUE SECRETARY<lb/> VIDHANA SOUDHA<lb/> DR. AMBEDKAR VEEDHI<lb/> BENGALURU -560 001. …RESPONDENT<lb/> (BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI. V. SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H.C, HCGP)<lb/> THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA<lb/> PRAYING QUASH THE ORDER DATED 21.12.2017 IN<lb/> LGC (S) NO. 504/2017 ON THE FILE OF THE<lb/> KARNATAKA LAND GRABBING PROHIBITION SPECIAL<lb/> COURT, BANGLORE, (CH-1) AS PER ANNWXURE-G,<lb/> ACCORDING TO LAW.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	IN W.P. NO.8191/2018:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>C. MANJULA<lb/> D/O MVC HANUMANTHAIAH<lb/> AGED ABOUT 42 YEARS<lb/> RESIDING AT NO 2<lb/> WEST PARK ROA,<lb/> MALLESHWARAM<lb/> BENGALURU -560 003.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>...PETITIONER<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	(BY SRI. S. SHAKAR SHETTY, ADVOCATE)<lb/> AND:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> REP. BY ITS REVENUE SECRETARY<lb/> VIDHANA SOUDHA 89<lb/> DR. AMBEDKAR VEEDHI<lb/> BENGALURU -560 001. …RESPONDENT<lb/> (BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI. V. SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H.C, HCGP)<lb/> THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA<lb/> PRAYING QUASH THE ORDER DATED 21.12.2017 IN<lb/> LGC (S) NO. 505/2017 ON THE FILE OF THE<lb/> KARNATAKA LAND GRABBING PROHIBITION SPECIAL<lb/> COURT, BANGLORE, (CH-1) AS PER ANNWXURE-G,<lb/> ACCORDING TO LAW.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	IN W.P. NO.8210/2018:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>SRI. A.M. NARAYANASWAMY<lb/> S/O MUNICHIKKANNA<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	AGED ABOUT 58 YEARS<lb/> RESIDING AT ARASANAHALLI<lb/> VILLAGE, SULIBELE POST<lb/> HOSAKOTE TALUK -562114<lb/> BENGALURU RURAL DISTRICT.<lb/> ...PETITIONER<lb/> (BY SRI. BHADRINATH R, ADVOCATE)<lb/> AND:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>1 .<lb/> THE STATE OF KARANATAKA<lb/> DEPARTMENT OF REVENUE<lb/> M S BUILDING<lb/> BENGALURU -560001<lb/> REPRESENTED BY ITS<lb/> PRINCIPAL SECRETARY. 90<lb/> .<lb/> THE REGIONAL COMMISSIONER<lb/> BMTC BUILDING II FLOOR<lb/> BENGALURU DIVISION<lb/> BENGALURU -560004.<lb/> .<lb/> THE DEPUTY COMMISSIONER<lb/> BENGALURU RURAL DISTRICT<lb/> V V TOWER, BENGALURU -560 001.<lb/> .<lb/> THE ASSISTANT COMMISSIONER<lb/> DODDABALLAPURA SUB DIVISION<lb/> DODDABALLAPURA -561203<lb/> BENGALURU RURAL DISTRICT.<lb/> .<lb/> THE THASILDAR<lb/> HOSKOTE TALUK HOSKOTE -562114<lb/> BENGALURU RURAL DISTRICT.<lb/> .<lb/> SRI B N GOPALA GOWDA<lb/> S/O LATE NARAYANA GOWDA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 82 YEARS<lb/> RESIDING AT BENNIGANAHALLI<lb/> VILLAGE, SULIBELE HOBLI<lb/> HOSKOTE TALUK -562114<lb/> BANGALORE RURAL DISTRICT.<lb/> .<lb/> SRI B C CHIKKA BACHE GOWDA<lb/> S/O LATE CHANNA BYRE GOWDA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 76 YEARS<lb/> RESIDING AT BENNIGANAHALLI<lb/> VILLAGE, SULIBELE HOBLI,<lb/> HOSKOTE TALUK -562114<lb/> BANGALORE RURAL DISTRICT.<lb/> .<lb/> SRI B N VENKATARAMANA GOWDA<lb/> S/O LATE NARAYANA GOWDA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 71 YEARS<lb/> RESIDING AT BENNIGANAHALLI<lb/> VILLAGE, SULIBELE HOBLI,<lb/> HOSKOTE TALUK -562114<lb/> BANGALORE RURAL DISTRICT. 91<lb/> 9 .<lb/> SRI B N BACHE GOWDA<lb/> S/O LATE NARAYANA GOWDA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 69 YEARS<lb/> RESIDING AT BENNIGANAHALLI<lb/> VILLAGE, SULIBELE HOBLI,<lb/> HOSKOTE TALUK -562114<lb/> BANGALORE RURAL DISTRICT.<lb/> 10 . SRI B C VENKATESH GOWDA<lb/> S/O LATE CHANNA BYREGOWDA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 67 YEARS<lb/> RESIDING AT BENNIGANAHALLI<lb/> VILLAGE, SULIBELE HOBLI,<lb/> HOSKOTE TALUK -562114<lb/> BANGALORE RURAL DISTRICT …RESPONDENTS<lb/> (BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI. V. SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H.C, HCGP FOR R-1 TO R-5;<lb/> SRI. P.M. SIDDAMALLAPPA, ADVOCATE R-6,7, 9 &amp; 10)<lb/> THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA<lb/> PRAYING QUASH THE ORDER DATED 04.01.2018 IN<lb/> CASE LGC (S) NO.1252 OF 2017 PASSED BY THE<lb/> KARNATAKA LAND GRABBING PROHIBITION SPECIAL<lb/> COURT, BANGALORE AS FOUND AT ANNEXURE-A.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	IN W.P. NO.8585/2018:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>THARIQ KHAN<lb/> S/O MAJEED KHAN<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	AGED ABOUT 43 YEARS<lb/> R/AT BILGUNDA VILLAGE<lb/> AMMATHI HOBLI, VIRAJAPET<lb/> TALUK, KODAGU DISTRICT.<lb/> ...PETITIONER 92<lb/> (BY SRI. SACHIN B.S, ADVOCATE)<lb/> AND:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>1 .<lb/> STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> DEPARTMENT OF REVENUE<lb/> M.S. BUILDING, BANGALORE-560 001<lb/> REPRESENTED BY ITS SECRETARY.<lb/> 2 .<lb/> TAHASILDAR<lb/> VIRAJAPET TALUK, VIRAJAPET<lb/> KODAGU DISTRICT-571 218.<lb/> …RESPONDENTS<lb/> (BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI. V. SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H.C, HCGP)<lb/> THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA<lb/> PRAYING DECLARE THE KARNATAKA LAND GRABBING<lb/> PROHIBITION ACT 2011 AS ULTRA VIRES THE<lb/> CONSTITUTION OF INDIA QUASH THE IMPUGNED<lb/> ORDER DATED 25.01.2018 AND ENTIRE PROCEEDING<lb/> SIN PROCEEDINGS ON THE FILE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> SPECIAL COURT FOR LAND GRABBING PROHIBITION<lb/> BANGALORE VIDE ANEX-A<lb/> IN W.P. NO.9116/2018:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/> SMT. A.S. NIRMALA<lb/> W/O LATE VIVEK<lb/> AGED ABOUT 71 YEARS<lb/> RESIDING AT NO.49/3, 16TH<lb/> CROSS, 4TH MAIN ROAD<lb/> MALLESHWARAM<lb/> BENGALURU -560 003.<lb/> ...PETITIONER<lb/> (BY SRI. P.S. RAJAGOPAL, SR. COUNSEL FOR<lb/> (BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI. V. SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H.C, HCGP R-1 TO R-3;<lb/> SRI. RAJESH SHETTY, ADVOCATE FOR R-4;<lb/> SRI. RAGHUNATH V, ADVOCATE FOR R-5)<lb/> THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA<lb/> PRAYING TO DECLARE THE KARNATAKA LAND<lb/> GRABBING PROHIBITION ACT 2011 (KARNATAKA ACT<lb/> 38/2014) AS ULTRA VIRES THE CONSTITUTION OF<lb/> INDIA BEING VIOLATION OF ARTICLE 14, 20, 21 AND<lb/> 300A.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	IN W.P. NO.9117/2018:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>SRI. M. KRISHNA MURTHY<lb/> S/O LATE M.S. MUNIKEMPAIAH<lb/> AGED ABOUT 46 YEARS<lb/> RESIDING AT MEDAHALLI EXTENSION<lb/> (BEHIND RAMARA TEMPLE)<lb/> VIRGONAGAR POST<lb/> BIDARAHALLI POST<lb/> BENGALURU EAST TALUK<lb/> BENGALURU -560 049.<lb/> ...PETITIONER<lb/> (BY SRI. P.S. RAJAGOPAL, SR. COUNSEL FOR<lb/> SRI. BHADRINATH R, ADVOCATE)<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	AND:<lb/>
	<email>1 .<lb/></email>

	<note type="funding">THE STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> DEPARTMENT OF REVENUE,<lb/> M.S. BUILDING<lb/> BENGALURU -560 001<lb/> REPRESENTED BY ITS<lb/> PRINCIPAL SECRETARY.<lb/> THE TAHASILDAR<lb/> CHIKKAMAGALURU TALUK<lb/> AND DISTRICT<lb/> CHIKKAMAGALURU -577 101. …RESPONDENTS<lb/> (BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI. V. SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H.C, HCGP)<lb/> THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA<lb/> PRAYING TO DECLARE THE KARNATAKA LAND<lb/> GRABBING PROHIBITION ACT 2011 IS ULTRA VIRES OF<lb/> THE CONSTITUTION BY STRIKING DOWN THE SAID ACT<lb/> AND QUASH THE NOTICE ISSUED TO THE PETITIONER<lb/> BY THE KARNATAKA LAND GRABBING PROHIBITION<lb/> SPECIAL COURT AT BANGALORE IN LGC (S)<lb/> NO.1712/2017 AT ANNEX-A IN THIS W.P.<lb/></note>

	<reference>IN W.P. NO.11767/2018:<lb/></reference>

	BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>1 .<lb/> VISTARA VENTURES<lb/> REPRESENTED BY ITS PARNTER<lb/> S.K. PRAJWAL<lb/> AGED ABOUT 42 YEARS<lb/> OFFICE AT NO.191, 2ND FLOOR<lb/> 16TH MAIN, 36TH CROSS<lb/> 4TH T BLOCK, JAYANAGAR<lb/> BENGALURU -560 054.<lb/> 2 .<lb/> SMT. V. PADMAVATHY<lb/> D/O LATE A. VENKATAPPA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 54 YEARS<lb/> RESIDING AT NO.255/6<lb/> 7TH MAIN ROAD, N.S. PALYA<lb/> BTM 2ND STAGE<lb/> BENGALURU -560 076.<lb/> ...PETITIONERS<lb/> (BY SRI. HEMANTH KUMAR D, ADVOCATE)<lb/> (BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI. V. SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H.C, HCGP)<lb/> THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA<lb/> PRAYING TO DECLARE THE KARNATAKA LAND<lb/> GRABBING PROHIBITION ACT 2011 (KARNATAKA ACT<lb/> 38 OF 2014) AS ULTRA VIRES ARTICLES 14, 20 (1), 21<lb/> AND 300A OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	IN W.P. NO.11975/2018:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>SRI. KRISHNADEVERAYA EDUCATION<lb/> TRUST, A TRUST REGISTERED UNDER<lb/> THE INDIAN TRUSTS ACT<lb/> HAVING ITS OFFICE AT<lb/> NO.16, BALLARI ROAD<lb/> SADASHIVANAGAR<lb/> BANGALORE -560 080<lb/> REPRESENTED BY ITS<lb/> SECRETARY MR. K. SYAMA RAJU.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>...PETITIONER<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	(BY MS. NAYANATARA, ADVOCATE FOR<lb/> SRI. G.L. VISHWANATH, ADVOCATE)<lb/> AND:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>THE STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> REPRESENTED BY ITS<lb/> CHIEF SECRETARY<lb/> REVENUE DEPARTMENT<lb/> M.S. BUILDING, 5TH FLOOR<lb/> BANGALORE -560 001 …RESPONDENT<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	(BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI. V. SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H.C, HCGP) 102<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES 226<lb/> AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA PRAYING TO<lb/> DECLARE<lb/> THE<lb/> KARNATAKA<lb/> LAND<lb/> GRABBING<lb/> PROHIBITION ACT 2011 (KARNATAKA ACT 38/2014) AS<lb/> ULTRA VIRES ARTICLES 14, 20 (1), 21 AND 300A OF<lb/> THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	IN W.P. NO.12264/2018:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>SRI. D.R. SIDDARAMAIAH<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	S/O LATE RANGAPPA<lb/> R/O DODDANARAVANGALA VILLAGE<lb/> BELLAVI HOBLI -572 153<lb/> TUMAKURU TALUK AND DISTRICT.<lb/> ...PETITIONER<lb/> (BY SRI. V.B. SIDDARAMAIAH, ADVOCATE)<lb/> AND<lb/> 1 .<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>THE STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> REP. BY PRL.SECRETARY<lb/> REVENUE DEPARTMENT<lb/> M.S. BUILDING<lb/> BANGALORE -01.<lb/> 2 .<lb/> SRI. D. GANGANNA<lb/> S/O LATE CHIKKURAIAH<lb/> R/O NO.20, 11TH CROSS<lb/> MANJUNATHANAGAR<lb/> MAGADI ROAD<lb/> BENGALURU -560 023. …RESPONDENTS<lb/> (BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI. V. SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H.C, HCGP FOR R-1;<lb/> SRI. A.V. GANGADHARAPPA, ADVOCATE FOR R-2)<lb/> THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA 103<lb/> PRAYING TO SET ASIDE THE ORDER DATED 24.01.2018<lb/> PASSED BY THE KARNATAKA LAND GRABBING<lb/> PROHIBITION SPECIAL COURT, DATED 24.01.2018, IN<lb/> CASE LGC (P) NO.1369/2017 VIDE ANNEXURE-P, WITH<lb/> RESPECT TO THE LAND BEARING SY.NO.21 OF<lb/> DODDANARAVANGALA<lb/> VILLAE,<lb/> BELLAVI<lb/> HOBLI,<lb/> TUMAKURU TALUK, MEASURING 8 ACRES 20 GUNTAS<lb/> AND THEREBY DROP THE PROCEEDING SIN CASE LGC<lb/> (P) NO.1369/2017 ON THE FILE OF THE KARNATAKA<lb/> LAND GRABBING PROHIBITION SPECIAL COURT,<lb/> BENGALURU.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	IN W.P. NO.12614/2018:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/> 1 .<lb/> SRI. S.G. GOVINDAIAH<lb/> S/O LATE GIRIGOWDA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 64 YEARS.<lb/> 2 .<lb/> SMT. PRIYANKA G<lb/> D/O. S.G. GOVINDAIAH<lb/> AGED ABOUT 34 YEARS.<lb/> 3 .<lb/> SMT. NEETHU G<lb/> D/O S.G. GOVINDAIAH<lb/> AGED ABOUT 32 YEARS.<lb/> THE PETITIONERS ARE<lb/> RESIDING AT #75<lb/> II &quot;H&quot; MAIN ROAD<lb/> 11TH BLOCK<lb/> NAGARABHAVI II STAGE<lb/> BENGALURU -560 072.<lb/> ...PETITIONERS<lb/>
	<note type="copyright">(BY SRI. SRINIVASA D.C, ADVOCATE)<lb/></note>

	AND:<lb/>
	<email>1 .<lb/> STATE</email>

	<note type="doctype">OF KARNATAKA<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>S/O RAJANAHALLI LAXMANASETTY<lb/> AGED ABOUT 79 YEARS<lb/> PRESIDENT<lb/> M/S BAPUJI EDUCATION ASSOCIATION<lb/> PJ EXTENSION, DAVANAGERE -577 002.<lb/> .<lb/> MUDDEGOWDRU REVANA SIDDAPPA<lb/> S/O MUDDEGOWDRU CHENNABASAPPA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 85 YEARS<lb/> VICE PRESIDENT<lb/> M/S BAPUJI EDUCATION ASSOCIATION<lb/> PJ EXTENSION, DAVANAGERE -577 002.<lb/> .<lb/> DR. SHAMANUR SHIVASHANKARAPPA<lb/> S/O LATE S KALLAPPA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 80 YEARS<lb/> SECRETARY<lb/> M/S BAPUJI EDUCATION ASSOCIATION PJ<lb/> EXTENSION, DAVANAGERE -577 002.<lb/> .<lb/> S.S. MALLIKARJUN<lb/> S/O S.S. SHIVASHANKARAPPA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 50 YEARS<lb/> JOINT SECRETARY<lb/> M/S BAPUJI EDUCATION ASSOCIATION<lb/> PJ EXTENSION, DAVANAGERE -577 002.<lb/> .<lb/> A.C. JAYANNA<lb/> S/O A. CHANNABASAPPA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 80 YEARS<lb/> TREASURER<lb/> M/S BAPUJI EDUCATION ASSOCIATION<lb/> PJ EXTENSION, DAVANAGERE -577 002.<lb/> .<lb/> A.S. VEERANNA<lb/> S/O A. CHANNABASAPPA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 72 YEARS<lb/> MEMBER<lb/> M/S BAPUJI EDUCATION ASSOCIATION<lb/> PJ EXTENSION, DAVANAGERE -577 002.<lb/> .<lb/> MAKANUR MALLIKARJUNAPPA<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>S/O SRI. SHIVAPPA MALLAPUR<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	AGED ABOUT 33 YEARS<lb/> R/O PURADAKERE<lb/> HEREKERUR TALUK<lb/> HAVERI.<lb/> .<lb/> SRI. SIDDESH<lb/> S/O SRI. THIPPESHAPPA BANAKAR<lb/> AGED ABOUT 38 YEARS<lb/> R/O PURADAKERE<lb/> HEREKERUR TALUK<lb/> HAVERI.<lb/> .<lb/> SRI. BUDEPPA<lb/> S/O SRI. VEERAPPA BADIGER<lb/> ALIAS ARKACHARI<lb/> AGED ABOUT 72 YEARS<lb/> R/O PURADAKERE<lb/> HEREKERUR TALUK<lb/> HAVERI.<lb/> .<lb/> SRI GADIGEPPA<lb/> S/O SRI.VEERAPPA KUMBLUR,<lb/> AGED ABOUT 49 YEARS<lb/> R/O PURADAKERE<lb/> HEREKERUR TALUK<lb/> HAVERI.<lb/> .<lb/> SRI. NAGARAJ<lb/> S/O SRI. VIRUPAKSHAPPA<lb/> BEVINAHALLI<lb/> AGED ABOUT 40 YEARS<lb/> R/O.PURADAKERE,<lb/> HEREKERUR TALUK,<lb/> HAVERI.<lb/> .<lb/> SRI. YOGESH<lb/> S/O SRI. BASAPPA KAYAKAD<lb/> AGED ABOUT 40 YEARS<lb/> R/O PURADAKERE<lb/> HEREKERUR TALUK<lb/> HAVERI. 120<lb/> .<lb/> SRI. NAGAPPA<lb/> S/O SRI. BASAPPA KAYAKAD<lb/> AGED ABOUT 42 YEARS<lb/> R/O PURADAKERE<lb/> HEREKERUR TALUK<lb/> HAVERI.<lb/> .<lb/> SRI. SHIVARAJ<lb/> S/O SRI NAGARAJ BAVENAHALLI,<lb/> R/O.PURADAKERE,<lb/> HEREKERUR TALUK,<lb/> HAVERI.<lb/> . SRI. VIRUPAKSHAPPA<lb/> S/O SRI. SIDDALINGAPPA<lb/> BEVINAHALLI<lb/> AGED ABOUT 74 YEARS<lb/> R/O PURADAKERE<lb/> HEREKERUR TALUK<lb/> HAVERI.<lb/> . SRI. SHAREIFF SAB<lb/> S/O SRI. KAJI SAB BADIGER<lb/> AGED ABOUT 47 YEARS<lb/> R/O PURADAKERE<lb/> HEREKERUR TALUK<lb/> HAVERI.<lb/> . SRI. TIPPU SULTAN<lb/> S/O SRI. KAJA SAB JATIGAR<lb/> AGED ABOUT 56 YEARS<lb/> R/O PURADAKERE<lb/> HEREKERUR TALUK<lb/> HAVERI.<lb/> . SRI. MOHAMAD SAB<lb/> S/O KHAZI SAB JATIGAR<lb/> ALIAS BADIGERE<lb/> AGED ABOUT 60 YEARS<lb/> R/O PURADAKERE<lb/> HEREKERUR TALUK<lb/> HAVERI.<lb/> ...PETITIONERS 121<lb/> (BY SRI. M.V. HIREMATH, ADVOCATE)<lb/> AND:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>1 .<lb/> THE PRINCIPAL SECRETARY<lb/> DEPARTMENT OF REVENUE<lb/> GOVERNMENT OF KARNATAKA<lb/> M.S. BUILDING<lb/> BENGALURU -560 001.<lb/> 2 .<lb/> SRI. SRINGERI MUTT VIDABHINAVA<lb/> NARASIMHA BHARATI SWAMI GURU<lb/> SACHIDANANDA SHANKAR BHARATI<lb/> SWAMIGALU, KUDLI<lb/> SHIVAMOGGA TALUK<lb/> SHIVAMOGGA -577 227.<lb/> 3 .<lb/> THE TAHASILDHAR<lb/> HIREKERUR TALUK<lb/> HAVERI -581 111.<lb/> …RESPONDENTS<lb/> (BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI. V. SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H.C, HCGP FOR R-1 &amp; R-3<lb/> R-2 SERVED)<lb/> THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA<lb/> PRAYING TO DECLARE THE PROVISIONS OF SECTIONS<lb/> 2, 7, 11, 20 OF THE KARNATAKA LAND GRABBING AND<lb/> PROHIBITION ACT OF 2011 AS VOID, ARBITRARY,<lb/> UNJUST AS THEY ARE VIOLATIVE OF PROVISIONS OF<lb/> THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	IN W.P. NO.22817/2018:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>SRI. MANJUNATHA<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	AGED ABOUT 49 YEARS<lb/> S/O LATE GOVINDAPPA<lb/> R/AT H. THIMMAPURA VILLAGE 122<lb/>
	<reference>BELENHALLI POST, KASABA HOBLI<lb/> TARIKERE TALUK, CHIKKAMAGALURU<lb/> DISTRICT -577 228.<lb/> ...PETITIONER<lb/></reference>

	(BY SRI. PUNDIKAI ISHWARA BHAT, ADVCOATE)<lb/> AND:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>1 .<lb/> THE STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> REP. BY ITS SECRETARY<lb/> DEPARTMENT OF FOREST<lb/> M.S. BUILDING<lb/> BENGALURU -560 001.<lb/> 2 .<lb/> THE DEPUTY CONSERVATOR<lb/> OF FOREST, FOREST DEPARTMENT<lb/> BHADRAVATHI DIVISION<lb/> BHADRAVATHI, SHIVAMOGGA<lb/> DISTRICT -577 301.<lb/> 3 .<lb/> THE ASSISTANT CONSERVATOR<lb/> OF FOREST, FOREST DEPARTMENT<lb/> TARIKERE SUB DIVISION<lb/> TARIKERE CHIKKAMAGALURU -577 228.<lb/> 4 .<lb/> THE RANGE FOREST OFFICER<lb/> FOREST DEPARTMENT<lb/> LAKKAVALLI RANGE<lb/> TARIKERE TALUK<lb/> CHIKKAMAGALURU<lb/> DISTRICT -577 228. …RESPONDENTS<lb/> (BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI. V. SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H.C, HCGP FOR R-1 TO R-4)<lb/> THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA<lb/> PRAYING TO QUASH THE ORDER DATED 15.12.2017<lb/> PASSED BY KARNATAKA LAND GRABBING PROHIBITION</titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	123<lb/> SPECIAL<lb/> COURTS,<lb/> BENGALURU<lb/> IN<lb/> L.G.C.(T)NO.1984/2017 (ANNEXURE-A)<lb/> IN W.P. NO.22837/2018:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>M/S VINAYAKA BUILDERS AND<lb/> DEVELOPERS, A REGISTERED<lb/> PARTNERSHIP FIRM, HAVING ITS<lb/> OFFICE AT 10/1 LAKSHMINARAYAN<lb/> COMPLEX, PALACE ROAD<lb/> VASANTHANAGAR<lb/> BENGALURU -560 052<lb/> REPRESENTED BY ITS<lb/> AUTHORIZED SIGNATORY<lb/> SRI. K.M. LINGARAJA.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>...PETITIONER<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	(BY SRI. CHANDAN K, ADVOCATE)<lb/> AND:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>THE STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> REPRESENTED BY ITS<lb/> CHIEF SECRETARY<lb/> REVENUE DEPARTMENT<lb/> M.S. BUILDING, 5TH FLOOR<lb/> BANGALORE -560 001. …RESPONDENT<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	(BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI. V. SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H.C, HCGP)<lb/>
	<note type="funding">THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA<lb/> PRAYING TO QUASH THE KARNATAKA LAND GRABBING<lb/> PROHIBITION ACT, 2011 (&apos;THE ACT&apos;) AND QUASH THE<lb/> PROCEEDINGS IN LGC (S) NO.1611 OF 2017 IN<lb/> KARNATAKA LAND GRABBING PROHIBITION SPECIAL<lb/> COURT, KANDAYA BHAVANA (&apos;THE SPECIAL COURT&apos;) 124<lb/> VIDE ANNEXURE-D IN SO FAR AS THE PETITIONER IS<lb/> CONCERNED.<lb/></note>

	<reference>IN W.P. NO.23435/2018:<lb/></reference>

	BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>1 .<lb/> SRI. B.S. PATIL<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	AGED ABOUT 63 YEARS<lb/> S/O SANGANAGOUDA PATIL.<lb/> 2 .<lb/> SMT. SHANTA PATIL<lb/> AGED ABOUT 59 YEARS<lb/> W/O B.S. PATIL.<lb/> NO 112, SECTOR II 2ND CROSS<lb/> 7TH MAIN, NOBO NAGAR<lb/> BANNERGHATTA ROAD<lb/> BENGALURU -560 076.<lb/> ...PETITIONERS<lb/> (BY SRI. RAMESHCHANDRA, ADVOCATE)<lb/> AND:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>1 .<lb/> THE STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> REPRESENTED BY ITS<lb/> CHIEF SECRETARY<lb/> REVENUE DEPARTMENT<lb/> M.S. BUILDING<lb/> BENGALURU -560 001<lb/> BENGALURU CITY.<lb/> 2 .<lb/> ASSISTANT EXECUTIVE ENGINEER<lb/> SWD, BBMP, BOMMANAHALLI<lb/> BENGALURU -560 068. …RESPONDENTS<lb/> (BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI. V. SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H.C, HCGP FOR R-1;<lb/> SRI. N.R. JAGADEESWARA, ADVOCATE FOR R-2)</titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	125<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA<lb/> PRAYING TO QUASH ANNEXURE-A ORDER DATED<lb/> 29.01.2018 TAKING COGNIZANCE IN L.G.C.NO. (G)<lb/> NO.131 OF 2018 AGAINST THE PETITIONER&apos;S ON THE<lb/> FILE<lb/> OF<lb/> THE<lb/> KARNATAKA<lb/> LAND<lb/> GRABBING<lb/> PROHIBITION SPECIAL COURT, BENGALURU.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	IN W.P. NO.23437/2018:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>SMT. UMA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 65 YEARS<lb/> W/O SUBRAMANYAM<lb/> NO.122B, 2ND CROSS<lb/> 7TH MAIN, NOBO NAGARA<lb/> BANNERGHATTA ROAD<lb/> BENGALURU -560 076.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>...PETITIONER<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	(BY SRI. RAMESHCHANDRA, ADVOCATE)<lb/> AND:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>1 .<lb/> THE STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> REPRESENTED BY ITS<lb/> CHIEF SECRETARY<lb/> REVENUE DEPARTMENT<lb/> M.S. BUILDING<lb/> BENGALURU -560 001<lb/> BENGALURU CITY.<lb/> 2 .<lb/> ASSISTANT EXECUTIVE ENGINEER<lb/> SWD, BBMO, BOMMANAHALLI<lb/> BENGALURU -560 068. …RESPONDENTS<lb/> (BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI. V. SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H.C, HCGP FOR R-1;<lb/> R-2 SERVED)</titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	126<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA<lb/> PRAYING TO QUASH ANNEXURE-A ORDER DATED<lb/> 29.01.2018 TAKING COGNIZANCE AGAINST THE<lb/> PETITIONER ON THE FILE OF THE KARNATAKA LAND<lb/> GRABBING<lb/> PROHIBITION<lb/> SPECIAL<lb/> COURT,<lb/> BENGALURU.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	IN W.P. NO.23819/2018:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>SRI. RAMARAYA NAYAK<lb/> AGED ABOUT 67 YEARS<lb/> S/O LATE K.N. NAYAK<lb/> NO.113, BHAGYASHREE NILAYA<lb/> 2ND CROSS, 7TH MAIN, SECTOR II<lb/> NOBO NAGARA, BANNERGHATTA<lb/> ROAD, BENGALURU -560 076.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>...PETITIONER<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	(BY SRI. RAMESHCHANDRA, ADVOCATE)<lb/> AND:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>1 .<lb/> THE STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> REPRESENTED BY ITS<lb/> CHIEF SECRETARY<lb/> REVENUE DEPARTMENT<lb/> M.S. BUILDING<lb/> BENGALURU -560 001<lb/> BENGALURU CITY.<lb/> 2 .<lb/> ASSISTANT EXECUTIVE ENGINNER<lb/> SWD, BBMO BOMMANAHALLI<lb/> BENGALURU -560 068,<lb/> …RESPONDENTS<lb/> (BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI. V. SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H.C, HCGP FOR R-1;<lb/> R-2 SERVED)<lb/> THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA 127<lb/> PRAYING TO QUASH ANNEXURE-A ORDER DATED<lb/> 29.01.2018 TAKING COGNIZANCE IN L.G.C.NO.(G)<lb/> NO.133 OF 2018 AGAINST THE PETITIONER ON THE<lb/> FILE<lb/> OF<lb/> THE<lb/> KARNATAKA<lb/> LAND<lb/> GRABBING<lb/> PROHIBITION SPECIAL COURT, BENGALURU.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	IN W.P. NO.25761/2018:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>G. LAKSHMANAPPA<lb/> S/O LATE GOVINDAPPA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 65 YEARS<lb/> R/A KADIVANAKATTE VILLAGE<lb/> HEBBALLI PSOT HOSADURGA<lb/> TLAUK, CHITRADURGA<lb/> DISTRICT -577 554.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>...PETITIONER<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	(BY SRI. VIRUPAKSHAIAH P.H, ADVOCATE)<lb/> AND:<lb/>
	<email>1 .<lb/></email>

	<note type="funding">STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> REPRESENTED BY<lb/> PRINCIPAL SECRETARY<lb/> REVENUE DEPARTMENT<lb/> M.S. BUILDING<lb/> BANGALORE -560 001.<lb/> 2 .<lb/> THE DEPUTY COMMISSIONER<lb/> CHITRADURGA DISTRICT<lb/> CHITRADURGA -577 501.<lb/> 3 .<lb/> THE ASSISTANT COMMISSIONER<lb/> HOSADURGA SUB DIVISION<lb/> CHITRADURGA -577 527.<lb/> 4 .<lb/> THE TAHSILDAR<lb/> HOSADURGA TALUK<lb/> CHITRADURGA -577 527. …RESPONDENTS 128<lb/> (BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI. V. SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H.C, HCGP)<lb/> THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA<lb/> PRAYING TO DECLARE THAT THE KARNATAKA LAND<lb/> GRABBING PROHIBITION ACT, 2011 (KARNAATAKA ACT<lb/> 38/2014) AS ULTRA VIRES THE CONSTITUTION OF<lb/> INDIA BEING VIOLATIVE OF ARTICLE 14, 20, 21 AND<lb/> 300-A AND / OR IN THE ALTERNATIVE.<lb/></note>

	<reference>IN W.P. NO.25768/2018:<lb/></reference>

	BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>SRI. MUTHAPPA B.K<lb/> S/O LATE KORAGAPPA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 66 YEARS<lb/> RESIDING AT PODAVADA VILLAGE<lb/> KARADA, NAPOKLU HOBLI<lb/> MADIKERI TALUK<lb/> KODAGU DISTRICT -574 214.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>...PETITIONER<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	(BY SRI. RANJAN KUMAR K, ADVOCATE)<lb/> AND:<lb/>
	<email>1 .<lb/></email>

	<note type="funding">THE REVENUE INSPECTOR<lb/> NAPOKLU HOBLI<lb/>REPRESENTED BY ITS<lb/> CHIEF SECRETARY<lb/> REVENUE DEPARTMENT<lb/> VIDHANA SOUDHA<lb/> BENGALURU -560 001. …RESPONDENTS<lb/> (BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI. V. SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H.C, HCGP FOR R-1 TO R-4)<lb/> THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA<lb/> PRAYING TO SET ASIDE THE ORDER DATED 05.01.2018<lb/> PASSED BY THE COURT OF THE LAND GRABBING<lb/> PROHIBITION<lb/> SPECIAL<lb/> COURT<lb/> IN<lb/> LGC<lb/> (T)<lb/> NO.1694/2017 (ANNEXURE-J).<lb/></note>

	IN W.P. NO.26054/2018:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>SRI. NAMBUDAMADA PRAKASH<lb/> S/O MACHAIAH<lb/> AGED ABOUT 51 YEARS<lb/> RESIDING AT V. BADAGA VILLAGE<lb/> VEERAJPET TALUK<lb/> KODAGU DISTRICT -571 218.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>...PETITIONER<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	(BY SRI. VENUGOPAL M.S, ADVOCATE)<lb/> AND:<lb/>
	<email>1 .<lb/></email>

	<note type="funding">THE STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> REPRESENTED BY ITS<lb/> CHIEF SECRETARY<lb/> VIDHANA SOUDHA<lb/> BENGALURU -560 001.<lb/> 2 .<lb/> THE PRINCIPAL SECRETARY<lb/> TO GOVERNMENT<lb/> REVENUE DEPARTMENT</note>

	130<lb/>
	<reference>M.S. BUILDING<lb/> DR. B.R. AMBEDKAR VEEDHI<lb/> BENGALURU -560 001.<lb/> 3 .<lb/> THE THASILDAR<lb/> VEERAJPET TALUK<lb/> KODAGU DISTRICT -571 218. …RESPONDENTS<lb/></reference>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>(BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI. V. SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H.C, HCGP FOR R-1 TO R-3)<lb/> THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA<lb/> PRAYING TO DECLARE THAT THE SECTION 4 AND 5 OF<lb/> THE KARNATAKA LAND GRABBING PROHIBITION ACT<lb/> 2011 AS UN CONSTITUTIONAL AND STRIKE DOWN THE<lb/> SAME VIDE ANNEXURE-A.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	IN W.P. NO.26481/2018:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>1.<lb/> SMT. K.S. KAVANA<lb/> W/O B/G. ANANDA PRAKASH<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>AGED ABOUT 36 YEARS<lb/> BADAVANADINNE, KOLUR VILLAGE<lb/> KENJIGE POST, BANAKAL HOBALI<lb/> MUDIGERE TALUK -577 132.<lb/> 2.<lb/> SRI. B.G. ANANDA PRAKASH<lb/> S/O B.P. GAPALAGOWDA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 43 YEARS<lb/> AGROCITIROST, BADAVANADINNE<lb/> KOLUR VILLAGE, KENJIGE POST<lb/> BANAKAL HOBALI<lb/> MUDIGERE TALUK -577 132<lb/> CHIKKAMAGALUR DISTRICT. …PETITIONERS<lb/> (BY SRI. SUYOG, ADVOCATE FOR<lb/> SRI. ARUNA SHYAM M, ADVOCATE)<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>MURTHY NAIKA<lb/> S/O SOMLA NAIKA<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	AGED ABOUT 50 YEARS.<lb/> 4 .<lb/> T.H. SIDDAIAH<lb/> S/O HANUMANTHAPPA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 60 YEARS.<lb/> ALL ARE AGRICULTURISTS AND<lb/> R/A KATHEHOLE VILLAGE<lb/> UDUVALLI POST, HIRIYUR TALUK<lb/> CHITRADURGA DISTRICT -577 598.<lb/> ...PETITIONERS<lb/> (BY SRI. VIRUPAKSHAIAH P.H, ADVOCATE)<lb/> AND:<lb/>
	<email>1 .<lb/></email>

	<note type="funding">STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> REPRESENTED BY PRINCIPAL<lb/> SECRETARY, REVENUE<lb/> DEPARTMENT, M.S. BUILDING<lb/> BANGALORE -560 001.<lb/> 2 .<lb/> THE DEPUTY COMMISSIONER<lb/> CHITRADURGA DISTRICT<lb/> CHITRADURGA -577 501.<lb/> 3 .<lb/> THE TAHSILDAR<lb/> HIRIYUR TALUK<lb/> CHITRADURGA DISTRICT -577 598. …RESPONDENTS<lb/> (BY SRI. PRABHILING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI. V. SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H.C, HCGP FOR R-1 TO 3)<lb/> THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA 133<lb/> PRAYING TO DECLARE THE KARNATAKA LAND<lb/> GRABBING PROHIBITION ACT, 2011 (KARNATAKA ACT<lb/> 38 OF 2014) AS ULTRA VIRES THE CONSTITUTION OF<lb/> INDIA BEING VIOLATIVE OF ARTICLE 14, 20, 21 AND<lb/> 300-A AND / OR IN THE ALTERNATIVE.<lb/></note>

	<reference>IN W.P. NO.26546/2018:<lb/></reference>

	BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>1 .<lb/> LAKKAMMA<lb/> W/O KARIYAPPA<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	AGED ABOUT 60 YEARS.<lb/> 2 .<lb/> HONNANAYAKA<lb/> S/O RANGANAYAKA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 80 YEARS.<lb/> BOTH THE PETITIONERS ARE<lb/> AGRICULTURISTS AND<lb/> R/A KATHEHOLE VILLAGE<lb/> UDUVALLI POST, HIRIYUR TALUK<lb/> CHITRADURGA DISTRICT -577 598.<lb/> ...PETITIONERS<lb/> (BY SRI. VIRUPAKSHAIAH P.H, ADVOCATE)<lb/> AND:<lb/>
	<email>1 .<lb/></email>

	<note type="funding">STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> REPRESENTED BY<lb/> PRINCIPAL SECRETARY<lb/> REVENUE DEPARTMENT<lb/> M.S. BUILDING<lb/> BANGALORE -560 001.<lb/> 2 .<lb/> THE DEPUTY COMMISSIONER<lb/> CHITRADURGA DISTRICT<lb/> CHITRADURGA -577 501.<lb/> 3 .<lb/> THE TAHSILDAR<lb/> HIRIYUR TALUK CHITRADURGA 134<lb/> DISTRICT -577 598. …RESPONDENTS<lb/> (BY SRI. PRABHILING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI. V. SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H.C, HCGP)<lb/> THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA<lb/> PRAYING TO DECLARE THE KARNATAKA LAND<lb/> GRABBING PROHIBITION ACT, 2011 (KARNATAKA ACT<lb/> 38 OF 2014) AS ULTRA VIRES THE CONSTITUTION OF<lb/> INDIA BEING VIOLATIVE OF ARTICLE 14, 20, 21, AND<lb/> 300-A AND / OR IN THE ALTERNATIVE.<lb/></note>

	<reference>IN W.P. NO.27912/2018:<lb/></reference>

	BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>1 .<lb/> RAMESH PADATHARE<lb/> S/O BAPURAO<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	AGED ABOUT 53 YEARS.<lb/> 2 .<lb/> ANNAPOORNA BAI<lb/> W/O LAKSHMANARAO PADTHARE<lb/> AGED ABOUT 39 YEARS.<lb/> PETITIONERS 1 AND 2 ARE<lb/> RESIDENTS OF GANDHINAGAR<lb/> VILLAGE, SUNNADAHALLI POST<lb/> BHADRAVATHI TALUK -577 302<lb/> SHIVAMOGGA DISTRICT.<lb/> ...PETITIONERS<lb/> (BY SRI. S V PRAKASH, ADVOCATE)<lb/> AND:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>1 .<lb/> STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> REVENUE DEPARTMENT<lb/> BY ITS PRINCIPAL SECRETARY<lb/> VIDHANA SOUDHA<lb/> DR. B.R. AMBEDKAR VEEDHI<lb/> BENGALURU -560 001.<lb/> REPRESENTED BY ITS<lb/> CHIEF SECRETARY<lb/> VIDHANA SOUDHA<lb/> BENGALURU -560 001.<lb/> 2 .<lb/> THE PRINCIPAL SECRETARY<lb/> TO GOVERNMENT, REVENUE<lb/> DEPARTMENT, M.S. BUILDING<lb/> DR. B.R. AMBEDKAR VEEDHI<lb/> BENGALURU -560 001.<lb/> 3 .<lb/> THE RANGE FOREST OFFICER<lb/> BALEHONNUR RANGE<lb/> NARASIMHARAJAPURA TALUK<lb/> CHIKKAMAGALUR DISTRICT -577 134. …RESPONDENTS<lb/> (BY SRI. PRABHILING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI. V. SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H.C, HCGP)<lb/> THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA<lb/> PRAYING TO DECLARE THAT THE KARNATKAK LAND<lb/> GRABBING<lb/> PROHIBITION<lb/> ACT<lb/> 2011<lb/> AS<lb/> UN<lb/> CONSTITUTIONAL AND STRICKE DOWN THE SAME<lb/> VIDE ANNEXURE-A.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	IN W.P. NO.28215/2018:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>SMT. JANAKI<lb/> W/O LATE KANTHU MUKHARI<lb/> AGED ABOUT 70 YEARS<lb/> RESIIDNG AT KUCHCHIGUDDE<lb/> DARKHASTH HOUSE, DOOR NO 1-18<lb/> SHIMANTHOORU VILLAGE,<lb/> MULKI HOBLI, MANGALORE -574 154.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>...PETITIONER<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	(BY SRI. VENUGOPAL M.S. ADVOCATE)<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>AT NO.1/8, ARTILLERY ROAD<lb/> ULSOOR, BENGALURU -560 008<lb/> REPRESENTED BY ITS MANAGING<lb/> DIRECTOR, MR.S. APPADURAI<lb/> AGED ABOUT 50 YEARS<lb/> S/O MR. SRI. RAM.<lb/> ...PETITIONER<lb/> (BY SRI. APPAIAH P.B, ADVOCATE)<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	AND:<lb/>
	<email>1 .<lb/></email>

	STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> REPRESENTED BY ITS<lb/> CHIEF SECRETARY<lb/> VIDHANA SOUDHA<lb/> DR. B.R. AMBEDKAR VEEDHI<lb/> BENGALURU -560 001.<lb/> 2 .<lb/> THE DEPUTY COMMISSIONER<lb/> CHIKMAGALUR DISTRICT<lb/> CHIKMAGALUR -577 101.<lb/> 3 .<lb/> THE TAHSILDAR<lb/> CHIKMAGALUR TALUK<lb/> CHIKMAGALUR DISTRICT<lb/> CHIKMAGALUR -577 101.<lb/> 4 .<lb/>
	<note type="funding">THE REVENUE INSPECTOR<lb/> JAGRA HOBLI, CHIKMAGALUR<lb/> TALUK, CHIKMAGALUR DISTRICT<lb/> CHIKMAGALUR -577 101. …RESPONDENTS<lb/> (BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI. V. SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H.C, HCGP)<lb/> THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA<lb/> PRAYING TO DECLARE THAT THE KARNATAKA LAND<lb/> GRABBING PROHIBITION ACT, 2011 (KARNATAKA ACT<lb/> NO.38 OF 2014) IN UN-CONSTITUTIONAL AS IT VILATES<lb/> THE PETITIONER&apos;S RIGHT TO A FREE AND FAIR TRIAL 139<lb/> GUARANTEED<lb/> UNDER<lb/> ARTICLE<lb/> 21<lb/> OF<lb/> THE<lb/> CONSTITUTION OF INDIA.<lb/></note>

	IN W.P. NO.29281/2018:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>ASHOK MADIVALA<lb/> S/O MANJAPPA<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	AGED ABOUT 58 YEARS<lb/> VENOOR HOBLI &amp; VILLAGE<lb/> BELTHANGADY TALUK<lb/> D.K. DISTRICT.<lb/> ...PETITIONER<lb/> (BY SRI. SHRIHARI K, ADVOCATE)<lb/> AND:<lb/>
	<email>1 .<lb/></email>

	<note type="funding">THE STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> DEPARTMENT OF REVENUE<lb/> REPRESENTED BY ITS SECRETARY<lb/> M.S. BUILDING, BANGALORE -560 001<lb/> REPRESETED BY ITS SECRETARY.<lb/> 2 .<lb/> THE TAHASILDAR<lb/> BELTHANGADY TALUK<lb/> D.K. DISTRICT -574 214.<lb/> 3 .<lb/> THE DEPUTY COMMISSIONER<lb/> D.K. DISTRICT -574 214. …RESPONDENTS<lb/> (BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI. V. SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H.C, HCGP FOR R-1 TO 3)<lb/> THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA<lb/> PRAYING TO DECLARE THE KARNATAKA LAND<lb/> GRABBING PROHIBITION ACT 2011 AS ULTRA VIRES<lb/> THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA.</note>

	140<lb/> IN W.P. NO.32121/2018:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>SRI. SATHISH<lb/> S/O LATE M. GURUSHANTAIAH<lb/> AGED ABOUT 38 YEARS<lb/> RESIDENT OF BEGUVALLI<lb/> TUDUR POST, TIRTHAHALLI TALUK<lb/> SHIVAMOGGA DISTRICT.<lb/> ...PETITIONER<lb/> (BY SRI. SAMMITH S, ADVOCATE FOR<lb/> SRI. SHIVANANDA, ADVOCATE )<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	AND:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>1 .<lb/> THE STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> REPRESETNED BY ITS<lb/> PRINCIPAL SECRETARY<lb/> REVENUE DEPARTMENT<lb/> VIKASA SOUDHA<lb/> BENGALURU -560 001.<lb/> 2 .<lb/> THE RANGE FOREST OFFICER<lb/> MANDAGADDE DIVISION/RANGE<lb/> MANDAGADDE AT &amp; POST -577 220<lb/> THIRTHAHALLI TALUK<lb/> SHIVAMOGGA DISTRICT<lb/> …RESPONDENTS<lb/> (BY SRI. PRBHULING K. NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI. V. SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H.C, HCGP)<lb/> THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA<lb/> PRAYING TO QUASH THE PROCEEDINGS IN CASE NO.<lb/> LGC (G) 2284/2017 ON THE FILE OF THE HON&apos;BLE<lb/> SPECIAL COURT FOR PREVENTION<lb/> OF LAND<lb/> GRABBING,<lb/> KANDAYA<lb/> BHAVAN,<lb/> BANGALORE<lb/> PRODUCED AT ANNEXURE-G AS AGAINST THE<lb/> PETITIONER HEREIN.</titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	141<lb/> IN W.P. NO.33339/2018:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>1 .<lb/> BORALINGAIAH<lb/> S/O RAMAIAH<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	AGED ABOUT 48 YEARS<lb/> 2 .<lb/> CHIKKANNA<lb/> S/O RANGAPPA,<lb/> AGED ABOUT 52 YEARS.<lb/> 3 .<lb/> NINGAPPA<lb/> S/O HANUMANTHAPPA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 50 YEARS.<lb/> 4 .<lb/> PATHAPPA<lb/> S/O UGRAPPA,<lb/> AGED ABOUT 60 YEARS.<lb/> 5 . KENCHAMMA<lb/> W/O LACHHAPPA,<lb/> AGED ABOUT 60 YEARS.<lb/> 6 .<lb/> MOHAN<lb/> S/O MANNANGATTAPPA,<lb/> AGED ABOUT 40 YEARS.<lb/> 7 .<lb/> MARIMUTTU<lb/> S/O MANNANGATTAPPA,<lb/> AGED ABOUT 55 YEARS.<lb/> 8 .<lb/> GANGAJJI<lb/> W/O LAXMIAH,<lb/> AGED ABOUT 75 YEARS.<lb/>
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>9 .<lb/> ANGAYAMMA<lb/> D/O MARIYAPPA,<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	AGED ABOUT 70 YEARS.<lb/> ALL THE PETITIONERS ARE<lb/> AGRICULTURIST<lb/> R/A KATHEHOLE VILLAGE<lb/> UDUVALLI POST, HIRIYUR<lb/> TALUK, CHITRADURGA<lb/> RESIDING AT DASALU KUNTE<lb/> VILLAGE, C.N. DURGA HOBLI<lb/> KORATIKERE TALUK<lb/> TUMKUR DISTRICT -572 129.<lb/> 2 .<lb/> MANJUNATHA<lb/> S/O NAGARAJ<lb/> AGED ABOUT 30 YEARS.<lb/> BOTH ARE RESIDING AT<lb/> DASALU KUNTE VILLAGE<lb/> C.N. DURGA HOBLI<lb/> KORATIKERE TALUK<lb/> TUMKUR DISTRICT -572 129.<lb/> ...PETITIONERS<lb/> (BY SRI. SRIKANTH N.V, ADVOCATE )<lb/> AND:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>1 .<lb/> STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> DEPARTMENT OF REVENUE<lb/> REPRESENTED BY ITS<lb/> PRINCIPAL SECRETARY<lb/> VIDHANA SOUDHA<lb/> BENGALURU -01.<lb/> 2 .<lb/> DEPUTY CONSERVATOR OF FOREST<lb/> FOREST DEPARTMENT<lb/> BHADRAVATHI DIVISION<lb/> BHADRAVATHI, SHIMOGGA<lb/> DISTRICT -577 301.<lb/> 3 .<lb/> ASSISTANT CONSERVATOR<lb/> OF FOREST, FOREST DEPARTMENT<lb/> TARIKERE SUB DIVISION<lb/> TARIKERE, CHIKMAGALORE<lb/> DISTRICT -577 528.</titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	144<lb/> 4 .<lb/>
	<note type="funding">THE RANGE FOREST OFFICER<lb/> FOREST DEPARTMENT<lb/> LAKKAVALLI RANGE<lb/> TARIKERE TALUK, CHIKMAGALORE<lb/> DISTRICT -577 528. …RESPONDENTS<lb/> (BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI. V. SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H.C, HCGP)<lb/> THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA<lb/> PRAYING TO QUASH THE NOTICES DATED 22.03.2018<lb/> ISSUED BY THE SPECIAL COURT CONSTITUTED UNDER<lb/> THE KARNATAKA LAND GRABBING PROHIBITION ACT,<lb/> 2011 INTIMATING THE PETITIONERS THAT THE SUIT IN<lb/> O.S. NO.132</note>

	<note type="copyright">/2016 PENDING ON THE IFLE OF CIVIL<lb/> JUDGE, TARIKERE FILED BY THE PETITIONERS<lb/> AGAINST THE R-2 TO 4 STANDS TRANSFERRED TO THE<lb/> SPECIAL COURT CONSTITUTED UNDER SECTION 20<lb/> KARNATAKA LAND GRABBING PROHIBITION ACT, 2011<lb/> AND NUMBERED AS L.G.C. (T)NO.1992/2017 AND THE<lb/> PETITIONERS ARE REQUIRED TO APPEAR BEFORE THE<lb/> SPECIAL COURT AS PER ANNEXURE-A AND B.<lb/></note>

	<reference>IN W.P. NO.34292/2018:<lb/></reference>

	BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>1 .<lb/> SRI. MAHABOOB SAB<lb/> S/O BELLARI VALISAB<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	AGED ABOUT 42 YEARS.<lb/> 2 .<lb/> SRI. ZAKRIYA<lb/> S/O ALLAHA BAKSHI,<lb/> AGED ABOUT 54 YEARS.<lb/> 3 .<lb/> SRI. NOORULLA<lb/> S/O ALLAHA BAKSHI,<lb/> AGED ABOUT 39 YEARS. 145<lb/> .<lb/> SRI. MAHABOOB SAB<lb/> S/O ALLAHA BAKSHI,<lb/> AGED ABOUT 40 YEARS.<lb/> .<lb/> MUJEEBUR REHAMAN<lb/> S/O JABBAR SAB<lb/> AGED ABOUT 44 YEARS.<lb/> .<lb/> NOOR AHMED<lb/> S/O RASOOL SAB<lb/> AGED ABOUT 45 YEARS.<lb/> .<lb/> SRI. HAJI ASADULLA<lb/> S/O KHASIM SAB<lb/> AGED ABOUT 52 YEARS.<lb/> .<lb/> SRI. IMTIYAZ<lb/> S/O SHA KHAN<lb/> AGED ABOUT 50 YEARS.<lb/> .<lb/> SRI. ABDULLA<lb/> S/O DODDA HONNUR SAB<lb/> AGED ABOUT 53 YEARS.<lb/> . FAZULLA<lb/> S/O ALLABAKSHI<lb/> AGED ABOUT 48 YEARS.<lb/> . NOOR AHMED<lb/> S/O ALLABAKSHI<lb/> AGED ABOUT 51 YEARS.<lb/> . SRI SUBAN SAB<lb/> S/O HUSEN SAB<lb/> AGED ABOUT 47 YEARS.<lb/> MAMADI<lb/> S/O NABI SAB<lb/> AGED ABOUT 38 YEARS.<lb/> . NAHEEM<lb/> S/O ABDUL REHAMAN<lb/> AGED ABOUT 45 YEARS. 146<lb/> 15 . KHADAR BASHA<lb/> S/O ABBAS SAB<lb/> AGED ABOUT 49 YEARS.<lb/> 16 . HAJI LAL KHAJAHUSSAN<lb/> S/O DODDA HUNNUR SAB<lb/> AGED ABOUT 52 YEARS.<lb/> 17 . SRI JEELAN<lb/> S/O RASOOL SAB<lb/> AGED ABOUT 58 YEARS.<lb/> 18 . SRI JABI<lb/> S/O BASAPUR RAZAK SAB<lb/> AGED ABOUT 48 YEARS.<lb/> 19 . MOHAMMED GHOUSE<lb/> S/O ALLAHA BAKSHI<lb/> AGED ABOUT 57 YEARS.<lb/> PETITIONERS 1 TO 19 ARE<lb/> R/AT SY. NO.32, RAMPUR<lb/> VILLAGE, MOLAKALMURU<lb/> TALUK, CHITRADURGA<lb/> DISTRICT -577 535.<lb/> ...PETITIONERS<lb/> (BY SRI. NAVEED AHMED, ADVOCATE)<lb/> AND:<lb/>
	<email>1 .<lb/></email>

	<note type="funding">STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> REP. BY ITS CHIEF SECRETARY<lb/> GOVERNMENT OF KARNATAKA<lb/> VIDHANA SOUDHA<lb/> BANGALORE -560 001.<lb/> 2 .<lb/> THE TAHSILDAR<lb/> MOLAKALMURU TALUK,<lb/> CHITRADURGA DISTRICT -577 535.</note>

	147<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>.<lb/> THE PANCHAYAT DEVELOPMENT<lb/> OFFICER (PDO), RAMPUR VILLAGE<lb/> MOALAKALMUR TALUK<lb/> CHITRADURGA -577 535.<lb/> .<lb/> DISTRICT WAKF OFFICER<lb/> CHITRADURGA DISTRICT<lb/> CHITRADURGA 577 501.<lb/> .<lb/> ABDUL BASHEER<lb/> S/O ABDUL AZEEZ<lb/> R/AT BB ROAD, 2ND WARD<lb/> RAMPUR VILLAGE, MOALAKALMUR<lb/> TALUKK CHITRADURGA -577 535.<lb/> .<lb/> R. NISAR AHMED<lb/> DEPUTY TAHSILDAR<lb/> RAMPUR VILLAGE, MOLAKALMUR<lb/> TALUK, CHITRADURGA<lb/> DISTRICT -57 535.<lb/> .<lb/> BELLARI VALISAB<lb/> S/O IBRAHIMSAB<lb/> AGE NO KNOWN.<lb/> .<lb/> MASTAN SAB<lb/> S/O BELLARI VALISAB<lb/> AGE NO KNOWN.<lb/> .<lb/> SAIFULLA<lb/> S/O MAHABOOB SAB<lb/> AGE NO KNOWN.<lb/> . MUJEEBUR REHAMAN<lb/> S/O JABBER SAB,<lb/> AGE NOT KNOWN.<lb/> . RAMESHA<lb/> S/O PARAMESHWARAPPA,<lb/> AGE NOT KNOWN.<lb/> . AZAM<lb/> REPRESENTED BY ITS PARTNER<lb/> B. M. KARUNESH<lb/> S/O LATE B MADAIAH<lb/> AGED ABOUT 54 YEARS<lb/> ...PETITIONER<lb/> (BY SRI. K. SHASHIKIRAN SHETTY, SR.CL.<lb/> FOR SMT. LATHA S. SHETTY, ADVOCATE)<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	AND:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>1.<lb/> THE STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> REPRESENTED BY ITS CHIEF SECRETARY<lb/> REVENUE DEPARTEMNT<lb/> M. S. BUILDING<lb/> BENGALURU-560001.<lb/> 2 .<lb/> THE TAHSILDAR<lb/> BENGALURU NORTH (ADDITIONAL) TALUK,<lb/> BENGALURU-560066<lb/> 3 .<lb/> K. H, CHANDRASHEKAR,<lb/> S/O LATE HANUMANTHARAYAPPA,<lb/> AGED ABOUT 53 YEARS,<lb/> R/O KOLIPURA VILLAGE<lb/> JALA HALI<lb/> B. K. HALLI POST,<lb/> BENGALURU NORTH(ADDL) TALUK<lb/> BENGALURU-562149<lb/> 4 .<lb/> S. RAMACHANDRAIAH,<lb/> S/O LATE S MUNISWAMAPPA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 55 YEARS,<lb/> R/O UTTANAHALLI VILLAGE</titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	151<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>JALA HOBLI CHIKKAJALA POST<lb/> BENGALURU NORTH(ADDL) TALUK<lb/> BENGALURU-562157<lb/> 5 .<lb/> S. L. NATARAJ<lb/> S/O S N LAKSHMINARAYANA DIXHIT<lb/> SIR M VISVESWARAIAH HOUSE<lb/> BUILDING CO-OPERATIVE SOCIETY LIMITED<lb/> NO.35, FIRST FLOOR 5TH A CROSS<lb/> A SECTOR, YELAHANAK NEW TOWN<lb/> BENGALURU-560064 …RESPONDENTS<lb/> (BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI.V SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H C., HCGP FOR R-1 AND R-2;<lb/> BY SRI. B.S. ANILKUMAR, ADVOCATE FOR R-3;<lb/> R-4 SERVED)<lb/> THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA<lb/> PRAYING TO QUASH THE PROCEEDINGS PENDING<lb/> BEFORE EHT LAND GRABBING SPECIAL COURT IN<lb/> PROCEEDINGS NO. LGC(P) NO.310/ 2017 AS AGAINST<lb/> THE PETITIONER FOR OFFENCE PUNISHABLE UNDER<lb/> SECTION 4[3] OF THE KARNATAKA LAND GRABBING<lb/> PHOHIBITION ACT 2011 [ANNEXURE-B] AND ETC.<lb/> IN W.P. NO. 36459/2018:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>1 .<lb/> SRI C. GOVARDHAN REDDY<lb/> S/O. C. CHANDRA SEKHAR REDDY,<lb/> AGRICULTURIST,<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	AGED ABOUT 42 YEARS<lb/> 2 .<lb/>
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>SRI C. JANARDHAN REDDY<lb/> S/O. C. CHANDRA SEKHAR REDDY,<lb/> AGRICULTURIST,<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	AGED ABOUT 44 YEARS 152<lb/> BOTH ARE RESIDENTS OF<lb/> KOLAGAL VILLAGE,<lb/> BELLARY TALUK &amp; DISTRICT-583 101<lb/> ...PETITIONERS<lb/> (BY SRI. RAGHUPATHY T. N., ADVOCATE)<lb/> AND:<lb/>
	<email>1 .<lb/></email>

	<note type="funding">STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> REPRESENTED BY ITS<lb/> PRINCIPAL SECRETARY,<lb/> RENENUE DEPARTMENT,<lb/> VIDHANA SOUDHA,<lb/> AMBEDKAR VEEDHI,<lb/> BENGALURU-560 001.<lb/> 2 .<lb/> THE DEPUTY COMMISSIONER<lb/> OFFICE OF THE DEPUTY COMMISSIONER,<lb/> STATION ROAD,<lb/> BELLARY-583 101.<lb/> 3 .<lb/> THE TAHSILDAR<lb/> OFFICE OF THE TAHSILDAR,<lb/> STATION ROAD,<lb/> BELLARY-583 101. …RESPONDENTS<lb/> (BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI.V SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H C., HCGP)<lb/> THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA<lb/> PRAYING TO QUASH THE PROCEEDINGS IN NO. LGC[T]<lb/> NO.319/2018<lb/> BEFORE<lb/> THE<lb/> KARNATAKA<lb/> LAND<lb/> GRABBING PROHIBITION SPECIAL COURT INITIATED AS<lb/> PER ANNEXURE-F AND ETC.<lb/></note>

	IN W.P. NO. 36539/2018:<lb/> BETWEEN: 153<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>SMT.PARVATHI<lb/> W/O LATE MUTHU MOGERTHI<lb/> AGED ABOUT 49 YEARS,<lb/> OCC: AGRICULTURE<lb/> R/AT DEVALGUNDA VILLAGE,<lb/> KUNDAPURA TALUK,<lb/> UDUPI DISTRICT<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>...PETITIONER<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	(BY SRI. VIGHNESHWAR S SHASTRI, ADVOCATE )<lb/> AND:<lb/>
	<email>1 .<lb/></email>

	<note type="funding">STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> REPRESENTED BY ITS SECRETARY<lb/> DEPARTMENT OF REVENUE,<lb/> M S BUILDING,<lb/> BANGALORE-560001<lb/> 2 .<lb/> DEPUTY COMMISSIONER<lb/> UDUPI DISTRICT,<lb/> UDUPI-576101<lb/> 3 .<lb/> TAHASILDAR<lb/> KUNDAPURA TALUK<lb/> UDUPI DISTRICT-576217 …RESPONDENTS<lb/> (BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI.V SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H C., HCGP)<lb/> THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA<lb/> PRAYING TO QUASH THE PROCEEDINGS IN CASE NO.<lb/> LGC(G) NO. 1427/2017 AND ORDER DATED 18.07.2018<lb/> ON THE FILE OF THE HON&apos;BLE SPECIAL COURT FOR<lb/> PREVENTION OF LAND GRABBING, KANDAYA BHAVAN,<lb/> BANGALORE, AS AGAINST THE PETITIONER HEREIN AS<lb/> PER ANNEXURE-D AND ETC.</note>

	154<lb/> IN W.P. NO. 36737/2018:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>N. B. POOVIAH<lb/> S/O. BOPAIAH<lb/> AGED 43 YEARS,<lb/> KANDANGALA VILLAGE,<lb/> VIRAJPET TALUK<lb/> KODAGU DISTRICT-571 218<lb/> ...PETITIONER<lb/> (BY SRI. BASAVARAJ S, ADVOCATE )<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	AND:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>1 .<lb/> THE STATE OF KARANATAKA<lb/> REPRESENTED BY ITS CHIEF SECRETARY<lb/> REVENUE DEPARTMENT<lb/> M. S. BUILDING<lb/> BENGALURU-560 001<lb/> 2 .<lb/> THE RANGE FOREST OFFICER,<lb/> VIRAJPET,<lb/> KODAGU DISTRICT<lb/> MADIKERI-571 218<lb/> 3 .<lb/> DEPUTY CONSERVATOR OF FOREST<lb/> KODAGU DISTRICT<lb/> MADIKERI-571 218<lb/> 4 .<lb/> TAHSILDAR<lb/> VIRAJPET TALUK<lb/> KODAGU DISTRICT<lb/> MADIKERI-571 218 …RESPONDENTS<lb/> (BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI.V SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H C., HCGP)<lb/> THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA</titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	155<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>PRAYING TO QUASH THE CRIMINAL PROCEEDINGS<lb/> PENDING BEFORE THE LAND GRABBING SPECIAL<lb/> COURT IN PROCEEDINGS 273/2018 AGAINST THE<lb/> PETITIONER UNDER SECTION 9 OF THE KARNATAKA<lb/> LAND GRABBING PROHIBITION ACT 2011 VIDE ANNX-B<lb/> AND ETC.<lb/> IN W.P. NO. 36863/2018:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/> 1 .<lb/> SMT. PARVATHI NACHIAPPAN<lb/> W/O LATE R NACHIAPPAN<lb/> AGED ABOUT 82 YEARS<lb/> OCCUPATION: HOUSEHOLD<lb/> R/AT NO.7, ABHISHEK APARTMENTS<lb/> GANGAI STREET, BESENT NAGAR,<lb/> CHENNAI-600 090.<lb/> (NOTE: SENIOR CITIZEN BENEFIT<lb/> NOT CLAIMED BY THE PETITIONER)<lb/> 2 .<lb/> SRI. NACHIAPPAN RAMANATHAN,<lb/> S/O LATE RAMANATHAN NACHIAPPAN<lb/> AGED ABOUT 30 YEARS,<lb/> OCC: AGRICULTURE,<lb/> R/AT KUMARAN ESTATE<lb/> HAKATTHUR, MADIKERI TALUK,<lb/> KODAGU DISTRICT-571 201.<lb/> ...PETITIONERS<lb/> (BY SRI. PRASANNA V. R., ADVOCATE)<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	AND:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>1 .<lb/> STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> REPRESENTED BY ITS CHIEF SECRETARY<lb/> VIDHANA SOUDHA<lb/> BENGALURU-560 001.<lb/> 2 .<lb/> THE PRINCIAL SECRETARY TO GOVERNMENT<lb/> REVENUE DEPARTMENT, M S BUILDING,<lb/> DR.B. R. AMBEDKAR VEEDHI,<lb/> BENGALURU-560 001.</titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	156<lb/> 3 .<lb/> THE TAHSILDAR<lb/> MADIKERI TALUK,<lb/> MADIKERI , KODAGU DISTRICT-571 201. …RESPONDENTS<lb/> (BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI.V SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H C., HCGP)<lb/>
	<note type="funding">THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA<lb/> PRAYING TO QUASH THE ENTIRE PROCEEDINGS IN<lb/> CASE NO. LGC(G) NO. 265/2018 ON THE FILE OF THE<lb/> SPECIAL COURT-I, BENGALURU, AS NOTIFIED IN<lb/> NOTIFICATION DATED 17.03.2018, VIDE ANNEXURE-B<lb/> AND ETC.<lb/></note>

	IN W.P. NO. 39179/2018:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>SMT K. A. MUTHAVVA<lb/> W/O LATE SRI K. M. ACHAIAH,<lb/> AGED ABOUT 76 YEARS,<lb/> W/O LATE K. M. ACHAIAH,<lb/> R/OF BENGUR-IVOTHOKLU VILLAGE,<lb/> MADIKERI TALUK,<lb/> KODAGU DISTRICT,<lb/> NOW RESIDING AT<lb/> PENSION LANE, MADIKERI TOWN,<lb/> KODAGU DISTRICT-571201<lb/> ...PETITIONER<lb/> (BY SRI. C.R. GOPALASWAMY, ADVOCATE)<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	AND:<lb/>
	<email>1 .<lb/></email>

	<note type="funding">STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> MINISTRY OF URBAN &amp; RURAL DEVELOPMENT,<lb/> REP BY ITS CHIEF SECRETARY,<lb/> VIKASA SOUDHA,<lb/> AMBEDKAR VEEDHI,<lb/> BENGALURU-560001 157<lb/> 2 .<lb/> THE TAHSILDAR<lb/> MADIKERI TALUK,<lb/> KODAGU DISTRICT-571201<lb/> 3 .<lb/> THE COMMISSIONER<lb/> CITY MUNCIPAL COUNCIL,<lb/> MADIKERI,<lb/> KODAGU DISTRICT-571201<lb/> …RESPONDENTS<lb/> (BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI.V SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H C., HCGP)<lb/> THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA PRAYING TO<lb/> QUASH THE IMPUGNED ORDER DATED 22.12.2017<lb/> PASSED BY THE KARNATAKA LAND GRABBING<lb/> PROHIBITION SPECIAL COURTS AT BENGALURU VIDE<lb/> NO. LGC (T) NO. LGC(T) NO. 1235/ 2017, O.S. NO.<lb/> 98/2014 PRODUCED AT ANNEXURE-B AND ETC.<lb/></note>

	IN W.P. NO. 40311/2018:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>SRI Y.N. PADMANABHA<lb/> SON OF Y. D. NANJEGOWDA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 50 YEARS,<lb/> RESIDENT OF LINGAPURA VILLAGE<lb/> AREHALLI HOBLI, BELUR TALUK -573121.<lb/> REPRESENTED BY GPA HOLDER<lb/> SRI Y. N. MALLESHGOWDA<lb/> SON OF Y. D. NANJEGOWDA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 60 YEARS<lb/> RESIDENT OF LINGAPURA VILLAGE<lb/> AREHALLI HOBLI,<lb/> BELUR TALUK -573121<lb/> ...PETITIONER 158<lb/> (BY SRI. SAMMITH S, ADVOCATE FOR<lb/> SRI. SHIVANANDA S, ADVOCATE)<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	AND:<lb/>
	<email>1 .<lb/></email>

	<note type="funding">THE STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> REPRESENTED BY ITS PRINCIPAL SECRETARY<lb/> REVENUE DEPARTMENT,<lb/> VIKASA SOUDHA<lb/> BENGALURU -560001<lb/> 2 .<lb/> THE DEPUTY COMMISSIONER<lb/> HASSAN DISTRICT, HASSAN -573219<lb/> 3 .<lb/> THE ASSISTANT COMMISSONER<lb/> SAKALESHPURA SUB DIVISION<lb/> SAKALESHPURA -573134<lb/> 4 .<lb/> THE TAHSILDAR<lb/> SAKALESHPURA TALUK<lb/> SAKALESHPURA -573134 …RESPONDENTS<lb/> (BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI.V SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H C., HCGP)<lb/> THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA<lb/> PRAYING TO QUASH THE ORDER PASSED IN CASE NO.<lb/> LGC (T) 110/2018, DATED 10.07.2018 ON THE FILE OF<lb/> THE HON&apos;BLE KARNATAKA LAND GRABBING<lb/> PROHIBITION SPECIAL COURTS AT BENGALURU AT<lb/> ANNEX-G AND ETC.<lb/></note>

	<reference>IN W.P. NO. 41277/2018:<lb/></reference>

	BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>SRI. KESHAVAMURTHY K. C.</docAuthor>
	</byline>

	159<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>S/O SRI. CHIKKAPUTTAPPA,<lb/> R/AT NO.86, K.NARAYANAPURA,<lb/> KOTHANUR POST, K.R.PURAM HOBLI,<lb/> BENGALURU EAST TALUK,<lb/> BENGALURU-560077<lb/> ...PETITIONER<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	(BY SRI. H.R. ANANTHA KRISHNAMURTHY, ADVOCATE )<lb/> AND:<lb/>
	<keyword>THE TAHASILDAR<lb/> BENGALURU EAST TALUK,<lb/> BENGALURU-560 077. …RESPONDENT<lb/></keyword>

	(BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI.V SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H C., HCGP)<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION PRAYING TO<lb/> QUASH THE IMPUGNED NOTICE DATED 21.08.2017<lb/> ISSUED BY THE R-1 VIDE ANNX-A AND ETC.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<reference>IN W.P. NO. 43275/2018:<lb/></reference>

	BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>S.L. NATARAJ<lb/> S/O S.N.LAKSHMINARAYANA DIXIT,<lb/> AGED 52 YEARS,<lb/> SRI M.VISVESWRAIAH HOUSE<lb/> BUILDING CO-OPERATIVE SOCIETY LIMITED,<lb/> NO.35, FIRST FLOOR, 5TH &apos;A&apos; CROSS,<lb/> &apos;A&apos; SECTOR, YELAHANKA NEW TOWN,<lb/> BANGALORE-64.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>...PETITIONER<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	(BY SRI. S. K. ACHARYA, ADVOCATE ) 160<lb/> AND:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>1 .<lb/> STATE OF KARNATAKA,<lb/> REP. BY ITS CHIEF SECRETARY,<lb/> VIDHANA SOUDHA,<lb/> BANGALORE-560001.<lb/> 2 .<lb/> THE PRINCIPAL SECRETARY TO GOVERNMENT<lb/> REVENUE DEPARTMENT,<lb/> M.S.BUILDING,<lb/> DR.B.R.AMBEDKAR VEDHI,<lb/> BANGALORE-560001.<lb/> 3 .<lb/> K. H. CHANDRASHEKAR<lb/> S/O LATE HANUMANTHARAYAPPA,<lb/> AGED ABOUT 54 YEARS,<lb/> R/O KOLIPURA VILLAGE,<lb/> JALA HOBLI,<lb/> B.K.HALLI POST,<lb/> BANGALORE NORTH (ADDL.) TALUK,<lb/> BANGALORE-562149.<lb/> 4 .<lb/> S. RAMACHANDRAIAH<lb/> S/O LATE S.MUNISWAMAPPA,<lb/> AGED ABOUT 56 YEARS,<lb/> R/O UTTANAHALLI VILLAGE,<lb/> JALA HOBLI,<lb/> CHIKKAJALA POST,<lb/> BANGALORE NORTH (ADDL.) TALUK,<lb/> BANGALORE-562157.<lb/> …RESPONDENTS<lb/> (BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI.V SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H C., HCGP FOR R1 AND R2;<lb/> BY SRI. B.S. ANILKUMAR, ADVOCATE FOR R3;<lb/> R4-SERVED)<lb/> THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION PRAYING TO<lb/> QUASH THE IMPUGNED PROCESS/ ORDER DATED<lb/> 08.03.2018 PASSED IN LGC (P) 310/2017 ON THE FILE<lb/> OF THE KARNATAKA LAND GRABBING PROHIBITION</titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	161<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>SPECIAL COURT, BENGALURU VIDE ANNEXURE-B AND<lb/> TO DECLARE THE SAME AS ILLEGAL AND ETC.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	IN W.P. NO. 43352/2018:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>SRI PADMANABHAIAH @ PADMANABHACHARI<lb/> S/O SRI NARAYANASWAMY,<lb/> AGED ABOUT 50 YEARS,<lb/> R/O MYLANAHALLI HOBLI,<lb/> JALA HOBLI,<lb/> BENGALURU NORTH (ADNL) TALUK-560064<lb/> ...PETITIONER<lb/> (BY SRI. SAMPATH BAPAT, ADVOCATE)<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	AND:<lb/>
	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 .<lb/> STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> DEPT. OF REVENUE,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>AMBEDKAR VEEDHI,<lb/> VIDHANA SOUDHA,<lb/> BENGALURU-560001.<lb/></address>

	<note type="funding">REP. BY ITS SECRETARY.<lb/> 2 .<lb/> THE DEPUTY COMMISSIONER<lb/> BENGALURU URBAN DISTRICT,<lb/> BENGALURU-560064.<lb/> 3 .<lb/> THE TAHSILDAR,<lb/> BENGALURU NORTH (ADNL) TALUK,<lb/> MINI VIDHANA SOUDHA,<lb/> BENGALURU URBAN DISTRICT. …RESPONDENTS<lb/> (BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI.V SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H C., HCGP)<lb/> THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION PRAYING TO<lb/> QUASH THE PROCEEDINGS INITIATED AGAINST THE<lb/> PETITIONER IN CASE NO.L.G.C.[G] NO. 233/2018</note>

	162<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>DATED 05.01.2018 VIDE ANNEXURE-K PENDING ON<lb/> THE<lb/> FILE<lb/> OF<lb/> KARNATAKA<lb/> LAND<lb/> GRABBING<lb/> PROHIBITION SPECIAL COURT AND ETC.<lb/> IN W.P. NO.45660/2018:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/> 1.<lb/> SRI D PUTTARAJU<lb/> S/O LATE THIMME GOWDA @ UGRE GOWDA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 70 YEARS<lb/> 2.<lb/> SRI D T SHANMUKHE GOWDA<lb/> S/O LATE THIMMEGOWDA @ UGRE GOWDA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 48 YEARS<lb/> 3.<lb/> SRI VENKATESH<lb/> S/O LATE MUDDE GOWDA,<lb/> AGED ABOUT 50 YEARS<lb/> 4.<lb/> SRI SREENIVAS<lb/> S/O LATE MUDDE GOWDA,<lb/> AGED ABOUT 60 YEARS<lb/> 5.<lb/> SRI NAGESH<lb/> S/O LATE NANJE GOWDA,<lb/> AGED ABOUT 40 YEARS<lb/> 6.<lb/> SRI BALAKRISHNA<lb/> S/O LATE NANJE GOWDA,<lb/> AGED ABOUT 50 YEARS<lb/> 7.<lb/> SRI DEVARAJ<lb/> S/O KARIYAPPA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 50 YEARS<lb/> 8.<lb/> SRI UMESH<lb/> S/O PUTTARAJU<lb/> AGED ABOUT 40 YEARS<lb/> PETITIONERS 1-8 ARE ALL RESIDENTS OF<lb/> DODDENAHALLI VILLAGE<lb/> GONDANAHALLI POST 163<lb/> BINDIGANAVILE POST<lb/> NAGAMANGALA TALUK<lb/> MANDYA DISTRICT -571 432.<lb/> 9.<lb/> SRI D T LINGARAME GOWDA<lb/> S/O LATE THIMME GOWDA @ UGRE GOWDA,<lb/> R/AT BALEMARANAHALLI VILLAGE<lb/> NOW CALLED AS LAKSHMISAGARA VILLAGE,<lb/> DODDAGUPPENAHALLI POST,<lb/> KASABA HOBLI,<lb/> BHADRAVATHI TALUK,<lb/> SHIVAMOGGA DISTRICT-577 229.<lb/> ...PETITIONERS<lb/> (BY SRI. K.N. PUTTEGOWDA, ADVOCATE)<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	AND:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>1.<lb/> STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> REP. BY PRINCIPAL SECRETARY TO<lb/> GOVERNMENT,<lb/> DEPARTMENT OF REVENUE<lb/> M S BUILDING,<lb/> DR B.R.AMBEDKAR VEEDHI,<lb/> BENGALURU -560 001.<lb/> 2.<lb/> STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> BY ITS PRINCIPAL SECRETARY TO GOVERNMENT,<lb/> DEPARTMENT OF ANIMAL HUSBANDRY<lb/> M.S.BUILDING,<lb/> DR.B.R AMBEDKAR VEEDHI,<lb/> BENGALURU-560 001.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	3.<lb/> THE DEPUTY DIRECTOR<lb/>
	<byline>
	<affiliation>AMRUTH MAHAL BREEDING CENTER,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>AJJAMPURA,<lb/> TARIKERE TALUK,<lb/> CHICKKAMAGALURU DISTRICT-577 228.<lb/> 4.<lb/> THE TAHSHILDAR<lb/> NAGAMANGALA TALUK,<lb/> NAGAMANGALA,<lb/> MANDYA DISTRICT -571 432.</address>

	164<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>….RESPONDENTS<lb/> (BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI. V SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA HC, HCGP FOR R-1 TO R-4)<lb/> THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLE<lb/> 226 &amp; 227 OF CONSTITUTION OF INDIA PRAYING TO<lb/> DECLARE THAT THE KARNATAKA LAND GRABBING<lb/> PROHIBITION ACT, 2011 (KARNATAKA ACT, 38/2014) AS<lb/> ULTRA VIRES OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA BEING<lb/> VIOLATIVE OF ARTICLES 14, 20, 21 &amp; 300-A; WHICH IS<lb/> MARKED AS ANNEXURE-A.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	IN W.P. NO. 47066/2018:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<keyword>SRI SHADAKSHARI<lb/> MANAGING DIRECTOR,<lb/> RAMANASHREE GROUP,<lb/> RAJARAM MOHAN ROY ROAD,<lb/> BENGALURU-25<lb/> ...PETITIONER<lb/></keyword>

	(BY SRI. H. R. ANANTHAKRISHNAMURTHY, ADVOCATE )<lb/> AND:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>THE ASSISTANT EXECUTIVE ENGINEER<lb/> STROM WATER DRAIN SUB-DIVISION,<lb/> YELAHANKA ZONE, BBMP,<lb/> BENGALURU-560 064 …RESPONDENT<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	(BY SRI. I.G. GACHCHINAMATH, ADVOCATE )<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION PRAYING TO<lb/> (i)QUASH THE CASE ORDER IN LGC(S) NO.30/2017<lb/> PENDING BEFORE THE HON&apos;BLE LAND GRABBING<lb/> SPECIAL COURT (CH-2) PRODUCED VIDE ANNEXURE-<lb/>H; (ii) FOR COSTS AND ANY OTHER RELIEF AS THIS<lb/> HON&apos;BLE COURT MAY DEEM FIT AND ETC.</titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	165<lb/> IN W.P. NO. 47540/2018:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>SRI. BASAVARAJAPPA<lb/> SON OF LATE SUBBANNA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 50 YEARS<lb/> RESIDING AT HANAGAWADI VILLAGE,<lb/> SASVEHALLI HOBLI<lb/> HONNALI TALUK<lb/> DAVANAGERE DISRTRICT<lb/> PIN CODE-577 224.<lb/> ...PETITIONER<lb/> (BY SRI. SIDDAMALLAPPA P. M., ADVOCATE)<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	AND:<lb/>
	<email>1 .<lb/></email>

	<note type="funding">STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> REPRESENTED BY ITS CHIEF SECRETARY<lb/> VIDHANA SOUDHA<lb/> BENGALURU-560 001.<lb/> 2 .<lb/> THE PRINCIPAL SECRETARY TO GOVERNMENT<lb/> REVENUE DEPARTMENT<lb/> M S BUILDING<lb/> DR B. R. AMBEDKAR VEEDHI<lb/> BENGALURU-560 001<lb/> 3 .<lb/> THE TAHSILDAR<lb/> HONNALI TALUK<lb/> DAVANAGERE DISTRICT,<lb/> PIN CODE-577 201. …RESPONDENTS<lb/> (BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI.V SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H C., HCGP)<lb/> THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION PRAYING TO 166<lb/> QUASH THE ENTIRE PROCEEDING IN CASE NO. LGC(G)<lb/> NO. 837/2018 ON THE FILE OF THE SPECIAL COURT-I,<lb/> BENGALURU AS SUMMONS NOTICE DATED 01.08.2018<lb/> VIDE ANNX-B AND ETC.<lb/></note>

	<reference>IN W.P. NO. 47543/2018:<lb/></reference>

	BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>SRI. VEERESH RAO<lb/> SON OF LATE LAKSHMANA RAO<lb/> AGED ABOUT 48 YEARS<lb/> RESIDING AT HANAGAWADI VILLAGE<lb/> SASVEHALLI HOBLI<lb/> HONNALI TALUK<lb/> DAVANAGERE DISTRICT<lb/> PIN CODE-577 224<lb/> ...PETITIONER<lb/> (BY SRI. SIDDAMALLAPPA P. M., ADVOCATE)<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	AND:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>1 .<lb/> STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> REPRESENTED BY ITS CHIEF SECRETARY<lb/> VIDHANA SOUDHA<lb/> BENGALURU-560 001<lb/> 2 .<lb/> THE PRINCIPAL SECRETARY TO GOVERNMENT<lb/> REVENUE DEPARTMENT<lb/> M. S. BUILDING<lb/> DR. B. R. AMBEDKAR VEEDHI<lb/> BENGALURU-560 001<lb/> 3 .<lb/> THE TAHSILDAR<lb/> HONNALI TALUK<lb/> DAVANAGERE DISTRICT<lb/> PIN CODE-577 201 …RESPONDENTS<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	(BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI.V SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H C., HCGP) 167<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION PRAYING TO<lb/> QUASH THE ENTIRE PROCEEDINGS IN CASE NO. LGC<lb/> [G] NO. 835/2018 ON THE FILE OF THE SPECIAL<lb/> COURT-I, BENGALURU AS SUMMONS NOTICE DTD:<lb/> 01.08.2018 VIDE ANNEXURE-B AND ETC.<lb/> IN W.P. NO. 47827/2018:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/> NANJUNDAPPA<lb/> S/O MALUR VENKATAPPA,<lb/> AGED ABOUT 58 YEARS,<lb/> R/AT RENUKALAHALLI VILLAGE,<lb/> MANDIKAL HOBLI,<lb/> CHIKKABALLAPURA TALUK,<lb/> CHIKKABALLAPURA DISTRICT-562104<lb/> ...PETITIONER<lb/> (BY SRI. SHARATH S GOWDA, ADVOCATE)<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	AND:<lb/>
	<email>1 .<lb/></email>

	<note type="funding">THE STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> DEPARTMENT OF REVENUE,<lb/> M.S BUILDING,<lb/> BANGALORE-560001<lb/> REPRESENTED BY ITS PRINCIPAL SECRETARY<lb/> 2 .<lb/> THE TAHSHILDAR<lb/> CHIKKABALLAPURA TALUK,<lb/> CHIKKABALLAPURA DISTRICT-562101<lb/> 3 .<lb/> MOHAMMED HUSSAIN<lb/> S/O FAKRUDDIN SAB,<lb/> AGED ABOUT 58 YEARS,<lb/> R/AT GUDIBANDE TOWN,<lb/> 3RD WARD, &apos;A&apos; BLOCK,<lb/> VINAYAKA NAGAR,<lb/> GUDIBANDE TALUK,<lb/> CHIKKABALLAPURA DISTRICT-561209 …RESPONDENTS 168<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>(BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI.V SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H C., HCGP FOR R-1 &amp; R-2;<lb/> SRI. M. ASWATHANARAYANA REDDY, ADVOCATE<lb/> FOR R-3)<lb/> THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION PRAYING TO<lb/> QUASH THE PROCEEDINGS INITIATED BEFORE THE<lb/> KARNATAKA LAND GRABBING PROHIBITION SPECIAL<lb/> COURT IN LGC [P] NO. 2132/2017 VIDE ANNEXURE-A<lb/> AND ETC.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	IN W.P. NO. 47841/2018:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>THE ADARSHA EDUCATION SOCIETY<lb/> SAUNDATTI TALUK RAIBAGH<lb/> BELAGAVI DISTRICT<lb/> BY ITS CHAIRMAN<lb/> IRAGOWDA PATIL<lb/> S/O DHULA GOWDA PATIL<lb/> ...PETITIONER<lb/> (BY SRI. K. R. SREENIVASA PATAVARDHAN, ADVOCATE)<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	AND:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>1 .<lb/> THE STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> REPRESENTED BY ITS SECRETARY<lb/> REVENUE DEPARTMENT<lb/> M. S. BUILDING,<lb/> BENGALURU-560 001<lb/> 2 .<lb/> THE TAHSILDAR<lb/> RAIBAGH<lb/> RAIBAGH TALUK<lb/> BELGAVI DISTRICT-590 001 …RESPONDENTS<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	(BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI.V SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> IN W.P. NO. 50668/2018:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>B. T. SANJEEVAIAH<lb/> S/O LATE THIMMEGOWDA,<lb/> AGED ABOUT 65 YEARS,<lb/> RESIDING AT BILLINA KOTE VILLAGE,<lb/> SOMPURA HOBLI,<lb/> NELAMANGALA TALUK,<lb/> BANGALORE RURAL DISTRICT-562123<lb/> ...PETITIONER<lb/> (BY SRI. LOKESH S. G., ADVOCATE)<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	AND:<lb/>
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>1 .<lb/> B S JAYARAM<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>S/O LATE SOMEGOWDA,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>BILLINAKOTE SOMPURA HOBLI,<lb/> NELAMANGALA TALUK,<lb/> BANGALORE RURAL DISTRICT-562123<lb/> 2 .<lb/> THE TAHASILDAR<lb/> NELAMANGALA TALUK,<lb/> BANGALORE RURAL DISTRICT-562123<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>3 .<lb/> THE PANCHAYATH DEVELOPMENT OFFICER<lb/> KULUVANAHALLI PANCHAYATH,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>NELAMANGALA TALUK,<lb/> BANGALORE RURAL DISTRICT-562123 …RESPONDENTS<lb/></address>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>(BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI.V SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H.C., HCGP FOR R-2;<lb/> SRI. AJAY M.D., ADVOCATE FOR R-1;<lb/> R-3 SERVED)<lb/> THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLE<lb/> 226 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA PRAYING TO<lb/> QUASH THE IMPUGNED ORDER I.E., ORDER DATED<lb/> 23.10.2018 PASSED BY THE HON&apos;BLE SPECIAL COURT<lb/> FOR PROHIBITION OF KARNATAKA LAND GRABBING 173<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	(COURT HALL NO.1) BANGALORE VIDE ANNEXURE-A<lb/> AND ETC.<lb/>
	<reference>IN W.P. NO. 51528/2018:<lb/></reference>

	BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>1 .<lb/> SRI N. K. RAMANNA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 58 YEARS<lb/> S/O LATE N K KRISHNASWAMY<lb/> RESIDING AT KOPPA TALUK<lb/> CHIKKAMAGALURU DISTRICT<lb/> WORKING AS DEPUTY<lb/> TAHASILDAR KOPPA,<lb/> CHIKKAMAGALURU-577 126.<lb/> 2 .<lb/> SRI A. P. GANEYANAIK,<lb/> AGED 65 YEARS,<lb/> S/O LATE PEEKA NAIK,<lb/> VINAYAKANAGAR, TARIKERE<lb/> CHIKKAMANGALURU DISTRICT-577 228<lb/> 3 .<lb/> SRI H. MALLAPPA,<lb/> AGED ABOUT 72 YEARS,<lb/> S/O LATE HOCHILAPPA<lb/> R/AT RANGENAHALLI,<lb/> TARIKERE TALUK,<lb/> CHIKKAMAGALUR DISTRICT-577 144<lb/> PETITIONER NOS 2 AND 3 NOT CLAIMING<lb/> THE BENEFIT OF SENIOR CITIZENS.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>...PETITIONERS<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	(BY SRI. G. R. MOHAN, ADVOCATE)<lb/> AND:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>1 .<lb/> STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> REVENUE DEPARTMENT<lb/> BY ITS PRINCIPAL SECRETARY<lb/> VIDHANA SOUDHA,<lb/> BENGALURU-560 001 174<lb/> 2 .<lb/> STATION HOUSE OFFICER<lb/> N R PURA CIRCLE POLICE<lb/> N R PURA TALUK,<lb/> CHIKKAMAGALUR DISTRICT-577 …RESPONDENTS<lb/> (BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI.V SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H.C., HCGP)<lb/> THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLE<lb/> 226 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA PRAYING TO SET<lb/> ASIDE THE IMPUGNED ORDER DATED 12.07.2018 AS<lb/> PER ANNEXURE-E IN L.G.C.[G] 691/17 PENDING<lb/> BEFORE<lb/> THE<lb/> KARNATAKA<lb/> LAND<lb/> GRABBING<lb/> PROHIBITION SPECIAL COURT BENGALURU AND ETC.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	IN W.P. NO. 52017/2018:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<reference>SMT. K. R. SHANTHA<lb/> W/O. LATE SRI. K. P. SRINIVAS AND<lb/> D/O. LATE SRI. K. C. RAMAIAH,<lb/> AGED ABOUT 78 YEARS,<lb/> RESIDING AT NO. 65/2,<lb/> RAM IYENGAR ROAD,<lb/> V.V. PURAM,<lb/> BENGALURU-560 004.<lb/> ...PETITIONER<lb/></reference>

	(BY SRI. B. K. CHANDRASHEKAR, ADVOCATE)<lb/> AND:<lb/>
	<email>1 .<lb/></email>

	<note type="funding">THE STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> REPRESENTED BY ITS<lb/> REVENUE SECRETARY,<lb/> REVENUE DEPARTMENT,<lb/> MULTISTORIED BUILDING,<lb/> DR. AMBEDKAR ROAD,<lb/> BANGALORE-560 001. 175<lb/> 2 .<lb/> THE REGISTRAR<lb/> SPECIAL COURT FOR<lb/> KARNATAKA LAND GRABBING PROHIBITION,<lb/> III FLOOR, KANDAYA BHAVANA,<lb/> K.G. ROAD,<lb/> BENGALURU-560 009.<lb/> 3 .<lb/> THE THASSILDAR<lb/> MINI VIDHANA SOUDHA BUILDING,<lb/> DEVANAHALLI,<lb/> BENGALURU RURAL DISTRICT-56197.<lb/> 4 .<lb/> THE DEPUTY THASSILDAR<lb/> NADA KACHERI,<lb/> KUNDANA,<lb/> DEVANAHALLI TALUK,<lb/> BENGALURU RURAL DISTRICT-56197.<lb/> 5 .<lb/> THE REVENUE INSPECTOR<lb/> VISHWANATHAPURA CIRCLE,<lb/> VISHWANATHAPURA,<lb/> KUNDANA HOBLI,<lb/> DEVANAHALLI TALUK,<lb/> BENGALURU RURAL DISTRICT-56197.<lb/> 6 .<lb/> THE VILLAGE ACCOUNTANT<lb/> VISHWANATHAPURA CIRCLE,<lb/> VISHWANATHAPURA,<lb/> KUNDANA HOBLI,<lb/> DEVANAHALLI TALUK,<lb/> BENGALURU RURAL DISTRICT-56197.<lb/> 7.<lb/> KARNATAKA LAND<lb/> GRABBING PROHIBITION<lb/> SPECIAL COURT<lb/> KHADAYA BHAVAN<lb/> 3RD FLOOR, K.G. ROAD<lb/> BANGALORE-01. …RESPONDENTS<lb/> (BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI.V SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H.C., HCGP FOR R-1, R-3 TO R-6; 176<lb/> R-2 AND R-7 ARE DELETED V/O DT: 17.07.2019)<lb/> THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA<lb/> PRAYING TO QUASH THE IMPUGNED ORDER AND THE<lb/> PROCEEDINGS INITIATED AS PER ANNEXURE-B AND<lb/> NOTICE<lb/> ANNEXURE-B<lb/> DECLARING<lb/> THAT<lb/> THE<lb/> PROCEEDINGS INITIATED IN PURSUANCE OF THE<lb/> KARNATAKA LAND GRABBING PROHIBITION ACT 2011<lb/> IS VIOLATION OF NATURAL JUSTICE AND ETC.<lb/></note>

	<reference>IN W.P. NO. 52106/2018:<lb/></reference>

	BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<reference>SRI. VENKATESH<lb/> S/O LATE BETTEGOWDA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 50 YEARS,<lb/> R/A NO.3<lb/> 7TH CROSS, 60 FEET ROAD,<lb/> J. C. NAGAR, MAHALAKSHMIPURAM,<lb/> BANGALORE-560086<lb/> ...PETITIONER<lb/></reference>

	(BY SRI. K.V. NARASIMHAN, ADVOCATE)<lb/> AND:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>1 .<lb/> STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> DEPARTMENT OF REVENUE<lb/> M.S. BUILDING, DR. AMBEDKAR ROAD,<lb/> BANGALORE-560001<lb/> REPRESENTED BY ITS SECRETARY<lb/> 2 .<lb/> BRUHATH BANGALORE MAHANAGARA<lb/> PALIKE, N. R. SQUARE,<lb/> BANGALORE-560001<lb/> 3 .<lb/> SRI. MUNNEGOWDA,<lb/> S/O LATE AKKALLAPPA<lb/> R/AT NO.73, 7TH CROSS,<lb/> 60 FEET ROAD, J. C. NAGAR<lb/> MAHALAKSHMIPURAM,</titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	177<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>BANGALORE-560086 …RESPONDENTS<lb/> (BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI.V SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H.C., HCGP FOR R-1;<lb/> BY SRI. I.G. GACHCHINAMATH, ADVOCATE FOR R-2;<lb/> R-3 SERVED)<lb/> THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA<lb/> PRAYING TO QUASH THE PROCEEDINGS IN L.G.C.[P]<lb/> NO. 1532/2018 ON THE FILE OF THE KARNATAKA LAND<lb/> GRABBING<lb/> PROHIBITION<lb/> SPECIAL<lb/> COURT<lb/> AT<lb/> ANNEXURE-H AND J AND ETC.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	IN W.P. NO. 53025/2018:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>SRI A. N. RAMASWAMY,<lb/> S/O LATE. A. NAGAPPA NAIK<lb/> AGED ABOUT 62 YEARS,<lb/> R/AT KAGGA VILALGE,<lb/> KASABA HOBLI<lb/> BOMBALAPURA POST<lb/> KOPPA TALUK-577120<lb/> CHIKMAGALUR DISTRICT<lb/> ...PETITIONER<lb/> (BY SMT. RAKSHITHA D.J., ADVOCATE)<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	AND:<lb/>
	<email>1 .<lb/></email>

	<note type="funding">STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> REVENUE DEPARTMENT,<lb/> M. S. BUILDING,<lb/> 5TH FLOOR,<lb/> DR. AMBEDKAR ROAD,<lb/> BANGALORE-560 001<lb/> REP BY ITS SECRETARY 178<lb/> 2 .<lb/> THE RANGE FOREST OFFICER<lb/> KOPPA RANGE<lb/> KOPPA-577120<lb/> CHIKMAGALUR DISTRICT …RESPONDENTS<lb/> (BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI.V SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H.C., HCGP)<lb/> THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA<lb/> PRAYING TO QUASH THE IMPUGNED ORDER DATED<lb/> 06.04.2018 VIDE ANNEXURE -A ISSUED BY THE<lb/> SPECIAL COURT CONSTITUTED UNDER KARNATAKA<lb/> LAND GRABBING PROHIBITION ACT, 2011, IN L.G.C.(G)<lb/> NO. 509/2018 AND ETC.<lb/></note>

	<reference>IN W.P. NO. 53049/2018:<lb/></reference>

	BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>G.S. MAHADEV<lb/> S/O SONNE GOWDA,<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	AGED ABOUT 40 YEARS<lb/> GONUR VILLAGE,<lb/>
	<reference>NARAYANAPURA POST,<lb/> VIJAYAPURA HOBLI,<lb/> DEVANAHALLI TALUK,<lb/> BANGALORE RURAL DISTRICT-562 135<lb/> ...PETITIONER<lb/></reference>

	<note type="copyright">(BY SRI. C.M. NAGABUSHANA, ADVOCATE)<lb/></note>

	AND:<lb/>
	<email>1 .<lb/></email>

	<note type="funding">THE STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> REP BY ITS PRINCIPAL SECRETARY,<lb/> DEPARTMENT OF REVENUE,<lb/> M.S.BUILDINGS,<lb/> DR.AMBEDKAR VEEDHI,<lb/></note>

	<address>BANGALORE-560 001.</address>

	179<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>.<lb/> DEPUTY COMMISSIONER<lb/> BANGALORE RURAL DISTRICT,<lb/> VISHWANATHAPURA,<lb/> DEVANAHALLI TALUK,<lb/> BANGALORE RURAL DISTRICT-562 110<lb/> .<lb/> TAHSILDAR<lb/> DEVANAHALLI TALUK,<lb/> DEVANAHALLI,<lb/> BANGALORE RURAL DISTRICT-562 110<lb/> .<lb/> MUNIKEMPANNA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 75 YEARS<lb/> S/O LATE KEMPANNA,<lb/> .<lb/> ANAND KUMAR<lb/> AGED ABOUT 42 YEARS<lb/> S/O PRASANNA KUMAR<lb/> .<lb/> G.V.VENKATASWAMMY<lb/> AGED ABOUT 55 YEARS,<lb/> S/O VENKATAPPA,<lb/> .<lb/> SRINIVAS GOWDA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 55 YEARS<lb/> S/O CHOWDEGOWDA,<lb/> .<lb/> G.N.LOKESH<lb/> AGED ABOUT 75 YEARS<lb/> S/O NARAYANASWAMY,<lb/> .<lb/> BASAPPA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 67 YEARS<lb/> S/O HANUMANTHAPPA,<lb/> . RAMANNA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 62 YEARS<lb/> S/O MUNISHAMAPPA,<lb/> . GANESH<lb/> AGED ABOUT 36 YEARS<lb/> S/O LATE KRISHANAPPA, 180<lb/> 12 . R.MANJUNATH<lb/> AGED ABOUT 38 YEARS<lb/> S/O RAMANNA,<lb/> 13 . ASWATH G.C.<lb/> AGED ABOUT 39 YEARS<lb/> S/O CHANNARAYAPPA,<lb/> 14 . G.M.MANJUNATH<lb/> AGED ABOUT 40 YEARS<lb/> S/O MUNIYAPPA,<lb/> ALL ARE RESIDENTS OF<lb/> GONUR AND GOLLAHALLI VILLAGE,<lb/> NARAYANAPURA POST,<lb/> VIJAYAPAURA HOBLI,<lb/> DEVANAHALLI TALUK,<lb/> BANGALORE RURAL DISTRICT-562 135. …RESPONDENTS<lb/> (BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI.V SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H.C., HCGP FOR R-1 TO R-3;<lb/> SMT. K. SHEELA ANISH, ADVOCATE FOR<lb/> R-4 TO R-10 &amp; R-12 TO R-14;<lb/> R-11 SERVED &amp; )<lb/> THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA<lb/> PRAYING TO QUASH THE PROCEEDINGS INITIATED<lb/> BEFORE THE KARNATAKA<lb/> LAND<lb/> GRABBING PROHIBITION SPECIAL COURT IN LGC(P)<lb/> NO.<lb/> 208/2017 DATED 28.06.2017 AT ANNEX-J.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	IN W.P. NO. 53204/2018:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>K. S. DAYANANDSHETTY<lb/> AGED 80 YEARS<lb/> S/O SEENAPPA SHETTY<lb/> T.D. HALLI , AREHALLI HOBLI,<lb/> SMT A SHAKUNTALA<lb/> W/O LATE MUNIVENKATAPPA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 86 YEARS,<lb/> 2 .<lb/> D. M PADMANABHA<lb/> S/O LATE MUNIVENKATAPPA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 67 YEARS,<lb/> 3 .<lb/> MR M MOHANSUNDAR<lb/> S/O LATE MUNIVENKATAPPA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 64 YEARS,<lb/> 4 .<lb/> MR. M RAJASHEKAR<lb/> S/O LATE H B MUNIVENKATAPPA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 63 YEARS,<lb/> 5 .<lb/> DR. M CHANDRASHEKARA<lb/> W/O LATE H. B MUNIVENKATAPPA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 60 YEARS,<lb/> ALL ARE R/A. NO.314 &quot;DWARAKA&quot;<lb/> INNER CIRLCE, WHITE FIELD,<lb/> NEAR K.R. PURAM HOBLI,<lb/> BENGALURU SOUTH-560 056<lb/> PETITIONERS ARE REPRESENTED BY<lb/> G.P.A. HOLDER,<lb/> SRI M. MOHANSUNDAR<lb/> S/O LATE MUNIVENKATAPPA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 64 YEARS,<lb/> R/A. NO.314 &quot;DWARAKA&quot;<lb/> INNER CIRCLE WHITE FILED<lb/> NEAR K. R. PURAM HOBLI<lb/> BENGALURU SOUTH -560 056<lb/> ...PETITIONERS<lb/> (BY SRI. MANMOHAN P. N., ADVOCATE)<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	AND:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>1 .<lb/> STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> 7.<lb/> BASAVANNA.T<lb/> S/O J HANUMANTHAPPA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 69 YEARS<lb/> R/AT NO 79,<lb/> DEVARAGUDDANAHALLI,<lb/> BALLARI DISTRICT-583103<lb/> 8.<lb/> K. BASAPPA<lb/> S/O MOKKABASAPPA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 50 YEARS<lb/> R/O DEVARAGUDDANAHALLI<lb/> BALLARI DISTRICT -583103<lb/> 9.<lb/> N RAGHAVENDRA<lb/> S/O HANUMANTHAPPA J<lb/> AGED ABOUT 36 YEARS<lb/> R/O BOMMAGHATTA VILLAGE,<lb/> SANDUR TALUK BALLARI DISTRICT -583128<lb/> 10. G CHINNAPARIPPA GOWDA<lb/> S/O THIPPANNA GOWDA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 66 YEARS<lb/> R/O BOMMAGHATTA VILLAGE,<lb/> SANDUR TALUK BALLARI DISTRICT -583128<lb/> …RESPONDENTS<lb/> (BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI. V SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA HC, HCGP FOR R-1 TO R-3;<lb/> SRI. S.N. BHAT, ADVOCATE R-5 TO R-10)<lb/> THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLE<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA<lb/> PRAYING TO DECLARE THAT SEC. 9 (1) WITH<lb/> REFERENCE TO CONFERRING THE JURISDICTION ON<lb/> SPECIAL COURT UNDER THE ACT ON AN APPLICATION<lb/> MADE BY ANY PERSON IS VIOLATIVE OF ARTICLE 14<lb/> OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA AND ALSO SEC. 4 (3)<lb/> AND SEC. 9 (5) (b) OF THE KARNATAKA ACT<lb/> NO.38/2014 ARE VIOLATIVE OF ARTICLES 20 AND 21<lb/> OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA.</titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	188<lb/> IN W.P. NO. 55214/2018:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>K. VENKATESH<lb/> AGED ABOUT 54 YEARS<lb/> S/O LATE KRISHNAPPA<lb/> R/AT NO.27/2, 2 ND MAIN<lb/> ATTIGUPPE, VIJAYANAGAR,<lb/> BENGALURU-560 001<lb/> ...PETITIONER<lb/> (BY SRI. C.M. NAGABHUSHANA, ADVOCATE)<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	AND:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>1.<lb/> STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> REPRESENTED BY ITS SECRETARY<lb/> REVENUE DEPARTMENT<lb/> M.S.BUILDING, VIDHANA SOUDHA<lb/> DR.AMBEDKAR VEEDHI<lb/> BENGALURU-560 001<lb/> 2.<lb/> THE TAHASILDAR<lb/> BENGALURU SOUTH TALUK<lb/> BENGALURU-560 009<lb/> 3.<lb/> HEMANTH RAJU<lb/> MAJOR IN AGE<lb/> S/O LATE MUNIRAJU<lb/> NO.32, ESHWAR TEMPLE ROAD<lb/> RAMOHALLI, KENGERI HOBLI<lb/> BENGALURU SOUTH TALUK<lb/> BENGALURU-560 074 …RESPONDENTS<lb/> (BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI. V SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA HC, HCGP FOR R-1 &amp; R-2)<lb/> THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLE<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA 189<lb/> PRAYING TO DECLARE THE KARNATAKA LAND<lb/> GRABBING PROHIBITITION ACT 2011 (KARNATAKA ACT<lb/> 38/2014) AS ULTRA VIRES THE CONSTITUTION OF<lb/> INDIA BEING VIOLATION OF ARTICLE 14, 20, 21 AND<lb/> 300A AND ETC.<lb/> IN W.P. NO. 56168/2018:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/> 1.<lb/> MR G PULLA REDDY<lb/> AGED ABOUT 53 YEARS<lb/> SON OF MR G NARAYANA REDDY<lb/> RESIDING AT BHARGAVA TOWER<lb/> 1ST FLOOR, PLOT NO.1 AND 20<lb/> DINNUR MAIN ROAD, R T NAGAR<lb/> BANGALORE-560 032<lb/> 2.<lb/> SRI RAMESH KUMAR TAINWALA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 62 YEARS<lb/> SON OF LATE MAHABEER PRASAD TAINWALA<lb/> 3.<lb/> SRI ABHISHEK TAINWALA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 22 YEARS<lb/> SON OF RAMESH KUMAR TAINWALA<lb/> 4.<lb/> SRI ANIL KUMAR TAINWALA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 60 YEARS<lb/> SON OF LATE MAHABEER PRASAD TAINWALA<lb/> 5.<lb/> SRI GAGAN TAINWALA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 21 YEARS<lb/> SON OF ANIL KUMAR TAINWALA<lb/> 6.<lb/> SRI LALITH KISHORE TAINWALA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 58 YEARS<lb/> SON OF LATE MAHABEER PRASAD TAINWALA …RESPONDENTS<lb/> (BY SRI.PRABHULING K.NAVADAGI, AG<lb/> A/W SRI V.SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT.KAVITHA H.C., HCGP FOR R-1 TO R-3)<lb/> THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLE 226<lb/> AND 227 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA PRAYING TO<lb/> DECLARE<lb/> THE<lb/> KARNATAKA<lb/> LAND<lb/> GRABBING<lb/> PROHIBITION ACT 2011 (KARNATAKA ACT 358/2014) AS<lb/> ULTRA VIRES THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA BEING<lb/> VIOLATION OF ARTICLES 14, 20, 21 AND 300A AND<lb/> ETC.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	IN W.P. NO.302/2019:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>K. MUGILESHWARI<lb/> W/O SUBRAMANI NAIDU<lb/> AGED ABOUT 53 YEARS<lb/> AGRICULTURIST,<lb/> R/O GOPALA VILLAGE,<lb/> LAKKAVALLI HOBLI,<lb/> TARIKERE TALUK,<lb/> CHIKKAMAGALURU DISTRICT-577 228.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>...PETITIONER<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	(BY SRI. S.V. PRAKASH, ADVOCATE)<lb/> AND:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>1 .<lb/> THE CHIEF SECRETARY<lb/> GOVERNMENT OF KARNATAKA,<lb/> VIDHANA SOUDHA<lb/> DR. B.R. AMBEDKAR VEEDHI,<lb/> BENGALURU-560001<lb/> 2 .<lb/> THE DEPUTY COMMISSIONER<lb/> CHIKKAMAGALURU DISTRICT,<lb/> CHIKKAMAGALURU-577101<lb/> AGED ABOUT 43 YEARS,<lb/> .<lb/> PAMENAHALLI NAGENDRAPPA<lb/> S/O HANUMAPPA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 53 YEARS,<lb/> .<lb/> SRI SALYAKKI RUDRAPPA<lb/> S/O BHEEMAPPA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 53 YEARS,<lb/> .<lb/> HADADI KAMALAPPA<lb/> S/O BHEEMAPPA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 53 YEARS,<lb/> PETITIONER NOS.1 TO 5 ARE<lb/> RESIDENT OF BELALAGERE VILLAGE<lb/> CHENNAGIRI TALUK<lb/> DAVANAGERE DISTRICT-577 213.<lb/> .<lb/> NARAYANA NAIKA<lb/> S/O KIRIYA NAYAKA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 59 YEARS,<lb/> .<lb/> MUKESH NAIKA<lb/> S/O TOLACHA NAIKA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 29 YEARS,<lb/> PETITIONER NOS. 6 AND 7 ARE<lb/> RESIDENT OF KAVALITHANDA VILLAGE<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	CHENNAGIRI TALUK<lb/> DAVANAGERE DISTRICT-577 213.<lb/> .<lb/> KURKI SIDDAPPA<lb/> S/O OBALAPPA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 63 YEARS,<lb/> .<lb/> KURKI THIUPPESHAPPA<lb/> S/O HANUMANTHAPPA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 33 YEARS,<lb/> . THIMMENAHALLI THIPPESHAPPA 222<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>S/O CHENNABASAPPA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 42 YEARS,<lb/> OCC:FARMER<lb/> 11 . MATTI ANJANAPPA<lb/> S/O CHANNABASAPPA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 45 YEARS,<lb/> OCC:FARMER<lb/> 12 . DODDAPPA<lb/> S/O HANUMANTHAPPA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 51 YEARS,<lb/> OCC:FARMER<lb/> 13 . CHANDRAPPA<lb/> S/O THIMMENAHALLI CHENNABASAPPA (B5)<lb/> AGED ABOUT 45 YEARS,<lb/> 14 . ANNAPPA @ KENGA DODDAPPARA<lb/> ANNAPPA OCC:FARMER<lb/> AGED ABOUT 27 YEARS<lb/> 15 . KANNI DODDAPPA<lb/> S/O BHEEMAPPA (B9)<lb/> AGED ABOUT 58 YEARS,<lb/> 16 . KOLENAHALLI SRINIVASA<lb/> S/O BHEEMAPPA (C1),<lb/> AGED ABOUT 35 YEARS,<lb/> PETITIONER NOS. 8 TO 16 ARE<lb/> RESIDENT OF BELALAGERE VILLAGE<lb/> CHENNAGIRI TALUK<lb/> DAVANAGERE DISTRICT-577 213.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>...PETITIONERS<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	(BY SRI. KALEEMULLAH SHARIFF, ADVOCATE)<lb/> AND:<lb/>
	<email>1 .<lb/></email>

	<note type="funding">THE PRINCIPAL SECRETARY<lb/> CONSTITUTION<lb/> OF<lb/> INDIA<lb/> AS<lb/> CONTAINED<lb/> IN<lb/> ANNEXURE-A.<lb/></note>

	IN W.P. NO.14457/2019:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>SRI. A.M. PRAKASH<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	AGED ABOUT 59 YEARS<lb/> S/O LATE. MUTHAPPA<lb/> NALVOTHOKLUL VILLAGE<lb/> AMMATHI HOBLI, VIRAJPET<lb/> TALUK -571 218<lb/> KODAGU DISTRICT.<lb/> ...PETITIONER<lb/> (BY SRI. N. RAVINDRANATH KAMATH, ADVOCATE)<lb/> AND:<lb/>
	<reference>1 .<lb/> THE STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> REVENUE DEPARTMENT<lb/> 5TH FLOOR, M.S. BUILDING<lb/> DR. AMBEDKAR ROAD<lb/> BENGALURU -560 001<lb/> REP BY ITS SECRETARY.<lb/> 2 .<lb/> THE TAHSILDAR<lb/> VIRAJPET TALUK<lb/> VIRAJPET -571 218<lb/> KODAGU DISTRICT. …RESPONDENTS<lb/></reference>

	(BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/>
	<meeting>SRI. V. SREENIDHI, AGA, AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA H.C, HCGP)<lb/> THIS PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLE 226 &amp; 227<lb/> OF CONSTITUTION OF INDIA PRAYING TO DECLARE THE<lb/> KARNATAKA LAND GRABBING PROHIBITION ACT, 2011<lb/> (KARNATAKA ACT 38 OF 2014) AS ULTRA VIRES AND BEING<lb/> VIOLATIVE OF ARTICLES 14, 20, 21 &amp; 300-A OF<lb/> CONSTITUTION OF INDIA AND ETC.<lb/></meeting>

	IN W.P. NO.18151/2019:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>1.<lb/> SRI. PURUSHOTHAMA BHARATHI PEETADHIPATHI</docAuthor>
	</byline>

	241<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>SREE SRINGERI SHIVAGANGA SHARAD MUTT,<lb/> SHIVAGANGA, NELAMANGALA TALUK,<lb/> BENGALURU RURAL DISTRICT.<lb/> 2.<lb/> SRI. S. S. SRINIVAS RAO<lb/> S/O. S. L. SEETHARAM RAO,<lb/> AGED ABOUT 41 YEARS,<lb/> ADMINISTRATOR,<lb/> SREE SRINGERI SHIVAGANGA SHARADA MUTT,<lb/> ADVOCATE, PARTNER,<lb/> HARANAHALLI LAW PARTNERS,<lb/> NO.160, R.T. NAGAR MAIN ROAD,<lb/> BENGALURU-560 032.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>...PETITIONERS<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	(BY SRI P.N.MANMOHAN, ADVOCATE)<lb/> AND:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>AGED ABOUT 63 YEARS<lb/> RETIRED EMPLOYEE,<lb/> WATERMAN,<lb/> MUDUGODU GRAMA PANCHAYATI<lb/> R/O IRRIGATION DEPARTMENT QUARTERS,<lb/> MUDUGODU VILLAGE-577144<lb/> LAKKAVALLI HOBLI,<lb/> TARIKERE TALUK<lb/> CHICKMAGALUR DISTRICT-577101.<lb/> .<lb/> SMT. SHARADAMMA<lb/> W/O THIMMANAIKA,<lb/> AGED ABOUT 53 YEARS<lb/> EMPLOYEE, HEALTH DEPARTMENT,<lb/> R/O IRRIGATION DEPARTMENT QUARTERS,<lb/> MUDUGODU VILLAGE-577144<lb/> LAKKAVALLI HOBLI,<lb/> TARIKERE TALUK<lb/> CHICKMAGALUR DISTRICT-577101.<lb/> .<lb/> SHIVAJI NAIKA<lb/> S/O ESHWAR NAIKA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 45 YEARS<lb/> EMPLOYEE, LINEMAN, MESCO<lb/> R/O IRRIGATION DEPARTMENT QUARTERS,<lb/> MUDUGODU VILLAGE-577144<lb/> LAKKAVALLI HOBLI,<lb/> TARIKERE TALUK<lb/> CHICKMAGALUR DISTRICT-577101<lb/> .<lb/> SMT. K. PADMA<lb/> W/O LATE VITTALA RAO<lb/> AGED ABOUT 65 YEARS,<lb/> HOUSEHOLD WORK<lb/> R/O IRRIGATION DEPARTMENT QUARTERS,<lb/> MUDUGODU VILLAGE-577144<lb/> LAKKAVALLI HOBLI,<lb/> TARIKERE TALUK<lb/> CHICKMAGALUR DISTRICT-577101<lb/> .<lb/> NATRAJ<lb/> S/O H.KARIYAPPA,<lb/> AGED ABOUT 59 YEARS,<lb/> BENGALURU-560 040.<lb/> .<lb/> SRI.D.SIDDARAJU<lb/> S/O LATE C.K.DODDAIAH,<lb/> AGED ABOUT 61 YEARS<lb/> .<lb/> SRI.D.HANUMANTHAIAH<lb/> S/O LATE C.K.DODDAIAH,<lb/> AGED ABOUT 62 YEARS<lb/> .<lb/> SRI.D.KRISHNA RAJU<lb/> S/O LATE C.K.DODDAIAH,<lb/> AGED ABOUT 56 YEARS<lb/> .<lb/> SRI.D.SHANKARAPPA<lb/> S/O LATE C.K.DODDAIAH,<lb/> AGED ABOUT 59 YEARS<lb/> .<lb/> SRI.DHANANJAYA<lb/> S/O LATE C.K.DODDAIAH,<lb/> AGED ABOUT 51 YEARS<lb/> PETITIONERS NO.2 TO 6 ARE RESIDING AT<lb/> CHOLANAYAKANAHALLI VILLAGE,<lb/> TAVAREKERE HOBLI,<lb/> BENGALURU SOUTH TALUK-562 130<lb/> .<lb/> SRI.S.T.KUBERA SWAMY<lb/> S/O THAMMANNA GOWDA,<lb/> AGED ABOUT 49 YEARS<lb/> .<lb/> SRI.S.T.RAMESH<lb/> S/O THAMMANNA GOWDA,<lb/> AGED ABOUT 47 YEARS<lb/> PETITIONER NO.7 AND 8 ARE RESIDING AT<lb/> DEVAMACHOHALLI VILLAGE,<lb/> TAVAREKERE HOBLI &amp; POST<lb/> BENGALURU SOUTH TALUK.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>.<lb/> SRI.J.N.SOMESHWARA<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<note type="funding">THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF CONSTITUTION OF INDIA PRAYING TO<lb/> DECLARE THAT THE KARNATAKA LAND GRABBING<lb/> PROHIBITION ACT OF 2011 (KARNATAKA ACT 38 OF<lb/> 2014) AS ULTRAVIRES THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA<lb/> BEING VIOLATIVE OF ARTICLES 14, 20, 21 AND 300A<lb/> AND/OR IN THE ALTERNATIVE; DECLARING THAT THE<lb/> KARNATAKA LAND GRABBING PROHIBITION ACT, 2011<lb/> (KARNATAKA ACT 38 OF 2014) IS NOT APPLICABLE TO<lb/> THE<lb/> FACTS<lb/> AND<lb/> CIRCUMSTANCES<lb/> OF<lb/> THE<lb/> PETITIONERS CASE IN L.G.C.(G) NO.279/2019.<lb/></note>

	IN W.P. NO.29668/2019:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>SRI SANTOSH A SHETTY<lb/> S/O ANAND SHETTY<lb/> AGED ABOUT 34 YEARS<lb/> OCC: AGRICULTURIST<lb/> RESIDING OF CHIKKA AGRAHARA<lb/> POST MEGHARAMAKKI<lb/> N.R.PURA TALUK<lb/> CHIKKAMAGALUR DISTRICT-567 201.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>...PETITIONER<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	(BY SRI. CHANDRAKANTH R. GOULAY, ADVOCATE)<lb/> AND:<lb/>
	<reference>1. THE STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> REP. BY ITS SECRETARY<lb/> DEPARTMENT OF REVENUE<lb/> M.S.BUILDING, DR.AMBEDKAR VEEDHI<lb/> BENGALURU-560 001.<lb/></reference>

	<note type="copyright">2. THE DEPUTY CONSERVATOR OF FOREST<lb/> CHIKKAMAGALUR DISTRICT<lb/> CHIKKAMAGALUR-567 201.<lb/> 3. THE RANGE FOREST OFFICER<lb/> CHIKKAAGRAHARA RANGE 273<lb/></note>

	<reference>N.R.PURA TALUK<lb/> CHIKKAMAGALUR DISTRICT-567 201. …RESPONDENTS<lb/></reference>

	(BY SRI. PRABHULING K. NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI V.SREENIDHI, AGA; SMT.KAVITHA H.C., HCGP)<lb/>
	<note type="funding">THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLES<lb/> 226 AND 227 OF CONSTITUTION OF INDIA PRAYING TO<lb/> QUASH THE ENTIRE PROCEEDINGS IN LGC(T)<lb/> NO.140/2018 ON THE FILE OF THE KARNATAKA LAND<lb/> GRABBING PROHIBITION SPECIAL COURT AS PER<lb/> ANNEXURE-H, AS WITHOUT COMPETENCE AND<lb/> JURISDICTION AND OTHERWISE BEING ARBITRARY,<lb/> ILLEGAL AND VOID; DECLARE THAT THE PROVISIONS<lb/> OF THE KARNATAKA LAND GRABBING PROHIBITION<lb/> ACT 2011 IS UNCONSTITUTIONAL AND ULTRA VIRUS TO<lb/> ARTICLES 14, 19, 21 AND 300A OF THE CONSTITUTION<lb/> OF INDIA AS ANNEXURE-J.<lb/></note>

	IN W.P. NO.30073/2019:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>1. MR.K.SHAMANNA<lb/> S/O LATE KEMPANNA<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	AGED ABOUT 69 YEARS<lb/> 2. MR. K.RAMMANNA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 52 YEARS<lb/> S/O LATE KEMPANNA<lb/> ...PETITIONERS<lb/> (BY SRI. BHARADWAJ K.R., ADVOCATE)<lb/> AND:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>1. THE STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> REPRESENTED BY ITS CHIEF SECRETARY<lb/> VIDHANA SOUDHA<lb/> BENGALURU-560 001.<lb/> T B RAMESHA<lb/> S/O BIMAPPA KALAKRADI,<lb/> AGED ABOUT 58 YEARS,<lb/> OCC-AGRICULTURE,<lb/> TALAGUPPA VILLAGE,<lb/> GENDLA POST, SORABA TALUK,<lb/> SHIVAMOGGA -577 419.<lb/> 2.<lb/> HIRANYAPPA<lb/> S/O VEERABADRAPPA,<lb/> AGED ABOUT 60 YEARS<lb/> OCC-AGRICULTURE,<lb/> TALAGUPPA VILLAGE,<lb/> GENDLA POST, SORABA TALUK,<lb/> SHIVAMOGGA -577 419.<lb/> 3.<lb/> ONKARAPPA<lb/> S/O BANGARAPPA,<lb/> AGED 45 YEARS,<lb/> OCC-AGRICULTURE,<lb/> TALAGUPPA VILLAGE,<lb/> GENDLA POST, SORABA TALUK,<lb/> SHIVAMOGGA -577 419.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>4.<lb/> MAALATHESH<lb/> S/O BALINDRAPPA,<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	AGED ABOUT 30YEARS,<lb/> OCC-AGRICULTURE, 309<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>PUTTANAHALLI VILLAGE,<lb/> DYAVANAHALLI POST,<lb/> SORABA TALUK,<lb/> SHIVAMOGGA -577 419.<lb/> 5.<lb/> SRIDHARA<lb/> S/O KALLAPPA,<lb/> AGED 40 YEARS,<lb/> OCC-AGRICULTURE,<lb/> TALAGUPPA VILLAGE,<lb/> GENDLA POST, SORABA TALUK,<lb/> SHIVAMOGGA -577 419.<lb/> 6.<lb/> CHANDRAPPA MULIMANE<lb/> S/O CHENNABASAPPA<lb/> AGED ABOUT 50 YEARS,<lb/> OCC-AGRICULTURE,<lb/> PUTTANAHALLI VILLAGE,<lb/> DYAVANAHALLI POST, SORABA TALUK<lb/> SHIVAMOGGA -577 419.<lb/> ...PETITIONERS<lb/> (BY SRI. MAHAVEER. K. JAIN, ADVOCATE)<lb/> AND:<lb/> 1.<lb/> THE STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> REPRESENTED BY ITS CHIEF SECREARY,<lb/> REVENUE DEPARTMENT, M.S.BUILDING,<lb/> BENGALURU-560 001.<lb/> 2.<lb/> DEPUTY CONSERVATOR OF FOREST<lb/> SHIMOGA,<lb/> SHIVAMOGGA DISTRICT -577 419.<lb/> 3.<lb/> THE RANGE FOREST OFFICER<lb/> ANAVATTI RANGE,<lb/> SHIVAMOGGA DISTRICT -577 419.<lb/> …..RESPONDENTS<lb/> (BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI. V SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA HC, HCGP)<lb/> REVENUE DEPARTMENT,<lb/> M.S. BUILDING,<lb/> DR. B. R. AMBEDKAR VEEDHI,<lb/> BENGALURU -560 001.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>3.<lb/> SMT. MALLAMMA<lb/> W/O M. GOPAL,<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	AGED ABOUT 45 YEARS,<lb/> 4.<lb/> SRI. VENKATESH<lb/> S/O NARAYANAPPA,<lb/> AGED ABOUT 45 YEARS,<lb/> 5.<lb/> SRI. DEVRAJ<lb/> S/O. APPAYAPPA,<lb/> AGED ABOUT 40 YEARS,<lb/> 6.<lb/> SRI. M. GOPAL<lb/> S/O MUNIYAPPA,<lb/> AGED ABOUT 50 YEARS,<lb/> 7.<lb/> SRI. KARIYAPPA<lb/> S/O. MUNIYAPPA,<lb/> AGED ABOUT 65 YEARS,<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>ALL ARE RESIDING AT APPASANDRA VILLAGE,<lb/> JADIGENAHALLI HOBLI,<lb/> HOSAKOTE TALUK,<lb/> HOSKOTE -562 114,<lb/> BENGALURU RURAL DISTRICT.<lb/> ….RESPONDENTS<lb/> (BY SRI. PRABHULING K NAVADAGI, AG A/W<lb/> SRI. V SREENIDHI, AGA AND<lb/> SMT. KAVITHA HC, HCGP FOR R-1&amp; R-2<lb/> SRI. B M HALASWAMY FOR R-3 TO R-7))<lb/> THIS WRIT PETITION IS FILED UNDER ARTICLE<lb/> 226 &amp; 227 OF CONSTITUTION OF INDIA PRAYING TO<lb/> CALL FOR ENTIRE RECORDS PERTAINING TO<lb/> IMPUGNED ORDER IN CASE No</titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<reference>.LGC(P) No.297/2019<lb/> VIDE ANNEXURE-B DATED 18.10.2019 FROM THE FILE 319<lb/></reference>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>OF THE KARNATAKA LAND GRABBING PROHIBITION<lb/> SPECIAL COURT AT BENGALURU AND ON PERUSAL OF<lb/> THE SAME.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	IN W.P. NO.51926/2019:<lb/> BETWEEN:<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>SRI. YALIYAPPA<lb/> S/O. NANJAPPA,<lb/> AGED ABOUT 65 YEARS,<lb/> R/AT APPASANDRA VILLAGE,<lb/> JADIGENAHALLI HOBLI,<lb/> HOSAKOTE TALUK,<lb/> ...PETITIONER<lb/> (BY SRI. VIJAYA KUMAR BHAT.A, ADVOCATE)<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	AND:<lb/>
	<byline>
	<affiliation>1.<lb/> STATE OF KARNATAKA<lb/> REP. BY ITS CHIEF SECRETARY,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>VIDHANA SOUDHA,<lb/> BENGALURU -560 001.<lb/></address>

	2.<lb/> THE PRINCIPAL SECRETARY TO GOVERNMENT<lb/> REVENUE DEPARTMENT,<lb/> M.S. BUILDING,<lb/> DR. B. R. AMBEDKAR VEEDHI,<lb/> BENGALURU -560 001.<lb/> 3.<lb/> SMT. MALLAMMA<lb/> W/O M. GOPAL,<lb/> AGED ABOUT 45 YEARS,<lb/> 4.<lb/> SRI. VENKATESH<lb/> S/O NARAYANAPPA,<lb/> AGED ABOUT 45 YEARS,<lb/> 5.<lb/> SRI. DEVRAJ<lb/> S/O. APPAYAPPA,<lb/> AGED ABOUT 40 YEARS,<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>25.CIVIL APPEAL NO. 7764 OF<lb/> 2014 AND SPECIAL<lb/> LEAVE<lb/> PETITION<lb/> (CIVIL)<lb/> NOS.<lb/> 8332-8333<lb/> OF<lb/> 2014<lb/> (D.D.07.08.2019):<lb/> RAVINDER KAUR GREWAL AND<lb/> OTHERS Vs. MANJIT<lb/> KAUR<lb/> AND OTHERS.<lb/> 26.AIR 2004 SC 456: PEOPLE&apos;S<lb/> UNION FOR<lb/> CIVIL<lb/> LIBERTIES AND ANOTHER Vs.<lb/> UNION OF INDIA.<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<reference>27.W.P. (CIVIL) NO.210/2012<lb/> (D.D.12.09.2012):<lb/> NAMIT<lb/> SHARMA Vs.<lb/> UNION<lb/> OF<lb/> INDIA.<lb/> 28.CIVIL APPEALS NOS. 71 TO 76<lb/> OF<lb/> 1953 (D.D. 29.05.1953)<lb/> :<lb/> K.C. GAJAPATI NARAYAN DEO<lb/> AND OTHERS Vs. THE STATE OF<lb/> ORISSA.<lb/> 29.W.P. NOS. 1118/1979 AND<lb/> CONNECTED (D.D.13.11.1980) :<lb/> AJAY HASIA AND OTHERS Vs.<lb/> KHALID MUJIB SEHRAVARDI<lb/> AND OTHERS.<lb/> 30.CRL.A. NOS.446-449/2004 AND<lb/> CONNECTED MATTERS (D.D.<lb/> 08.03.2006)<lb/> :<lb/> ZAHIRA<lb/> HABIBULLAH<lb/> SHEIKH<lb/> AND<lb/> ANOTHER<lb/> Vs.<lb/> STATE<lb/> OF<lb/> GUJARAJ AND OTHERS.<lb/> 31.(1998) 2 SCC 1 : MALPE<lb/> VISHWANATH<lb/> ACHARYA AND<lb/> OTHERS<lb/> Vs.<lb/> STATE<lb/> OF<lb/> MAHARASHTRA AND ANOTHER.<lb/> 7. (2012) 6 SCC 312 : STATE OF<lb/> MADHYA PRADESH<lb/> Vs.<lb/> REKESH KOHLI AND ANOTHER.<lb/> 8. (1980) 2 SCC 665 : V.C. SHUKLA<lb/> AND OTHERS<lb/> Vs.<lb/> STATE<lb/> (DELHI ADMINISTRATION) AND<lb/> OTHERS.<lb/> 9. 1952 SCR 435 : AIR 1952 SC<lb/> 123 : 1952 CRI LJ 805 : KATHI<lb/> RANING RAWAT Vs. STATE OF<lb/> SAURASHTRA.<lb/> 10.(1979) 1 SUPREME COURT<lb/> CASES 380 : IN RE<lb/> THE<lb/> SPECIAL COURTS BILL, 1978.<lb/> 11. (2015) 6 SCC 222: MOHAN LAL<lb/> Vs. STATE OF RAJASTHAN.<lb/> 12. S.L.P. (C) 19030/2002 (D.D.<lb/> 17.04.2003) : SHIV SHAKTI<lb/> COOPERATIVE<lb/> HOUSING<lb/> SOCIETY, NAGPUR Vs. M/S<lb/> SWARAJ<lb/> DEVELOPERS<lb/> AND<lb/> OTHERS.<lb/> 13. (2012) 8 SCC 243 : BAR<lb/> COUNCIL OF INDIA Vs. UNION<lb/> OF INDIA.<lb/> 14. 1995 SUPP (2) SCC 187 : P.N.<lb/> KRISHNA LAL AND OTHERS Vs.<lb/> GOVT.<lb/> OF<lb/> KERALA<lb/> AND<lb/> ANOTHER.<lb/> 15. (1994) 5 SCC 410 : SANJAY<lb/> DUTT Vs. STATE THROUGH<lb/> C.B.I., BOMBAY (II).<lb/> 16. (2013) 1 SCC 745 : NAMIT<lb/> SHARMA Vs. UNION OF INDIA.<lb/> 26. 1995 SUPP(4) SCC 684: MOHAN<lb/> LAL Vs. KARTAR SINGH AND OTHERS<lb/> 27. (1998) 6 SCC 288: EMPLOYEE&apos;S<lb/> STATE<lb/> INSURANCE<lb/> CORPORATION<lb/> Vs.<lb/> S.K.<lb/> AGGARWAL AND OTHERS<lb/> 28. (2004) 4 SCC 158:<lb/> ZAHIRA<lb/> HABIBULLA H. SHEIKH AND<lb/> ANOTHER<lb/> Vs.<lb/> STATE<lb/> OF<lb/> GUJARAT AND OTHERS.<lb/> 29.WRIT PETITION NO. 3879 OF<lb/> 2012 :2013 SCC BOM 833 :<lb/> SHRI.A.G. SAWANT Vs. SHRI.<lb/> SANJAY D. BERDE<lb/> 30. AIR 1953 SC 394 : RAO SHIV<lb/> BAHADUR SINGH AND ANOTHER<lb/> Vs.<lb/> STATE<lb/> OF<lb/> VINDHYA<lb/> PRADESH.<lb/> 31.(1994) 3 SCC 569:<lb/> KARTAR<lb/> SINGH Vs. STATE OF PUNJAB.<lb/> 32.1926 SCC ONLINE US SC 9: 269<lb/> US 385 (1926): 46 S.CT. 126: 70<lb/> L.ED.322:CONNALLY,<lb/> COMMISSIONER OF LABOR OF<lb/> OKLAHOMA, ETC . Vs. GENERAL<lb/> CONST.CO.<lb/> 33. AIR 1962 SC 316: COLLECTOR<lb/> OF CUSTOMS, MADRAS Vs.<lb/> NATHELLA SAMPATHU CHETTY<lb/> AND ANR.<lb/> 34. (2015) 9 SCC 502 : VIKRAM<lb/></reference>

	SINGH<lb/> ALIAS<lb/> VICKY AND
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
