<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>REPORTABLE <lb/>IN THE SUPREME COURT OF INDIA <lb/>CIVIL APPELLATE JURISDICTION <lb/>CIVIL APPEAL NO. 4795 OF 2021 <lb/>M/S PAHWA PLASTICS PVT. LTD. AND ANR. <lb/>…... Appellants <lb/>Versus <lb/>DASTAK NGO AND ORS. <lb/>….. Respondents <lb/>J U D G M E N T <lb/>INDIRA BANERJEE, J. <lb/></front>

			<body>This appeal under Section 22 of the National Green Tribunal Act, <lb/>2010, is against an order dated 3 rd June 2021 passed by the Principal <lb/>Bench of the National Green Tribunal (NGT) in O.A No.287/2020 at New <lb/>Delhi, inter alia, holding that establishments such as the <lb/>manufacturing units of the Appellants, which did not have prior <lb/>Environmental Clearance (EC) could not be allowed to operate. <lb/>2. <lb/>The question of law involved in this appeal is, whether an <lb/>establishment employing about 8000 workers, which has been set up <lb/>pursuant to Consent to Establish (CTE) and Consent to Operate (CTO) <lb/>from the concerned statutory authority and has applied for ex post <lb/>facto EC can be closed down pending issuance of EC, even though it <lb/></body>

			<page>1 <lb/>Digitally signed by <lb/>Sanjay Kumar <lb/>Date: 2022.03.25 <lb/>16:28:56 IST <lb/>Reason: <lb/>Signature Not Verified <lb/></page>

			<body>may not cause pollution and/or may be found to comply with the <lb/>required pollution norms. <lb/>3. <lb/>With increasing industrialization and the establishment of <lb/>factories which emitted smoke and other pollutants, there was <lb/>worldwide concern for protection of environment. In June 1972, the <lb/>United Nations Conference on the Human Environment was held in <lb/>Stockholm, where decisions were taken to take appropriate steps for <lb/>preservation of the natural resources of the earth, which, among other <lb/>things, included preservation of the quality of air and water by <lb/>controlling pollution. <lb/>4. <lb/>In 1974, Parliament enacted the Water (Prevention and Control of <lb/>Pollution) Act, 1974, with a view to prevent and control water pollution <lb/>and to maintain and restore wholesomeness of water. <lb/>5. <lb/>In furtherance of the decisions taken at Stockholm, Parliament <lb/>enacted the Air (Prevention and Control of Pollution) Act, 1981, <lb/>hereinafter referred to as &quot;the Air Pollution Act&quot;, to provide for <lb/>prevention, control and abatement of air pollution. <lb/>6. <lb/>The Air Pollution Act provides for the constitution of a Central <lb/>Pollution Control Board (CPCB) and State Pollution Control Boards <lb/>(SPCB) to deal with the problem of air pollution. Section 16 of the Air <lb/>Pollution Act enables the Central Pollution Control Board to take steps <lb/>to improve the quality of air and to prevent, control or abate air <lb/>pollution in the country. Section 17 of the Air Pollution Act enables the <lb/>State Pollution Control Boards to plan comprehensive programmes for <lb/></body>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<body>the prevention, control or abatement of air pollution, inter alia, by <lb/>laying down standards for emission of air pollutants. <lb/>7. <lb/>Section 18 of the Air Pollution Act enables the Central <lb/>Government to give directions by which the CPCB is to be bound. <lb/>Similarly, every SPCB is to be bound by directions in writing as might <lb/>be given by the CPCB or the State Government. <lb/>8. <lb/>Where a notification is issued under the Air Pollution Act, placing <lb/>an area within the control area of air pollution, permission is necessary <lb/>to set up and operate any factory or plant thereat. No person <lb/>operating any factory or plant in any air pollution control area is to <lb/>discharge or cause or permit to be discharged the emission of any air <lb/>pollutants, in excess of the standards laid down by the SPCB under <lb/>Clause (g) of sub-Section (1) of Section 17. <lb/>9. <lb/>The Environment (Protection) Act, 1986, hereinafter referred to <lb/>as &quot;the EP Act&quot; was also enacted pursuant to the decisions taken at <lb/>the United Nations Conference on the Human Environment, held in <lb/>Stockholm in June, 1972. As per the Statement of Objects and Reasons <lb/>for enactment of the EP Act, the said Act has been prompted by <lb/>concern over the environment, that has grown all over the world since <lb/>the 60s. <lb/>10. Sub-section (1) of Section 3 of the EP Act empowers the Central <lb/>Government to take all such measures as it might deem necessary or <lb/>expedient for the purpose of protecting and improving the quality of <lb/></body>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>the environment and preventing, controlling and reducing <lb/>environmental pollution. <lb/>11. Sub-section (2) of Section 3 of the EP Act enables the Central <lb/>Government to take, inter alia, the following measures: <lb/>&quot;(i) co-ordination of actions by the State Governments, officers and <lb/>other authorities-<lb/>(a) under this Act, or the rules made thereunder; or <lb/>(b) under any other law for the time being in force which is relatable <lb/>to the objects of this Act; <lb/>(ii) planning and execution of a nation-wide programme for the <lb/>prevention, control and abatement of environmental pollution; <lb/>(iii) laying down standards for the quality of environment in its <lb/>various aspects; <lb/>(iv) laying down standards for emission or discharge of <lb/>environmental pollutants from various sources whatsoever: <lb/>Provided that different standards for emission or discharge may be <lb/>laid down under this clause from different sources having regard to <lb/>the quality or composition of the emission or discharge of <lb/>environmental pollutants from such sources; <lb/>(v) restriction of areas in which any industries, operations or <lb/>processes or class of industries, operations or processes shall not be <lb/>carried out or shall be carried out subject to certain safeguards; <lb/>(vi) laying down procedures and safeguards for the prevention of <lb/>accidents which may cause environmental pollution and remedial <lb/>measures for such accidents; <lb/>(vii) laying down procedures and safeguards for the handling of <lb/>hazardous substances; <lb/>(viii) examination of such manufacturing processes, materials and <lb/>substances as are likely to cause environmental pollution; <lb/>(ix) carrying out and sponsoring investigations and research relating <lb/>to problems of environmental pollution; <lb/>(x) inspection of any premises, plant, equipment, machinery, <lb/>manufacturing or other processes, materials or substances and <lb/>giving, by order, of such directions to such authorities, officers or <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>persons as it may consider necessary to take steps for the <lb/>prevention, control and abatement of environmental pollution; <lb/>(xi) establishment or recognition of environmental laboratories and <lb/>institutes to carry out the functions entrusted to such environmental <lb/>laboratories and institutes under this Act; <lb/>(xii) collection and dissemination of information in respect of <lb/>matters relating to environmental pollution; <lb/>(xiii) preparation of manuals, codes or guides relating to the <lb/>prevention, control and abatement of environmental pollution; <lb/>(xiv) such other matters as the Central Government deems <lb/>necessary or expedient for the purpose of securing the effective <lb/>implementation of the provisions of this Act.&quot; <lb/>12. Sub-section (3) of Section 3 of the EP Act provides as follows: <lb/>&quot;3. Power of Central Government to take measures to protect and <lb/>improve environment.-<lb/>... <lb/>(3) The Central Government may, if it considers it necessary or <lb/>expedient so to do for the purposes of this Act, by order, <lb/>published in the Official Gazette, constitute an authority or <lb/>authorities by such name or names as may be specified in the <lb/>order for the purpose of exercising and performing such of the <lb/>powers and functions (including the power to issue directions <lb/>under Section 5) of the Central Government under this Act and <lb/>for taking measures with respect to such of the matters <lb/>referred to in sub-section (2) as may be mentioned in the order <lb/>and subject to the supervision and control of the Central <lb/>Government and the provisions of such order, such authority or <lb/>authorities may exercise the powers or perform the functions or <lb/>take the measures so mentioned in the order as if such <lb/>authority or authorities had been empowered by this Act to <lb/>exercise those powers or perform those functions or take such <lb/>measures.&quot; <lb/>13. Subject to the provisions of the EP Act, the Central Government <lb/>has power under sub-Section (1) of Section 3, to take all such <lb/>measures, as it deems necessary or expedient, for the purpose of <lb/></body>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>protecting and improving the quality of environment and preventing, <lb/>controlling or reducing environmental pollution. <lb/>14. Section 5 of the EP Act provides that notwithstanding anything <lb/>contained in any other law, but subject to the provisions of the EP Act, <lb/>the Central Government may, in exercise of its powers and <lb/>performance of its functions under the EP Act, issue directions in <lb/>writing to any person, officer or any authority and such person, officer <lb/>or authority shall be bound to comply with such directions. <lb/>15. In exercise of powers conferred by Sections 6 and 25 of the EP <lb/>Act, the Central Government has made the Environment (Protection) <lb/>Rules, 1986, hereinafter referred to as &quot;the EP Rules&quot;. <lb/>16. The Central Government issued an Environmental Impact <lb/>Assessment Notification dated 27 th January 1994 in exercise of powers <lb/>conferred by sub-section (1) and clause (v) of sub-section (2) of <lb/>Section 3 of the EP Act read with clause (d) of sub-rule (3) of Rule 5 of <lb/>the EP Rules, directing that on and from the date of publication of the <lb/>said notification in the Official Gazette, expansion or modernization of <lb/>any activity or a new project listed in Schedule I to the said notification <lb/>shall not be undertaken in any part of India, unless it has been <lb/>accorded EC by the Central Government in accordance with the <lb/>procedures specified in the said notification. <lb/>17. In exercise of powers conferred by sub-section (1) and clause (v) <lb/>of sub-section (2) of Section 3 of the EP Act read with clause (d) of sub-<lb/>rule (3) of Rule 5 of the EP Rules and in supersession of notification <lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>number S.O. 60 (E) dated 27 th January 1994, except in respect of things <lb/>done or omitted to be done before such supersession, the Central <lb/>Government issued a notification dated 14 th September 2006, being <lb/>Notification S.O. 1533 (E) requiring prior environmental clearance from <lb/>the Central Government or as the case may be, by the State-Level <lb/>Environment Assessment Authority, duly constituted by the Central <lb/>Government under sub-section (3) of Section 3 of the EP Act. <lb/>18. In terms of the said notification dated 14 th September 2006, the <lb/>process of environmental clearance for new projects was to comprise <lb/>of a maximum of four stages, all of which might not apply to particular <lb/>cases. <lb/>The stages were (1) Screening, (2) Scoping, (3) Public <lb/>Consultation and (4) Appraisal. <lb/>19. In the meanwhile, by a notification being S.O. 327 (E) dated 10 th <lb/>April 2001, published in the Gazette of India on 12 th April 2001, the <lb/>Central Government has delegated the powers vested in it under the <lb/>EP Act, to the Chairpersons of the respective State Pollution Control <lb/>Boards/Committees to issue directions to any industry or any local or <lb/>other authority to prevent violation of the Rules. <lb/>20. The Appellants carry on business, inter alia, of manufacture and <lb/>sale of basic organic chemicals, namely, Formaldehyde. The Appellant <lb/>No.1, M/s Pahwa Plastics Private Limited has two manufacturing units, <lb/>one at village Kharawar in Rohtak, hereinafter referred to as the <lb/>&quot;Rohtak Unit&quot; and the other at village Jathlana, Jagadhri in Yamuna <lb/>Nagar in Haryana, hereinafter referred to as the &quot;Yamuna Nagar Unit&quot;. <lb/></body>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>The Appellant No.2 has a manufacturing unit at village Ghespur in <lb/>Yamuna Nagar, Haryana which is hereinafter referred to as the <lb/>&quot;Yamuna Nagar Unit&quot;. The manufacturing units established, run and <lb/>operated by the respective Appellants fall in the category of Micro, <lb/>Small and Medium Enterprise (MSME) as defined under the Micro, <lb/>Small and Medium Enterprises Development Act, 2006, hereinafter <lb/>referred to as &quot;the MSME Act&quot;. <lb/>21. On or about 31 st March 2014, the Appellant No.1, M/s Pahwa <lb/>Plastics Ltd. applied for Consent to Establish (CTE) its Yamuna Nagar <lb/>unit for manufacture of Formaldehyde. <lb/>22. By a communication No. HSPCB/Consent/:2846616YAMCTE <lb/>3087415 dated 2 nd June 2016, the Haryana State Pollution Control <lb/>Board (HSPCB) granted Consent to Establish (CTE) to the Appellant <lb/>No.1 M/s Pahwa Plastics Private Limited in respect of its Yamuna Nagar <lb/>Unit. The CTE was to remain valid for 60 months from the date of its <lb/>issue, to be extended for another year at the discretion of the Board or <lb/>till the time the unit started its trial production, whichever was earlier. <lb/>23. Some of the terms and conditions on which CTE was granted are <lb/>set out hereinbelow:-<lb/>&quot;3. The officer/official of the Board shall have the right to access and <lb/>inspection of the industry in connection with the various processes <lb/>and the treatment facilities being provided simultaneously with the <lb/>construction of building/machinery. The effluent should conform the <lb/>effluent standards as applicable. <lb/>4. That necessary arrangement shall be made by the industry for <lb/>the control of Air Pollution before commissioning the plant. The <lb/></body>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<body>emitted pollutants will meet the emission and other standards as <lb/>laid/will be prescribed by the Board from time to time. <lb/>5. The applicant will obtain consent under section 25/26 of the Water <lb/>(Prevention &amp; Control of Pollution) Act, 1974 and under section <lb/>21/22 of the Air (Prevention &amp; Control of Pollution) Act, 1981 as <lb/>amended to-date-even before starting trial production. <lb/>6. The above Consent to Establish is further subject to the conditions <lb/>that the unit complies with all the laws/rules/decisions and <lb/>competent directions of the Board/Government and its functionaries <lb/>in all respect before commissioning of the operation and during its <lb/>actual working strictly. <lb/>*** <lb/>8. The Electricity Department will give only temporary connection <lb/>and permanent connection to the unit will be given after verifying <lb/>the consent granted by the Board, both under Water Act and Air Act. <lb/>*** <lb/>12. That there is no discharge directly or indirectly from the unit or <lb/>the process into any interstate river or Yamuna River or River <lb/>Ghaggar. <lb/>13. That the industry or the unit concerned is not sited within any <lb/>prohibited distances according to the Environmental Laws and Rules, <lb/>Notification, Orders and Policies of Central Pollution Control Board <lb/>and Haryana State Pollution Control Board. <lb/>*** <lb/>17. In case of change of name from previous Consent to Establish <lb/>granted, fresh Consent to Establish fee shall be levied. <lb/>18. Industry should adopt water conservation measures to ensure <lb/>minimum consumption of water in their Process. Ground water <lb/>based proposals of new industries should get clearance from Central <lb/>Ground Water Authority for scientific development of previous <lb/>resources. <lb/>19. That the unit will take all other clearances from concerned <lb/>agencies, whenever required. <lb/>20. That the unit will not change its process without the prior <lb/>permission of the Board. <lb/>21. That the Consent to Establish so granted will be invalid, if the <lb/>unit falls in Aravali Area or non conforming area. <lb/>22. That the unit will comply with the Hazardous Waste Management <lb/>Rules and will also make the non-leachate pit for storage of <lb/>Hazardous waste and will undertake not to dispose off the same <lb/>except for pit in their own premises or with the authorized disposal <lb/>authority. <lb/>23. That the unit will submit an undertaking that it will comply with <lb/>all the specific and general conditions as imposed in the above <lb/></body>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body>Consent to Establish within 30 days failing which Consent to <lb/>Establish will be revoked.&quot; <lb/>24. By <lb/>another <lb/>communication <lb/>No.HSPCB/Consent/: <lb/>2846618YAMCTO3098246 dated 26 th March 2018, HSPCB granted <lb/>consent to the Appellant No.1 to operate its Yamuna Nagar Unit from <lb/>8 th February 2018 to 31 st March 2022. <lb/>25. By an order No.HSPCB/YMN/2242, dated 31 st March 2010, the <lb/>Appellant No.2, M/s Apcolite Polymer Private Limited was granted CTE <lb/>to establish its Yamuna Nagar Unit for manufacture of Formaldehyde <lb/>with the manufacturing capacity of 80 tonnes per day. <lb/>26. <lb/>By <lb/>another <lb/>communication <lb/>Nos. <lb/>HSPCB/Consent/: <lb/>HSPCB/YMN/DLC/2011/4027 &amp; HSPCB/YMN/DLC/2011/4029 dated 16 th <lb/>January 2012, HSPCB granted the Appellant No.2, M/s Apcolite <lb/>Polymers Private Limited, Consent to Operate (CTO) its Yamuna Nagar <lb/>Unit. The CTO has been extended from 1 st April 2016 till 31 st March <lb/>2026, by a letter dated 13 th March 2016. The CTO is valid till March <lb/>2026. <lb/>27. By a communication No. HSPCB/Consent/: 2846616YAMCT <lb/>OHWM2630357 dated 13 th March 2016, HSPCB granted consent for <lb/>emission of AIR to Appellant No.2, M/s Apcolite Polymers Private <lb/>Limited in respect of its Yamuna Nagar Unit on, inter alia, the terms <lb/>and conditions specified in the said letter, some of which are extracted <lb/>hereinbelow:-<lb/></body>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<body>&quot;10. The air pollution control equipment of such specification which <lb/>shall keep the emissions within the emission standard as approved <lb/>by the State Board from time to time shall be installed and operated <lb/>in the premises where the industry is carrying on/proposed to carry <lb/>on its business. <lb/>11. The existing air pollution control equipment if required shall be <lb/>alerted or replaced in accordance with the direction on the Board. <lb/>12. All solid wastes arising in the factory premises shall be properly <lb/>graded and disposed of by:-<lb/>(i) In case of Land fill material, care should be taken to ensure that <lb/>the material does not give rise to leachate which may percolate in <lb/>ground water of carried away with storm run off. <lb/>(ii) Composting in case of bio degradable materials. <lb/>(iii) If the method of incineration is used for the disposal of solid <lb/>waste the consent application should be processed separately and it <lb/>should be taken up which consent is granted. <lb/>13. The industry shall submit an undertaking to the effect that the <lb/>above conditions shall be complied with by them. <lb/>14. The applicant shall submit its undertaking to the effect that the <lb/>above conditions shall be complied with by them. <lb/>15. The applicant shall make an application for grant of fresh <lb/>consent at least 90 days before the date of expiry of this consent. <lb/>*** <lb/>18. There should not be any fugitive emission from the premises. <lb/>19. The liquid effluent arising out of the operation of the air pollution <lb/>control equipment shall also be treated in a manner and to the <lb/>standards stipulated in the consent granted under Water (Prevention <lb/>&amp; Control of Pollution) Act, 1974 by this Board. <lb/>*** <lb/>21. If the industry fails to adhere to any of the condition of this <lb/>consent order the consent so granted shall automatically lapse. <lb/>*** <lb/>33. The industry shall submit Environment Audit report once in a <lb/>year. <lb/>*** <lb/>38. In case of by passing the emissions, the consent shall be <lb/>deemed revoked.&quot; <lb/></body>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body>28. It is the case of the Appellants that at the time when CTE was <lb/>granted to the Appellants, it was thought that EC was not required for <lb/>units which manufactured Formaldehyde. Even HSPCB itself was not <lb/>sure of whether EC was required for such units. <lb/>29. Mr. Gupta argued that the Appellants were bona fide under the <lb/>impression that the Appellants were not required to obtain prior EC for <lb/>setting up this establishment to manufacture Formaldehyde. On the <lb/>basis of CTE granted by HSPCB, the Appellants set up their units taking <lb/>huge loans from banks for which repayments have to be paid in <lb/>installments. <lb/>30. In exercise of power under Section 3(1) and Section 3(2)(v) of <lb/>the EP Act read with Rule 5(3)(d) of the EP Rules, the Central <lb/>Government issued a notification being S.O. 804(E) dated 14 th March <lb/>2017 which provides for grant of ex post facto EC for project <lb/>proponents who had commenced, continued or completed a project <lb/>without obtaining EC under the EP Act/ EP Rules or the Environmental <lb/>Impact Notification issued thereunder. Paragraphs 3, 4 and 5 of the <lb/>said notification, read as hereunder: <lb/>&quot;(3) In cases of violation, action will be taken against the project <lb/>proponent by the respective State or State Pollution Control Board <lb/>under the provisions of section 19 of the Environment (Protection) Act, <lb/>1986 and further, no consent to operate or occupancy certificate will <lb/>be issued till the project is granted the environmental clearance. <lb/>(4) The cases of violation will be appraised by respective sector <lb/>Expert Appraisal Committees constituted under sub-section (3) of <lb/>Section 3 of the Environment (Protection) Act, 1986 with a view to <lb/>assess that the project has been constructed at a site which under <lb/></body>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<body>prevailing laws is permissible and expansion has been done which <lb/>can be run sustainably under compliance of environmental norms <lb/>with adequate environmental safeguards; and in case, where the <lb/>finding of the Expert Appraisal Committee is negative, closure of the <lb/>project will be recommended along with other actions under the law. <lb/>(5) In case, where the findings of the Expert Appraisal Committee on <lb/>point at sub-para(4) above are affirmative, the projects under this <lb/>category will be prescribed the appropriate Terms of Reference for <lb/>undertaking Environment Impact Assessment and preparation of <lb/>Environment Management Plan. Further, the Expert Appraisal <lb/>Committee will prescribe a specific Terms of Reference for the <lb/>project on assessment of ecological damage, remediation plan and <lb/>natural and community resource augmentation plan and it shall be <lb/>prepared as an independent chapter in the environment impact <lb/>assessment report by the accredited consultants. The collection and <lb/>analysis of data for assessment of ecological damage, preparation of <lb/>remediation plan and natural and community resource <lb/>augmentation plan shall be done by an environmental laboratory <lb/>duly notified under Environment (Protection) Act, 1986, or a <lb/>environmental laboratory accredited by National Accreditation Board <lb/>for Testing and Calibration Laboratories, or a laboratory of a Council <lb/>of Scientific and Industrial Research institution working in the field of <lb/>environment.&quot; <lb/>31. The Notification of 2017 is a valid statutory notification issued by <lb/>the Central Government in exercise of power under Sections 3(1) and <lb/>3(2)(v) of the EP Act read with Rule 5(3)(d) of the EP Rules in the same <lb/>manner as the EIA Notification dated 27 th January 1994 and the <lb/>Notification dated 14 th September 2006. <lb/>32. Section 21 of the General Clauses Act, 1897 provides that where <lb/>any Central Act or Regulations confer a power to issue notifications, <lb/>orders, rules or bye-laws, that power includes the power, exercisable in <lb/></body>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<body>like manner, and subject to like sanction and conditions, if any, to add <lb/>to, amend, vary or rescind any notification, order, rule or bye-law so <lb/>issued. <lb/>The authority, which had the power to issue Notifications <lb/>dated 27 th January 1994 and 14 th September 2006 undoubtedly had, <lb/>and still has the power to rescind or modify or amend those <lb/>notifications in like manner. As held by this Court in Shree Sidhbali <lb/>Steels Ltd. &amp; Others v. State of Uttar Pradesh &amp; Others 1 , power <lb/>under Section 21 to amend, vary or rescind notifications, orders, rules <lb/>or bye-laws can be exercised from time to time having regard to the <lb/>exigency. <lb/>33. Puducherry Environment Protection Association filed a Writ <lb/>Petition being W.P. No.11189 of 2017 in the High Court of Madras <lb/>assailing the said notification dated 14 th March 2017. By a judgment <lb/>and order dated 13 th October 2017, a Division Bench of the High Court <lb/>refused to interfere with the said notification, holding that the <lb/>impugned notification did not compromise with the need to preserve <lb/>environmental purity. <lb/>34. The Ministry of Environment, Forest and Climate Change (MoEF <lb/>&amp;CC) issued a draft notification dated 23 rd March 2020 which was duly <lb/>published in the Gazette of India Extraordinary Part II. The Notification <lb/>was proposed to be issued in exercise of powers conferred by sub-<lb/>section (1) and clause (v) of sub-section (2) of Section 3 of the EP Act <lb/>for dealing with cases of violation of the notification with regard to EC. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">1 (2011) 3 SCC 193 <lb/></note>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<body>It was proposed that cases of violation would be appraised by the <lb/>Appraisal Committee with a view to assess whether the project had <lb/>been constructed or operated at a site which was permissible under <lb/>prevailing laws and could be run sustainably on compliance of <lb/>environmental norms with adequate environmental safeguards. <lb/>Closure was to be recommended if the findings of the Appraisal <lb/>Committee were in the negative. If the Appraisal Committee found <lb/>that such unit had been running sustainably upon compliance of <lb/>environmental norms with adequate environment safeguards, the unit <lb/>would be prescribed appropriate Terms of Reference (TOR) after which <lb/>the procedure for grant of EC would follow. <lb/>35. On 10 th November 2020, the Department of Environment and <lb/>Climate Change of the Government of Haryana issued an order which <lb/>is extracted hereinbelow for convenience: <lb/>&quot;Whereas the process of manufacturing of Formaldehyde is covered <lb/>under the provisions of 5(f) of Schedule of Environment Impact <lb/>Assessment Notification (EIA), 2006 of Government of India, and <lb/>requires the prior Environmental Clearance (EC) from the competent <lb/>authority State Environment Impact Assessment Authority <lb/>(SEIAA)/Ministry of Environment, Forest and Climate Change, <lb/>Government of India, before establishment and operation of such <lb/>units, besides other mandatory clearance, as applicable; <lb/>Whereas, it has come to the notice of Government that around <lb/>15 such units have been permitted to establish/operate in the State <lb/>of Haryana, without obtaining the necessary Prior Environmental <lb/>Clearances, but with the Consent of the Haryana State Pollution <lb/>Control Bureau (HSPCB), which misinterpreted the category of such <lb/>units and on realising the requirement of EC in these cases, has <lb/>revoked its consents issued earlier to these units recently; <lb/>Whereas, some of these units approached the Government <lb/>explaining their hardship due to such sudden revocation of their <lb/>consents and have sought time for obtaining the necessary EC from <lb/>the competent authority as the process is likely to take a minimum <lb/>of 6 months to one year period, and to allow them to operate with <lb/></body>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<body>all pollution control measures, following the pollution control norms <lb/>applicable, and, <lb/>Whereas, the Government has carefully considered their <lb/>request and the competent authority has decided that these units <lb/>shall be allowed to continue their operations for a period of six <lb/>months, without prejudice to any legal action taken against the <lb/>violations committed by them, by the competent authorities, with <lb/>the conditions that they will immediately apply for Environmental <lb/>Clearance from the competent authority and provide the proof of <lb/>such application within 60 days from the issuance of this <lb/>communication to Environment and Climate Change Department <lb/>and to Haryana State Pollution Control Board. <lb/>Therefore, it is ordered accordingly.&quot; <lb/>36. Referring to the Counter Affidavit filed by HSPCB before the NGT, <lb/>Mr. Gupta pointed out that, since HSPCB itself was under the <lb/>misconception that prior EC was not necessary for units such as the <lb/>Yamunanagar units of the Appellants Nos. 1 and 2 respectively. <lb/>HSPCB took a policy decision to allow the units which did not have <lb/>prior EC to operate for six months, on condition that they would apply <lb/>for EC within sixty days. <lb/>37. The Appellants duly applied for EC in respect of their <lb/>manufacturing units. After scrutinizing their applications and after <lb/>finding the units suitable for grant of EC in terms of the prevailing <lb/>guidelines, the Expert Appraisal Committee constituted by the <lb/>MoEF&amp;CC conducted a public hearing to finalize the cases of the <lb/>Appellants for issuance of Terms of Reference (TOR). <lb/>38. By an Office Memorandum, being F.No. 22-21/2020-1A III, dated <lb/>7 th July 2021, the MoEF&amp;CC issued Standard Operating Procedure (SOP) <lb/>for identification and handling of violation cases under EIA Notification <lb/>2006. <lb/></body>

			<page>16 <lb/></page>

			<body>39. The said Office Memorandum, inter alia, reads: <lb/>&quot;The Ministry had issued a notification number S.O.804(E), dated <lb/>the 14 th March, 2017 detailing the process for grant of Terms of <lb/>Reference and Environmental Clearance in respect of projects or <lb/>activities which have started the work on site and/or expanded the <lb/>production beyond the limit of Prior EC or changed the product mix <lb/>without obtaining Prior EC under the EIA Notification, 2006. <lb/>2. This Notification was applicable for six months from the date of <lb/>publication i.e. 14.03.2017 to 13.09.2017 and further based on court <lb/>direction from 14.03.2018 to 13.04.2018. <lb/>3. Hon&apos;ble NGT in Original Application No.287 of 2020 in the matter <lb/>of Dastak N.G.O. Vs Synochem Organics Pvt. Ltd. &amp; Ors. and in <lb/>applications pertaining to same subject matter in Original <lb/>Application No. 298 of 2020 in Vineet Nagar vs. Central Ground <lb/>Water Authority &amp; Ors., vide order dated 03.06.2021 held that &quot;(...) <lb/>for past violations, the concerned authorities are free to take <lb/>appropriate action in accordance with polluter pays principle, <lb/>following due process&quot;. <lb/>4. Further, the Hon&apos;ble National Green Tribunal in O.A. No. 34/2020 <lb/>WZ in the matter of Tanaji B. Gambhire vs. Chief Secretary, <lb/>Government of Maharashtra and Ors., vide order dated 24.05.2021 <lb/>has directed that&quot;.... a proper SoP be laid down for grant of EC <lb/>in such cases so as to address the gaps in binding law and <lb/>practice being currently followed. <lb/>The MoEF may also <lb/>consider circulating such SoP to all SEIAAs in the country&quot;. <lb/>5. Therefore, in compliance to the directions of the Hon&apos;ble NGT a <lb/>Standard Operating Procedure (SoP) for dealing with violation cases <lb/>is required to be drawn. The Ministry is also seized of different <lb/>categories of &apos;violation&apos; cases which have been pending for want of <lb/>an approved structural/procedural framework based on &apos;Polluter <lb/>Pays Principle&apos; and &apos;Principle of Proportionality&apos;. It is undoubtedly <lb/>important that action under statutory provisions is taken against the <lb/>defaulters/violators and a decision on the closure of the project or <lb/>activity or otherwise is taken expeditiously. <lb/>6. In the light of the above directions of the Hon&apos;ble Tribunal and the <lb/>issues involved, the matter has accordingly been examined in detail <lb/>in the Ministry. A detailed SoP has accordingly been framed and is <lb/>outlined <lb/>herein. <lb/>The <lb/>SoP <lb/>is <lb/>also <lb/>guided <lb/>by <lb/>the <lb/>observations/decisions of the Hon&apos;ble Courts wherein principles of <lb/>proportionality and polluters pay have been outlined.&quot; <lb/>40. The SOP formulated by the said Office Memorandum dated 7 th <lb/>July 2021 refers to and gives effect to various judicial pronouncements <lb/></body>

			<page>17 <lb/></page>

			<body>including the judgment of this Court in Alembic Pharmaceuticals <lb/>Ltd. v. Rohit Prajapati &amp; Others 2 . <lb/>41. In terms of the SOP, the proposal for grant of EC in cases of <lb/>violation are to be considered on merits, with prospective effect, <lb/>applying principles of proportionality and the principle that the polluter <lb/>pays and is liable for costs of remedial measures. <lb/>42. By an order dated 9 th July 2021, the MoEF&amp;CC confirmed the <lb/>minutes of an earlier meeting of the Expert Appraisal Committee and <lb/>recommended issuance of terms of reference to the Appellant No.1, <lb/>M/s Pahwa Plastics Private Limited for expansion of its Formaldehyde <lb/>Manufacturing unit from 60 TPD to 150 TPD. <lb/>43. In the meanwhile, on or about 26 th November 2020, the <lb/>Respondent No.1, a Non-Governmental Organisation (NGO) hereinafter <lb/>referred to as &quot;Dastak&quot; filed an application being O.A. No./287/2020 <lb/>before the NGT praying that the order dated 10 th November 2020 <lb/>passed by the State of Haryana be quashed and units which were <lb/>operating without EC be closed. The NGT disposed of the said <lb/>application of Dastak by the impugned order dated 3 rd June 2021. <lb/>44. A Public Interest Litigation being W.P. (MD) No. 11757 of 2021 <lb/>(Fatima v. Union of India) was filed before the Madurai Bench of the <lb/>Madras High Court challenging the said Memorandum dated 7 th July <lb/>2021. By an interim order dated 15 th July 2021 a Division Bench of the <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">2 2020 SCC Online SC 347 <lb/></note>

			<page>18 <lb/></page>

			<body>Madras High Court admitted the Writ Petition and stayed the said <lb/>memorandum. <lb/>45. The Madurai Bench of the Madras High Court observed and held:-<lb/>&quot;This writ petition has been filed as a public interest <lb/>litigation challenging the validity of the office memorandum <lb/>dated 07.07.2021, issued by the respondent. <lb/>2. We have heard Mr.A.Yogeshwaran, learned counsel <lb/>appearing for the writ petitioner and Mr.L.Victoria Gowri, <lb/>learned Assistant Solicitor General of India, accepts notice for <lb/>the respondent. <lb/>3. The impugned office memorandum is challenged as being <lb/>wholly without jurisdiction, contrary to the Environment Impact <lb/>Assessment Notification, 2006, ultra vires the powers of the <lb/>respondent under the Environment (Protection) Act, 1986 and <lb/>violative of the various principles enunciated by the Hon&apos;ble <lb/>Supreme Court, while interpreting Article 21 and Article 48-A of <lb/>the Constitution of India. <lb/>4. Further, it is submitted that the impugned notification is in <lb/>gross violation of the undertaking given before the Hon&apos;ble Full <lb/>Bench of this Court in W.P.No.11189 of 2017, wherein, the Court <lb/>took note of the submissions made on behalf of the <lb/>Government of India, that the notification impugned therein is <lb/>only a one-time measure. Further, it is submitted that the <lb/>respondent failed to see that concept of ex-post facto approval <lb/>is alien to environment jurisprudence and it is anathema to the <lb/>Environment Impact Assessment Notification, 2006. <lb/>5. Further, it is submitted that the impugned notification is in <lb/>gross violation of the judgment of the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court in <lb/>the case of Alembic Pharmaceuticals Ltd. vs Rohit <lb/>Prajapati, 2020 SCC Online SC 347 and the orders passed by <lb/>the National Green Tribunal, Principal Bench, New Delhi, in the <lb/>case of S.P.Muthuraman vs. Union of India &amp; Another, <lb/>2015 SCC Online NGT 169. <lb/>6 .Identical grounds were considered by us in a challenge to an <lb/>office memorandum dated 19.02.2021, which provided a <lb/>procedure for granting post facto clearance under Coastal <lb/>Regulation Zone (CRZ) Notification 2011, on the ground that <lb/>despite no such provisions in the notification and being <lb/>contrary to the earlier judgments and undertaking. The said <lb/>writ petition in W.P(MD).No.8866 of 2021 was admitted and by <lb/>order dated 30.04.2021, the said office memorandum dated <lb/>19.02.2021 has been stayed. <lb/>7. The core issue in this writ petition is whether the <lb/>Government of India could have issued the office memorandum <lb/>and brought about the Standard Operating Procedure for <lb/>dealing with violators, who failed to comply with the mandatory <lb/></body>

			<page>19 <lb/></page>

			<body>condition of obtaining prior environment clearance under the <lb/>Environment Impact Assessment Notification 2006, read with <lb/>the provisions of Environment (Protection) Act, 1986. This issue <lb/>was considered by the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court in Alembic <lb/>Pharmaceuticals Ltd (cited supra), and it was held that such <lb/>office memorandum in the nature of circular is without <lb/>jurisdiction. The operative portion of the judgment reads as <lb/>follows: <lb/>&quot;...What is sought to be achieved by the administrative circular <lb/>dated 14 May 2002 is contrary to the statutory notification <lb/>dated 27 January 1994. The circular dated 14 May 2002 does <lb/>not stipulate how the detrimental effects on the environment <lb/>would be taken care of if the project proponent is granted an ex <lb/>post facto EC. The EIA notification of 1994 mandates a prior <lb/>environmental clearance. The circular substantially amends or <lb/>alters the application of the EIA notification of 1994. The <lb/>mandate of not commencing a new project or expanding or <lb/>modernising an existing one unless an environmental clearance <lb/>has been obtained stands diluted and is rendered ineffective by <lb/>the issuance of the administrative circular dated 14 May 2002. <lb/>This discussion leads us to the conclusion that the <lb/>administrative circular is not a measure protected by Section 3. <lb/>Hence there was no jurisdictional bar on the NGT to enquire <lb/>into its legitimacy or vires. Moreover, the administrative <lb/>circular is contrary to the EIA Notification 1994 which has a <lb/>statutory character. The circular is unsustainable in law.&quot; <lb/>8. Despite the above decision, once again the Government of <lb/>India, Ministry of Environment, Forest and Climate Change have <lb/>chosen to adopt the route of issuing the office memorandum <lb/>and virtually setting at naught the provisions of the <lb/>Environment Impact Assessment Notification and the <lb/>Environment (Protection) Act. <lb/>9. Before the Hon&apos;ble First Bench, a public interest litigation <lb/>was filed by the Puducherry Environment Protection <lb/>Association, challenging the notification dated 14.03.2017, on <lb/>identical grounds and the Hon&apos;ble First Bench by judgment <lb/>dated 13.10.2017, recorded the submissions of the learned <lb/>Assistant Solicitor General of India that the said notification <lb/>was a one-time measure and accordingly, disposed of the writ <lb/>petition. <lb/>10. Once again, the Ministry of Environment, Forest and <lb/>Climate <lb/>Change <lb/>have <lb/>issued <lb/>the <lb/>impugned <lb/>office <lb/>memorandum. Thus, from what we have noted above, we are <lb/>of the clear view that the petitioner has made out a prima facie <lb/>case for entertaining the writ petition. Accordingly, the writ <lb/>petition is admitted and there shall be an order of interim <lb/>stay.&quot; <lb/></body>

			<page>20 <lb/></page>

			<body>46. It is true that in the case of Puducherry Environment <lb/>Protection Association v. Union of India 3 , the Division Bench of <lb/>Madras High Court took note of and recorded the submission made on <lb/>behalf of the Union of India that the relaxation was a one time <lb/>relaxation. In view of such submission, this Court held that a one time <lb/>relaxation was permissible. <lb/>47. It is, however, well settled that words and phrases and/or <lb/>sentences in a judgment cannot be read in the manner of a statute, <lb/>and that too out of context. The observation of the Division Bench that <lb/>a one time relaxation was permissible, is not to be construed as a <lb/>finding that relaxation cannot be made more than once. If power to <lb/>amend or modify or relax a notification and/or order exists, the <lb/>notification and/or order may be amended and/or modified as many <lb/>times, as may be necessary. A statement made by counsel in Court <lb/>would not prevent the authority concerned from making amendments <lb/>and/or modifications provided such amendments and/or modifications <lb/>were as per the procedure prescribed by law. <lb/>48. The Division Bench of Madras High Court fell in error in staying <lb/>the said office memorandum, by relying on observations made by this <lb/>Court in Alembic Pharmaceuticals Ltd. (supra), in the context of a <lb/>circular which was contrary to the statutory Environment Impact <lb/>Notification of 1994. The attention of the High Court was perhaps not <lb/>drawn to the fact that the notification of 7 th July 2021 was in pursuance <lb/>of the statutory notification of 2017 which was valid. The judgment of <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">3 2017 SCC OnLine Mad 7056 <lb/></note>

			<page>21 <lb/></page>

			<body>this Court in Alembic Pharmaceuticals Ltd. (supra), was clearly <lb/>distinguishable and could have no application to the office <lb/>memorandum dated 7 th July 2021 which was issued pursuant to the <lb/>notification dated 14 th March 2017. <lb/>49. The Appellants have already applied for EC. <lb/>The Expert <lb/>Appraisal Committee of the MoEF&amp;CC has, after scrutinizing the <lb/>application of the Appellants and finding them eligible for grant of EC, <lb/>recommended their cases for grant of Terms of Reference (ToR). ToR <lb/>was granted to the Appellants and a public hearing had also been <lb/>conducted. Only last procedural step of issuance of EC is left. <lb/>50. <lb/>It is claimed that the units of the Appellants are totally non-polluting <lb/>units having &quot;Zero Trade discharge&quot;. They have been in operation for <lb/>many years. In the reply affidavit filed by the State before the NGT, it was <lb/>mentioned that the units were operating in good faith with valid CTOs <lb/>granted by the HSPCB. It was stated that the units were not causing <lb/>pollution hazards. The only thing against the units was the procedural <lb/>lapse of not obtaining EC. <lb/>51. <lb/>By a communication No. F. No. IA-J-110011/185/2020-IA-II(I) dated <lb/>20 th July 2021 issued to the Appellant No.1, the MoEF&amp;CC rejected the <lb/>proposal for terms of reference on the purported ground that the activity <lb/>of the Appellant No.1 was covered under category &quot;A&quot; of item 5(f) <lb/>&quot;Synthetic Organic Chemicals&quot; of the Schedule to the EIA Notification, <lb/>2006. A similar communication was issued in respect of M/s Apcolite <lb/>Polymers Pvt. Ltd. Significantly, by an order dated 9 th July 2021, the <lb/>MoEF&amp;CC had confirmed the minutes of an earlier meeting of the Expert <lb/></body>

			<page>22 <lb/></page>

			<body>Appraisal Committee and recommended issuance of ToR to the Appellant <lb/>No.1, as observed above. The proposal for Terms of Reference has <lb/>obviously been rejected at the final stage after the public hearing, by <lb/>reason of the impugned order dated 3 rd June 2021 passed by the NGT on <lb/>the application of Dastak, which is under appeal. <lb/>52. <lb/>This appeal was listed for admission on 30 th September 2021, along <lb/>with an application for interim relief being I.A. No.110064 of 2021 praying <lb/>for orders permitting the Appellants to operate their units during the <lb/>pendency of the appeal. <lb/>The appeal was heard at length at the <lb/>admission stage and reserved for judgment along with the interim <lb/>application by an order dated 30 th September 2021. <lb/>53. <lb/>After receiving the communication dated 20 th July 2021 rejecting the <lb/>proposal for Terms of Reference, the Appellants requested HSPCB to <lb/>forward to the Appellants the proceedings of public hearing in respect of <lb/>the manufacturing units of the Appellants. By a communication No. <lb/>HSPCB/YR/2021/2830 dated 15 th February 2022, HSPCB forwarded <lb/>proceedings of the public hearing in respect of the Yamuna Nagar unit of <lb/>the <lb/>Appellant <lb/>No.1. <lb/>By <lb/>another <lb/>Communication <lb/>No. <lb/>HSPCB/YR/29021/2829 dated 15 th February 2022 the HSPCB forwarded to <lb/>the Appellant No.2 the proceedings of the public hearing held on 3 rd <lb/>February 2022 in connection with the Yamuna Nagar Unit of the Appellant <lb/>No.2. <lb/>54. <lb/>The manufacturing units of the Appellants appoint about 8,000 <lb/>employees and have a huge annual turnover. An establishment <lb/>contributing to the economy of the country and providing livelihood ought <lb/></body>

			<page>23 <lb/></page>

			<body>not to be closed down only on the ground of the technical irregularity of <lb/>not obtaining prior Environmental Clearance irrespective of whether or not <lb/>the unit actually causes pollution. <lb/>55. <lb/>In Electrosteel Steels Limited v. Union of India 4 , this Court <lb/>held:-<lb/>&quot;82. The question is whether an establishment <lb/>contributing to the economy of the country and <lb/>providing livelihood to hundreds of people should be <lb/>closed down for the technical irregularity of shifting its <lb/>site without prior environmental clearance, without <lb/>opportunity to the establishment to regularize its <lb/>operation by obtaining the requisite clearances and <lb/>permissions, even though the establishment may not <lb/>otherwise be violating pollution laws, or the pollution, if <lb/>any, can conveniently and effectively be checked. The <lb/>answer has to be in the negative. <lb/>83. The Central Government is well within the scope of its <lb/>powers under Section 3 of the 1986 Act to issue directions to <lb/>control and/or prevent pollution including directions for prior <lb/>Environmental Clearance before a project is commenced. Such <lb/>prior Environmental Clearance is necessarily granted upon <lb/>examining the impact of the project on the environment. Ex-<lb/>Post facto Environmental Clearance should not ordinarily be <lb/>granted, and certainly not for the asking. At the same time <lb/>ex post facto clearances and/or approvals and/or <lb/>removal of technical irregularities in terms of <lb/>Notifications under the 1986 Act cannot be declined <lb/>with pedantic rigidity, oblivious of the consequences of <lb/>stopping the operation of a running steel plant. <lb/>84. The 1986 Act does not prohibit ex post facto <lb/>Environmental Clearance. Some relaxations and even grant <lb/>of ex post facto EC in accordance with law, in strict compliance <lb/>with Rules, Regulations Notifications and/or applicable orders, <lb/>in appropriate cases, where the projects are in compliance <lb/>with, or can be made to comply with environment norms, is in <lb/>over view not impermissible. The Court cannot be oblivious to <lb/>the economy or the need to protect the livelihood of hundreds <lb/>of employees and others employed in the project and others <lb/>dependent on the project, if such projects comply with <lb/>environmental norms. <lb/>*** <lb/>88. The Notification being SO 804(E) dated 14th March, 2017 <lb/>was not an issue in Alembic Pharmaceuticals (supra). This <lb/>Court was examining the propriety and/or legality of a 2002 <lb/>circular which was inconsistent with the EIA Notification dated <lb/>27th January, 1994, which was statutory. Ex post facto <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">4 2021 SCC online SC 1247 <lb/></note>

			<page>24 <lb/></page>

			<body>environmental clearance should not however be granted <lb/>routinely, but in exceptional circumstances taking into account <lb/>all relevant environmental factors. Where the adverse <lb/>consequences of ex post facto approval outweigh the <lb/>consequences of regularization of operation of an industry by <lb/>grant of ex post facto approval and the industry or <lb/>establishment concerned otherwise conforms to the requisite <lb/>pollution norms, ex post facto approval should be given in <lb/>accordance with law, in strict conformity with the applicable <lb/>Rules, Regulations and/or Notifications. Ex post facto <lb/>approval should not be withheld only as a penal <lb/>measure. The deviant industry may be penalised by an <lb/>imposition of heavy penalty on the principle of &apos;polluter pays&apos; <lb/>and the cost of restoration of environment may be recovered <lb/>from it. <lb/>*** <lb/>96. The appeals are allowed. The impugned order is set aside. <lb/>The Respondent No. 1 shall take a decision on the <lb/>application of the Appellant for revised EC in <lb/>accordance with law, within three months from date. <lb/>Pending such decision, the operation of the steel plant <lb/>shall not be interfered with on the ground of want of EC, <lb/>FC, CTE or CTO.&quot; <lb/>56. As held by this Court in Electrosteel Steels Limited (supra) ex <lb/>post facto Environmental Clearance should not ordinarily be granted, <lb/>and certainly not for the asking. At the same time ex post facto <lb/>clearances and/or approvals and/or removal of technical irregularities <lb/>in terms of a Notification under the EP Act cannot be declined with <lb/>pedantic rigidity, oblivious of the consequences of stopping the <lb/>operation of mines, running factories and plants. <lb/>57. The 1986 Act does not prohibit ex post facto Environmental <lb/>Clearance. Grant of ex post facto EC in accordance with law, in strict <lb/>compliance with Rules, Regulations, Notifications and/or applicable <lb/>orders, in appropriate cases, where the projects are in compliance <lb/>with, or can be made to comply with environment norms, is in our view <lb/>not impermissible. The Court cannot be oblivious to the economy or <lb/></body>

			<page>25 <lb/></page>

			<body>the need to protect the livelihood of hundreds of employees and others <lb/>employed in the project and others dependent on the project, if such <lb/>projects comply with environmental norms. <lb/>58. As held by a three Judge Bench of this Court in Lafarge Umiam <lb/>Mining Private Limited v. Union of India 5 :-<lb/>&quot;119. The time has come for us to apply the constitutional <lb/>&quot;doctrine of proportionality&quot; to the matters concerning <lb/>environment as a part of the process of judicial review in <lb/>contradistinction to merit review. It cannot be gainsaid that <lb/>utilization of the environment and its natural resources has to <lb/>be in a way that is consistent with principles of sustainable <lb/>development and intergenerational equity, but balancing of <lb/>these equities may entail policy choices. In the circumstances, <lb/>barring exceptions, decisions relating to utilisation of natural <lb/>resources have to be tested on the anvil of the well-recognized <lb/>principles of judicial review. Have all the relevant factors been <lb/>taken into account? Have any extraneous factors influenced <lb/>the decision? Is the decision strictly in accordance with the <lb/>legislative policy underlying the law (if any) that governs the <lb/>field? Is the decision consistent with the principles of <lb/>sustainable development in the sense that has the decision-<lb/>maker taken into account the said principle and, on the basis <lb/>of relevant considerations, arrived at a balanced decision? <lb/>Thus, the Court should review the decision-making process to <lb/>ensure that the decision of MoEF is fair and fully informed, <lb/>based on the correct principles, and free from any bias or <lb/>restraint. Once this is ensured, then the doctrine of &quot;margin of <lb/>appreciation&quot; in favour of the decision-maker would come into <lb/>play.&quot; <lb/>59. In Alembic Pharmaceuticals Ltd.(supra), this Court observed:-<lb/>&quot;27. The concept of an ex post facto EC is in derogation of the <lb/>fundamental principles of environmental jurisprudence and is <lb/>an anathema to the EIA notification dated 27 January 1994. It <lb/>is, as the judgment in Common Cause holds, detrimental to the <lb/>environment and could lead to irreparable degradation. The <lb/>reason why a retrospective EC or an ex post facto clearance is <lb/>alien to environmental jurisprudence is that before the issuance <lb/>of an EC, the statutory notification warrants a careful <lb/>application of mind, besides a study into the likely <lb/>consequences of a proposed activity on the environment. An <lb/>EC can be issued only after various stages of the decision-<lb/>5 (2011) 7 SCC 338 <lb/></body>

			<page>26 <lb/></page>

			<body>making process have been completed. Requirements such as <lb/>conducting a public hearing, screening, scoping and appraisal <lb/>are components of the decision-making process which ensure <lb/>that the likely impacts of the industrial activity or the <lb/>expansion of an existing industrial activity are considered in the <lb/>decision-making calculus. Allowing for an ex post facto <lb/>clearance would essentially condone the operation of industrial <lb/>activities without the grant of an EC. In the absence of an EC, <lb/>there would be no conditions that would safeguard the <lb/>environment. Moreover, if the EC was to be ultimately refused, <lb/>irreparable harm would have been caused to the environment. <lb/>In either view of the matter, environment law cannot <lb/>countenance the notion of an ex post facto clearance. This <lb/>would be contrary to both the precautionary principle as well as <lb/>the need for sustainable development.&quot; <lb/>60. Even though this Court deprecated ex post facto clearances, in <lb/>Alembic Pharmaceuticals Ltd. (supra), this Court did not direct <lb/>closure of the units concerned but explored measures to control the <lb/>damage caused by the industrial units. This Court held:-<lb/>&quot;However, since the expansion has been undertaken and the <lb/>industry has been functioning, we do not deem it appropriate <lb/>to order closure of the entire plant as directed by the High <lb/>Court.&quot; <lb/>61. <lb/>The Notification being SO. 804(E) dated 14 th March 2017 was not <lb/>in issue in Alembic Pharmaceuticals Ltd. (supra). In Alembic <lb/>Pharmaceuticals Ltd. (supra) this Court was examining the propriety <lb/>and/or legality of a 2002 circular which was inconsistent with the EIA <lb/>Notification dated 27 th January 1994, which was statutory. The EIA <lb/>Notification dated 27 th January 1994 has, as stated above, been <lb/>superseded by the Notification dated 14 th September 2006. <lb/>62. There can be no doubt that the need to comply with the <lb/>requirement to obtain EC is non-negotiable. A unit can be set up or <lb/>allowed to expand subject to compliance of the requisite <lb/></body>

			<page>27 <lb/></page>

			<body>environmental norms. EC is granted on condition of the suitability of <lb/>the site to set up the unit, from the environmental angle, and also <lb/>existence of necessary infrastructural facilities and equipment for <lb/>compliance of environmental norms. To protect future generations and <lb/>to ensure sustainable development, it is imperative that pollution laws <lb/>be strictly enforced. Under no circumstances can industries, which <lb/>pollute, be allowed to operate unchecked and degrade the <lb/>environment. <lb/>63. Ex post facto environmental clearance should not be granted <lb/>routinely, but in exceptional circumstances taking into account all <lb/>relevant environmental factors. Where the adverse consequences of <lb/>denial of ex post facto approval outweigh the consequences of <lb/>regularization of operations by grant of ex post facto approval, and the <lb/>establishment concerned otherwise conforms to the requisite pollution <lb/>norms, ex post facto approval should be given in accordance with law, <lb/>in strict conformity with the applicable Rules, Regulations and/or <lb/>Notifications. The deviant industry may be penalised by an imposition <lb/>of heavy penalty on the principle of &apos;polluter pays&apos; and the cost of <lb/>restoration of environment may be recovered from it. <lb/>64. The question in this case is, whether a unit contributing to the <lb/>economy of the country and providing livelihood to hundreds of <lb/>people, which has been set up pursuant to requisite approvals from the <lb/>concerned statutory authorities, and has applied for ex post facto EC, <lb/>should be closed down for the technical irregularity of want of prior <lb/></body>

			<page>28 <lb/></page>

			<body>environmental clearance, pending the issuance of EC, even though it <lb/>may not cause pollution and/or may be found to comply with the <lb/>required norms. The answer to the aforesaid question has to be in the <lb/>negative, more so when the HSPCB was itself under the misconception <lb/>that no environment clearance was required for the units in question. <lb/>HSPCB has in its counter affidavit before the NGT clearly stated that a <lb/>decision was taken to regularize units such as the Apcolite Yamuna <lb/>Nagar and Pahwa Yamuna Nagar Units, since requisite approvals had <lb/>been granted to those units, by the concerned authorities on the <lb/>misconception that no EC was required. <lb/>65. It is reiterated that the 1986 Act does not prohibit ex post facto <lb/>EC. <lb/>Some relaxations and even grant of ex post facto EC in <lb/>accordance with law, in strict compliance with Rules, Regulations, <lb/>Notifications and/or applicable orders, in appropriate cases, where the <lb/>projects are in compliance with environment norms, is not <lb/>impermissible. As observed by this Court in Electrosteel Steels <lb/>Limited (supra), this Court cannot be oblivious to the economy or the <lb/>need to protect the livelihood of hundreds of employees and others <lb/>employed in the units and dependent on the units in their survival. <lb/>66. Ex post facto EC should not ordinarily be granted, and certainly <lb/>not for the asking. At the same time ex post facto clearances and/or <lb/>approvals cannot be declined with pedantic rigidity, regardless of the <lb/>consequences of stopping the operations. This Court is of the view <lb/></body>

			<page>29 <lb/></page>

			<body>that the NGT erred in law in directing that the units cannot be allowed <lb/>to function till compliance of the statutory mandate. <lb/>67. Accordingly, the appeal is allowed. The impugned order is set <lb/>aside in so far as the same is applicable to the units of the Appellants <lb/>established and operated pursuant to CTE and CTO from the HSPCB in <lb/>respect of which applications for ex post facto EC have been filed. <lb/>The Respondent shall take a decision on the applications of the <lb/>Appellants for EC in accordance with law within one month from date. <lb/>Pending decision, the operation of the Pahwa Yamuna Nagar Unit and <lb/>the Apcolite Yamuna Nagar Unit, in respect of which consents have <lb/>been granted and even public hearing held in connection with grant of <lb/>EC, shall not be interfered with. <lb/>68. The Appellants will be allowed to operate the units. Electricity, if <lb/>disconnected, shall be restored subject to payment of charges, if any. If <lb/>the application for EC is rejected on the ground of any contravention <lb/>on the part of the Appellants, it will be open to the Respondents to <lb/>disconnect the supply of electricity. <lb/>69. The Union of India had proceeded with the application for EC and <lb/>even public hearing had been held. Counsel appearing on behalf of <lb/>the Union of India contended that the Appellant had not submitted its <lb/>final application for EC, after public hearing. It is not clear what more <lb/>was required of the Appellants. Be that as it may, the Union of India <lb/>shall, within three working days from the date of receipt of a copy of <lb/>this judgment and order, inform the Appellants in writing of whether <lb/></body>

			<page>30 <lb/></page>

			<body>anything further is required to be done by the Appellants, and if so <lb/>what is required to be done. The Appellants shall, within a week <lb/>thereafter do the needful. The final decision on the application of the <lb/>Appellants for EC shall be taken within three weeks thereafter. <lb/>70. The application being I.A. No.110064/2021 and other pending <lb/>applications, if any, in this appeal are disposed of accordingly. <lb/>…..............................J. <lb/>[INDIRA BANERJEE] <lb/>................................J. <lb/>[J.K. MAHESHWARI] <lb/>NEW DELHI <lb/>MARCH 25, 2022 <lb/></body>

			<page>31 </page>


	</text>
</tei>
