<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="561822"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<extra>IN THE</extra>

	<court>HIGH COURT OF JUDICATURE AT MADRAS<lb/></court>

	<extra>Dated:</extra>

	<judgement_date>20.12.2018</judgement_date>

	<extra>CORAM<lb/> THE</extra>

	<judges>HON&apos;BLE MR.JUSTICE M.SUNDAR<lb/></judges>

	<case_numbers>C.S.No.461 of 2018<lb/> and O.A.Nos. 664 and 665 of 2018<lb/></case_numbers>

	<extra>1.</extra>

	<respondent>Mr.A.D.Padmasingh Isaac<lb/></respondent>
	<extra>Trading as Aachi Spices and Foods<lb/> Old No.4, New No.181/1,<lb/> 6 th Avenue, Thangam Colony,<lb/> Anna Nagar, Chennai -600 040.<lb/> 2.</extra>

	<respondent>M/s.Aachi Masala Foods (P) Ltd.</respondent>
	<extra>,<lb/> Old No.4, New No.181/1,<lb/> 6 th Avenue, Thangam Colony,<lb/> Anna Nagar, Chennai -600 040<lb/> Represented by its Director<lb/> Mr. Ashwin Pandian<lb/> ..Plaintiffs<lb/> Vs.<lb/></extra>

	<respondent>Mallika Thiagarajan,<lb/> AA-19, 3 rd Street,<lb/> Anna Nagar,<lb/> Chennai-600 040.<lb/></respondent>
	<extra>.. Defendants<lb/> This Civil Suit is preferred, under Order IV Rule 1 of O.S.<lb/> Rules and Order VII Rule 1 of Civil Procedure Code, read with<lb/> Sections 27(2),29, 134, 135 of the Trademarks Act, 1999 praying to<lb/> (a) granting a permanent injunction, restraining the<lb/> Defendant, by itself, its servants, agents, distributors, or anyone<lb/> claiming through him from manufacturing, selling, advertising and<lb/> offering for sale of goods/service using the Trade Mark &quot;ACHI&apos;S<lb/> SANTHAI&quot; or any other similar Trade Mark or similar sounding<lb/> made by them by the use of the impugned trademark &quot;ACHI&apos;S<lb/> SANTHAI&quot; on the goods referred and decree the suit for the profits<lb/> found to have been made by the Defendant, after the Defendant<lb/> has rendered accounts:<lb/> (e) directing the Defendant to pay to the Plaintiffs the cost to<lb/> the suit, and<lb/> (f) pass such further or other order, as this Hon&apos;ble Court<lb/> may deem fit and proper in the circumstances of the case and thus<lb/> render justice.<lb/> For Plaintiffs<lb/> :</extra>

	<petitioner_lawyers>Ms.Gladys Daniel<lb/></petitioner_lawyers>
	<extra>For Defendant :</extra>

	<respondent_lawyers>Set ex-parte
	<document_type>JUDGMENT</document_type>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
