<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<page>1 <lb/></page>

			<front>IN THE HIGH COURT OF JUDICATURE AT MADRAS <lb/>Dated: 31.01.2019 <lb/>CORAM <lb/>THE HON&apos;BLE MR.JUSTICE M.SUNDAR <lb/>C.S.No.290 of 2017 <lb/>and O.A.Nos.398 and 399 of 2017 <lb/>and A.No.2351 of 2017 <lb/>1.Mr.A.D.Padmasingh Isaac <lb/>Trading as Aachi Spices and Foods <lb/>Old No.4, New No.181/1, <lb/>6 th Avenue, Thangam Colony, <lb/>Anna Nagar, <lb/>Chennai -600 040. <lb/>2.M/s.Aachi Masala Foods (P) Ltd., <lb/>Old No.4, New No.181/1, <lb/>6 th Avenue, Thangam Colony, <lb/>Anna Nagar, <lb/>Chennai -600 040 <lb/>Represented by its Director <lb/>Mr.Ashwin Pandian <lb/>3.M/s.Heavenly Foods Pvt Ltd., <lb/>Plot No.1926, 34 th Street, <lb/>I Block, Ishwarya Colony, <lb/>Anna Nagar West, <lb/>Chennai -600 040. <lb/>Represented by its Director <lb/>Mr.Gibson Gnanasiromani Vedamani <lb/>.. Plaintiffs <lb/>Vs. <lb/>Aachi Mess <lb/>No.92/1, Sankari Main Road, <lb/>Seetharampalayam, <lb/>Tiruchengodu 637 209, <lb/>Namkkal (DT) <lb/>.. Defendant <lb/></front>

			<note place="footnote">http://www.judis.nic.in <lb/></note>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<body>This Civil Suit is preferred, under Order IV Rule -1 of the Original <lb/>Side Rules and Order VII Rule of the Civil Procedure Code, 1908 Read with <lb/>Sections 27(2), 29, 134 and 135 of the Trade Marks Act, 1999, Praying for <lb/>a) granting a permanent injunction, restraining the defendant, by <lb/>himself, its agents or servants or anyone claiming through him from <lb/>manufacturing, selling, advertising and offering for sale using the name <lb/>Aachi Mess or any other similar Trade Mark name or similar sounding <lb/>expression in any media and use the same in name board, invoices, letter <lb/>heads and visiting cards or by using any other trade mark/name which is in <lb/>any way visually or deceptively or phonetically similar to the 1 st Plaintiff&apos;s <lb/>trademark/ name AACHI/AACHI CHETINAD RESTAURANT/AACHI KITCHEN <lb/>and use the same in pouches, packets or use the mark in invoices, letters <lb/>heads and visiting cards or part of their Hotel/Restaurant name any other <lb/>trade literature or Menu card by using any other trade mark which is in any <lb/>way visually, or phonetically similar to the Plaintiffs &apos; registered Trade mark <lb/>Nos. 838786, 1116254, 1479159, 1715718 or in any manner infringing the 1 st <lb/>Plaintiff&apos;s registered Trade Marks referred herein. <lb/>b) granting a permanent injunction restraining the Defendant by <lb/>itself, its agents or servants or anyone claiming through or under him any <lb/>business marketing, selling advertising using in trade literature, menu <lb/>cards, invoices, name boards, website, internet advertisements the <lb/>mark/name Aachi Mess in relation to the Restaurant or with respect to or <lb/>any other food preparation or any other business the impugned <lb/>trademark/name which is in any manner deceptively or phonetically <lb/>confusingly similar to the Plaintiff&apos;s Trade Mark/name AACHI/AACHI <lb/>CHETINAD RESTAURANT/AACHI KITCHEN or in any other manner pass off <lb/>their hotel, business or goods as and for that of the plaintiffs. <lb/>c) directing the defendant to surrender to the Plaintiffs all the <lb/>packing material, cartons, advertisement materials and hoardings, letter-<lb/>heads, visiting cards, office stationery and all other materials <lb/>containing/bearing the name Aachi Mess or other identical trade mark used <lb/>in the pouches and packets bearing the word AACHI/AACHI HOTEL/AACHI <lb/>CHETINAD RESTAURANT/AACHI KITCHEN. <lb/>d) directing the defendant to render an account of profits made by <lb/>them by the use of the impugned trademark Aachi Mess, on the service <lb/>referred and decree the suit for the profits found to have been made by the <lb/>defendant, after the defendant has rendered accounts. <lb/>e) directing the defendant to pay to the Plaintiffs the costs to the <lb/>suit and <lb/>f) pass such further or other order, as this Hon&apos;ble Court may deem <lb/>fit and proper in the circumstances of the case and thus render justice. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">http://www.judis.nic.in <lb/></note>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<front>For Plaintiffs <lb/>: Ms. Gladys Daniel <lb/>For Defendant <lb/>: set ex-parte <lb/>JUDGMENT <lb/></front>

			<body>There are three plaintiffs. Plaintiff No.1 is an individual i.e., a <lb/>natural person. Plaintiff Nos.2 and 3 are Private Limited Companies i.e., <lb/>juristic persons. Ms.Gladys Daniel, counsel on record for all the three <lb/>plaintiffs is before this Commercial Division. <lb/>2. The sole defendant was duly served with suit summons on <lb/>23.05.2017, entered appearance through counsel, but said counsel reported <lb/>&apos;no instructions&apos; from defendant and no new counsel entered appearance on <lb/>behalf of defendant. Therefore, the sole defendant was set ex-parte on <lb/>23.01.2019 and the suit itself was set down for recording ex-parte evidence <lb/>before the learned Additional Master-II. One Mr.B.Gnana Sambandam <lb/>deposed as P.W.1, on behalf of all the three plaintiffs and 24 exhibits i.e., <lb/>Exs.P1 to P24 were marked through him. <lb/>3. Today, this suit is listed for arguments before this Commercial <lb/>Division. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">http://www.judis.nic.in <lb/></note>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>4. Before proceeding further, it is necessary to set out the case of <lb/>the plaintiffs in a nutshell. Main thrust of plaintiffs&apos; complaint is that the <lb/>defendant is infringing and passing off qua four of their registered <lb/>trademarks. The four trademarks are Trade Mark Nos.838786, 1116254, <lb/>1479159 and 1715718. These four trademarks have been marked as Exs.P18 <lb/>to P21. These four trademarks shall hereinafter be referred to as &apos;suit TMs&apos; <lb/>for the sake of brevity, convenience and clarity. The details of the suit TMs <lb/>can be tabulated and set out as below: <lb/>S.No. Trademark <lb/>No. <lb/>Class and goods <lb/>Mark <lb/>1 <lb/>838786 <lb/>30-Masala Powder and Spices <lb/>AACHI <lb/>2 <lb/>1116254 <lb/>30-All kinds of Food preparations <lb/>for human consumption coffee, Tea, <lb/>Coca, Sugar, Rice, Tapioca, Sago, <lb/>Coffee Substitutes, Flour and <lb/>Preparations made from cereals, <lb/>Bread, Biscuits, Cakes, Pastry and <lb/>Confectionery, Ice <lb/>3 <lb/>1479159 <lb/>30-All kinds of Masala Powders and <lb/>Spices, Honey, Crystallized Fruits, <lb/>Dates, Fruit Jellies, Jams, processed <lb/>peanut, pickle, potato chips and <lb/>potato crisps, all kinds of flour, <lb/>coffee, Tea cocoa, sugar, rice, <lb/>tapioca and artificial powder, <lb/>asafetida, turmeric powder, idly <lb/>chilly powder appalams, orid dhall, <lb/>Toor dhall, Moong Dhall and all <lb/>kinds of Dhall, included in class 30 <lb/>4 <lb/>1715718 <lb/>43-Services for chain of restaurants, <lb/>Providing of Food and Drink, <lb/>Temporary <lb/>Accommodation, <lb/>canteen, catering, self service <lb/>restaurants, fast food restaurants and <lb/>snack bars <lb/>AACHI KITCHN <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">http://www.judis.nic.in <lb/></note>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>5. It is the case of the plaintiffs that somewhere in March 2017, they <lb/>came to know about the alleged infringement of their suit TMs and passing <lb/>off by the defendant. The instant suit vide plaint dated 03.04.2017 was <lb/>presented/filed in this Court on 07.04.2017. Thereafter, this suit took the <lb/>trajectory, which has been set out supra. <lb/>6. Today in the hearing, learned counsel for plaintiffs Ms.Gladys <lb/>Daniel brings to my notice that the depiction of the suit TMs by the <lb/>plaintiffs has been marked by way of a photograph being Ex.P22 and the <lb/>same is as follows: <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">http://www.judis.nic.in <lb/></note>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>To be noted, one photograph is that of the Restaurant and the other is <lb/>photograph of a Menu card. These two together constitute Ex.P.22. <lb/>(Ideally it should have been marked as Ex.P22 series) <lb/>7. To buttress plaintiffs&apos; complaint of infringement and passing off <lb/>qua suit TMS, my attention is drawn to the alleged offending mark that <lb/>http://www.judis.nic.in <lb/></body>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>(according to plaintiffs) is being used by the defendant. Alleged offending <lb/>mark has been marked as Ex.P 24. Ex.P 24 is as follows: <lb/>8. To be noted, in suit TMs, word &apos;AACHI&apos; is a very prominent part of <lb/>the mark. In any event one of the suit TMs is &apos;AACHI&apos; itself. <lb/>9. Plaintiffs have set out the manner in which the suit TMs evolved. <lb/>This is articulated in paragraph Nos.8 to 10 of the plaint, which read as <lb/>follows: <lb/>&quot;8. A proprietary concern Aachi Spices and Foods was <lb/>registered on 28.12.2006. Aachi Masala Foods P Ltd., who <lb/>acquired the trademark AACHI on 30.11.2016 from Abishek <lb/>Enterprises and Naveen Products assigned the same in favour <lb/>of the 1 st plaintiff, trading as Aachi Spices And Foods on <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">http://www.judis.nic.in <lb/></note>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<body>30.03.2007. On 01.04.2007, the 1 st plaintiff, trading as Aachi <lb/>Spices and Foods executed a License User Agreement in <lb/>favour of Aachi Masala Foods P Ltd. The sole proprietary <lb/>concern of the 1 st plaintiff owned the Intellectual Property <lb/>Rights under the trademark AACHI. The Trademark AACHI <lb/>expanded on its list of products. The business of AACHI was <lb/>expanding in mammoth proportions. On 17.03.2010, Aachi <lb/>Spices and Foods Private Limited were incorporated. At the <lb/>time of incorporation of Aachi Spices and Foods Private <lb/>Limited the Memorandum of Association of the company <lb/>reiterated at Clause B-11 that the Trademark AACHI along <lb/>with its right, title and interest were vested with the 1 st <lb/>plaintiff who already owned the Trademark AACHI. On <lb/>21.04.2010 the 1 st plaintiff entered into a Licence User <lb/>Agreement with Aachi Spices and Foods Private Limited to <lb/>use the trademark AACHI. On 21.04.2010 the 1 st plaintiff <lb/>entered into a fresh License User Agreement with AACHI <lb/>Masala Foods Private Limited. <lb/>9. The 1 st plaintiff is the proprietor of the trademark <lb/>AACHI. He continues to use the trademark AACHI through his <lb/>Licensees AACHI Spices and Foods Private Limited and the 2 nd <lb/>Plaintiff. The 3 rd Plaintiff is the licensee of the 1 st Plaintiff&apos;s <lb/>registered Trade Marks AACHI KITCHEN and AACHI CHETTINAD <lb/>RESTAURANT. <lb/>10. The Plaintiffs have also diversified their business <lb/>activities and started manufacturing and marketing various <lb/>kinds of consumer goods, within a short span of 17 years. <lb/>The Plaintiffs have now become one of the leading <lb/>manufacturers of packaged masalas. Because of the efforts <lb/>undertaken by the Plaintiffs in promoting and advertising <lb/>their products through various mediums, their market share <lb/>http://www.judis.nic.in <lb/></body>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body>in these products have risen considerably. The Plaintiffs <lb/>have put in enormous effort, hard work and money towards <lb/>advertising their products AACHI in all forms of media such as <lb/>radio, newspapers, hoardings, magazines and television <lb/>networks. The Plaintiffs have also received many prestigious <lb/>awards for the quality of products and customer service.&quot; <lb/>10. Plaintiffs have also mentioned about the manner in which they <lb/>have used and promoted suit TMS, this is contained in paragraph Nos.13 <lb/>and 14 of the plaint, which read as follows: <lb/>&quot;13. The subject matter of this proceeding is in <lb/>respect of &apos;AACHI&apos; word mark. This word mark as whole has <lb/>been used by the Plaintiffs since 1995 and has become a well <lb/>known Trade Mark of the Plaintiffs. The Plaintiffs have <lb/>honestly adopted the mark and have put in enormous <lb/>amount of hard work and labour and invested huge sums of <lb/>money, for advertisement and sales promotional expenses. <lb/>Because of the efforts made by the Plaintiffs, the trade and <lb/>the public, associate the mark with the Plaintiffs and none <lb/>else. The Trade Mark of the Plaintiffs as used is registered. <lb/>14. The plaintiffs have been using this mark AACHI <lb/>with respect to almost all the masala preparations from the <lb/>commencement of its business. As a result of the efforts <lb/>undertaken by the Plaintiffs its turnover has been <lb/>increasing, substantially every year. The turnover and <lb/>promotional <lb/>expenditure <lb/>incurred <lb/>by <lb/>M/s.Abishek <lb/>Enterprises, M/s.Naveen Products, M/s.Nazareth Foods Pvt. <lb/>Ltd. and M/s.Aachi Masala Foods Pvt. Ltd., since 1995 is <lb/>given hereunder: <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">http://www.judis.nic.in <lb/></note>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<body>S.No. <lb/>Year <lb/>Turnover <lb/>(in Rs) <lb/>Advertising <lb/>Expenditure <lb/>(in Rs) <lb/>1 <lb/>1995-1996 <lb/>3,96,420.00 <lb/>9.983.00 <lb/>2 <lb/>1996-1997 <lb/>4,37,568.00 <lb/>4,691.00 <lb/>3 <lb/>1997-1998 <lb/>5,10,755.00 <lb/>352.00 <lb/>4 <lb/>1998-1999 <lb/>14,68,159.00 <lb/>15,820.00 <lb/>5 <lb/>1999-2000 <lb/>20,27,457.00 <lb/>16,775.00 <lb/>6 <lb/>2000-2001 <lb/>52,03,979.00 <lb/>57,676.00 <lb/>7 <lb/>2001-2002 <lb/>64,12,491.00 <lb/>2,13,512.00 <lb/>8 <lb/>2002-2003 <lb/>1,69,44,334.00 <lb/>6,62,290.00 <lb/>9 <lb/>2003-2004 <lb/>9,00,05,884.00 <lb/>19,63,479.00 <lb/>10 <lb/>2004-2005 <lb/>24,46,95,540.00 <lb/>1,13,28,450.00 <lb/>11 <lb/>2005-2006 <lb/>79,47,99,230.00 <lb/>4,63,96,880.00 <lb/>12 <lb/>2006-2007 <lb/>1,36,54,50,781.00 <lb/>5,68,45,817.00 <lb/>13 <lb/>2007-2008 <lb/>2,07,85,55,508.00 <lb/>7,87,06,261.00 <lb/>14 <lb/>2008-2009 <lb/>4,14,12,42,106.00 <lb/>9,40,86,979.00 <lb/>15 <lb/>2009-2010 <lb/>4,73,98,26,852.00 <lb/>10,76,86,530.00 <lb/>16 <lb/>2010-2011 <lb/>6,40,40,50,524.00 <lb/>11,63,97,497.00 <lb/>17 <lb/>2011-2012 <lb/>7,59,35,14,309.00 <lb/>12,42,15,050.00 <lb/>18 <lb/>2012-2013 <lb/>8,82,91,64,390.00 <lb/>13,72,06,476.00 <lb/>19 <lb/>2013-2014 <lb/>11,27,06,92,876.00 <lb/>19,57,87,446.00 <lb/>20 <lb/>2014-2015 <lb/>13,20,61,70,537.00 <lb/>21,00,17,044.00 <lb/>11. From the aforesaid details, it comes to light that the plaintiffs <lb/>have been expending/shelling out, substantial sums of money towards <lb/>advertisement expenditure. <lb/>12. Be that as it may, learned counsel for plaintiffs brings to my <lb/>notice that plaintiffs have been very diligently protecting their suit TMs as <lb/>http://www.judis.nic.in <lb/></body>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body>well as the other trademark registrations in their favour. It is highlighted <lb/>by learned counsel for plaintiffs that plaintiffs have been so diligent that <lb/>they have taken immediate action against a person in California in the <lb/>Trademark Trial and Appeal Board in United States of America. In this <lb/>regard, an order dated 13.09.2016 has been marked as Ex.P23. This is being <lb/>referred to, to emphasise that the plaintiffs have been very diligent in <lb/>protecting their marks/&apos;intellectual property rights&apos; (&apos;IPRs&apos; for brevity) and <lb/>particularly suit TMs. With regard to the inter se relationship between the <lb/>three plaintiffs, it is to be mentioned that the first plaintiff, who is a <lb/>natural person is the owner of the suit TMs. The second plaintiff, which is a <lb/>juristic person and a company is a general licensee under the first plaintiff <lb/>vide License User Agreement, which has been marked as Ex.P13. With <lb/>regard to plaintiff No.3, which is also a juristic person, I am informed that <lb/>plaintiff No.3 is a licensee with regard to one specific service i.e., <lb/>Restaurant services and this License User Agreement between the first and <lb/>third plaintiffs has been marked as Ex.P15. <lb/>13. Notwithstanding the fact that the defendant has not chosen to <lb/>enter appearance and resist the suit (owing to which the defendant has <lb/>been set ex-parte in this suit). I have perused the pleadings, deposition and <lb/>exhibits/documents that have been placed before me. I find that the <lb/>deposition of P.W.1 is in tune/ tandem with the pleadings in the plaint. In <lb/>http://www.judis.nic.in <lb/></body>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<body>other words, deposition of P.W.1 which is cogent and convincing supports <lb/>the pleadings in the plaint. <lb/>14. I have also compared the two marks i.e., Exs.P18 to P21 on one <lb/>side and Exs.P22 and P24 on the other side. <lb/>15. I find that plaintiffs have made out a clear and convincing case <lb/>for infringement and passing off. In my considered opinion plaintiffs have <lb/>proved their case. Therefore, the plaintiffs will certainly be entitled to the <lb/>reliefs of injunctions qua infringement and passing off, which are sub-<lb/>paragraphs (a) and (b) of pliant paragraph No.38. The other sub-paragraphs <lb/>are (c) to (f). While sub-paragraphs (c) and (d) are usual prayers for <lb/>surrender of offending mark and accounts respectively, sub-paragraph (e) is <lb/>for costs of the suit. To be noted, sub-paragraph (f) is a residuary prayer <lb/>limb. <lb/>16. In the light of the conclusion that the plaintiffs are entitled to <lb/>injunctive reliefs qua infringement of suit TMs and passing off, it follows as <lb/>a sequitur that the plaintiffs are entitled to surrender of offending <lb/>materials as well as accounts as sought for in sub-paragraphs (c) and (d) of <lb/>the plaint prayer paragraph. <lb/>http://www.judis.nic.in <lb/></body>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<body>17. With regard to costs prayer, on coming to know of the offending <lb/>use by the defendant in March 2017, plaintiffs have diligently <lb/>filed/presented the plaint dated 03.04.2017 on 07.04.2017 and carried it to <lb/>its logical end by pursuing the matter sincerely. Therefore, the plaintiffs <lb/>are entitled to costs. <lb/>18. Adverting to the residuary limb of the prayer paragraph being <lb/>sub-paragraph (f), Ms.Gladys Daniel, learned counsel submitted that the <lb/>trajectory of this suit will make it clear that plaintiffs are entitled to <lb/>compensatory costs under Section 35-A of &apos;The Code of Civil Procedure, <lb/>1908&apos; (&apos;CPC&apos; for brevity) as amended by &apos;The Commercial Courts Act, 2015&apos; <lb/>(&apos;said Act&apos; for brevity) and that this plea may please be considered under <lb/>the residuary limb of the prayer i.e., sub-paragraph (f) of prayer paragraph. <lb/>19. For the purpose of abundant clarity, I deem it appropriate to <lb/>extract/reproduce entire prayer paragraph i.e., paragraph 38. I do so and <lb/>the same reads as follows: <lb/>&apos;38. The plaintiffs, therefore, pray for a Judgment and <lb/>Decree for:-<lb/>a) granting a permanent injunction, restraining the <lb/>defendant, by himself, its agents or servants or anyone <lb/>claiming through him from manufacturing, selling, advertising <lb/>and offering for sale using the name Aachi Mess or any other <lb/>similar Trade Mark name or similar sounding expression in any <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">http://www.judis.nic.in <lb/></note>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<body>media and use the same in name board, invoices, letter heads <lb/>and visiting cards or by using any other trade mark/name <lb/>which is in any way visually or deceptively or phonetically <lb/>similar to the 1 st Plaintiff&apos;s trademark/ name AACHI/AACHI <lb/>CHETINAD RESTAURANT/AACHI KITCHEN and use the same in <lb/>pouches, packets or use the mark in invoices, letters heads and <lb/>visiting cards or part of their Hotel/Restaurant name any <lb/>other trade literature or Menu card by using any other trade <lb/>mark which is in any way visually, or phonetically similar to <lb/>the Plaintiffs &apos; registered Trade mark Nos. 838786, 1116254, <lb/>1479159, 1715718 or in any manner infringing the 1 st Plaintiff&apos;s <lb/>registered Trade Marks referred herein. <lb/>b) granting a permanent injunction restraining the <lb/>Defendant by itself, its agents or servants or anyone claiming <lb/>through or under him any business marketing, selling <lb/>advertising using in trade literature, menu cards, invoices, <lb/>name boards, website, internet advertisements the <lb/>mark/name Aachi Mess in relation to the Restaurant or with <lb/>respect to or any other food preparation or any other business <lb/>the impugned trademark/name which is in any manner <lb/>deceptively or phonetically confusingly similar to the <lb/>Plaintiff&apos;s <lb/>Trade <lb/>Mark/name <lb/>AACHI/AACHI <lb/>CHETINAD <lb/>RESTAURANT/AACHI KITCHEN or in any other manner pass off <lb/>their hotel, business or goods as and for that of the plaintiffs. <lb/>c) directing the defendant to surrender to the Plaintiffs <lb/>all the packing material, cartons, advertisement materials and <lb/>hoardings, letter-heads, visiting cards, office stationery and <lb/>all other materials containing/bearing the name Aachi Mess or <lb/>other identical trade mark used in the pouches and packets <lb/>bearing the word AACHI/AACHI HOTEL/AACHI CHETINAD <lb/>RESTAURANT/AACHI KITCHEN. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">http://www.judis.nic.in <lb/></note>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<body>d) directing the defendant to render an account of <lb/>profits made by them by the use of the impugned trademark <lb/>Aachi Mess, on the service referred and decree the suit for the <lb/>profits found to have been made by the defendant, after the <lb/>defendant has rendered accounts. <lb/>e) directing the defendant to pay to the Plaintiffs the <lb/>costs to the suit and <lb/>f) pass such further or other order, as this Hon&apos;ble <lb/>Court may deem fit and proper in the circumstances of the <lb/>case and thus render justice.&apos; <lb/>20. A perusal of the chronicle/dates, which give the trajectory of this <lb/>suit, according to learned counsel for plaintiffs, will reveal that defendant <lb/>has clearly adopted vexatious means of defending this suit. Learned <lb/>counsel pointed out that this Commercial Division has held that the <lb/>expression &apos;vexatious defence&apos; occurring in Section 35-A of CPC will include <lb/>vexatious means that may be adopted by defendants in defending this suit. <lb/>There is no difficulty in accepting this submission, as the defendant after <lb/>being duly served with suit summons on 23.05.2017, entered appearance, <lb/>but thereafter the counsel reported &apos;no instructions&apos; and defendant took no <lb/>steps or no efforts to engage a new counsel. In other words, the defendant <lb/>has compelled the plaintiffs to carry the suit to its logical end by expending <lb/>time, money, energy and effort. Receiving suit summons, entrusting the <lb/>matter to a counsel, thereafter not giving instructions to the counsel <lb/>putting the counsel to the embarrassment of reporting &apos;no instructions&apos; and <lb/>http://www.judis.nic.in <lb/></body>

			<page>16 <lb/></page>

			<body>thereafter not taking any steps to engage a new counsel clearly <lb/>demonstrates vexatious means of defending this suit and therefore, I have <lb/>no difficulty in agreeing with the submission of learned counsel for plaintiffs <lb/>that this is a fit case for imposing compensatory costs. <lb/>21. Considering all parameters and determinants, this Commercial <lb/>Division considers it appropriate to impose compensatory costs of <lb/>Rs.5,00,000/0 (Rupees Five Lakhs only). To be noted, learned counsel <lb/>brought to the notice of this Commercial Division that Section 35-A of CPC <lb/>has been amended by said Act and by virtue of amendment to Section 35-A, <lb/>brought in by said Act now there is no upper limit or financial cap for <lb/>imposition of compensatory costs, once this Commercial Division is <lb/>convinced that plaintiff is entitled to same. There is no difficulty in <lb/>accepting that this is the obtaining legal position. <lb/>22. In the light of the narrative supra, it follows as a necessary <lb/>sequitur that this suit deserves to be decreed with costs and compensatory <lb/>costs. <lb/>23. Suit is decreed with costs and compensatory costs. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Consequently, connected miscellaneous petitions are closed. <lb/>31.01.2019 <lb/>Speaking order <lb/>Index : Yes/No <lb/>http://www.judis.nic.in <lb/>17 <lb/>vsm <lb/>M.SUNDAR, J. <lb/>vsm <lb/>C.S.No.290 of 2017 <lb/>31.01.2019 <lb/>http://www.judis.nic.in </note>


	</text>
</tei>
