<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<page>1 <lb/></page>

			<front>In the High Court of Judicature at Madras <lb/>Reserved on : 28.03.2019 <lb/>Pronounced on: 24.04.2019 <lb/>CORAM: <lb/>THE HON&apos;BLE Dr. JUSTICE ANITA SUMANTH <lb/>W.P.Nos.26159, 26160, 26161, 26162, 26163, 26164, <lb/>26165 &amp; 26166 of 2017 <lb/>&amp; W.M.P.Nos.27803, 27804, 27805, 27809, 26164,27797, 27798, <lb/>27799,27800,27801, 27802, 27806, 27807, 27808, 27810, <lb/>27811 &amp; 27812 of 2017 <lb/>Dr.R.Siddheswaran <lb/>....Petitioner in W.P.No.26159 of <lb/>Dr.N.Karthick <lb/>....Petitioner in W.P.No.26160 of <lb/>Dr.M.Indhumathi <lb/>....Petitioner in W.P.No.26161 of <lb/>Dr.S.Gokulraj <lb/>....Petitioner in W.P.No.26162 of <lb/>Dr.R.Sheelarani <lb/>....Petitioner in W.P.No.26163 of <lb/>Dr.J.Kavina <lb/>....Petitioner in W.P.No.26164 of <lb/>Dr.B.Prameena <lb/>....Petitioner in W.P.No.26165 of <lb/>Dr.D.Jesuvathy Sornalatha <lb/>....Petitioner in W.P.No.26166 of <lb/>--Vs--<lb/>1.The University Grants Commission <lb/>Rep.by its Member Secretary <lb/>Bahadur Shah Zafar Marg <lb/>New Delhi 110 002 <lb/>2.The Registrar <lb/>University of Madras <lb/>Centenary Building <lb/>http://www.judis.nic.in <lb/>2 <lb/>Chepauk <lb/>Chennai 600 005 <lb/>3.Pachaiyappa&apos;s Trust Board <lb/>Rep.by its Member Secretary <lb/>Mr.K.Hemanath <lb/>Pachaiyappa&apos;s College Campus <lb/>Poonamallee High Road <lb/>Chennai 600 030 <lb/>...Respondents in all WP <lb/>4.The Principal <lb/>Pachaiyappa&apos;s College <lb/>Chennai 600 030 <lb/>... 4 th Respondent in W.P.Nos.26159, <lb/>26161, 26163, 26164, 26166 of 2017 <lb/>5.The Principal <lb/>C.Kandaswami Naidu College for Men <lb/>Anna Nagar, Chennai 600102 <lb/>... 4 th Respondent in W.P.Nos.26160, <lb/>26162, 26165 of 2017 <lb/>PRAYER in W.P.Nos.26159, 26161, 26163, 26164, 26166 of 2017: Writ <lb/>Petitions filed under Article 226 of the Constitution of India praying for a writ of <lb/>Certiorarified Mandamus calling relating to the order of the 2 nd respondent herein dt. <lb/>13.09.2017 in A-II/MPV/Pachaiyappa&apos;s Trust/AP-Approval/2017/334 and quash the <lb/>same and consequently, direct the respondents 2 and 3 herein to grant approval for <lb/>the qualification of the petitioners as Assistant Professor in the Department of Physics <lb/>and in Botany to petitioner in WP.No.26164 of 2017 in, Pachaiyappa&apos;s College, <lb/>Chennai 600 030 and grant salary to the petitioners with all attendant benefits from <lb/>the date of joining, viz.25.02.2016, 02.03.2016, 25.02.2016, 03.03.2016 &amp; <lb/>25.02.2016 till date. <lb/>PRAYER in W.P.Nos.26160, 26162, 26165 of 2017: Writ Petitions filed under <lb/>Article 226 of the Constitution of India praying for a writ of Certiorarified Mandamus <lb/>calling relating to the order of the 2 nd respondent herein dt. 13.09.2017 in A-<lb/>II/MPV/Pachaiyappa&apos;s Trust/AP-Approval/2017/334 and quash the same and <lb/>consequently, direct the respondents 2 and 3 herein to grant approval for the <lb/>qualification of the petitioners as Assistant Professor in the Department of Physics in <lb/>C.Kandaswami Naidu College for Men, Chennai 600 102 and grant salary to the <lb/>petitioners with all attendant benefits from the date of joining, viz. all dated <lb/>25.02.2016 till date. <lb/>For Petitioner in W.P.Nos.26159, 26160, <lb/>26163 to 26166 of 2017 <lb/>: Mr.AR.L.Sundaresan, S.C. <lb/></front>

			<note place="footnote">http://www.judis.nic.in <lb/></note>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<front>for Mrs.A.L.Ganthimathi <lb/>For Petitioner in W.P.Nos.26161 <lb/>&amp; 26162/2017 <lb/>: Mr.P.V.S.Giridhar <lb/>for M/s.D.Prasanna <lb/>For respondents in W.P.Nos.26159/2017 <lb/>: Mr.P.R.Gopinathan -R1 <lb/>Mr.Manisundar Gopal -R2 <lb/>Mr.K.V.Sundararajan for R3 <lb/>No Appearance for R4 <lb/>For respondents in W.P.Nos.26160, <lb/>26163 to 26166, 26161 and 26162/2017 <lb/>: Mr.P.R.Gopinathan -R1 <lb/>Mr.Manisundar Gopal -R2 <lb/>No Appearance for R3 &amp; R4 <lb/>C O M M O N O R D E R <lb/>Pachaiyappa&apos;s Trust Board was established under a scheme formulated by the <lb/>Supreme Court in 1909. Arrayed as the 3 rd respondent in all the Writ Petitions, the <lb/>Pachaiyappa&apos;s Trust Board (in short &apos;PTB&apos; or &apos;Board&apos;) runs several colleges that are <lb/>aided by the Government, being Pachaiyappa&apos;s College, Chennai (PCC), <lb/>C.Kandaswami Naidu College for Men, Chennai (CKNCMC), Chellammal Women&apos;s <lb/>College, Chennai (CWCC), Pachaiyappa&apos;s College for Men, Kancheepuram (PCMK), <lb/>Pachaiyappa&apos;s College for Women, Kancheepuram (PCWK) and C.Kandaswami Naidu <lb/>College for Women, Cuddalore (CKNCW). <lb/>2. This batch of eight (8) writ petitions have been filed by individuals qualified <lb/>for the post of Assistant Professor in the subjects of physics (7 petitioners) and <lb/>botany (1 petitioner). Their qualifications are not in question. Since the contentions <lb/>advanced are common across subjects, they are set out below without reference to <lb/>specific subjects and may be taken to be the common submissions of all petitioners. <lb/></front>

			<note place="footnote">http://www.judis.nic.in <lb/></note>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>3. Heard Mr.AR.L.Sundaresan, learned senior counsel for Mrs.AL.Gandhimathi <lb/>for the petitioners in W.P.Nos.26159, 26160, 26163 to 16166 of 2017 and <lb/>Mr.P.V.S.Giridhar, learned counsel for Ms.D.Prasanna, learned counsel for the <lb/>petitioners in W.P.Nos.26161 and 26162 of 2017. The prayers in Writ Petition are <lb/>identical and one is extracted below for completion of narration, as follows: <lb/>Writ Petitions filed under Article 226 of the Constitution of <lb/>India praying for a writ of Certiorarified Mandamus calling relating to the <lb/>order of the 2 nd respondent herein dt. 13.09.2017 in A-<lb/>II/MPV/Pachaiyappa&apos;s Trust/AP-Approval/2017/334 and quash the same <lb/>and consequently, direct the respondents 2 and 3 herein to grant <lb/>approval for the qualification of the petitioners as Assistant Professor in <lb/>the Department of Physics and in Botany to petitioner in WP.No.26164 of <lb/>2017 in, Pachaiyappa&apos;s College, Chennai 600 030 and grant salary to the <lb/>petitioners with all attendant benefits from the date of joining, <lb/>viz.25.02.2016, 02.03.2016, 25.02.2016, 03.03.2016 &amp; 25.02.2016 till <lb/>date. <lb/>4. There were 66 vacancies in the sanctioned posts of Assistant <lb/>Professors/Librarian in PCC, CKNCMC, CWCC, PCMK, PCWK and CKNCW. <lb/>Recruitment notices were issued in The Hindu and Daily Thanthi on 02.12.2015 <lb/>calling for direct recruitments to the post of Assistant Professor in the Departments of <lb/>Tamil, English, Sanskrit, Mathematics, Physics, Chemistry, Botany, Zoology, <lb/>Commerce, Economics, Philosophy, History and Librarian. On-line applications were <lb/>invited, the last date for submission being 16.12.2015. <lb/>5. In so far as physics is concerned, application for 12 posts were solicited, 6 in <lb/>PCC, 3 in CKNCM, 2 in PCMK and 1 in PCWK. As far as botany is concerned, there <lb/>were 3 vacancies in 3 colleges, one each in PCC, PCWK and CKNCWC. The petitioners <lb/>are fully qualified to hold the position of Assistant Professor for Physics and Botany as <lb/>per the norms issued by the University Grants Commission (&apos;UGC&apos;) and applied for <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">http://www.judis.nic.in <lb/></note>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>the posts. A call letter was issued by R3 on 05.02.2016, calling upon the petitioners <lb/>to appear for certificate verification and interview on 17.02.2016 at CKNCM. <lb/>6. The petitioners appeared for the interview before a Common Selection <lb/>Committee and were selected for appointment to the respective posts to which they <lb/>had applied. The petitioners joined the posts on 25.02.2016, 25.02.2016, <lb/>02.03.2016, 25.02.2016, 25.02.2016, 03.03.2016, 25.02.2016, &amp; 25.02.2016 <lb/>respectively and have been working in the posts till date. <lb/>7. On 18.09.2017, the petitioners received intimation from R3, conveying the <lb/>decision/Resolution of the University of Madras, vide letter dated 13.09.2017, <lb/>cancelling the approval granted in respect of their appointments. The ground on <lb/>which the grant of approval was rejected as not approved, was that there was a lack <lb/>of quorum as stipulated by the UGC at the time of selection. All letters are identical <lb/>and one of the letters is extracted below for the sake of completion and clarity: <lb/>PACHAIYAPPA&apos;S TRUST BOARD, CHENNAI-600 030 <lb/>Thiru. K.Hemanath, B.E., M.B.A., <lb/>Pachaiyappa&apos;s College <lb/>Campus, <lb/>Member Secretary <lb/>E.V.R.Periyar Road, Shenoy <lb/>Nagar, <lb/>Chennai -600 030 <lb/>Phone: 044 26681001 <lb/>Email: <lb/>vallalpachaiyappas1754@gmail.com <lb/>Rc.No.A1/536/2016 <lb/>Dated:18.09.2017 <lb/>NOTE FROM THE MEMBER SECRETARY <lb/>Sub: Aided Colleges -C.Kandaswami Naidu College for Men, Chennai-<lb/>Grant of Qualification Approval -Assistant <lb/>Professors of Physics -Not <lb/>approved by the University -<lb/>Letter -Received -Intimated -Reg. <lb/>http://www.judis.nic.in <lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>Ref: Letter of the registrar-in-charge, University of Madras <lb/>No.AII/MPV/Pachaiyappa&apos;s Trust/AP-Approval/2017/334, dated <lb/>13.09.2017. <lb/>**** <lb/>The following individuals, who had been appointed as Assistant Professors <lb/>of Physics in C.Kandaswami Naidu College for Men, Chennai are informed <lb/>that the Registrar, University of Madras has sent a letter, cited under <lb/>reference, informing the resolution passed by the Syndicate on <lb/>11.08.2017. <lb/>1.Dr.B.Prameena <lb/>A.P. Of Physics <lb/>2.Dr.S.Gokulraj <lb/>A.P. Of Physics <lb/>3.Dr.N.Karthick <lb/>A.P. Of Physics <lb/>Resolution: <lb/>Resolved that the grant of approval of qualification for the <lb/>appointment of Assistant Professors in Physics in C.Kandaswami <lb/>Naidu College for Men, Chennai be not approved for the said <lb/>faculty members due to lack of quorum as stipulated by the UGC. <lb/>The copy of the letter of the Registrar, University of Madras, cited under <lb/>reference, is enclosed herewith. <lb/>This is for the information of the said individuals concerned. Further, they <lb/>are informed that the Pachaiyappa&apos;s Trust Board has sent an appeal to the <lb/>University of Madras besides initiating further action as per the rules. <lb/>Sd/. XXX <lb/>MEMBER <lb/>SECRETARY <lb/>To <lb/>1.Dr.B.Prameena <lb/>A.P. Of Physics <lb/>2.Dr.S.Gokulraj <lb/>A.P. Of Physics <lb/>3.Dr.N.Karthick <lb/>A.P. Of Physics <lb/>Copy to the Principal, C.Kandaswami Naidu College for Men, Chennai. <lb/>8. The petitioners challenge the above communications by way of the present <lb/>writ petitions. Counters affidavits have been filed by all the respondents objecting to <lb/>the averments raised. <lb/>9. Regulation 3 of the &apos;UGC Regulations, 2000 regarding Minimum <lb/>Qualifications for Appointment and Career Advancement of Teachers in Universities <lb/>and Colleges&apos; (&apos;UGC 2000&apos;) sets out the guidelines to be followed for constitution of a <lb/>selection committee and states thus: <lb/>http://www.judis.nic.in <lb/></body>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>3.0.0. Selection Committees recommended by the UGC <lb/>3.1.0 Lecturer in a Private College <lb/>1. Chairperson of the Governing Body of the college or his/her <lb/>nominee to be the Chairperson of the Selection Committee. <lb/>2. The Principal of the concerned College. <lb/>3. One senior teacher/Head of the Department (of the concerned <lb/>subject) preferably having not less than 10 years of services as a teacher. <lb/>4. Two nominees of the Vice-Chancellor of the affiliating University <lb/>of whom one should be a subject expert. <lb/>5. Two subject-experts not connected with the College to be <lb/>nominated by the Chairperson of the governing body out of a panel of <lb/>names approved by the Vice-Chancellor. <lb/>For Government Colleges, the State Public Service Commissions <lb/>must invite three subject experts for which the State Public Service <lb/>Commissions will involved the University in the selection. The Principal and <lb/>Head of the Department should be necessarily included in the Selection <lb/>Committee. <lb/>The quorum for the meeting should be five of which at least two <lb/>must be from out of the three subject experts.&apos; <lb/>10. The Trust had addressed a communication dated 07.12.2015 to the <lb/>University of Madras requesting it to furnish a panel of subject experts from out of <lb/>which the Vice-Chancellor of each college may nominate experts to conduct the <lb/>selection process for appointment to a specific college. The University of Madras <lb/>furnished a list of Vice-Chancellor nominees and panel of subject experts to be <lb/>included in the selection committee, separately per college and per department. This <lb/>was communicated to the Secretary, Pachaiyappa&apos;s Trust Board vide communication <lb/>dated 11.01.2015. Pursuant thereto and in line with Regulation 3.1.0 extracted <lb/>above, a separate selection committee had been constituted in respect of each <lb/>college and department in which vacancies were to be filled. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">http://www.judis.nic.in <lb/></note>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<body>11. The list of nominees for Physics and Botany in the PCC and Physics in <lb/>CKNCMC, are as follows (extracted from the communications issued by the University <lb/>of Madras dated 11.12.2015 and 11.01.2016): <lb/>Pachaiyappa&apos;s College, Chennai <lb/>Sl. No. <lb/>Subjec <lb/>t <lb/>Two Nominees of the Vice Chancellor <lb/>PANEL of Subject Experts to be <lb/>approved by the Vice-Chancellor <lb/>1,2,3… <lb/>.. <lb/>… <lb/>… <lb/>4. <lb/>Physics 1) Dr.M.Ravichandran, <lb/>Professor of Commerce and Director, <lb/>University of Madras, IDE, <lb/>Chepauk, Chennai -600 005. <lb/>2) Dr.C.Venkateswaran, <lb/>Professor and Head, <lb/>Dept. of Nuclear Physics, <lb/>University of Madras, <lb/>Guindy Campus, <lb/>Chennai -600 025. <lb/>1.Dr.R.Geetha, <lb/>Associate Professor of Physics, <lb/>Govt. Arts College for Men, <lb/>Nandanam, Chennai -600 035. <lb/>2. Dr.K.H.Rajini, <lb/>Associate Professor of Physics, <lb/>Stella Marys College, <lb/>Chennai -600 086. <lb/>3.Dr.K.Tamilarasan, <lb/>Associate Professor of Physics, <lb/>Sir Theagaraya College, <lb/>Chennai -21. <lb/>4. Dr.J.Madhavan, <lb/>Associate Professor of Physics, <lb/>Loyola College, <lb/>Chennai 600 034. <lb/>…5 <lb/>.. <lb/>… <lb/>6. <lb/>Botany 1) Dr.N.Ravichandran <lb/>Professor of Commerce and Director, <lb/>University of Madras, IDE, <lb/>Chepauk, Chennai -600 005. <lb/>2.) Dr.N.Mathivannan, <lb/>Professor and Head, <lb/>Department of Botany, <lb/>University of Madras, <lb/>Guindy, Chennai -600 025. <lb/>1.Dr.V.Lilly, <lb/>Associate Professor of Botany, <lb/>Quaid-E-Milleth <lb/>College <lb/>for <lb/>Women, Chennai -600 002. <lb/>2.Dr.S.Natarajan, <lb/>Associate Professor of Botany, <lb/>Gurunanak College, <lb/>Chennai -600 042. <lb/>3.Dr.C.V.Citty Babu, <lb/>Associate Professor of Botany, <lb/>Presidency College, <lb/>Chennai -600 005. <lb/>4.Dr.S.Selvaraju, <lb/>Associate Professor of Botany, <lb/>D.G.Vaishnav College, <lb/>Chennai -600 106. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">http://www.judis.nic.in <lb/></note>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body>C.Kandaswami Naidu College for Men, Chennai <lb/>1 <lb/>Physics <lb/>1) Dr.P.Ravishankar, <lb/>Professor &amp; Head, <lb/>Department of Anna Centre for <lb/>Public Affairs, University of Madras, <lb/>Chepauk, Chennai -5. <lb/>(University Representative on the <lb/>Governing Body of the college for <lb/>the period from 09.05.2014 to <lb/>08.05.2016) <lb/>2)Dr.C.Venkateswaran <lb/>Professor and Head, <lb/>Dept. of Nuclear Physics, <lb/>University of Madras, <lb/>Chennai -600 025. <lb/>3) One Co-opted member (SC/ST <lb/>common for all subjects) <lb/>Dr.M.Sakthivel <lb/>Asst. Professor of Geography, <lb/>University of Madras, Chepauk, <lb/>Chennai -600 <lb/>1)Dr.K.Chitra, <lb/>Associate Professor of Physics, <lb/>Bharathi Women&apos;s College, <lb/>Chennai -600 108 <lb/>2) Dro.J.Madhavan, <lb/>Associate Professor of Physics, <lb/>Loyola College, <lb/>Chennai -600 034. <lb/>3) Dr.N.Ramesh, <lb/>Associate Professor of Physics, <lb/>A.M.Jain College, <lb/>Meenambakkam, Chennai -114 <lb/>4.Dr.K.Tamilarasan, <lb/>Associate Professor of Physics, <lb/>Sir Theagaraya College, <lb/>Chennai -21. <lb/>12. According to the University, some of the subject experts specifically <lb/>nominated, such as C.Venkateshwaran and Dr.K.H.Rajini, (Physics) (PCC), <lb/>Dr.N.Ramesh (Physics) (CKNCMC) and Dr.N.Mathivanan (Botany) (PCC) had not <lb/>attended the selection committee meeting and the selection had taken place in their <lb/>absence. However, the interviews for selection had been conducted by a common <lb/>committee comprising of several persons, including experts in the same subjects who <lb/>had been appointed to be part of the committee for other colleges. Dr.R.Geetha <lb/>(Physics), Dr.K.Chitra (Physics), Dr.V.Lilly (Botany) and Dr.S.Natarajan (Botany), all <lb/>of who had, admittedly, been nominated had been part of the selection committee, <lb/>had sat in for the selection of the candidates. Thus, the petitioners argue that since <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">http://www.judis.nic.in <lb/></note>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<body>there were subject experts in the committee that interviewed them, though <lb/>nominated for another college, this would amount to substantial compliance with the <lb/>UGC Regulations and the procedure followed, as well their selection, was proper. <lb/>13. The offending Resolution had been passed by the Syndicate on 11.08.2017 <lb/>and conveyed to the Member Secretary, PTB vide letter dated 13.09.2017. The <lb/>services of the petitioners had, as on that date, been availed of for a period of <lb/>eighteen (18) months when the resolution was passed by the Syndicate. <lb/>14. The petitioners also argue that all Institutions managed by the Trust <lb/>constitute a single unit/entity and thus the appointments by a consolidated and <lb/>common committee are proper and valid. Thus, no separate committee need be <lb/>constituted per college and per department. If the aforesaid stand be accepted, the <lb/>requisite Quorum would have been achieved as there is no dispute on the position <lb/>that there were other subject experts who were available and sitting as part of the <lb/>selection committee and it is only specific persons who had been named for specific <lb/>colleges who had absented themselves. The necessity for the nominated and named <lb/>members pales into insignificance and insistence upon their presence loses relevance. <lb/>15. Letter dated 09.06.1993, from the Commissioner of Collegiate Education to <lb/>the Secretary of the Pachaiyappa&apos;s Trust specifically refers to the Explanation under <lb/>Rule 11 of the Tamil Nadu Private Colleges (Rules) 1976 to the effect that any <lb/>educational agency established and administering more than one college set up under <lb/>the control of the agency shall be treated as one unit for the purposes of <lb/>appointment of staff, promotions, transfers etc. Thus, according to them, the colleges <lb/>in question are all under the umbrella of a common agency and have rightly <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">http://www.judis.nic.in <lb/></note>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body>constituted one single selection committee that has conducted all the interviews. The <lb/>subject experts appointed to any one of the colleges are thus to be treated as <lb/>experts for other colleges of the group as well. <lb/>16. The petitioners also point out that they have been in service since the date <lb/>of their selection and it was only one and a half years after they assumed charge that <lb/>the offending Resolution dated 11.08.2017 has been passed by the University. They <lb/>have since been rendering service by virtue of an order of stay granted by this Court <lb/>without the benefit of pay, and are evidently, greatly prejudiced. <lb/>17. The petitioner relies on the following cases: <lb/>Union of India &amp; Ohters V. Sh.Somasundaram Viswanath and others <lb/>(AIR 1988 SC 2255) <lb/>J.M.Jacqueline Maley &amp; Ors. V. Union of India &amp; Ors. ((2009) 7 MLJ 749) <lb/>State of M.P. And Ors. V.Lalit Kumar Verma ((2007) 1 SCC 575) <lb/>Municipal Corpn., Jabalpur V. Om Prakash Dubey ((2007) 1 SCC 373) <lb/>Dr.K.R.S.Girija Shyamsundar and others V. The State of Tamilnadu <lb/>(2015-3-L.W.163) <lb/>18. Mr.P.R.Gopinathan, appears for the UGC, Mr.Manisundar Gopal for the <lb/>University of Madras and Mr.K.V.Sundararajan for PTB. <lb/>19. Learned counsel for the University vehemently objects to the case of the <lb/>petitioners. He takes me through the UGC Regulations that set out the Constitution of <lb/>the Selection Committee. Regulation 3 prescribes the composition of the Committee <lb/>for selection and appointment of a lecturer in a private college. The constitution is, (i) <lb/>Chairperson of the governing body of the college or nominee as Chairperson, (ii) the <lb/>Principal of the concerned College, (iii) one senior teacher/Head of the department of <lb/>http://www.judis.nic.in <lb/></body>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<body>the concerned special subject preferably carrying not less than ten(10) years of <lb/>service as a teacher, (iv) two nominees of the Vice Chancellor one of whom should be <lb/>a subject expert and (v) two subject experts unconnected with the college to be <lb/>nominated by the Chairperson of the Governing body, out of a panel of names <lb/>approved by the Vice Chancellor. The Quorum prescribed is five (5) Members. <lb/>20. According to him, the above Rule has not been scrupulously adhered to <lb/>and in some cases even the Quorum has not been achieved. Where the Quorum has <lb/>been achieved, the committee does not contain the stipulated number of subject <lb/>experts. According to him, the UGC Regulations are mandatory and any deviation in <lb/>regard to the constitution of the Selection Committee would be fatal to the validity of <lb/>the appointments made by such Committee. This is his primary submission. <lb/>21. The constitution of the committee for appointment of Assistant Professors, <lb/>Physics in PCC, and the attendees therein, was, according to the University, as <lb/>below: <lb/>UGC Regulation <lb/>Composition of members <lb/>Present/ <lb/>Absent <lb/>V.C. nominee <lb/>Other members <lb/>Chairperson or his <lb/>nominee <lb/>S.Jayachandran (1) <lb/>Present <lb/>Principal of the <lb/>concerned college <lb/>Dr.P.Gajivaradhan (2) <lb/>Present <lb/>Sr.Teacher/HOD <lb/>Dr.Arulmozhi <lb/>Chelvan(3) <lb/>Absent <lb/>Two nominees of <lb/>the VC <lb/>Dr.M.Ravichandran(4) <lb/>Absent <lb/>Dr.C.Venkateshwaran <lb/>(Subject Expert) (5) <lb/>Absent <lb/>Two <lb/>Subject <lb/>experts nominated <lb/>by the Chairperson <lb/>out of the panel <lb/>given by the VC <lb/>Dr.R.Geetha (6) <lb/>Present <lb/>Dr.K.H.Rajini (7) <lb/>Absent <lb/>http://www.judis.nic.in <lb/></body>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<body>TOTAL : 7 <lb/>PRESENT: 3 <lb/>University representative <lb/>for SC/ST/Women etc. <lb/>Dr.B.Venugopal <lb/>Present <lb/>22. The constitution of the committee for appointment of Assistant Professors, <lb/>Physics in the CKNCMC and the attendees therein, was as below: <lb/>UGC Regulation <lb/>Composition of members <lb/>Present/ <lb/>Absent <lb/>V.C. nominee <lb/>Other members <lb/>Chairperson or his <lb/>nominee <lb/>Mr.S.Jayachandran(1) <lb/>Present <lb/>Principal of the <lb/>concerned college <lb/>Dr.P.Sekar (2) <lb/>Present <lb/>Sr.Teacher/HOD <lb/>Dr.G.R.Ramkumar(3) <lb/>Present <lb/>Two nominees of <lb/>the VC <lb/>Dr.P.Ravishankar(4) <lb/>Present <lb/>Dr.C.Venkateshwaran <lb/>(Subject Expert) (5) <lb/>Absent <lb/>Two <lb/>Subject <lb/>experts nominated <lb/>by the Chairperson <lb/>out of the panel <lb/>given by the VC <lb/>Dr.K.Chitra (6) <lb/>Present <lb/>Dr.N.Ramesh (7) <lb/>Absent <lb/>TOTAL: 7 <lb/>PRESENT: 5 <lb/>University <lb/>representative for <lb/>SC/ST/ Women etc. <lb/>Dr.Mr.M.Shaktivel <lb/>Present <lb/>23. The constitution of the committee for appointment of Assistant Professors, <lb/>Botany in PCC, and the attendees therein, was as below: <lb/>UGC Regulation <lb/>Composition of members <lb/>Present/ <lb/>Absent <lb/>V.C. nominee <lb/>Other members <lb/>Chairperson or his <lb/>nominee <lb/>Dr.S.Jayachandran(1) <lb/>Present <lb/>Principal of the <lb/>concerned college <lb/>Dr.P.Gajivaradhan(2) <lb/>Present <lb/>Sr.Teacher/HOD <lb/>Dr.K.Umarajan (3) <lb/>Absent <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">http://www.judis.nic.in <lb/></note>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<body>Two nominees of <lb/>the VC <lb/>Dr.M.Ravichandran(4) <lb/>Absent <lb/>Dr.N.Mathivanan (Subject <lb/>Expert) (5) <lb/>Absent <lb/>Two <lb/>Subject <lb/>experts nominated <lb/>by the Chairperson <lb/>out of the panel <lb/>given by the VC <lb/>Dr.V.Lilly (6) <lb/>Present <lb/>Dr.S.Natrajan (7) <lb/>Present <lb/>TOTAL : 7 <lb/>PRESENT: 4 <lb/>University <lb/>representative for <lb/>SC/ST/ Women etc. <lb/>Dr.B.Venugopal <lb/>Present <lb/>24. In addition to the prescription in Regulation 3, a University representative <lb/>for SC/ST/Women was also included in all three committees as above. According to <lb/>learned counsel for the University, this additional member was included only as a <lb/>measure of abundant caution and in line with the 2010 Regulations, there being no <lb/>such provision in UGC 2000 for such a member. <lb/>25. Learned counsel relies on the following cases to bolster his submissions: <lb/>(i) The Secretary, Kamaraj College, Thoothukudi V. D.S.Arulmani, <lb/>Reader etc. (2008-1-L.W.530) <lb/>(ii) Kalyani Mathivanan V. K.V.Jeyaraj and others ((2015) 6 SCC 363 <lb/>26. Secondly, he states that the Explanation to Rule 11 relied on by the <lb/>petitioners does not apply to them at all. According to him the Explanation is placed <lb/>at the end of sub-rule 4 and is thus applicable specifically only to the said sub-rule, <lb/>which talks about promotions. Thus it is only for the purpose of promotions that the <lb/>Explanation would apply and not for the purpose of recruitment per se. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">http://www.judis.nic.in <lb/></note>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<body>27. Mr.K.V.Sundararajan, learned counsel for the Trust commences by stating <lb/>that he only assists the Court and endeavors to ensure that the correct law is laid <lb/>down. His mandate is not to support any private or individual interest. I quote him as <lb/>specifically stating that that there is no allegation of malpractice involved in the <lb/>procedure for selection nor is there any deficiency in the rendition of services by the <lb/>petitioners as faculty, post their appointments. <lb/>28. This Court had, by its order dated 14.06.2018, appointed a retired Judge of <lb/>this Court, Justice P.Shanmugam, as Interim Administrator for conduct of the <lb/>Elections to the Trust and to administer the Board till such time the new Board of <lb/>Trustees takes over. <lb/>29. A common counter dated 01.03.2019 has been filed by the Secretary <lb/>appointed by the Interim Administrator suggesting that the fixation of a combined <lb/>selection committee is not in accordance with Regulation 3 of the UGC 2000. The <lb/>Trust also urges that the &apos;single unit&apos; principle set out in Rule 11(4) of the Tamil Nadu <lb/>Private Colleges (Regulations) Rules 1976 will apply only in the case of promotions. <lb/>The Trust thus suggests that the common selection that has been undertaken is not <lb/>in conformity with the UGC Regulations and does not have any support in law. Thus, <lb/>PTB, in effect sails with the University in stating that the procedure followed by the <lb/>erstwhile Board in the manner of appointments was improper and contrary to the <lb/>Regulations. <lb/>30. On an appreciation of the factual and legal submissions made by all learned <lb/>counsel and the rival contentions advanced, the issues that I am called upon to <lb/>resolve are crystallized below: <lb/>http://www.judis.nic.in <lb/></body>

			<page>16 <lb/></page>

			<body>(i) Whether the Board attracts Explanation under Rule 11(4)(i) and (ii) of the <lb/>Tamil Nadu Private Colleges (Rules), 1976 and whether all colleges set up and <lb/>managed by and under the Board are to be treated as one unit for purposes of <lb/>appointment/promotions/transfers of staff? <lb/>(ii) Whether the University Grants Commission (Minimum Qualifications <lb/>Required for the Appointment and Career Advancement of Teachers in Universities <lb/>and Institutions affiliated to it) Regulations, 2000, are mandatory or directory? <lb/>(iii) Whether the procedure followed for selection of the candidates is proper in <lb/>the light of the UGC Regulations 2000 and consequently whether the impugned <lb/>Resolutions holding the appointments to be invalid are to be upheld? <lb/>31. Adverting to the first issue, Rule 11 deals with &apos;Conditions of service etc. of <lb/>teachers and other persons in college&apos;. Sub-rule (1) talks about the cap on the <lb/>appointments stating that the number of teachers employed shall not exceed the <lb/>number of posts fixed by the Director. Sub-rule (1-A) to (1-D) deals with <lb/>&apos;reservation&apos; with which we are not concerned in these Writ Petitions. Sub-rule (2) <lb/>refers to documentation to be entered into with the employees other than teachers <lb/>with the college. Sub-rule (3) refers to the methodology for filling up of regular and <lb/>temporary vacancies. Sub-rule (4) talks about promotions in respect of the teaching <lb/>staff and the methodology for filing the same. The Rule, to the extent it is relevant <lb/>for the purposes of this Writ Petition is extracted below, along with the Explanation <lb/>thereto: <lb/>&apos;11. Conditions of service, etc. of teachers and other persons in college:-<lb/>http://www.judis.nic.in <lb/></body>

			<page>17 <lb/></page>

			<body>(1)The number of teachers employed in a college shall not exceed the number <lb/>of posts fixed by the Director, from time to time, with reference to the academic <lb/>requirements and norms of work load prescribed by the respective Universities <lb/>and overall financial consideration. <lb/>(1-A)... <lb/>(1-B)... <lb/>(1-C)... <lb/>(1-D)... <lb/>(2)(i) The committee of every college shall enter into an agreement with the <lb/>teachers in Form 7-A and with the employees other than teachers in Form 7-C. <lb/>If the appointment is for a period not exceeding three months, the agreement <lb/>shall be made in Form 7-B in the case of teachers and in Form 7-D in the case of <lb/>employees other than teachers. <lb/>(ii)..... <lb/>(3) In the case of regular vacancies, a fully qualified candidate shall be <lb/>appointed only on a regular basis. However, in a temporary vacancy arising on <lb/>account of leave, deputation for training or suspension, etc., a qualified <lb/>candidate may be appointed temporarily for a specified period provided that <lb/>such teachers&apos; services shall not be terminated before the expiry of the said <lb/>period. <lb/>4(i) Promotions in respect of teaching staff shall be made on grounds of merit <lb/>and ability, seniority, being considered only where merit and ability are <lb/>approximately equal, and in respect of non-teaching staff promotions shall be <lb/>made on seniority basis, provided other conditions regarding qualification are <lb/>satisfied. <lb/>(ii) The committee shall fill up the posts by promotion or by direct recruitment. <lb/>The committee shall, while making promotion, consider the claims of all the <lb/>qualified teachers in that college. If, however, none of the qualified teachers in <lb/>the college is found suitable for promotion, the vacancy shall be filled up by <lb/>direct recruitment by calling for applications from qualified persons through the <lb/>Press or by calling for a list of candidates from the Employment Exchange by <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">http://www.judis.nic.in <lb/></note>

			<page>18 <lb/></page>

			<body>following the rule of reservation ordered by the Government from time to time <lb/>for direct recruitment. <lb/>Explanation -For purposes of this rule, if an educational agency has established <lb/>and administered more than one college, then the colleges under the control of <lb/>that educational agency shall be treated as one unit.&apos; <lb/>32. The Explanation is placed at the end of the sub-rule (4) and states that &apos;for <lb/>the purpose of this rule&apos;, if the educational agency administers more than one <lb/>college, then all colleges under its control shall be treated as one unit. The word used <lb/>is &apos;rule&apos; and not &apos;sub-rule&apos;. Moreover, the Explanation is placed in the centre of the <lb/>Rule and Rules (1) to (4) refer to various parameters in regard to conditions of <lb/>service of teachers including matters of employment, either by way of direct <lb/>recruitment or by way of promotion. <lb/>33. I am thus of the view that the Explanation would refer to Rule 11, sub-<lb/>rules 1 to 4 and not sub-rule 4 alone. I also go by the literal word used, being &apos;rule&apos; <lb/>and not &apos;sub-rule&apos;. If the intention of the Explanation was to restrict the same only to <lb/>promotions, then the word used would have been &apos;sub-rule and not &apos;rule&apos;. <lb/>34. I am also inclined to take this view in the light of the position that both the <lb/>Board as well as the authorities, more significantly the latter, appear to have been of <lb/>the opinion that the Pachaiyappas Trust Board is an Educational Agency for the <lb/>purposes of the Tamil Nadu Private Colleges (Regulations) Act, 1976, (in short <lb/>&apos;TNPCR Act&apos;), a view that is in consonance with Rule 11 itself. An Educational Agency <lb/>is defined under Section 4 of the aforesaid Act as follows: <lb/>(4) &quot;educational agency&quot;, in relation to-<lb/>http://www.judis.nic.in <lb/></body>

			<page>19 <lb/></page>

			<body>(a) any minority college, means any person who, or body of persons <lb/>which, has established and is administering or proposed to establish and <lb/>administer such minority college; and <lb/>(b) any other private college, means any person or body of persons <lb/>permitted or deemed to be permitted under the Act to establish and <lb/>maintain such other private college. <lb/>35. My attention has also been drawn to a communication inter se the <lb/>Commissioner of Collegiate Education and the PTB as early as in 1993 that supports <lb/>my view, as aforesaid. The communication is extracted in full below: <lb/>&apos;From <lb/>To <lb/>V.Palanichamy, I.A.S. <lb/>The Secretary, <lb/>Commissioner of Collegiate <lb/>Pachaiyapa&apos;s Trust, <lb/>Education, <lb/>Madras. <lb/>Madras -6 <lb/>Rc.No.73158/F2/92, dated 09.06.93 <lb/>Sir, <lb/>Sub: Aided Colleges -Colleges under Pach.Trust -<lb/>Applicability of re-deployment -Clarification -<lb/>Sought for -reg. <lb/>Ref : Your letters Rc.No.A4/8297/90, dt 29.10.92 <lb/>And 14.12.92. <lb/>With reference to your letters cited, I am to inform you <lb/>that as per the explanation under rule 11(4)(i) &amp; (ii) of <lb/>Tamil <lb/>Nadu Private Colleges (R) Rules 1976, if any Educational agency has <lb/>established and administered more than one college then the colleges <lb/>under the control of the Educational agency shall be treated as one unit. <lb/>Accordingly the six colleges administered by the Pach.Trust should be <lb/>treated as one unit for purposes of appointment of staff, their <lb/>promotions, transfers etc. subject to the Court verdict on the W.Ps. filed <lb/>by Tmt.Tamilselvi and Thiru K.Venkataraman. <lb/>In view of the above, I am also to state that the pay of <lb/>the incumbent who are transferred from one college to another within <lb/>the same management may be claimed in the pay rolls of the respective <lb/>colleges where they are actually working. <lb/>Yours faithfully, <lb/>Sd/. <lb/>V.Palanichamy <lb/>Commissioner of Collegiate Education, <lb/>Copy to: <lb/>1.Regional Dy.D.C.E,, Madras -Region, Madras -2. <lb/>2.Regional Dy.D.C.E., Trichy Region, Trichy. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">http://www.judis.nic.in <lb/></note>

			<page>20 <lb/></page>

			<body>/true copy/ <lb/>Sd./ <lb/>For Commissioner of Collegiate Education&apos; <lb/>36. The PTB is admittedly engaged in the Management of multiple Colleges and <lb/>thus constitutes an Educational Agency for the purposes of the TNPCR Act. The <lb/>clarification issued by the Commissioner of Collegiate Education makes it more than <lb/>clear that all six colleges administered by the Board will be treated as one Unit, not <lb/>merely for promotions as is urged and suggested by the respondents but also for <lb/>purposes of appointment of staff, transfers, etc. For the aforesaid reasons, I accept <lb/>the first submission of the petitioners that all colleges under the control of PTB shall <lb/>be treated as one unit, the Board being the &apos;common educational agency&apos; in respect <lb/>of them all. <lb/>37. In doing so, I am conscious of the position that I have taken a stand <lb/>contrary to the arguments advanced not only by the UGC and the University of <lb/>Madras but also by the present Interim Board. The counter suggests that the <lb/>constitution of the combined selection committee &apos;may not be&apos; in accordance with the <lb/>UGC Regulations, 2000 as the principle of one common educational agency with <lb/>multiple colleges under its Management would only be applicable for promotions. <lb/>These are the only flaws pointed out, which, if accepted, are serious and would <lb/>certainly vitiate the selection process in full. However, in the light of the discussion as <lb/>aforesaid, I reject the aforesaid suggestions/argument of the respondents. The first <lb/>issue is answered in favour of the petitioner reiterating that (i) the Board constitutes <lb/>an Educational Agency (ii) all six colleges managed in common by the Board <lb/>http://www.judis.nic.in <lb/></body>

			<page>21 <lb/></page>

			<body>constitute one unit and (iii) consequently, the proviso located after sub-rule 4 would <lb/>apply to sub-rules 1 through 4 of Rule 11 and not merely to sub-rule 4. Incidentally, <lb/>the counter filed refers to writ petitions of the year 2016 challenging the selection of <lb/>other Assistant Professors and urges that the additional counter affidavit filed in those <lb/>Writ Petitions also be taken into account by me in disposing this batch of Writ <lb/>Petitions. Such an omnibus request could have been considered had the other Writ <lb/>Petitions of the year 2016 been clubbed and placed for consolidated hearing after <lb/>following appropriate procedure in that regard. There has been no request along <lb/>these lines at any juncture and this has not been done. This averment in counter has <lb/>also not been pursued during the detailed hearing and I refer to the same here only <lb/>for the sake of completion. <lb/>38. Now I advert to the second issue as to whether the UGC Regulations are <lb/>mandatory or only directory, for the purpose of which I analyze some judgments <lb/>cited at the Bar, and extracted below. <lb/>39. In the case of Kalyani Mathivanan Vs. K.V.Jeyaraj and Other reported in <lb/>[(2015) 6 SCC 363] at paragraph 27, the Supreme Court states thus: <lb/>27. From the aforesaid provisions, we find that the University Grants <lb/>Commission has been established for the determination of standard <lb/>of Universities, promotion and co-ordination of University education, <lb/>for the determination and maintenance of standards of teaching, <lb/>examination and research in Universities, for defining the <lb/>qualifications regarding the teaching staff of the University, <lb/>maintenance of standards etc. For the purpose of performing its <lb/>functions under the UGC Act (see Section 12) like defining the <lb/>qualifications and standard that should ordinarily be required of any <lb/>person to be appointed in the Universities [see Section 26(1)(e)(g)] <lb/>UGC is empowered to frame regulations. It is only when both the <lb/>Houses of the Parliament approve the regulation, the same can be <lb/>given effect. Thus, we hold that the U.G.C. Regulations though a <lb/>subordinate legislation has binding effect on the Universities to which <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">http://www.judis.nic.in <lb/></note>

			<page>22 <lb/></page>

			<body>it applies; and consequence of failure of the University to comply <lb/>with the recommendations of the Commission, the UGC may <lb/>withhold the grants to the university made out of the Fund of the <lb/>Commission. (See Section 14) <lb/>This judgment is sought to be distinguished by the petitioners on the ground <lb/>that it applies to the appointment of a Vice-chancellor, which is a non-teaching post. <lb/>40. In the case of The Secretary, Kamaraj College, Thoothukudi-629003 Vs. <lb/>D.S.Arulmani, Reader and Head of Department of Tamil, Kamaraj College, <lb/>Thoothukudi-628 003 and Others [(2008) 1-L.W.530] at paragraphs 24, 25, 31, and <lb/>43, a Division Bench of this Court considered the question as to whether the UGC <lb/>Regulations were mandatory and also what the interplay between the aforesaid <lb/>Regulation and State level prescriptions for selection of candidates for colleges, <lb/>would be. The Bench, in the aforesaid context states thus: <lb/>24. Thus, the Tamil Nadu Act is primarily intended to regulate (i) the <lb/>establishment of Private Colleges and (ii) the management and <lb/>administration of the affairs of the private colleges. Therefore, all the <lb/>provisions of the Tamilnadu Act will have to be read, interpreted and <lb/>understood only in the context in which they have been made and <lb/>the purpose they seek to achieve. <lb/>25. If that is so, then the next question that arises for consideration <lb/>is as to whether the constitution of Selection Committees in a <lb/>particular manner, is a matter that could be traced to the &quot;co-<lb/>ordination and determination of standards&quot; (relating to Entry 66 of <lb/>List I) or to the &quot;establishment and management of educational <lb/>institutions&quot; (relating to Entry 25 of List III). The contention of the <lb/>appellants is that while the prescription of qualifications for teachers, <lb/>would fall within the ambit of &quot;co-ordination and determination of <lb/>standards&quot;, the constitution of Selection Committees in a particular <lb/>manner, has nothing to do with &quot;co-ordination and determination of <lb/>standards&quot;. <lb/>. . . . <lb/>31. Once it is found that the impugned Regulations could be traced <lb/>only to the law making power under Entry 66 of List I and that the <lb/>constitution of the Selection Committee prescribed by the <lb/>http://www.judis.nic.in <lb/></body>

			<page>23 <lb/></page>

			<body>Regulations, is wholly with a view to maintain standards in <lb/>institutions, then the question of repugnancy and the question of <lb/>encroachment into occupied field does not arise. A situation converse <lb/>to the one on hand was considered by the Supreme court in State of <lb/>Andhra Pradesh v. K. Purushotham Reddy , and the Apex court held <lb/>as follows: <lb/>19. The conflict in legislative competence of Parliament and <lb/>the State Legislatures having regard to Article 246 of the <lb/>Constitution of India must be viewed in the light of the <lb/>decisions of this Court which in no uncertain terms state that <lb/>each entry has to be interpreted in a broad manner. Both the <lb/>parliamentary legislation as also the State legislation must <lb/>be considered in such a manner so as to uphold both of them <lb/>and only in a case where it is found that both cannot coexist, <lb/>the State Act may be declared ultra vires. Clause (1) <lb/>of Article 246 of the Constitution of India does not provide <lb/>for the competence of Parliament or the State Legislatures as <lb/>is ordinarily understood but merely provides for the <lb/>respective legislative fields. Furthermore, the courts should <lb/>proceed to construe a statute with a view to uphold its <lb/>constitutionality. <lb/>25. In R. Chitralekha v. State of Mysore , Subba Rao, J. <lb/>categorically held that the question as regards the impact of <lb/>Entry 66 List I and Entry 25 List III must be determined by <lb/>reading the Central Act as well as the State Act conjointly. A <lb/>State law providing for such standards having regard to <lb/>Entry 66 of List I would be struck down as unconstitutional <lb/>only in the event the same is found so heavy or devastating <lb/>so as to wipe out or appreciably abridge the Central field and <lb/>not otherwise. Once the powers and functions of the Council <lb/>are found to be subject to the guidelines issued by UGC and <lb/>the perspective plan prepared by it would be subject to its <lb/>approval, the question of standard of education set up by <lb/>the State Act cannot be said to be leading to wipe out or <lb/>appreciably abridge the Central field. <lb/>Therefore the real endeavour of the Court in such <lb/>circumstances should be to save both the legislations and to <lb/>see if they could co-exist. In the present case, the &quot;College <lb/>Committee&quot; prescribed by the Tamil Nadu Private Colleges <lb/>(Regulation) Act is different from the &quot;Selection Committee&quot; <lb/>prescribed by the impugned U.G.C. Regulations. Both of <lb/>them cannot co-exist and hence, the State Act (relating to <lb/>Entry 25 of List III) has necessarily to give way for the <lb/>impugned U.G.C. Regulations (relating to Entry 66 of List I). <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">http://www.judis.nic.in <lb/></note>

			<page>24 <lb/></page>

			<body>43. It was contended on behalf of the appellants that the <lb/>impugned Regulations could be construed only as recommendatory <lb/>in nature and not as mandatory. However, we are unable to accept <lb/>the said contention. In Vidya Dhar Pande v. Vidyut Grih Siksha <lb/>Samiti AIR 1989SC 341: (1988) 4 SCC 734 : 1989-I-LLJ-81 it was <lb/>held as follows: <lb/>&quot;8.The question whether a regulation framed under power <lb/>conferred by the provisions of a Statute has got statutory power and <lb/>whether an order made in breach of the said Regulation will be <lb/>rendered illegal and invalid came up for consideration before the <lb/>Constitution Bench in the case of Sukhdev Singh v. Bhagatram <lb/>Sardar Singh Raghuvanshi AIR 1975-SC 1331 : (1975) 1 SCC 421 : <lb/>1975-I-LLJ-399 : (1975) 3 SCR 619. In this case, it was held that: <lb/>&quot;There is no substantial difference between a rule and a <lb/>regulation inasmuch as both are subordinate legislation under <lb/>powers conferred by the statute. A regulation framed under a statute <lb/>applies uniform treatment to everyone or to all members of some <lb/>group or class. The Oil and Natural Gas Commission, the Life <lb/>Insurance Corporation and Industrial Finance Corporation are all <lb/>required by the statute to frame regulations inter alia for the purpose <lb/>of the duties and conduct and conditions of service of officers and <lb/>other employees. These regulations impose obligation on the <lb/>statutory authorities. The statutory authorities cannot deviate from <lb/>the conditions of service. Any deviation will be enforced by legal <lb/>sanction of declaration by courts to invalidate actions in violations of <lb/>rules and regulations. The existence of rules and regulations under <lb/>statute is to ensure regular conduct with a distinctive attitude to that <lb/>conduct as a standard. The statutory regulations in the cases under <lb/>consideration give the employee a statutory status and impose <lb/>restriction on the employer and the employee with no option to vary <lb/>the conditions&quot;. <lb/>9. There is therefore, no escape from the conclusion that <lb/>regulations have force of law. The order of the High Court must <lb/>therefore be reversed on this point unhesitatingly&quot;. <lb/>Again in Medical Council of India v. State of Karnataka and <lb/>Ors. AIR 1998 SC 2423 : (1998) 6 SCC 131, it was held as follows: <lb/>&quot;24. ...Regulations framed under Section 33 of the Medical <lb/>Council Act with the previous sanction of the Central Government are <lb/>statutory. These regulations are framed to carry out the purposes of <lb/>the Medical Council Act and for various purposes mentioned <lb/>in Section 33. If a regulation falls within the purposes referred <lb/>under Section 33 of the Medical Council Act, it will have mandatory <lb/>force. Regulations have been framed with reference to Clauses (fa), <lb/>(fb) and (fc) (which have been introduced by the Amendment Act of <lb/>1993 w.e.f. 27.08.1992) and Clauses (j), (k) and (l) of Section 33.&quot; <lb/>http://www.judis.nic.in <lb/></body>

			<page>25 <lb/></page>

			<body>In St. Johns Teachers Training Institute v. Regional Director, <lb/>N.C.T.E. 2003 AIR SCW 894 it was held as follows: <lb/>&quot;The main justification for delegated legislation is that the <lb/>legislature being over burdened and the needs of the modern day <lb/>society being complex it cannot possibly foresee every administrative <lb/>difficulty that may arise after the Statute has begun to operate. <lb/>Delegated legislation fills those needs. The Regulations made under <lb/>power conferred by the Statue are supporting legislation and have <lb/>the force and effect, if validly made, as the Act passed by the <lb/>competent legislature. (see Sukhdev Singh v. Bhagatram AIR 1975 <lb/>SC 133).&quot; <lb/>The above view was reiterated in Maharashtra University of <lb/>Health Sciences v. Paryani Mukesh Jawaharlal and Ors. 2007(3) ESC <lb/>467 (SC) on the following lines: <lb/>&quot;MCI has been set up as an expert body to control the <lb/>minimum standards of medical education and to regulate their <lb/>observance. The regulations framed by the MCI with the previous <lb/>sanction of the Central Government, in regard to any of the matters <lb/>referred to in Section 33 of the Indian Medical Council Act, 1956, will <lb/>have statutory force and are mandatory. Universities must <lb/>necessarily be guided by the MCI Regulations. Any regulations made <lb/>by the Universities which are inconsistent with the MCI Regulations, <lb/>or which dilute the criteria laid down by MCI will not be valid to the <lb/>extent of inconsistency or dilution.&quot; <lb/>Therefore, the impugned Regulations have statutory force and <lb/>the Universities as well as the Colleges affiliated to the Universities <lb/>are obliged to follow the same. <lb/>. . . . <lb/>45. In fine, we hold that the impugned U.G.C. Regulations, more <lb/>particularly, paragraph Nos. 3.1.0 and 3.5.0 of the same, are <lb/>perfectly valid and there are no valid and proper reasons to strike <lb/>down the same as unconstitutional and ultravires. The writ Appeal <lb/>Nos. 585 and 1305 of 2006 arising out of W.P. No. 17630 of 2005, <lb/>are devoid of merits. The selection of Dr. J. Mohanraj as the Principal <lb/>of Kamaraj College, Tuticorin, (appellant in W.A. No. 585 of 2006) by <lb/>a Committee other than the Selection Committee prescribed by the <lb/>U.G.C. Regulations, 2000, has been rightly set at naught by a well <lb/>considered judgment of the learned Judge. We see no reason to <lb/>interfere with the said Judgement. Consequently, all the writ appeals <lb/>are dismissed. Connected M.Ps. are closed. No costs. <lb/>http://www.judis.nic.in <lb/></body>

			<page>26 <lb/></page>

			<body>41. Per contra, the petitioners refer to some judgments holding that the <lb/>Regulations are only recommendatory and in any event, the flaw in selection <lb/>procedure, if any, in the present cases, constitutes only an irregularity and not an <lb/>illegality. The Division Bench of this Court in J.M.Jacqueline Maley Vs. Union of India <lb/>(2009-7-MLJ-749) has held as follows: <lb/>Though the authorities have deviated from the earlier mode of <lb/>selection of test/interview to that of taking into consideration the <lb/>50% of the marks obtained in the SSLC or its equivalent and 50% of <lb/>marks obtained in Diploma/Degree in Pharmacy secured by the <lb/>candidates, they have strictly followed the latter version and have <lb/>selected the meritorious candidates among the applicants, to which <lb/>no motive or malafide intention has either been attributed or proved <lb/>by the applicants/unsuccessful candidates. Therefore, we are in <lb/>complete agreement with the arguments advanced on the part of the <lb/>successful candidates that if at all the appointments of the selected <lb/>candidates could only be irregular and can never be illegal, in view of <lb/>our above discussion, and therefore, they need not be made to suffer <lb/>any further agony. <lb/>42. In Dr.N.Nagbhushanam Vs Vasudeva Reddy and another W.A.No.574 and <lb/>Batch of 1995 decided on 08.08..1996 (1996 SCC Online AP 535), a Division Bench of <lb/>the Andhra Pradesh High Court considered the appointments made by the Shri <lb/>Venkateswara University. The challenge was on the ground that the constitution of <lb/>the selection committee was illegal. After considering several judgments cited at the <lb/>Bar, the Bench came to the conclusion that the appointments were valid <lb/>notwithstanding that a few members of the Committee has been absent on the date <lb/>of selection. <lb/>43. The petitioners also argue that the applicable Regulations would be the <lb/>2010 UGC Regulations and not those issued in 2000. The University has itself <lb/>included a member of the SC/ST/Woman in the committee thus clearly following only <lb/>http://www.judis.nic.in <lb/></body>

			<page>27 <lb/></page>

			<body>the 2010 Regulations. Thus it is estopped from contending that the selection process <lb/>is in violation of the 2000 Regulations. Reliance, in this regard is placed on a decision <lb/>of this Court in the case of The Chairman of Board of Rustees vs. Dr.K.R.S.Girija <lb/>Shyamsundar (W.A.No.1222 of 2015, order dated 22.06.2017, passed by a Division <lb/>Bench of this Court). This objection cannot be sustained in the light of the response <lb/>of the University pointing out that both the 2000 as well as the 2010 Regulations are <lb/>in pari materia with each other in regard to the procedure to be adopted for selection <lb/>of candidates except for the addition of the SC/ST/Woman member in the latter. This <lb/>submission has not been controverted by the petitioner and is thus accepted as <lb/>reflecting the correct position. <lb/>44. There is no doubt that the UGC Regulations have been held to be <lb/>mandatory and are to be strictly and scrupulously adhered to. The second issue is <lb/>answered accordingly. Having said so, the Regulations have to be seen and applied in <lb/>the context of the structure of the Institution itself and not in a vacuum. I have taken <lb/>the view that the Board constitutes an Educational Agency and all six colleges form a <lb/>single unit under its umbrella and I now proceed to examine the procedure followed <lb/>by the Board in making the appointments in question, in the light of my decisions on <lb/>the issues as aforesaid, bringing me to the third issue. <lb/>45. The selection procedure for a lecturer in a private college has been set out <lb/>in the UGC Regulations, specifically Regulation 3 of the Notification issued in March <lb/>2000, constituting the constitution of Committee. I have adverted to the same earlier <lb/>in this order and do not refer to same again for the sake of brevity. The educational <lb/>qualification of the petitioners before me viz-a-viz the post they are appointed to, are <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">http://www.judis.nic.in <lb/></note>

			<page>28 <lb/></page>

			<body>not in dispute nor is their competence. Importantly, there is no allegation of <lb/>impropriety in the selection of the candidates as noted by my elsewhere as well. <lb/>46. The constitution of and the quorum of the committee in the case of the <lb/>petitioners is set out below: <lb/>In respect of the appointment of Dr.J.Kavina (Botany) in Pachaiyappa&apos;s <lb/>College, Chennai the following five (5) members were present, two (2) of whom were <lb/>subject experts. <lb/>Chairperson <lb/>S.Jayachandran <lb/>Principal of the College <lb/>Dr.P.Gajivardhan <lb/>Two Nominees of the University of Madras of <lb/>whom one should be subject expert <lb/>N.A <lb/>Two subject-experts nominated by the <lb/>Chairperson <lb/>Dr.V.Lilly <lb/>Dr.C.V.ChittyBabu <lb/>One <lb/>common <lb/>Nominee <lb/>of <lb/>SC/ST/OBC/Minority/Women <lb/>Dr.B.Venuglpal (SC/ST) <lb/>In the case of Assistant Professors (Physics) of C.Kandaswamy College for <lb/>Men the following six (6) members were present including two (2) subject experts. <lb/>Chairperson <lb/>S.Jayachandran <lb/>Principal of the College <lb/>Dr.P.Sekar <lb/>HOD(Physics) <lb/>Dr.G.R.Ramkumaar <lb/>Two Nominees of the University of Madras of <lb/>whom one should be subject expert <lb/>Dr.P.Ravishankar <lb/>Subject-experts nominated by the <lb/>Chairperson <lb/>Dr.K.Chitra <lb/>One <lb/>common <lb/>Nominee <lb/>of <lb/>SC/ST/OBC/Minority/Women <lb/>Dr.M.Sakthivel (SC/ST/Women) <lb/>http://www.judis.nic.in <lb/></body>

			<page>29 <lb/></page>

			<body>In the case of Assistant Professors (Physics) for Pachaiyappa&apos;s College, <lb/>Chennai, the following four (4) members were present, including one (1) subject <lb/>expert: <lb/>Chairperson <lb/>S.Jayachandran <lb/>Principal of the College <lb/>Dr.P.Gajivardhan <lb/>Subject-experts nominated by the <lb/>Chairperson <lb/>Dr.R.Geetha <lb/>One <lb/>common <lb/>Nominee <lb/>of <lb/>SC/ST/OBC/Minority/Women <lb/>Dr.B.Venuglpal (SC/ST/Women) <lb/>In addition to Dr.R.Geetha of Pachaiyappa&apos;s College, Chennai, a subject-<lb/>expert, Dr.K.Chitra was also present. Both are admittedly in the panel of subject-<lb/>experts recommended by the University of Madras though the latter was in the panel <lb/>for the CKNCMC. <lb/>47. However, since all colleges fall under the agency of the PTB and constitute <lb/>a single unit, the application of Regulation 3, stipulating the aspect of Constitution <lb/>and Quorum of Committee should be viewed in that background. <lb/>48. The petitioners state that the selection process took place in CKNCMC and <lb/>this is not disputed either in counter or in the course of the arguments before me. <lb/>From the records of selection produced before me, the selection appears to have <lb/>taken place qua subject, and not qua college. The proceedings have been scanned <lb/>and are extracted below: <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">http://www.judis.nic.in <lb/></note>

			<page>30 <lb/></page>

			<body>49. Thus, each committee constituted qua subject has sat in attendance to <lb/>select the candidates for all colleges in one location. Though some named nominees <lb/>are admittedly absent, other subject experts are, also admittedly, present in the very <lb/>http://www.judis.nic.in <lb/></body>

			<page>31 <lb/></page>

			<body>same committee. This has resulted in a committee qua subject that has members in <lb/>excess of the required quorum, including the required number of subjects experts. <lb/>There can, in my view, be no infirmity in this manner of selection, seeing as all <lb/>colleges constitute one single unit. <lb/>50. Moreover, the composition of the selection committee and attendees filed <lb/>by the Board and extracted below, confirm unequivocally the position that there are <lb/>sufficient subject experts in attendance at the common selection who have been part <lb/>of the committee formed qua subject during the selection process. <lb/>PACHAIYAPPA&apos;S TRUST BOARD, CHENNAI-600 030 <lb/>Direct Recruitment for the Post of Assistant Professors/Librarian <lb/>S.No. <lb/>COMMON SELECTION COMMITTEE MEETING <lb/>PRESENT <lb/>OF THE PACHAIYAPPA&apos;S TRUST BOARD AIDED <lb/>ON <lb/>ARTS &amp; SCIENCE COLLEGES UNDER UGC <lb/>17-02-2016 <lb/>REGULATION <lb/>1 <lb/>Thiru.S.JAYACHANDRAN <lb/>(President/Chairman) <lb/>Signed <lb/>Chairperson of Governing Body <lb/>2 <lb/>Dr.P.GAJIVARADHAN <lb/>(Principal) <lb/>Signed <lb/>Pachaiyappa&apos;s College Chennai-30 <lb/>17.02.2016 <lb/>3 <lb/>Dr.P.SEKAR <lb/>(Principal) <lb/>Signed <lb/>C.Kandaswami Naidu College for Men Chennai-102 <lb/>17.02.2016 <lb/>4 <lb/>Dr.(Tmt) V.G.VIJAYALAKSHMI <lb/>(Principal) <lb/>Signed <lb/>Chellammal Women&apos;s College Guindy Chennai-32 <lb/>17.02.2016 <lb/>5 <lb/>Dr.S.KALIRAJ <lb/>(Principal) <lb/>Signed <lb/>Pachaiyappa&apos;s College for Men Kanchipuram <lb/>17.02.2016 <lb/>6 <lb/>Dr. Tmt. R.SUBBULAKSHMI <lb/>(Principal) <lb/>Signed <lb/>Pachaiyappa&apos;s College for Women Kanchipuram <lb/>17.02.2016 <lb/>7 <lb/>Dr.(Tmt.) MALLIKA CHANDIRAN <lb/>(Principal) <lb/>Signed <lb/>C.Kandaswami Naidu College for Women Cuddalore <lb/>17.02.2016 <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">http://www.judis.nic.in <lb/></note>

			<page>32 <lb/></page>

			<body>-TAMIL <lb/>…. <lb/>-ENGLISH <lb/>…. <lb/>-SANSKRIT <lb/>…. <lb/>-MATHEMATICS <lb/>-PHYSICS <lb/>43 <lb/>DR. P. ARULMOZHICHELVAN <lb/>(HOD) Physics <lb/>Pachaiyappa&apos;s College Chennai-30 <lb/>44 <lb/>DR. G.R. RAMKUMAR <lb/>(HOD) Physics <lb/>Signed <lb/>C.Kandaswami Naidu College for Men, Chennai <lb/>17.02.2016 <lb/>45 <lb/>MR. J. GOVINDARAJ <lb/>(HOD) Physics <lb/>Signed <lb/>Pachaiyappa&apos;s College for Men, Kanchipuram <lb/>17.02.2016 <lb/>PACHAIYAPPA&apos;S COLLEGE, CHENNAI <lb/>46 <lb/>DR. M. RAVICHANDRAN <lb/>University of Madras -V.C. Nominee <lb/>47 <lb/>DR. C. VENKATESWARAN <lb/>University of Madras -V.C. Nominee <lb/>48 <lb/>DR. R. GEETHA <lb/>Signed <lb/>University of Madras -Subject Expert (Nominated by <lb/>17.02.2016 <lb/>Chairperson) <lb/>49 <lb/>DR. K.H. RAJINI <lb/>University of Madras -Subject Expert (Nominated by <lb/>Chairperson) <lb/>50 <lb/>DR. B. VENUGOPAL <lb/>Signed <lb/>University of Madras-Nomination-Academician <lb/>Representing SC/ST/WOMEN/MINORITY etc., <lb/>C.KANDASWAMI NAIDU COLLEGE FOR MEN, CHENNAI <lb/>51 <lb/>DR. P. RAVISHANKAR <lb/>Signed <lb/>http://www.judis.nic.in <lb/></body>

			<page>33 <lb/></page>

			<body>University of Madras -V.C. Nominee <lb/>17.02.2016 <lb/>52 <lb/>DR. C. VENKATESWARAN <lb/>University of Madras -V.C. Nominee <lb/>53 <lb/>DR. K. CHITRA <lb/>Signed <lb/>University of Madras -Subject Expert (Nominated by <lb/>17.02.2016 <lb/>Chairperson) <lb/>54 <lb/>DR. N. RAMESH <lb/>University of Madras -Subject Expert (Nominated by <lb/>Chairperson) <lb/>55 <lb/>DR. M. SAKTHIVEL <lb/>Signed <lb/>University of Madras -Nomination-Academician <lb/>17.02.2016 <lb/>Representing SC/ST/WOMEN/MINORITY etc.,) <lb/>PACHAIYAPPA&apos;S COLLEGE FOR MEN, KANCHIPURAM <lb/>56 <lb/>DR. S. ELUMALAI <lb/>Signed <lb/>University of Madras -V.C. Nominee <lb/>17.02.2016 <lb/>57 <lb/>DR. G. ANBALAGAN <lb/>Signed <lb/>University of Madras -V.C. Nominee <lb/>17.02.2016 <lb/>58 <lb/>DR. AZHAGIRI <lb/>Signed <lb/>University of Madras -Subject Expert (Nominated by <lb/>17.02.2016 <lb/>Chairperson) <lb/>59 <lb/>DR. V. UJLAGENDRAN, <lb/>Signed <lb/>University of Madras -Subject Expert (Nominated by <lb/>Chairperson) <lb/>60 <lb/>DR. T. RAJU <lb/>Signed <lb/>University of Madras -Nomination-Academician <lb/>Representing SC/ST/WOMEN/MINORITY etc.,) <lb/>PACHAIYAPPA&apos;S COLLEGE FOR WOMEN, KANCHIPURAM <lb/>61 <lb/>DR. S. SUMATHI <lb/>Signed <lb/>University of Madras -V.C. Nominee <lb/>62 <lb/>DR. G. ANBALAGAN <lb/>Signed <lb/>http://www.judis.nic.in <lb/></body>

			<page>34 <lb/></page>

			<body>University of Madras -V.C. Nominee <lb/>17.02.2016 <lb/>63 <lb/>DR. G. PRABHAGARAN <lb/>Signed <lb/>University of Madras -Subject Expert (Nominated by <lb/>Chairperson) <lb/>64 <lb/>DR. K. RAVICHANDRAN <lb/>Signed <lb/>University of Madras -Subject Expert (Nominated by <lb/>Chairperson) <lb/>65 <lb/>DR. K. PANDIAN <lb/>Signed <lb/>University of Madras -Nomination-Academician <lb/>Representing SC/ST/WOMEN/MINORITY etc.,) <lb/>009 -CHEMISTRY <lb/>…. <lb/>005--BOTANY <lb/>93 <lb/>DR. K.M. UMARAJAN <lb/>(HOD) Botany <lb/>Pachaiyappa&apos;s College Chennai-30 <lb/>94 <lb/>TMT. T. VASANTHI <lb/>(HOD) Botany <lb/>C.Kandaswami Naidu College for Women, Cuddalore <lb/>PACHAIYAPPA&apos;S COLLEGE, CHENNAI <lb/>95 <lb/>DR. M. RAVICHANDRAN <lb/>University of Madras -V.C. Nominee <lb/>96 <lb/>DR. N. MATHIVANAN <lb/>University of Madras -V.C. Nominee <lb/>97 <lb/>DR. V. LILLY <lb/>Signed <lb/>University of Madras -Subject Expert (Nominated by <lb/>Chairperson) <lb/>98 <lb/>DR. S. NATARAJAN <lb/>Signed <lb/>University of Madras -Subject Expert (Nominated by <lb/>17.02.2016 <lb/>Chairperson) <lb/>99 <lb/>DR. B. VENUGOPAL <lb/>Signed <lb/>University of Madras -Nomination-Academician <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">http://www.judis.nic.in <lb/></note>

			<page>35 <lb/></page>

			<body>Representing SC/ST/WOMEN/MINORITY etc.,) <lb/>PACHAIYAPPA&apos;S COLLEGE, CHENNAI <lb/>100 <lb/>DR. S. SUMATHI <lb/>Signed <lb/>University of Madras -V.C. Nominee <lb/>101 <lb/>DR. V. LILLY <lb/>Signed <lb/>University of Madras -V.C. Nominee <lb/>102 <lb/>DR. C.V. CHITTIBABU <lb/>Signed <lb/>University of Madras -Subject Expert (Nominated by <lb/>17.02.2016 <lb/>Chairperson) <lb/>103 <lb/>DR. S. NATARAJAN <lb/>Signed <lb/>University of Madras -Subject Expert (Nominated by <lb/>17.02.2016 <lb/>Chairperson) <lb/>104 <lb/>DR. K. PANDIAN <lb/>Signed <lb/>University of Madras -Nomination-Academician <lb/>Representing SC/ST/WOMEN/MINORITY etc.,) <lb/>C.KANDASWAMY NAIDU COLLEGE FOR WOMEN, CUDDALORE <lb/>105 <lb/>DR. H. MUNAVARJAN <lb/>Signed <lb/>Thiruvalluvar University -V.C. Nominee <lb/>106 <lb/>MRS. KAVERIAMMAL <lb/>Signed <lb/>Thiruvalluvar University -Subject Expert <lb/>17.02.2016 <lb/>007 -ZOOLOGY <lb/>…. <lb/>013 -ECONOMICS <lb/>…. <lb/>002 -PHILOSOPHY <lb/>…. <lb/>012 -HISTORY <lb/>…. <lb/>003 -LIBRARIAN <lb/>http://www.judis.nic.in <lb/></body>

			<page>36 <lb/></page>

			<body>51. The proceedings of the PTB for selection to the post of Asst. Professors -<lb/>Botany -is set out hereunder as illustrative of the methodology adopted for selection <lb/>by all the committees. <lb/>PACHAIYAPPA&apos;S TRUST BOARD, CHENNAI-600 030 <lb/>(Pachaiyappa&apos;s College Campus, Harington Road) <lb/>Proceedings of the meeting of the Combined Selection Committee constituted under <lb/>provision of the UGC Regulations for recruitment to the post of Assistant Professors in Botany <lb/>in respect of Pachaiyappa&apos;s Trust Board Art&apos;s and Science Colleges, held on 17.02.2016 at <lb/>C.Kandaswami Naidu College for Men, Chennai. <lb/>Resn.No.5 Re: <lb/>Aided Colleges -Pachaiyappa&apos;s Trust Board -Teaching staff -<lb/>Various Faculties -Certain Vacant posts permitted to be filled up by DCE, Chennai -Direct <lb/>Recruitment 2015-16-From out of Combined list of Candidates applied online basis and <lb/>sponsored through employment exchange -Assistant Professor in Botany -Selection -<lb/>Recommendation -Reg. <lb/>Order: <lb/>It has been brought to the notice of the Selection Committee that pertaining to <lb/>Assistant Professor in Botany in respect of Pachaiyappa&apos;s Trust Board Colleges that there <lb/>were following approved Vacancies: <lb/>VACANCY POSITION WITH COMMUNAL RESERVATION POINTS <lb/>College <lb/>wise <lb/>Vacancies <lb/>Vacan <lb/>cies <lb/>GT <lb/>(G <lb/>) <lb/>GT <lb/>(W) <lb/>BC <lb/>(OBCM) <lb/>(G) <lb/>BC <lb/>(OBCM) <lb/>(W) <lb/>MBC <lb/>(DNC <lb/>) <lb/>(G) <lb/>MBC <lb/>(DNC <lb/>) <lb/>(W) <lb/>SC <lb/>(G <lb/>) <lb/>SC <lb/>(W) <lb/>SC <lb/>(A) <lb/>(W) <lb/>ST <lb/>(G <lb/>) <lb/>Botany -<lb/>FACULTY <lb/>CODE <lb/>-<lb/>005 <lb/>03 <lb/>Pachaiyap <lb/>pa&apos;s <lb/>College, <lb/>Chennai <lb/>01 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/></body>

			<page>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">C.Kandas <lb/>wami <lb/>Naidu <lb/>College <lb/>for <lb/>Women, <lb/>01 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>http://www.judis.nic.in <lb/></note>

			<page>37 <lb/></page>

			<body>Cuddalore <lb/>Pachaiyap <lb/>pa&apos;s <lb/>College <lb/>for <lb/>Women, <lb/>Kanchipur <lb/>am <lb/>01 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>TOTAL <lb/>03 <lb/>For the aforesaid vacancies the applications responded through online and list of candidate <lb/>sponsored through employment exchange were combined and they were called for certificate <lb/>verification and for Interview before the selection committee. <lb/>Faculty Code Subjects <lb/>Vacancies <lb/>Number of <lb/>valid <lb/>Candidates <lb/>applied <lb/>online basis <lb/>Number of <lb/>Candidates <lb/>sponsored <lb/>through <lb/>Employment <lb/>Exchange <lb/>Total <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>4 &amp; 5 <lb/>005 <lb/>Botany <lb/>03 <lb/>36 <lb/>15 <lb/>51 <lb/>Out of the 51 candidates 23 Number of candidates turned up for interview and out of <lb/>the candidates turned up and after scrutiny of their testimonials and screening them with <lb/>regard to their eligibility with reference to UGC Regulations and Qualification prescribed there <lb/>on only 23 Number of candidates found to be eligible during certificate verification and they <lb/>were interviewed by the selection committee with reference to their merits, experience, ability <lb/>and performance in the interview by adopting yardstick in awarding marks by the selection <lb/>committee. <lb/>After the detailed scrutiny of the each and every candidates performance, this selection <lb/>committee recommends that the under mentioned candidates were found suitable for <lb/>appointment to the post of Assistant Professor in Botany and to be posted at <lb/>Pachaiyappa&apos;s Trust Board Colleges as per Communal Reservation notified against their <lb/>names. <lb/>A) <lb/>SELECTED CANDIDATES <lb/>Sl <lb/>Spl. <lb/>College to <lb/>http://www.judis.nic.in <lb/></body>

			<page>38 <lb/></page>

			<body>. <lb/>N <lb/>o. <lb/>Name of the <lb/>Candidates <lb/>Communal <lb/>Reservation <lb/>Category <lb/>Reservation <lb/>SUBJECT <lb/>which the <lb/>candidates to <lb/>be posted <lb/>1 <lb/>J.KAVINA <lb/>BC(OBCM) <lb/>Botany <lb/>PACHAIYAPPAS <lb/>COLLEGE, <lb/>CHENNAI <lb/>2 <lb/>S.POOMPOZHILl <lb/>SC <lb/>(W) <lb/>Botany <lb/>PACHAIYAPAS <lb/>COLLEGE FOR <lb/>WOMEN, <lb/>KANCHIPURAM <lb/>3 <lb/>Dr.S.SRIDEVI <lb/>appointed as Asst. <lb/>Prof. Of Botany in <lb/>obedience to Hon&apos;ble <lb/>High <lb/>Court <lb/>in <lb/>WP.No.39264/2915 <lb/>dt. 25/10/2016 <lb/>MBC/DC <lb/>Botany <lb/>C.KANDASAMI <lb/>NAIDU <lb/>COLLEGE FOR <lb/>WOMEN, <lb/>CUDDALORE <lb/>B) <lb/>RESERVE CANDIDATES <lb/>Sl <lb/>. <lb/>N <lb/>o. <lb/>Name of the <lb/>Candidates <lb/>Communal <lb/>Reservation <lb/>Spl. <lb/>Category <lb/>Reservation <lb/>SUBJECT <lb/>College to <lb/>which the <lb/>candidates to <lb/>be posted <lb/>1 D.BODHINI <lb/>BC(OBCM) <lb/>Botany <lb/>PACHAIYAPPAS <lb/>COLLEGE, <lb/>CHENNAI <lb/>2 K.THAMIZSELVI <lb/>SC <lb/>(W) <lb/>Botany <lb/>PACHAIYAPAS <lb/>COLLEGE FOR <lb/>WOMEN, <lb/>KANCHIPURAM <lb/>3 <lb/>MBC/DC <lb/>Botany <lb/>A) University Selection Committee Members <lb/>1. <lb/>DR. M. RAVICHANDRAN <lb/>University of Madras -V.C. Nominee <lb/>2. <lb/>DR. N. MATHIVANAN <lb/>University of Madras -V.C. Nominee <lb/>3. <lb/>DR. V. LILLY <lb/>Signed <lb/>http://www.judis.nic.in <lb/></body>

			<page>39 <lb/></page>

			<body>University <lb/>of <lb/>Madras <lb/>-<lb/>Subject <lb/>Expert <lb/>(Nominated by Chairperson) <lb/>4. <lb/>DR. S. NATARAJAN <lb/>(University of Madras -Subject Expert <lb/>(Nominated by Chairperson) <lb/>Signed <lb/>17.02.2016 <lb/>5. <lb/>DR. B. VENUGOPAL <lb/>University of Madras-Nomination-Academician <lb/>Representing SC/ST/ WOMEN/MINORITY etc., <lb/>Signed <lb/>6. <lb/>DR. S. SUMATHI <lb/>University of Madras -V.C. Nominee <lb/>Signed <lb/>7. <lb/>DR. V. LILLY <lb/>University of Madras -V.C. Nominee <lb/>Signed <lb/>8. <lb/>DR. C.V. CHITTIBABU <lb/>University of Madras-Subject Expert (Nominated <lb/>by Chairperson) <lb/>Signed <lb/>17.02.2016 <lb/>9. <lb/>DR. S. NATARAJAN <lb/>University <lb/>of <lb/>Madras <lb/>-<lb/>Subject <lb/>Expert <lb/>(Nominated by Chairperson) <lb/>Signed <lb/>17.02.2016 <lb/>10. <lb/>DR. K. PANDIAN <lb/>University of Madras-Nomination-Academician <lb/>Representing SC/ST/ WOMEN/MINORITY etc., <lb/>Signed <lb/>11. <lb/>DR. H. MUNAVARJAN <lb/>Thiruvalluvar University -V.C. Nominee <lb/>Signed <lb/>17.02.2016 <lb/>12. <lb/>MRS. KAVERIAMMAL <lb/>Thiruvalluvar University -Subject Expert <lb/>Signed <lb/>17.02.2016 <lb/>B) HOD of the Trust Colleges <lb/>1. <lb/>DR. K.M. UMARAJAN (HOD) Botany <lb/>Pachaiyappa&apos;s College Chennai-30 <lb/>2. <lb/>TMT. T. VASANTHI (HOD) Botany <lb/>C.Kandaswami Naidu College for Women <lb/>Cuddalore <lb/>C) Principal of the Trust Colleges <lb/>1. <lb/>DR. P. GAJIVARADHAN <lb/>(Principal) <lb/>Pachaiyappa&apos;s College, Chennai <lb/>Signed <lb/>2. <lb/>DR. R. SUBBALAKSHMI <lb/>(Principal) <lb/>Signed <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">http://www.judis.nic.in <lb/></note>

			<page>40 <lb/></page>

			<body>Pachaiyappa&apos;s College for Women, Kanchipuram <lb/>17.02.2016 <lb/>3. <lb/>DR. MALLIGA CHANDIRAN <lb/>(Principal) <lb/>C.Kandaswami Naidu College for Women, <lb/>Cuddalore <lb/>Signed <lb/>17.02.2016 <lb/>D) Chairperson of the Governing Body <lb/>1. <lb/>Thiru. S. JAYACHANDRAN <lb/>President / Chairman <lb/>Pachaiyappa&apos;s Trust Board, Chennai-30 <lb/>-<lb/>52. The Board has also circulated the records of the selection process (three <lb/>documents). I extract a format of the parameters adopted for selection for the sake <lb/>of illustration, duly signed by the members of the selection Committee. This is <lb/>relevant to determine the veracity of the procedure followed by the Board in the case <lb/>of the petitioners. The signatures appended at the end of the proceedings of the <lb/>selection committees also attests to the fact that the numbers of attendees is in <lb/>excess of the required quorum and comprises of sufficient subject experts. <lb/>http://www.judis.nic.in <lb/></body>

			<page>41 <lb/></page>

			<body>PACHAIYAPPA&apos;S TRUST BOARD, CHENNAI -30 -SELECTION PROCESS FOR THE POST OF TEACHING STAFF -2015-16 <lb/>Prescribed Qualification <lb/>PG/SLET/NET/Ph.D., <lb/>Date: 17.02.2016 -Session -A.N. No of Candidates: 69 <lb/>S <lb/>e <lb/>r <lb/>i <lb/>a <lb/>l <lb/>N <lb/>u <lb/>m <lb/>b <lb/>e <lb/>r <lb/>C <lb/>al <lb/>l <lb/>L <lb/>et <lb/>te <lb/>r <lb/>N <lb/>u <lb/>m <lb/>b <lb/>er <lb/>PHYS -BOARD -1 <lb/>MERITS <lb/>ABILITY <lb/>Prescribed <lb/>Qualification <lb/>Additional <lb/>Qualification <lb/>Experience <lb/>Teaching Learning and Evaluation Activities <lb/>Interview <lb/>Online <lb/>Registration <lb/>Number <lb/>Name of the <lb/>Candidate <lb/>Maximum <lb/>-9 Marks <lb/>(Col.5,6 <lb/>&amp; 7) <lb/>Max -2 <lb/>Marks <lb/>Max -2 <lb/>marks <lb/>Max.15 <lb/>marks <lb/>Maximum 7 marks <lb/>(Col.11,2,13 &amp; 14) <lb/>Maximum 5 marks <lb/>(Col.15, 16 &amp; 17) <lb/>P <lb/>G <lb/>A <lb/>N <lb/>D <lb/>S <lb/>L <lb/>E <lb/>T <lb/>/ <lb/>N <lb/>E <lb/>T <lb/>( <lb/>5 <lb/>m <lb/>a <lb/>r <lb/>k <lb/>s <lb/>) <lb/>P <lb/>G <lb/>W <lb/>i <lb/>t <lb/>h <lb/>M <lb/>. <lb/>P <lb/>H <lb/>I <lb/>L <lb/>/ <lb/>S <lb/>E <lb/>L <lb/>T <lb/>/ <lb/>N <lb/>E <lb/>T <lb/>( <lb/>6 <lb/>m <lb/>a <lb/>r <lb/>k <lb/>s <lb/>) <lb/>P <lb/>G <lb/>W <lb/>i <lb/>t <lb/>h <lb/>P <lb/>h <lb/>. <lb/>D <lb/>( <lb/>9 <lb/>n <lb/>i <lb/>n <lb/>e <lb/>M <lb/>a <lb/>r <lb/>k <lb/>s <lb/>) <lb/>Any <lb/>oth <lb/>er <lb/>UG <lb/>(1 <lb/>Mar <lb/>ks)/ <lb/>PG <lb/>(2 <lb/>Mar <lb/>ks) <lb/>oth <lb/>er <lb/>tha <lb/>n <lb/>rele <lb/>van <lb/>t <lb/>Sub <lb/>ject <lb/>(Ma <lb/>xim <lb/>um <lb/>2 <lb/>mar <lb/>ks) <lb/>Pas <lb/>sed <lb/>by <lb/>oth <lb/>er <lb/>cour <lb/>se <lb/>con <lb/>duct <lb/>ed <lb/>by <lb/>UG <lb/>C <lb/>apa <lb/>rt <lb/>fro <lb/>m <lb/>SLE <lb/>T/N <lb/>ET <lb/>(Ea <lb/>ch 1 <lb/>mar <lb/>k <lb/>Max <lb/>imu <lb/>m 2 <lb/>mar <lb/>ks) <lb/>Experie <lb/>nce <lb/>(each <lb/>year 2 <lb/>marks <lb/>-<lb/>Maximu <lb/>m (15 <lb/>marks) <lb/>T <lb/>e <lb/>a <lb/>c <lb/>hi <lb/>n <lb/>g <lb/>R <lb/>el <lb/>at <lb/>e <lb/>d <lb/>a <lb/>ct <lb/>iv <lb/>iti <lb/>e <lb/>s <lb/>( <lb/>3 <lb/>m <lb/>ar <lb/>k <lb/>s) <lb/>D <lb/>o <lb/>m <lb/>ai <lb/>n <lb/>K <lb/>n <lb/>o <lb/>w <lb/>le <lb/>d <lb/>g <lb/>e <lb/>( <lb/>2 <lb/>m <lb/>ar <lb/>k <lb/>s) <lb/>P <lb/>ar <lb/>ti <lb/>ci <lb/>p <lb/>at <lb/>io <lb/>n <lb/>in <lb/>E <lb/>x <lb/>a <lb/>m <lb/>in <lb/>at <lb/>io <lb/>n <lb/>a <lb/>n <lb/>d <lb/>E <lb/>v <lb/>al <lb/>u <lb/>at <lb/>io <lb/>n <lb/>( <lb/>1 <lb/>m <lb/>ar <lb/>k <lb/>) <lb/>C <lb/>o <lb/>n <lb/>t <lb/>r <lb/>i <lb/>b <lb/>u <lb/>t <lb/>i <lb/>o <lb/>n <lb/>t <lb/>o <lb/>i <lb/>n <lb/>n <lb/>o <lb/>v <lb/>a <lb/>t <lb/>e <lb/>t <lb/>e <lb/>a <lb/>c <lb/>h <lb/>i <lb/>n <lb/>g <lb/>n <lb/>e <lb/>w <lb/>c <lb/>o <lb/>u <lb/>r <lb/>s <lb/>e <lb/>e <lb/>t <lb/>c <lb/>( <lb/>1 <lb/>M <lb/>a <lb/>r <lb/>k <lb/>) <lb/>N <lb/>. <lb/>S <lb/>. <lb/>S <lb/>/ <lb/>N <lb/>. <lb/>C <lb/>. <lb/>C <lb/>/ <lb/>C <lb/>U <lb/>L <lb/>T <lb/>U <lb/>R <lb/>A <lb/>L <lb/>/ <lb/>A <lb/>D <lb/>V <lb/>I <lb/>C <lb/>E <lb/>M <lb/>E <lb/>N <lb/>T <lb/>&amp; <lb/>C <lb/>O <lb/>U <lb/>N <lb/>S <lb/>E <lb/>L <lb/>LI <lb/>N <lb/>G <lb/>( <lb/>M <lb/>a <lb/>xi <lb/>m <lb/>u <lb/>m <lb/>2 <lb/>m <lb/>ar <lb/>k <lb/>s) <lb/>C <lb/>o <lb/>n <lb/>tr <lb/>ib <lb/>u <lb/>ti <lb/>o <lb/>n <lb/>to <lb/>c <lb/>or <lb/>p <lb/>or <lb/>at <lb/>e <lb/>lif <lb/>e <lb/>a <lb/>n <lb/>d <lb/>m <lb/>a <lb/>n <lb/>a <lb/>g <lb/>e <lb/>m <lb/>e <lb/>n <lb/>t <lb/>-<lb/>D <lb/>e <lb/>pt <lb/>/I <lb/>n <lb/>st <lb/>i/ <lb/>A <lb/>c <lb/>a <lb/>d <lb/>e <lb/>m <lb/>ic <lb/>/ <lb/>A <lb/>d <lb/>m <lb/>in <lb/>is <lb/>tr <lb/>at <lb/>iv <lb/>e <lb/>/ <lb/>C <lb/>o <lb/>m <lb/>m <lb/>it <lb/>te <lb/>e <lb/>s <lb/>a <lb/>n <lb/>d <lb/>re <lb/>s <lb/>p <lb/>o <lb/>n <lb/>si <lb/>bi <lb/>lit <lb/>ie <lb/>s <lb/>-<lb/>2 <lb/>m <lb/>ar <lb/>k <lb/>s) <lb/>Pr <lb/>of <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">e <lb/>s <lb/>si <lb/>o <lb/>n <lb/>al <lb/>d <lb/>e <lb/>v <lb/>el <lb/>o <lb/>p <lb/>m <lb/>e <lb/>n <lb/>t <lb/>a <lb/>ct <lb/>iv <lb/>iti <lb/>e <lb/>s/ <lb/>s <lb/>e <lb/>m <lb/>in <lb/>ar <lb/>s/ <lb/>c <lb/>o <lb/>nf <lb/>er <lb/>e <lb/>n <lb/>c <lb/>e <lb/>s/ <lb/>tr <lb/>ai <lb/>ni <lb/>n <lb/>g <lb/>c <lb/>o <lb/>u <lb/>rs <lb/>e <lb/>/ <lb/>ta <lb/>lk <lb/>s/ <lb/></note>

			<body>le <lb/>ct <lb/>u <lb/>re <lb/>s/ <lb/>ar <lb/>ti <lb/>cl <lb/>e <lb/>s <lb/>-<lb/>( <lb/>1 <lb/>m <lb/>ar <lb/>k <lb/>) <lb/>Intervi <lb/>ew <lb/>(10 <lb/>Marks <lb/>) <lb/></body>

			<page>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>7 <lb/>8 <lb/>9 <lb/>10 <lb/>11 <lb/>12 <lb/>13 <lb/>14 <lb/>15 <lb/>16 <lb/>17 <lb/>18 <lb/>76 <lb/>076 <lb/>1177267512 <lb/>SARAVANAN L <lb/>-<lb/></note>

			<body>-<lb/>9 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/></body>

			<page>1 <lb/>1 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>6 <lb/>77 <lb/>077 <lb/>136997809 <lb/>SARAVANAN R <lb/>-<lb/></note>

			<body>-<lb/>9 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/></body>

			<page>2 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>5 <lb/>78 <lb/>078 <lb/>1177693971 <lb/>SATHEESH K <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>ABSENT <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>http://www.judis.nic.in <lb/></note>

			<page>42 <lb/></page>

			<body>53. The following points thus reveal themselves clearly to me: <lb/>(i) Selection has been qua subject (ii) this method of selection is valid, seeing <lb/>as the PTB is the common Educational Agency of all colleges that constitute one unit. <lb/>(iii) The Committee constituted contains, in all cases, more members than the <lb/>required quorum (iv) The committee, in all cases, comprises of adequate numbers of <lb/>subject experts. In my considered view, the procedure adopted is in line with the <lb/>UGC Regulations and passes muster. (v) The view adopted by the University is <lb/>hyper-technical and ignores the presence of some members of the sitting committee. <lb/>This is clearly incorrect since the process of selection has been qua subject and not <lb/>qua college. (vi) Then again, an expert in physics or botany is a subject expert, <lb/>whosoever the person is, and irrespective of the college he/she has been nominated <lb/>to. Obviously, the contents of the subject do not change from college to college but <lb/>remains the same. This would suffice for full compliance with the Regulations. <lb/>54. In fine, and having perused the details and materials submitted carefully I <lb/>am of the view that there is no infirmity in the process of selection of the petitioners <lb/>as faculty and the impugned orders thus fail. <lb/>55. After conclusion of the hearings spanning several sessions, written <lb/>submissions were filed by the parties. In the written submissions filed, the Trust has <lb/>raised some concerns about the appointments made for various other posts in the <lb/>colleges of the PTB as well. No arguments or even submissions were ever advanced <lb/>along these lines during the hearings before me and it has been left to me to peruse <lb/>these additional points and draw such inferences as I may. The matters were listed <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">http://www.judis.nic.in <lb/></note>

			<page>43 <lb/></page>

			<body>on several occasions to ensure that the parties were given full time and liberty to <lb/>made complete and comprehensive submissions. They have chosen to restrict their <lb/>pursuit of the matters only to the pleadings in the writ petitions and detailed oral <lb/>submissions advanced and I will, similarly, not traverse beyond this scope. I also <lb/>reiterate that Mr.Sundararajan appearing for the PTB has also repeatedly emphasized <lb/>to the Court that there is nothing untoward in the appointments other than the two <lb/>flaws in procedure pointed out in their counter and pursued in arguments. I leave this <lb/>matter, at that. <lb/>56. One more thing. The petitioners have, admittedly, assumed positions on <lb/>various dates between 25.02.2016 and 03.03.2016. The missive from the University <lb/>in the form of the present proceedings holding their appointments to be invalid has <lb/>been issued only on 18.09.2017 after the petitioners&apos; have rendered service for 18 <lb/>months. This is an unfortunate situation. Committed and qualified teachers are scarce <lb/>resources and becoming scarcer by the day. Without question, the Regulations of a <lb/>Regulatory body such as the UGC have to be followed and they are seen to have <lb/>been followed in the present cases. However, even assuming that the appointments <lb/>were invalid, there is no justification or explanation available for the elapse of <lb/>eighteen (18) months for the UGC to arrive at a decision regarding their <lb/>appointments. In the present cases, the services of the petitioners has not been <lb/>found to be lacking or inadequate. There is no such allegation in the counters. Even <lb/>otherwise, there are detailed terms and conditions in the appointment letters issued <lb/>to the candidates and if at all there are lacunae or shortfall in the merits of any <lb/>specific candidates, the Board will take appropriate action in specific cases to ensure <lb/>http://www.judis.nic.in <lb/></body>

			<page>44 <lb/></page>

			<body>that merit and quality of the faculty is maintained at all times. Even for this reason, in <lb/>addition to the reasoning in the earlier paragraphs of this order, I find the impugned <lb/>proceedings to be unsustainable. <lb/>57. Impugned orders dated 18.09.2017 holding the appointments of the <lb/>petitioners as invalid are set aside. Necessary orders approving the appointments <lb/>shall be passed by the respondents forthwith, and at any rate within a period of four <lb/>(4) weeks from date of receipt of this order, simultaneous with payments of service <lb/>emoluments due to the petitioners. The writ petitions are allowed in the above terms. <lb/>Consequently miscellaneous petitions are closed. No costs. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">24.04.2019 <lb/>Speaking order <lb/>Index: Yes <lb/>Internet: Yes <lb/>ska/sl <lb/>To <lb/>1.The University Grants Commission <lb/>Rep.by its Member Secretary <lb/>Bahadur Shah Zafar Marg <lb/>New Delhi 110 002 <lb/>2.The Registrar <lb/>University of Madras <lb/>Centenary Building <lb/>Chepauk <lb/>Chennai 600 005 <lb/>http://www.judis.nic.in <lb/>45 <lb/>DR.ANITA SUMANTH. J, <lb/>Ska <lb/>Pre-Delivery Order in <lb/>W.P.Nos.26159, 26160, <lb/>26161, 26162, 26163, 26164, <lb/>26165 &amp; 26166 of 2017 <lb/>&amp; W.M.P.Nos.27803, 27804, 27805 <lb/>, 27809, 26164,27797, 27798, 27799, <lb/>27800,27801, 27802, 27806, <lb/>27807, 27808, 27810, <lb/>27811 &amp; 27812 of 2017 <lb/>24.04.2019 <lb/>http://www.judis.nic.in </note>


	</text>
</tei>
