<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<note place="headnote">W.P.Nos.22236, 22238, 22242 and 22244 of <lb/></note>

			<front>IN THE HIGH COURT OF JUDICATURE AT MADRAS <lb/>DATED: 25.10.2021 <lb/>CORAM <lb/>THE HON&apos;BLE Mr.JUSTICE M.SUNDAR <lb/>W.P.Nos.22236, 22238, 22242 and 22244 of 2021 <lb/>M.Balaraja, <lb/>Shop No.8799, <lb/>Door No.27, Mahatma Gandhi Road, <lb/>Kumaran Nagar, Padi, <lb/>Chennai 600 050. <lb/>...Petitioner in W.P.No.22236 of 2021 <lb/>V.Sendoorapandy, <lb/>Shop No.8903, <lb/>Door No.52/186, Red Hills Road, <lb/>Pudur, Ambattur, <lb/>Chennai-600 053. <lb/>... Petitioner in W.P.No.22238 of <lb/>V.Selvam, <lb/>Shop No.446, <lb/>Door No.106, McNichols Road, <lb/>Chetpet, <lb/>Chennai 600 031. <lb/>... Petitioner in W.P.No.22242 of <lb/>N.Udayappa, <lb/>Shop No.9069, <lb/>Door Nos.288 &amp; 114, <lb/>Trunk Road, Poonamallee, <lb/>Chennai-600056. <lb/>...Petitioner in W.P.No.22244 of <lb/>-Vs.-<lb/></front>

			<page>1/11 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">https://www.mhc.tn.gov.in/judis/ <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">W.P.Nos.22236, 22238, 22242 and 22244 of 2021 <lb/></note>

			<front>1. The Tamil Nadu State Marketing Corporation Ltd.,(TASMAC) <lb/>Rep.by its Managing Director, <lb/>&quot;Thalamuthu Natarajan Maaligai&quot;, <lb/>Gandhi-Irwin Road, <lb/>Egmore, Chennai-600 008. <lb/>2. The Tamil Nadu State Marketing Corporation Ltd.,(TASMAC), <lb/>Rep.by its Senior Regional Manager, <lb/>LLA Building, Anna Salai, Chennai-600 002. <lb/>... 1 st &amp; 2 nd Respondents in all W.P.s <lb/>3. The Tamil Nadu State Marketing Corporation Ltd.,(TASMAC), <lb/>Rep. by its District Manager, Thiruvallur (East) District, <lb/>No.1, Banglore Highway, <lb/>Sembarambakkam, Chennai 602 103, <lb/>Thiruvallur District. <lb/>... 3 rd Respondent <lb/>in W.P.Nos.22236, 22238 &amp; 22244 of 2021 <lb/>3. The Tamil Nadu State Marketing Corporation Ltd.,(TASMAC), <lb/>Rep.by its District Manager, <lb/>Chennai (Central), District, <lb/>No.B-4, Ambattur Industrial Estate, <lb/>Ambattur, Chennai-600 058. <lb/>...3rd Respondent in W.P.No.22242 of 2021 <lb/>Writ Petitions filed under Article 226 of the Constitution of India <lb/>praying to issue a Writ of Mandamus, to direct the respondents to <lb/>forthwith extend the Bar license period of the petitioner for TASMAC <lb/>Shop Nos.8799, 8903, 446 and 9069 respectively corresponding to the <lb/>closure period due to COVID 19 pandemic, by considering and passing <lb/>necessary orders on the representations of the Petitioners dated <lb/>27.08.2021 respectively. <lb/></front>

			<page>2/11 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">https://www.mhc.tn.gov.in/judis/ <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">W.P.Nos.22236, 22238, 22242 and 22244 of 2021 <lb/></note>

			<front>For Petitioner in all W.P.s <lb/>: <lb/>Mr.K.Selvaraj <lb/>For Respondents in all W.P.s <lb/>: <lb/>Mr.K.Sathish Kumar <lb/>standing counsel <lb/>for TASMAC <lb/>****** <lb/>C O M M O N O R D E R <lb/></front>

			<body>This common order will govern all the captioned four writ <lb/>petitions. <lb/>2. Mr.K.Selvaraj, learned counsel for writ petitioners in all four <lb/>writ petitions are before this virtual Court. Learned counsel submits that <lb/>there are four different writ petitioners, but the issue is same. Learned <lb/>counsel submits that the writ petitioners were given two years license <lb/>(from 2019 to 2021) for selling short eats and collecting empty bottles <lb/>from Bars attached to four different retail liquor outlets run by &apos;Tamil <lb/>Nadu State Marketing Corporation Limited&apos; [&apos;TASMAC&apos;], but in 2019-<lb/>2021 period, Corona virus pandemic and consequent lock down which is <lb/>collectively referred to as &apos;COVID 19 situation&apos;, which the writ petitioner <lb/>could neither portend nor presage, intervened. Learned counsel for writ <lb/>petitioners submits that there was lock down and therefore, writ <lb/>petitioners could not have the benefit of entire two years period. <lb/>3/11 <lb/>https://www.mhc.tn.gov.in/judis/ <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">W.P.Nos.22236, 22238, 22242 and 22244 of 2021 <lb/></note>

			<body>3. Notwithstanding the expansive prayer in all the four writ <lb/>petitions, learned counsel, on instructions, abridges the prayer and <lb/>restricts the prayer to a simple Mandamus to dispose of representations <lb/>all dated 27.08.2021 made by each of the four writ petitioners. The <lb/>details are as follows: <lb/>S.No Shop No./Retail <lb/>Outlet No. <lb/>Name of Writ <lb/>Petitioner <lb/>W.P.Nos <lb/>1 <lb/>8799 <lb/>M.Balaraja <lb/>22236 of 2021 <lb/>2 <lb/>8903 <lb/>V.Sendoorapandy 22238 of 2021 <lb/>3 <lb/>446 <lb/>V.Selvam <lb/>22242 of 2021 <lb/>4 <lb/>9069 <lb/>N.Udayappa <lb/>22244 of 2021 <lb/>4. Mr.K.Sathish Kumar, learned standing counsel for TASMAC, <lb/>accepts notice on behalf of all the 3 respondents in all the four writ <lb/>petitions. On instructions, learned standing counsel submits that no fee <lb/>was collected from the writ petitioners during the lock down period. <lb/>5. However, owing to the extremely limited abridged/restricted <lb/>prayer writ petitioners are now making, this Court deems it appropriate to <lb/>accede to the limited abridged prayer. <lb/></body>

			<page>4/11 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">https://www.mhc.tn.gov.in/judis/ <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">W.P.Nos.22236, 22238, 22242 and 22244 of 2021 <lb/></note>

			<front>6. Before this Court proceeds further, it is deemed appropriate to <lb/>extract and reproduce four representations that has been placed before <lb/>Court (as part of the common typed set of papers). The four <lb/>representations are as follows: <lb/></front>

			<page>5/11 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">https://www.mhc.tn.gov.in/judis/ <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">W.P.Nos.22236, 22238, 22242 and 22244 of 2021 <lb/></note>

			<page>6/11 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">https://www.mhc.tn.gov.in/judis/ <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">W.P.Nos.22236, 22238, 22242 and 22244 of 2021 <lb/></note>

			<page>7/11 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">https://www.mhc.tn.gov.in/judis/ <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">W.P.Nos.22236, 22238, 22242 and 22244 of 2021 <lb/></note>

			<page>8/11 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">https://www.mhc.tn.gov.in/judis/ <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">W.P.Nos.22236, 22238, 22242 and 22244 of 2021 <lb/></note>

			<body>7. Captioned four writ petitions are disposed of with a directive to <lb/>first respondent to consider and dispose of all the four writ petitioners&apos; <lb/>representations (all dated 27.08.2021) on its own merits, in accordance <lb/>with law as expeditiously as the business of the first respondent would <lb/>permit and in any event, within three weeks from today i.e., on or before <lb/>15.11.2021. <lb/>8. Proceedings/orders disposing all the aforementioned four <lb/>representations of the four writ petitioners shall be communicated to the <lb/>respective writ petitioners under due acknowledgment within five <lb/>working days from the dates of disposal of the representations. Though <lb/>obvious, it is made clear that this Court has not expressed any opinion or <lb/>view on the merits of the matter and the first respondent shall consider <lb/>the representations on their own merits and in accordance with law. <lb/>9/11 <lb/>https://www.mhc.tn.gov.in/judis/ <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">W.P.Nos.22236, 22238, 22242 and 22244 of 2021 <lb/></note>

			<front>9. Captioned four Writ Petitions are disposed of in the aforesaid <lb/>manner by this common order. There shall be no order as to costs. <lb/>25.10.2021 <lb/>Speaking/Non-speaking order <lb/>Index: Yes/No <lb/>Internet : Yes/No <lb/>nsa/mk <lb/>To <lb/></front>

			<body>1. Managing Director, <lb/>The Tamil Nadu State Marketing Corporation Ltd.,(TASMAC) <lb/>&quot;Thalamuthu Natarajan Maaligai&quot;, <lb/>Gandhi-Irwin Road, <lb/>Egmore, Chennai-600 008. <lb/>2. Senior Regional Manager, <lb/>The Tamil Nadu State Marketing Corporation Ltd.,(TASMAC), <lb/>LLA Building, Anna Salai, Chennai-600 002. <lb/>3. District Manager, <lb/>The Tamil Nadu State Marketing Corporation Ltd.,(TASMAC), <lb/>Thiruvallur (East) District, <lb/>No.1, Banglore Highway, <lb/>Sembarambakkam, Chennai 602 103, <lb/>Thiruvallur District. <lb/>4. District Manager, <lb/>The Tamil Nadu State Marketing Corporation Ltd.,(TASMAC), <lb/>Chennai (Central), District, <lb/>No.B-4, Ambattur Industrial Estate, <lb/>Ambattur, Chennai-600 058. <lb/>10/11 <lb/>https://www.mhc.tn.gov.in/judis/ <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">W.P.Nos.22236, 22238, 22242 and 22244 of 2021 <lb/></note>

			<front>M.SUNDAR.J., <lb/>mk <lb/>W.P.Nos.22236, 22238, 22242 and 22244 of 2021 <lb/>25.10.2021 <lb/></front>

			<page>11/11 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">https://www.mhc.tn.gov.in/judis/ </note>


	</text>
</tei>
