<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<p>W.P. No.8180 of 2019 has been filed seeking a direction to<lb/> respondents 1 and 2 to evacuate the third respondent in encroachments<lb/> of the general path and to ensure the petitioner to utilise the same to<lb/> cultivate her land based upon her representation dated 28.08.2018.<lb/> W.P. No.21436 of 2019 has been filed challenging the impugned<lb/> Proceedings Ka.No.01/2018/U.Pe dated 12.07.2019 issued by the first<lb/> respondent and seeking a direction to the first respondent to survey the<lb/> entire extent of the property comprised in Survey No.217 at Romapuri<lb/> Village, Cuddalore District and other lands which are encroached by the<lb/> second respondent and others and to pass appropriate orders after<lb/> providing sufficient opportunity to the petitioner and others.<lb/></p>

			<p>2.Since the issue involved in both the writ petitions are common,<lb/> these are intertwined and disposed of by way of common order with the<lb/> consent of either side.<lb/></p>

			<p>3.The facts of the case in W.P. No.8180 of 2019 are that the<lb/> petitioner has been cultivating her land, situated at 30 feet road, near<lb/> NHAI Road and that the general pathway belongs to NHAI, has been used<lb/> for reaching the petitioner&apos;s land. The grievance of the petitioner is that<lb/> the land of respondents 3 and 4 is situated near to her land and they have<lb/> been occupying the general pathway by preventing the petitioner from<lb/> entering and cultivating her land. In this regard, the petitioner has made a<lb/> representation to respondents 1 and 2 on 04.07.2018 to take necessary<lb/> action against the third respondent for removing the encroachment made<lb/> by respondents 3 and 4 in the government land. Since no action was<lb/> taken against them, the petitioner is before this Court.<lb/></p>

			<p>4.The facts of the case in W.P. No.21436 of 2019 are that in the<lb/> year 2006, the government had issued patta to several persons in Survey<lb/> No.172/15 Ramapuri Village, Cuddalore District to an extent of 32.50 ares<lb/> under the scheme of landless people by order dated 14.09.2006. After the<lb/> assignment, the petitioner and others are enjoying the above said land<lb/> without any hindrance by constructing a small house in a portion of the<lb/> said land. While so, the second respondent is having a land in S.No.38/4<lb/> adjoining the petitioner&apos;s land in S.No.172/15 and by way of encroaching<lb/> the Highways land, she constructed a building in the above said highways<lb/> property in S.No.217 and the said property has been let out for rent to<lb/> third parties and thereby, she has been earning monthly income of<lb/> Rs.35,000/-. In order to harass the petitioner, the second respondent had<lb/> filed a suit in O.S. No.53 of 2003 before the District Munsif-cum-Judicial<lb/> Magistrate, Neyveli seeking relief for declaration and permanent injunction<lb/> as against the petitioner and others with respect to the above said<lb/> property. By judgment and decree dated 02.07.2013, the District Munsif<lb/> cum Judicial Magistrate dismissed the said suit. As against the same, the<lb/> second respondent has filed an Appeal in A.S. No.1 of 2015 before the<lb/> Subordinate Judge, Neyveli and the same was also dismissed by judgment<lb/> and decree dated 24.07.2015. Suppressing the above facts, the second<lb/> respondent has filed the above writ petition in W.P. No.8180 of 2019<lb/> before this Court to evict the petitioner. While so, the first respondent has<lb/> issued the above proceedings only on the inducement of the second<lb/> respondent. Therefore, the petitioner is before this Court challenging the<lb/> same and seeking the above direction.<lb/></p>

			<p>5.Heard the learned counsel for the petitioners, learned<lb/> Government Advocate and the learned counsel for R3 and R4 and perused<lb/> the materials on record.<lb/></p>

			<p>6.Considering the submissions made by both sides, we are of the<lb/> opinion that the issue involved in both the writ petitions is nothing, but a<lb/> disputed question of facts. As the same cannot be agitated before this<lb/> Court, we are constrained to direct the Assistant Engineer, National<lb/> Highways, Vridhachalam, Cuddalore District to conduct an enquiry and<lb/> survey the said lands in the presence of the parties, by issuing notice to<lb/> both the petitioners as well as the fourth respondent in W.P. No.8180 of<lb/> 2019. After enquiry, if he comes to the conclusion that there was an<lb/> encroachment made in the above lands, he is further directed to remove<lb/> R.SUBBIAH, J<lb/> and<lb/> R.PONGIAPPAN, J<lb/> vga<lb/> the encroachment in accordance with law, within a period of 12 weeks<lb/> from the date of receipt of a copy of this order. With the above directions,<lb/> the writ petitions stand disposed of. Consequently, connected W.M.Ps are<lb/> closed. No costs.<lb/></p>

			<p>[R.P.S., J]<lb/></p>

			<p>[R.P.A., J]<lb/></p>

			<p>14.02.2020<lb/></p>

			<item>Index:yes/no<lb/> vga<lb/></item>

			<item>To<lb/></item>

 1.The District Collector,<lb/> Cuddalore District,<lb/> Cuddalore.<lb/></item>

			<item>2.The Assistant Engineer,<lb/> National Highways,<lb/> Vridhachalam,<lb/> Cuddalore District.<lb/></item>

			<item>Writ Petition Nos.8180 &amp; 21436 of 2019<lb/> and W.M.P. Nos.20637 &amp; 20640 of 2019</item>


	</text>
</tei>
