<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			IN THE HIGH COURT OF HIMACHAL PRADESH AT
			<lb />
			SHIMLA
			<lb />
			R.S.A. No. 464 of 2012
			<lb />
			Reserved on: 25.11.2019
			<lb />
			Decided on : 01.01.2020
			<lb />
			______________________________________________________
			<lb />
			Rukmani   Devi   (since   deceased)   through   her   legal
			<lb />
			representative Sh. Gulab Singh son of late Sh. Tule Ram.
			<lb />
			…..Appellant
			<lb />
			Versus
			<lb />
			Prem Lata  &amp; Anr.                        …Respondents
			<lb />
			_____________________________________________________
			<lb />
			Coram:
			<lb />
			The Honble Mr. Justice Chander Bhusan Barowalia, Judge.
			<lb />
			1 Whether approved for reporting? Yes.
			<lb />
			__________________________________________________________
			<lb />
			For the appellant: Mr.Bimal   Gupta,   Senior Advocate,
			<lb />
			with Ms. Kusum Chaudhary, Advocate.
			<lb />
			For the respondents:    Mr.   O.P.   Sharma,   Sr.   Advocate   with
			<lb />
			Mr. Gurmeet Bhardwaj, Advocate.
			<lb />
			Chander Bhusan Barowalia, Judge.
			<lb />
		</front>
		<body>
			Chander Bhusan Barowalia, Judge.
			<lb />
			The present regular second appeal is maintained by
			<lb />
			the appellant under Section 100 of the Code of Civil Procedure,
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -11/07/2022 23:02:53 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			2
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			against the judgment and decree dated 15.5.2012, passed by
			<lb />
			the learned Additional District Judge (Fast Track Court),
			<lb />
			Kullu, in Civil Appeal No.28 of 2011, affirming the judgment
			<lb />
			and decree dated 14.10.2011, passed by the learned Civil Judge
			<lb />
			(Sr. Division), Manali, District Kullu, H.P., in Civil Suit No.43
			<lb />
			of 2008.
			<lb />
			2.
			<lb />
			Briefly stating the facts giving rise to the present
			<lb />
			appeal are that the plaintiff/appellant (hereinafter to be called
			<lb />
			as &apos;the plaintiff&apos;) filed a suit for declaration to the effect that
			<lb />
			the land comprised in Khata Khatoni No.55/105, Khasra Nos.
			<lb />
			1202, 1218, land measuring 11841 hectare and Khata
			<lb />
			Khatoni No.56/106 to 56/114, Khasra No.1126, 1174, 1176,
			<lb />
			1178, 1179, 1220, 1250, 1251, 1291, 1300, 1413, 1501, 1182,
			<lb />
			1183, 1184, 1188, 1189,1217,1269,1451,1452,1348,1180,1219,
			<lb />
			1252,1253, 1263, 1268, 1297,1232,1334,1496,1292,1293,1415,
			<lb />
			1152,1127,1175,1177, 1260,1261,1301,1325, 1333, 1497 &amp; 1226
			<lb />
			total land measuring 45781 hectares as per jamabandi for the
			<lb />
			year 200001, to the extent of 1/4th share situated at Phati
			<lb />
			Soyal, Kothi Barshai and two houses wherein the plaintiff is
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -11/07/2022 23:02:53 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			3
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			residing, as per site plan (hereinafter to be called as &apos;suit
			<lb />
			property&apos;). The plaintiff has alleged that she had solemnized
			<lb />
			marriage in the year, 1957 with Atma Ram(deceased) and at
			<lb />
			that time Atma Ram had given two bighas of Ropa and five
			<lb />
			bighas and 10 biswas of Bathal land to her as &apos;Istridhan&apos;, which
			<lb />
			is adjoining to the the house and is in exclusive possession of
			<lb />
			the plaintiff since then.
			<lb />
			3.
			<lb />
			As per the applicant, thereafter, he had developed
			<lb />
			love and affection with respondent/defendant No.1 (hereinafter
			<lb />
			called the &apos;defendant No.1), who is daughter of Tulsi, the
			<lb />
			Godsister of the plaintiff. Tulsi, lateron settled in the house of
			<lb />
			Atma Ram, however, she could not bear any child from the
			<lb />
			loins of her husband, Atma Ram. As per the plaintiff defendant
			<lb />
			No.1 was the daughter of Tulsi from her previous husband. In
			<lb />
			the month of March,2008, Atma Ram fell ill and had grown
			<lb />
			very weak and was mentally infirm and treatment was given to
			<lb />
			him in Manali hospital. Defendant No.1 used to take Atma
			<lb />
			Ram under the pretext of treatment to Manali and used to take
			<lb />
			his signatures on many papers. Plaintiff averred that he never
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -11/07/2022 23:02:53 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			4
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			executed any Will. After his death, the last rites of Atma Ram
			<lb />
			were performed by the plaintiff. The defendants never rendered
			<lb />
			any services to Atma Ram during his life time. After about 15
			<lb />
			days of the death of Atma Ram to utter shock and surprise of
			<lb />
			plaintiff, the defendant No.1 and her husband started saying
			<lb />
			that they have got the Will of Atma Ram. The defendant No.1
			<lb />
			procured Will in her favour fraudulently under the pretext of
			<lb />
			treatment of her husband. On 3.7.2008, plaintiff again was
			<lb />
			shocked to know that the defendant had got herself entered as
			<lb />
			nominee of Atma Ram in the bank accounts in connivance with
			<lb />
			the bank officials. Hence, the suit for declaration to declare the
			<lb />
			Will Ext.DW5/B, null and void and decreeing the suit for
			<lb />
			permanent prohibitory injunction restraining the defendants
			<lb />
			from interfering into the ownership and possession of plaintiff
			<lb />
			over the suit property in any manner and defendant No.1 be
			<lb />
			directed through a decree of mandatory injunction to hand over
			<lb />
			the entire amount withdrawn by her from the banks.
			<lb />
			4.
			<lb />
			The defendants filed written statement and
			<lb />
			resisted the suit on merits as well they maintained the
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -11/07/2022 23:02:53 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			5
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			preliminary objections. On merits, it is averred that Atma Ram
			<lb />
			married for the second time with Smt. Tulsi Devi mother of
			<lb />
			defendant No.1 and kept her as second wife. During his life
			<lb />
			time, Atma Ram gifted his land in favour of defendant No.1 on
			<lb />
			19.12.2001,as per deed Ex.DW2/A and mutation number 57,58
			<lb />
			Ext.DW1/E and Ext. DW1/F were attested. It has been denied
			<lb />
			that any land was given to the plaintiff as Women&apos;s Estate
			<lb />
			(ISTRIDHAN). The defendant averred that she was born from
			<lb />
			the wedlock of Atma Ram and Tulsi Devi, as is evident from
			<lb />
			her school certificates Ext.DW1/B &amp; C and Atma Ram has been
			<lb />
			recorded as her father. Atma Ram was suffering from heart
			<lb />
			ailment and was treated at Chandigarh and defendant No.1
			<lb />
			and she incurred rupees five lakh on his treatment. Atma Ram
			<lb />
			was satisfied with the services of defendant No.1 and he had
			<lb />
			gifted suit property vide gift deed Ex.DW2/B and thereafter,
			<lb />
			Atma Ram had duly executed Will Ex.DW5/B. As per Will
			<lb />
			Ex.DW5/B, the plaintiff has also been given share in the land
			<lb />
			as well as in the house. It has been averred that deceased Atma
			<lb />
			Ram had desired that his last rites be performed by defendant
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -11/07/2022 23:02:53 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			6
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			No.2 and for the said purpose, he had also given part of the suit
			<lb />
			property to him in the Will Ex.DW5/B. It has also been averred
			<lb />
			that as per the wish of deceased Atma Ram, defendant offered
			<lb />
			two lacs to the plaintiff, but she refused to accept the same.
			<lb />
			5.
			<lb />
			On the pleadings of the parties, the learned Trial
			<lb />
			Court framed the following issues for determination and
			<lb />
			adjudication:
			<lb />
			&quot;1. Whether the plaintiff was only wife of
			<lb />
			deceased Atma Ram, as alleged? OPP.
			<lb />
			2.
			<lb />
			Whether the plaintiff
			<lb />
			has inherited the
			<lb />
			entire estate left by deceased Atma Ram, as
			<lb />
			alleged? OPP.
			<lb />
			3.
			<lb />
			Whether the plaintiff is owner in possession
			<lb />
			of the suit land, as alleged ? OPP.
			<lb />
			4.
			<lb />
			Whether the plaintiff is entitled for relief of
			<lb />
			permanent
			<lb />
			prohibitory
			<lb />
			injunction,
			<lb />
			as
			<lb />
			alleged? OPP
			<lb />
			5.
			<lb />
			Whether the plaintiff is entitled for a relief of
			<lb />
			mandatory injunction as alleged? OPP
			<lb />
			6.
			<lb />
			Whether the plaintiff is estopped by her acts
			<lb />
			and conduct from filing the present suit?
			<lb />
			OPD.
			<lb />
			7.
			<lb />
			Whether the suit of the plaintiff is not
			<lb />
			maintainable? OPD.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -11/07/2022 23:02:53 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			7
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			8.
			<lb />
			Whether the suit is bad for nonjoinder of
			<lb />
			necessary parties? OPD.
			<lb />
			9.
			<lb />
			Whether the defendant No.1 is coowner in
			<lb />
			the suit land as per gift dated 19.12.2001?
			<lb />
			OPD.
			<lb />
			10. Whether the suit is bad for misjoinder of
			<lb />
			necessary parties? OPD.
			<lb />
			11. Whether deceased Atma Ram executed valid
			<lb />
			and last Will dated 16.5.2008 in favour of
			<lb />
			plaintiff and defendants, as alleged? OPD.
			<lb />
			12. Relief.&quot;
			<lb />
			6.
			<lb />
			The learned Trial Court after deciding Issue No.1
			<lb />
			in favour of the plaintiff, Issue No. 2 against the plaintiff, Issue
			<lb />
			No.3 partly in favour of the plaintiff, Issue No.4 against the
			<lb />
			plaintiff, Issue No.5 against the plaintiff, Issue No.6 and 7 in
			<lb />
			favour of the defendant, Issue No.8 against the defendant,
			<lb />
			Issue No.9 in favour of the defendant, Issue No.10 against the
			<lb />
			defendant and Issue No.11 in favour of the defendant
			<lb />
			dismissed the suit.
			<lb />
			7.
			<lb />
			The plaintiff, thereafter, maintained an appeal
			<lb />
			before the learned lower Appellate Court, which was dismissed
			<lb />
			vide the impugned judgment and hence, the present regular
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -11/07/2022 23:02:53 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			8
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			second appeal, which was admitted for hearing on the following
			<lb />
			Substantial Questions of Law::
			<lb />
			&quot;1. Whether Will dated 16.5.2008 (Ex.DW5/B) is
			<lb />
			executed in accordance with Section 63 of
			<lb />
			the Indian Succession Act.
			<lb />
			2. Whether findings of the Courts below are
			<lb />
			based upon misreading, misinterpreting and
			<lb />
			misconstruing of oral and documentary
			<lb />
			evidence on record and the view taken by
			<lb />
			both the Courts below is totally perverse and
			<lb />
			contrary to evidence led by the propounder
			<lb />
			of the Will.&quot;
			<lb />
			8.
			<lb />
			I have heard the learned counsel for the parties and
			<lb />
			have carefully gone through the record.
			<lb />
			9.
			<lb />
			Mr. Bimal Gupta, learned Senior Counsel for the
			<lb />
			appellant, while referring to Section 63 of the Indian
			<lb />
			Succession Act, has argued that the two conditions necessary
			<lb />
			for the execution of the Will are:
			<lb />
			(i) That the testator should sign the Will in
			<lb />
			the presence of
			<lb />
			atleast two
			<lb />
			attesting
			<lb />
			witnesses; and
			<lb />
			(ii) the witnesses should sign the Will in the
			<lb />
			presence of the Testator.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -11/07/2022 23:02:53 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			9
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			He has argued that neither the scribe nor the witnesses in
			<lb />
			their examinationinchief has deposed that the witnesses
			<lb />
			have signed the Will in the presence of the Testator. He has
			<lb />
			further argued that as per the scribe and the witness DW 5
			<lb />
			and DW6, the Testator has not signed the Will on that
			<lb />
			particular day, as the hands of the Testator were trembling
			<lb />
			and thus put his thumb impression on the Will, which is a
			<lb />
			concocted story.
			<lb />
			10.
			<lb />
			While inviting attention of this Court of the
			<lb />
			document (Ext.DW5/B) of the Court below, he has argued
			<lb />
			that on the same day the Testator has signed the
			<lb />
			withdrawal slip in the Bank while withdrawing the amount.
			<lb />
			So, as per the learned Senior Counsel for the appellant, the
			<lb />
			Will is suspicious and the Will is required to be declared null
			<lb />
			and void, which the Courts below have wrongly upheld. He
			<lb />
			has argued that the Court below while dealing with the
			<lb />
			issue in paragraph 13 of the judgment passed by the learned
			<lb />
			First Appellate Court and in Para 22 and 23 of the leaned
			<lb />
			Trial Court, both the Courts below have not touched this
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -11/07/2022 23:02:53 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			10
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			issue while upholding the Will that when a person can sign
			<lb />
			on the same day why he will put the right hand thumb
			<lb />
			impression on the Will. In these circumstances also, the
			<lb />
			Will becomes suspicious.
			<lb />
			11.
			<lb />
			The learned Counsel has placed reliance
			<lb />
			upon the decision of Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court rendered
			<lb />
			in case titled Charan Dass(deceased through his
			<lb />
			Lrs) versus Dole Ram in RSA No.48/2001, decided
			<lb />
			on 06.11.2012 and Sohan Lal and Another versus
			<lb />
			Thakur Dass and others 2019 SCC HP 1975.
			<lb />
			12.
			<lb />
			Conversely, Mr. O.P. Sharma, learned Senior counsel
			<lb />
			for the respondents argued that no question of law is involved
			<lb />
			in the appeal and so the appeal needs dismissal. He has argued
			<lb />
			that even otherwise also, the present appeal cannot be
			<lb />
			maintained as it is the respondent only who is legally entitled
			<lb />
			to inherit the property as per the law laid down by the Hon&apos;ble
			<lb />
			Supreme Court. To support his arguments he has relied
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -11/07/2022 23:02:53 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			11
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			upon the judgments passed by the Hon&apos;ble Apex Court
			<lb />
			rendered in State of Rajasthan &amp; Ors. versus Shiv Dayal &amp;
			<lb />
			Anr. (CA No.7363 of 2000
			<lb />
			and Vijay Devi versus
			<lb />
			Navendra Singh Katoch, 2009 (2) Shim.LC 316, and in
			<lb />
			Bishan Singh (deceased) by his L.Rs versus Saran Singh
			<lb />
			and ors.
			<lb />
			13.
			<lb />
			Mr. O.P. Sharma, Senior counsel appearing for the
			<lb />
			defendant has further argued that the Will contains right hand
			<lb />
			Thumb impression of the executant on it, but when he
			<lb />
			appeared before the learned Registrar for the registration of
			<lb />
			the Will, he has put left hand thumb impression. He has
			<lb />
			further argued that the law does not require which thumb
			<lb />
			impression is to be marked by the testator. He has also argued
			<lb />
			that there is no allegation that Atma Ram was not of sound
			<lb />
			state of mind at the time of execution of the Will. Mr. Sharma
			<lb />
			has further argued that the Bank Officer, while appearing in
			<lb />
			the witness box, has specifically stated that the hands of the
			<lb />
			testator were trembling and he could sign with difficulty and
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -11/07/2022 23:02:53 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			12
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			there is no contradiction in the statement of the marginal
			<lb />
			witnesses and that of Bank Manager, as it is on record that the
			<lb />
			testator was signing with his left hand and that is the reason
			<lb />
			that he could put his left thumb impression. He has further
			<lb />
			relied upon a judgment of this Hon&apos;ble High Court rendered in
			<lb />
			Ishwar Dass versus Smt. Neelam Dassi deceased through
			<lb />
			her Lrs Shesh Ram and others, Latest HLJ 2016 (HP)
			<lb />
			1252. He has further argued that the law is settled that the
			<lb />
			property inherited by the widow and in case of no legal heir
			<lb />
			from her husband, it will go to the heirs of the husband and not
			<lb />
			to any other person. So, in these circumstances, he has argued
			<lb />
			that the property cannot be inherited by the present appellant.
			<lb />
			In these circumstances also, the appellant/plaintiff has no case
			<lb />
			in his favour. As per this, the daughter of late Atma Ram also
			<lb />
			can inherit the property. He has also placed reliance on the
			<lb />
			matriculation certificate of Mrs. Prem Lata. He has also relied
			<lb />
			upon a judgment rendered in Smt. Malkani versus Jamadar
			<lb />
			and others, AIR 1987 Supreme Court, 767 and argued that
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -11/07/2022 23:02:53 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			13
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			the beneficiaries taking active partition in the execution of the
			<lb />
			Will does not make the Will suspicious. He has further argued
			<lb />
			that as per the law settled in Bhagat Ram (D) by L.Rs.
			<lb />
			versus Teja Singh (D) L.Rs. AIR 2002 Supreme Court 1,
			<lb />
			after the death of Rukmani, no one on her side could inherit the
			<lb />
			estate of Atma Ram, as the property goes to the source from
			<lb />
			where it has come. He has emphasized that the appeal be
			<lb />
			dismissed as both the judgments are after appreciating the
			<lb />
			facts in accordance with law.
			<lb />
			14.
			<lb />
			In rebuttal Mr. Gupta, senior counsel has argued
			<lb />
			that Atma Ram was capable of signing the documents whereas
			<lb />
			he had put his right thumb impression, hence, the Will in
			<lb />
			question becomes suspicious.
			<lb />
			15.
			<lb />
			To appreciate the arguments of the learned
			<lb />
			counsel for the parties, I have gone through the record in
			<lb />
			detail.
			<lb />
			16.
			<lb />
			Perusal of the record depicts that marriage
			<lb />
			between the plaintiff Rukmani and Atma Ram was solemnized
			<lb />
			on 17.10.1957 and no issue was born out of their wedlock.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -11/07/2022 23:02:53 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			14
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			Thereafter, Atma Ram started cohabiting with Smt. Tulsi Devi
			<lb />
			sometime in the year 1970. Any Hindu Marriage to be held
			<lb />
			valid has to fulfill conditions of Section 5 of the Hindu
			<lb />
			Marriage Act, which reads as under:
			<lb />
			5. Conditions for a Hindu marriage:
			<lb />
			A marriage may be solemnized between any
			<lb />
			two Hindus, if the following conditions are
			<lb />
			fulfilled namely:
			<lb />
			(I)
			<lb />
			Neither party has a spouse living at the
			<lb />
			time of the marriage,
			<lb />
			1[(ii) at the time of marriage, neither party
			<lb />
			(a) Is incapable of giving a valid consent to
			<lb />
			it in consequence of unsoundness of
			<lb />
			mind; or
			<lb />
			(b) Though capable of giving a valid
			<lb />
			consent, has been suffering from mental
			<lb />
			disorder of such a kind or to such an
			<lb />
			extent as to be unfit for marriage and
			<lb />
			the procreation of children; or
			<lb />
			(c) Has been subject to recurrent attacks of
			<lb />
			insanity 2[***]
			<lb />
			(iii) The bridegroom has completed the age
			<lb />
			of 3[twentyone years] and the bride,
			<lb />
			the age of 4[ eighteen years] at the time
			<lb />
			of marriage;
			<lb />
			(iv) The parties are not within the degrees of
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -11/07/2022 23:02:53 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			15
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			prohibited relationship unless the
			<lb />
			custom or usage governing each of
			<lb />
			them permits of a marriage between the
			<lb />
			two;
			<lb />
			(v) The parties are not Sapindas of each
			<lb />
			other, unless the custom or usage
			<lb />
			governing each of them permits of a
			<lb />
			marriage between the two;
			<lb />
			17.
			<lb />
			PW1, Smt. Rukmani has stated that she was the
			<lb />
			wife of deceased Atma Ram, as the marriage was solemnized in
			<lb />
			the year 1957 and at the time of marriage Atma Ram had given
			<lb />
			her 2 Bighas of Ropa and 5 Bighas and 10 Biswas of Bathal
			<lb />
			land, as Istridhan. There were no children. Thereafter, Atma
			<lb />
			Ram developed love and affection with defendant No.1 (Prem
			<lb />
			Lata), who is the daughter of Tulsi, who was her Godsister and
			<lb />
			used to visit her quite often. Tulsi later on settled in the house
			<lb />
			of Atma Ram, but there were no children between the union of
			<lb />
			Atma Ram and Tulsi and defendant No.1 Prem Lata is the
			<lb />
			daughter of Tulsi Devi from her previous husband. She used to
			<lb />
			look after her husband Atma Ram. In March, 2008, Atma Ram
			<lb />
			fell seriously ill and had grown very weak and was mentally
			<lb />
			infirm. Atma Ram was under treatment at Manali hospital
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -11/07/2022 23:02:53 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			16
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			and defendant No.1 used to take Atma Ram under the pretext
			<lb />
			of treatment of Manali and used to take his signatures on
			<lb />
			many papers. Atma Ram never executed any Will during his
			<lb />
			life time. Atma Ram expired on 23.5.2008 and after 15 days of
			<lb />
			his death to her surprise defendant No.1 proclaimed that Atma
			<lb />
			Ram had executed a Will during his life time. Thereafter, she
			<lb />
			enquired about the matter from the local Patwari and came to
			<lb />
			know that a mutation had been got entered by the defendants
			<lb />
			on the basis of Will dated 16.5.2008 Ext. DW5/B. In cross
			<lb />
			examination, she has stated that her husband had three
			<lb />
			brothers. She has further admitted that last rites of Atma Ram
			<lb />
			were performed by defendant No.2 Rajesh Kumar. Defendant
			<lb />
			No.1 was brought up, educated and married off by Atma Ram.
			<lb />
			She has denied that Atma Ram had gifted part of suit land to
			<lb />
			defendant No.1 Prem Lata during his life time. She has also
			<lb />
			denied that Prem Lata used to look after Atma Ram and also
			<lb />
			helped in his medical treatment. She has denied that defendant
			<lb />
			No.1 Prem Lata had offered her a sum of Rs.2,00,000/ which
			<lb />
			she had refused. Atma Ram used to sign and did not affix
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -11/07/2022 23:02:53 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			17
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			thumb impression. Atma Ram had performed Kanya Dan of
			<lb />
			Prem Lata. She has denied that she is out of possession of the
			<lb />
			suit land.
			<lb />
			18.
			<lb />
			PW2 Cheering Ram was an Officer from
			<lb />
			Himachal Gramin Bank Banzar branch, who presented
			<lb />
			withdrawal receipts Ext.PW2/A to Ext.PW2/D of Atma Ram.
			<lb />
			He has stated that Atma Ram used to sign the documents. Last
			<lb />
			withdrawal by Shri Atma Ram had been done on 16.5.2008. In
			<lb />
			his crossexamination, he has admitted that Atma Ram was ill
			<lb />
			and his hands used to tremble.
			<lb />
			19.
			<lb />
			PW3 Sher Singh was the dealing Clerk of the
			<lb />
			Bank, who brought withdrawal voucher Ext.PW3/A and stated
			<lb />
			that Atma Ram used to sign. In crossexamination, he has
			<lb />
			admitted that he did not know Atma Ram personally. RPW1
			<lb />
			Sangat Ram was the witness, who was examined by the
			<lb />
			plaintiff in rebuttal. He has reiterated the version of plaintiff in
			<lb />
			examinationinchief. In crossexamination, he expressed his
			<lb />
			ignorance as to how much land was in whose possession. Now,
			<lb />
			coming to the Ext.DW5/B, i.e. Will, perusal of it shows that
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -11/07/2022 23:02:53 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			18
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			DW5 Lekh Raj, Advocate is scribe of the Will in question. He
			<lb />
			has stated that the Will was drafted as per the directions of
			<lb />
			Atma Ram in presence of marginal witnesses namely, K.G.
			<lb />
			Thakur and Om Prakash Advocates. Thereafter, Will was read
			<lb />
			over and explained to Atma Ram, who admitted the contents to
			<lb />
			be correct and affixed his right thumb impression over the
			<lb />
			same. He has further stated that Atma Ram did not sign the
			<lb />
			Will, as due to his old age, his hands were trembling and his
			<lb />
			eye sight was weak. Thereafter, the Will was got registered
			<lb />
			before the Registrar. In crossexamination, he has stated that
			<lb />
			he does not remember as to how many documents he has
			<lb />
			scribed. The Will was got typed on Computer. Om Prakash had
			<lb />
			come to him along with K.G. Thakur, Advocate, Rukmani
			<lb />
			(plaintiff) and Tulsi Devi. He does not remember as to who had
			<lb />
			brought the papers. He had made a rough draft of Will. Atma
			<lb />
			Ram had affixed his thumb impression on the Will as his hands
			<lb />
			were trembling and his eye sight was weak. He does not
			<lb />
			remember as to who had called Om Prakash Sharma,
			<lb />
			Advocate. He has denied that Atma Ram was not in sound
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -11/07/2022 23:02:53 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			19
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			disposing mind at the time of execution of Will Ext.DW5/B. He
			<lb />
			has denied that Will is a forged document.
			<lb />
			20.
			<lb />
			The judgments as cited by the learned counsel for
			<lb />
			the appellant are considered. In Charan Dass (deceased
			<lb />
			through his LRs) versus Dole Ram, in RSA No.48 of 2001,
			<lb />
			decided on 06.11.2012. wherein it has been held as under:
			<lb />
			&quot;10.
			<lb />
			In the light of the above provisions
			<lb />
			and the above decision, the evidence has to be
			<lb />
			appreciated as to whether it complies with the
			<lb />
			above provisions of law or not. In the present
			<lb />
			case, the will in question has been proved in
			<lb />
			evidence as Ex.PW2/A. It was executed by Smt.
			<lb />
			Bresti, who thumb marked the Will dated
			<lb />
			15.3.1989. The names of the scribe mentioned is
			<lb />
			as Sh. Anup Ram, Document Writer and the
			<lb />
			name of the attesting witness mentioned is as
			<lb />
			Mohar Singh, s/o Kanshi Ram and there are
			<lb />
			signatures of one Khyal Chand, Pradhan, Gram
			<lb />
			Panchayat also over the Will. Out of these
			<lb />
			persons, the plaintiffs examined the scribe as
			<lb />
			PW4, Anup Ram. A perusal of the statement
			<lb />
			shows that he simply stated that at the instance
			<lb />
			of Smt. Bresti, he wrote the Will Ex.PW2/A. He
			<lb />
			stated that in red circle &quot;B&quot;, there are his
			<lb />
			signatures. He further stated that the Will was
			<lb />
			read over to Bresti, who affixed her thumb
			<lb />
			mark on being satisfied and thereafter, the
			<lb />
			witness Khyal Chand and Mohar Singh signed
			<lb />
			the same.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -11/07/2022 23:02:53 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			20
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			11.
			<lb />
			It is clear from the perusal of the
			<lb />
			statement that this witness never stated that
			<lb />
			the Will was read over to Smt. Bresti in
			<lb />
			presence of the witnesses and she signed it in
			<lb />
			presence of the witnesses or both the witnesses
			<lb />
			signed in her presence. His statement only
			<lb />
			proves that it was thumb marked by Bresti and
			<lb />
			then it was signed by both the witnesses and
			<lb />
			nothing else was stated as is required by law as
			<lb />
			mention above. He admitted that he is not an
			<lb />
			attesting witness of the Will. Out of the two
			<lb />
			attesting witnesses, Khayala Ram was stated to
			<lb />
			be dead and the plaintiffs examined PW2
			<lb />
			Mohar Singh. A perusal of the statement of
			<lb />
			Mohar Singh shows that the Will was executed
			<lb />
			in favour of the plaintiffs mark A/ Ex.PW2/A. He
			<lb />
			further stated that within a circle, there are his
			<lb />
			signatures and the Will was read over and the
			<lb />
			second witness Khayala Ram is dead. He
			<lb />
			further stated that it was written by the Deed
			<lb />
			Writer.
			<lb />
			12.
			<lb />
			From a perusal of the statement, it is
			<lb />
			also clear that he did not state that the will was
			<lb />
			thumb marked by Smt. Bresti, in presence of both
			<lb />
			the witnesses or that both the witnesses signed in
			<lb />
			her presence. Therefore, the statement of both
			<lb />
			these witnesses, the attesting witness and scribe
			<lb />
			do not prove that the requirements of Section 63
			<lb />
			of Indian Succession Act and Section 68 of
			<lb />
			Evidence Act were complied with.&quot;
			<lb />
			21.
			<lb />
			In the instant case, the attesting witnesses have
			<lb />
			deposed that the Will was signed by the Testator in their
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -11/07/2022 23:02:53 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			21
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			presence. Thereafter, it was attested in the office of the Sub
			<lb />
			Registrar where the witnesses were present and it was attested
			<lb />
			in the presence of the witnesses. So, this judgment is not
			<lb />
			applicable to the facts of the present case.
			<lb />
			22.
			<lb />
			In Sohan Lal and Another versus Thakur Dass
			<lb />
			and others 2019 SCC HP 975, it has been held :
			<lb />
			&quot;14. The controversy in the case in hand mainly
			<lb />
			relates to Section 63(c) of the Indian Succession
			<lb />
			Act, 1925 (hereinafter referred to as &quot;the Act&quot;).
			<lb />
			At the very outset the same is extracted
			<lb />
			hereunder:
			<lb />
			&quot;Section 63 in The Indian Succession Act,
			<lb />
			63. Execution of unprivileged Wills.
			<lb />
			Every testator, not being a soldier employed in
			<lb />
			an expedition or engaged in actual warfare, 12
			<lb />
			[or an airman so employed or engaged,] or a
			<lb />
			mariner at sea, shall execute his Will according to
			<lb />
			the following rules:
			<lb />
			(a) The testator shall sign or shall affix his mark
			<lb />
			to the Will, or it shall be signed by some other
			<lb />
			person in his presence and by his direction.
			<lb />
			(b) The signature or mark of the testator, or the
			<lb />
			signature of the person signing for him, shall be
			<lb />
			so placed that it shall appear that it was
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -11/07/2022 23:02:53 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			22
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			intended thereby to give effect to the writing as a
			<lb />
			Will.
			<lb />
			(c) The Will shall be attested by two or more
			<lb />
			witnesses, each of whom has seen the testator
			<lb />
			sign or affix his mark to the Will or has seen
			<lb />
			some other person sign the Will, in the presence
			<lb />
			and by the direction of the testator, or has
			<lb />
			received
			<lb />
			from
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			testator
			<lb />
			a
			<lb />
			personal
			<lb />
			acknowledgement of his signature or mark, or
			<lb />
			the signature of such other person; and each of
			<lb />
			the witnesses shall sign the Will in the presence
			<lb />
			of the testator, but it shall not be necessary that
			<lb />
			more than one witness be present at the same
			<lb />
			time, and no particular form of attestation shall
			<lb />
			be necessary.&quot;
			<lb />
			15. Thus, as highlighted above, as per the
			<lb />
			mandate of Section 63(c) of the Act, a Will is to be
			<lb />
			attested by two or more witnesses, each of them
			<lb />
			must have seen the testator of the Will putting
			<lb />
			his/her signatures or affix mark on the Will and
			<lb />
			the witnesses must put their signatures on the
			<lb />
			Will in the presence of the testator. Thus, Section
			<lb />
			63 of the Act lays down conditions qua proof of
			<lb />
			execution of valid Will. A Will has to be proved in
			<lb />
			the manner provided in Section 63 of the
			<lb />
			Act. Section 63(c) clearly provides that a Will has
			<lb />
			to be attested by two or more witnesses, but it is
			<lb />
			not mandatory that both these witnesses should
			<lb />
			be present simultaneously and they put their
			<lb />
			signatures in each others&apos; presence. The
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -11/07/2022 23:02:53 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			23
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			mandatory requirement is that these witnesses
			<lb />
			must have seen the testator signing the Will or
			<lb />
			affixing his mark thereon or they have received
			<lb />
			personal acknowledgement from the testator of
			<lb />
			his signature or mark on the Will. Besides this,
			<lb />
			other mandatory prerequisite is that the
			<lb />
			attesting witnesses of the Will must sign the Will
			<lb />
			in presence of the testator.
			<lb />
			16. Thus, in view of mandatory requirements
			<lb />
			laid down by Section 63 of the Act the
			<lb />
			propounder of the Will must prove that the
			<lb />
			attesting witnesses saw him signing the Will or
			<lb />
			affixing his mark thereon and they also signed
			<lb />
			in his presence.
			<lb />
			23.
			<lb />
			This judgment, if applied, to the facts of the present
			<lb />
			case, as the witnesses have deposed that it was thumb mark by
			<lb />
			the Testator, the inference is that had they seen the Testator
			<lb />
			while affixing his thumb impression.
			<lb />
			24.
			<lb />
			In Punni versus Sumer Chand and others,
			<lb />
			AIR 1995 HP, 74, it has been held:
			<lb />
			&quot;11.
			<lb />
			As regards attestation, Clause (c)
			<lb />
			aforementioned requires that the Will shall be
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -11/07/2022 23:02:53 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			24
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			attested by two or more witnesses. It is not
			<lb />
			necessary that both of them be present
			<lb />
			simultaneously at the time of putting their
			<lb />
			signatures but the requirement is that each of
			<lb />
			the attesting witness must have seen the testator
			<lb />
			sign or affix his mark to the Will or has received
			<lb />
			from the testator a personal acknowledgment of
			<lb />
			his signature or mark on the Will. There is also
			<lb />
			an additional requirement that each of the
			<lb />
			attesting witness shall also sign the Will in the
			<lb />
			presence of the testator…...&quot;
			<lb />
			25.
			<lb />
			The learned Counsel has placed reliance upon a
			<lb />
			decision of this Hon&apos;ble High Court rendered in Bal Krishan
			<lb />
			&amp; Anr. versus Shangri Devi &amp; Ors. 2008 (1) Cur.L.J.(HP)
			<lb />
			584, it has been held :
			<lb />
			&quot;13.
			<lb />
			The learned counsel appearing on
			<lb />
			behalf of the plaintiff before the trial Court had
			<lb />
			submitted that there were as many as 5
			<lb />
			suspicious
			<lb />
			circumstances
			<lb />
			to
			<lb />
			doubt
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			genuineness of the will: (i) the active
			<lb />
			participation by the legatee, (ii) the denial of
			<lb />
			benefit to the plaintiff who was otherwise
			<lb />
			entitled to succeed to him, (iii) the witness Amar
			<lb />
			Singh being related (brother in law of the
			<lb />
			legatee), (iv) inherently improbable disposition
			<lb />
			made in the will, and (v) nonproduction of the
			<lb />
			Will at the earliest time.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -11/07/2022 23:02:53 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			25
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			17.
			<lb />
			The other suspicious circumstance is
			<lb />
			the manner in which the Will in question was
			<lb />
			written and executed. It has come in the
			<lb />
			evidence that the Will was written by one Shri
			<lb />
			Sanjeev. Shri Sanjeev has not been examined as
			<lb />
			a witness on the ground that he had died. The
			<lb />
			appellant, Bal Krishan has not produced on
			<lb />
			record even the death certificate of Sanjeev to
			<lb />
			prove his death. The presence of Shri Krishan
			<lb />
			Dutt Sharma at the time of the execution of the
			<lb />
			Will is also doubtful in view of the
			<lb />
			contradictions in the statements made by Bal
			<lb />
			Krishan (DW1) and Shri Amar Singh (DW2).
			<lb />
			Moreover, Amar Singh (DW2) is closely related
			<lb />
			to Bal Krishan and his statement with regard to
			<lb />
			the execution of the Will cannot be believed
			<lb />
			being interested witness. There are material
			<lb />
			contradictions in the manner in which the
			<lb />
			parties have left for Rajgarh for the execution of
			<lb />
			the Will from their respective villages. There is
			<lb />
			no explanation why Matha would go to the
			<lb />
			house of Amar Singh to witness the execution of
			<lb />
			the Will. According to Bal Krishan (DW1),
			<lb />
			Matha had gone to visit Amar Singh for taking
			<lb />
			him on 11.2.1985 and on that day they all had
			<lb />
			reached and stayed at village Shargaon in the
			<lb />
			evening of 11.2.1985. Next day they left for
			<lb />
			Rajgarh at about 8.00 a.m. from Shargaon.
			<lb />
			However, Amar Singh (DW2) had stated that
			<lb />
			Matha had come to him 2 or 3 days before for
			<lb />
			informing his intention to execute a Will. Amar
			<lb />
			Singh had not stated that he had come with
			<lb />
			Matha and Bal Krishan to village Shargaon in
			<lb />
			the evening of 11.2.1985 and all of them had
			<lb />
			gone on 12.2.1985 to Rajgarh. He had stated that
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -11/07/2022 23:02:53 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			26
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			he had met Matha Ram and Bal Krishan in the
			<lb />
			Tehsil office at Rajgarh on 12.2.1985. It also
			<lb />
			casts doubt about the very presence of Shri
			<lb />
			Amar Singh at the time of execution of the will.
			<lb />
			Shri Krishan Dutt Sharma has not been
			<lb />
			examined as a witness. He was the material
			<lb />
			witness to explain the manner in which the will
			<lb />
			was executed. It also appears from the bare
			<lb />
			perusal of Ex.DW2/A that the document has not
			<lb />
			been registered by completing all the codal
			<lb />
			formalities. The manner in which the signatures
			<lb />
			of the witnesses and testator have been
			<lb />
			obtained have been dealt with extensively by
			<lb />
			the trial Court and those findings are affirmed.
			<lb />
			20.
			<lb />
			Their Lordships of the Hon&apos;ble Supreme
			<lb />
			Court have held in Ram Purnima Deb and
			<lb />
			another v. Kumar Khagendra Narayan Deb and
			<lb />
			another, AIR 1962, SC 567 that there is no doubt
			<lb />
			if a Will has been registered, that is a
			<lb />
			circumstance which may, having regard to the
			<lb />
			circumstances, proved its genuineness. But the
			<lb />
			mere fact that a Will is registered Will not by
			<lb />
			itself be sufficient to dispel all suspicions. Their
			<lb />
			Lordships have held as under: &quot;There is no
			<lb />
			doubt that if a Will has been registered, that is a
			<lb />
			circumstance which may, having regard to the
			<lb />
			circumstances, prove its genuineness. But the
			<lb />
			mere fact that a will is registered Will not by
			<lb />
			itself be sufficient to dispel all suspicion
			<lb />
			regarding it where suspicion exists, without
			<lb />
			submitting the evidence of registration to a close
			<lb />
			examination. If the evidence as to registration
			<lb />
			on a close examination reveals that the
			<lb />
			registration was made in such a manner that it
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -11/07/2022 23:02:53 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			27
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			was brought home to the testator that the
			<lb />
			document of which he was admitting execution
			<lb />
			was a will disposing of his property and
			<lb />
			thereafter he admitted its execution and signed
			<lb />
			it in token thereof, the registration Will dispel
			<lb />
			the doubt as to the genuineness of the Will. But
			<lb />
			if the evidence as to registration shows that it
			<lb />
			was done in a perfunctory manner, that the
			<lb />
			officer registering the Will did not read it over to
			<lb />
			the testator or did not bring to him that he was
			<lb />
			admitting the execution of a will or did not
			<lb />
			satisfy himself in some other way (as, for
			<lb />
			example, by seeing the testator reading the will)
			<lb />
			that the testator knew that it was a will the
			<lb />
			execution of which he was admitting, the fact
			<lb />
			that the will was registered would not be of
			<lb />
			much value. It is not unknown that registration
			<lb />
			may take place without the executant really
			<lb />
			knowing what he was registering. Law reports
			<lb />
			are full of cases in which registered wills have
			<lb />
			not been acted upon : (see, for example,
			<lb />
			Vellaswamy Servai v. Siraraman Servai, ILR 8
			<lb />
			Rang 179 : (AIR 1930 PC 24), Surendra Nath v.
			<lb />
			Jnanendra Nath, AIR 1932 Cal 574 and Girja
			<lb />
			Datt Singh v. Gangotri Datt Singh, (S) AIR 1055
			<lb />
			SC 346. Therefore, the mere fact of registration
			<lb />
			may not by itself be enough to dispel all
			<lb />
			suspicion that may attach to the execution and
			<lb />
			attestation of a will; though the fact that there
			<lb />
			has been registration would be an important
			<lb />
			circumstance in favour of the will being genuine
			<lb />
			if the evidence as to registration establishes that
			<lb />
			the testator admitted the execution of the will
			<lb />
			after knowing that it was a will the execution of
			<lb />
			which he was admitting. The question therefore
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -11/07/2022 23:02:53 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			28
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			is whether in the circumstances of the present
			<lb />
			case the evidence as to registration discloses
			<lb />
			that the testator knew that he was admitting the
			<lb />
			execution of a will when he is said to have put
			<lb />
			down his signature at the bottom of the will in
			<lb />
			the presence of Arabali. We have scrutinized
			<lb />
			that evidence carefully and we must say that the
			<lb />
			evidence falls short of satisfying us in the
			<lb />
			circumstances of this case that the testator knew
			<lb />
			that the document the execution of which he
			<lb />
			was admitting before Arabali and at the bottom
			<lb />
			of which he signed was his will. Therefore we
			<lb />
			are left with the bald fact of registration which
			<lb />
			in our
			<lb />
			opinion is
			<lb />
			insufficient
			<lb />
			in the
			<lb />
			circumstances of this case to dispel the
			<lb />
			suspicious circumstances which we have
			<lb />
			enumerated above. We are therefore not
			<lb />
			satisfied about the due execution and attestation
			<lb />
			of this Will by the testator and hold that the
			<lb />
			propounder has been unable to dispel the
			<lb />
			suspicious circumstances which surround the
			<lb />
			execution and attestation of this Will. In the
			<lb />
			circumstances, no letters of administration in
			<lb />
			favour of the respondent can be granted on the
			<lb />
			basis of it.&quot;
			<lb />
			26.
			<lb />
			The facts of the present case are different as the
			<lb />
			Attesting witnesses have stated that the Thumb impression was
			<lb />
			put in their presence and they were present before the Registering
			<lb />
			Authority when it was registered, which is clear from the
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -11/07/2022 23:02:53 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			29
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			photographs, on the Will, so the above judgment is not applicable to
			<lb />
			the facts of the present case.
			<lb />
			27.
			<lb />
			Hon&apos;ble Punjab &amp; Haryana High Court in Bishan
			<lb />
			Singh (deceased) by his Lrs versus Saran Singh &amp; Ors.,
			<lb />
			2007(1) Civil Court Cases 209(P&amp;H), held :
			<lb />
			&quot;8.
			<lb />
			The common practice in the rural
			<lb />
			arreas amongst the illiterates is that except on
			<lb />
			account of some physical disability, it is
			<lb />
			generally the left thumb mark which is put on
			<lb />
			important documents like a will or other
			<lb />
			documents creating a right or title in some
			<lb />
			property by the males and right thumb
			<lb />
			impression is put by the ladies. In fact even in
			<lb />
			respect of Panchayat proceedings and other
			<lb />
			day to day working amongst (the rural
			<lb />
			persons as a matter of practice and habit, the
			<lb />
			left thumb impression is put on documents by
			<lb />
			male members and right thumb impression by
			<lb />
			ladies where because of the illiteracy they are
			<lb />
			unable to sign. This being the practice it is
			<lb />
			easy in case of any doubt or ambiguity to
			<lb />
			compare the thumb impression with the
			<lb />
			standard thumb impressions of the person
			<lb />
			concerned. Deviating from his practice would
			<lb />
			result in great hardship and any one wanting
			<lb />
			to set up a document like a Will of someone
			<lb />
			could easily be able to do so by putting a right
			<lb />
			thumb impression in the case of a male and
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -11/07/2022 23:02:53 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			30
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			left thumb impression in the case of already
			<lb />
			so as to, in case of doubt or suspicion, avoid
			<lb />
			the comparison of their thumb impressions
			<lb />
			with their standard and admitted thumb
			<lb />
			impression which are otherwise generally
			<lb />
			available. In Smt. Harbans Kaur and Anoop
			<lb />
			Singh 1991 Shimla Law Journal 217, this
			<lb />
			Court considered the question as to which
			<lb />
			thumb impression is normally to be affixed by
			<lb />
			a male executant on a sale deed. It was held
			<lb />
			that petition writers always get the left thumb
			<lb />
			impression of a male on a sale deed and in
			<lb />
			case it is not possible to do so, only then the
			<lb />
			right thumb impression of a male executant is
			<lb />
			got affixed. The same would apply to
			<lb />
			documents like Wills executed by males.
			<lb />
			Therefore, this practice of accepting the right
			<lb />
			thumb impressions of male executants on
			<lb />
			documents like a Will is liable to be
			<lb />
			discouraged and it is only when it can
			<lb />
			otherwise be shown as to why the standard
			<lb />
			form of putting the left thumb impression in
			<lb />
			the case of a male and a right thumb
			<lb />
			impression in the case of a female is being
			<lb />
			deviated from, the court would consider the
			<lb />
			question in the facts and circumstances of
			<lb />
			each case. Physical disability to put the left
			<lb />
			thumb impression in the case of a male and
			<lb />
			right thumb impression in the case of a lady
			<lb />
			can be a valid ground for deviating from the
			<lb />
			practice.
			<lb />
			9.
			<lb />
			In the case in hand, no reason has been
			<lb />
			given for deviating from his practice. Therefore,
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -11/07/2022 23:02:53 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			31
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			it is somewhat unusual for Fakir Singh to have
			<lb />
			put has right thumb impression on a document
			<lb />
			which is an important document being his Will
			<lb />
			when in the normal circumstances on the sale
			<lb />
			deed dated 1.5.1981 Ex. D.1 he had put his left
			<lb />
			thumb impression which is as per the prevalent
			<lb />
			practice. The intention of putting the right
			<lb />
			thumb impression on the Will can only be to
			<lb />
			avoid the comparison of the same with the
			<lb />
			standard thumb impression of the executant so
			<lb />
			as to take the stand that the executant
			<lb />
			inadvertently and unknowingly put the right
			<lb />
			thumb impression which is now not comparable.
			<lb />
			The propounder of the will has failed to dispel
			<lb />
			this suspicious circumstance which he was
			<lb />
			under an obligation to remove by leading cogent
			<lb />
			and convincing evidence. The reason recorded
			<lb />
			by the learned trial Court is that the
			<lb />
			handwriting expert has opined that the
			<lb />
			disputed document bears the right thumb
			<lb />
			impression of deceased Fakir Singh. It is further
			<lb />
			recorded by the learned trial Court that : &quot;But I
			<lb />
			could not understand as to how this expert has
			<lb />
			come to this conclusion. It is not specifically
			<lb />
			mentioned that RTI (Right Thumb Impression)
			<lb />
			of deceased Fakir Singh were taken in the Court
			<lb />
			and then it was compared with specimen thumb
			<lb />
			impression of L.T.I. (Left thumb Impression) of
			<lb />
			deceased.&quot; Accordingly the contention of the
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -11/07/2022 23:02:53 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			32
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			learned Counsel for the defendant was held to
			<lb />
			be not maintainable. In fact the thumb
			<lb />
			impressions of a deceased person could not
			<lb />
			possibly have been taken in court. Therefore,
			<lb />
			the reasoning recorded by the learned Trial
			<lb />
			Court in rejecting the argument of the learned
			<lb />
			Counsel for the defendant is not tenable.
			<lb />
			Therefore, in my view the reasons and findings
			<lb />
			recorded by the Courts below as regards the
			<lb />
			validity of the Will dated. 3.6.1985 (Ex. P.1) are
			<lb />
			without any merit. The right thumb impressions
			<lb />
			were put so as to avoid the possibility of the
			<lb />
			same being got compared with the standard left
			<lb />
			thumb impression of Fakir Singh the testator of
			<lb />
			the Will (Ex. P.1). As such it is evident that in
			<lb />
			the case in hand the right thumb impression of
			<lb />
			the testator has been put so that the thumb
			<lb />
			impressions cannot be got compared. This
			<lb />
			circumstance in the facts and circumstance of
			<lb />
			the case makes the Will (EX. P.1) set up by the
			<lb />
			plaintiffs to be doubtful inasmuch as the thumb
			<lb />
			impression could not be got compared.&quot;
			<lb />
			28.
			<lb />
			This judgment is also not applicable to the facts of the
			<lb />
			present case, as it was Thumb marked when it was being
			<lb />
			registered and the Thumb mark of the testator was noted put
			<lb />
			that time also. So, this does not create any doubt in the mind
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -11/07/2022 23:02:53 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			33
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			of the Court that the Will was not executed out of the free mind
			<lb />
			by the testator as the testator was having only one daughter
			<lb />
			who is the respondent.
			<lb />
			29.
			<lb />
			The judgments as relied upon by the learned
			<lb />
			counsel for the respondent are considered and this Court finds
			<lb />
			that these are applicable to the facts of the present case as the
			<lb />
			left hand thumb impression was put on the Will when the
			<lb />
			testator appeared before the registering Authority for
			<lb />
			attestation of the Will.
			<lb />
			30.
			<lb />
			In these circumstances, the Will cannot be said to
			<lb />
			be suspicious. In in Bhagat Ram (D) by L.Rs. versus Teja
			<lb />
			Singh (D) L.Rs. AIR 2002 Supreme Court 1, in para 8
			<lb />
			whereof it has been held as under:
			<lb />
			8.
			<lb />
			We do not find any merit in the contention
			<lb />
			raised by the Counsel for the respondents. Admittedly,
			<lb />
			Smt. Santi inherited the property in question from her
			<lb />
			mother. If the property held by a female was inherited
			<lb />
			from her father or mother, in the absence of any son or
			<lb />
			daughter of the deceased, including the children of any
			<lb />
			pre-deceased son or daughter, it would only devolve upon
			<lb />
			the heirs of the father and, in this case, her sister Smt.
			<lb />
			Indro was the only legal heir of her father. Deceased Smt.
			<lb />
			Santi admittedly inherited the property in question from
			<lb />
			her mother. It is not necessary that such inheritance
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -11/07/2022 23:02:53 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			34
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			should have been after the commencement of the Act. The
			<lb />
			intent of the Legislature is clear that the property, if
			<lb />
			originally belonged to the parents of the deceased female,
			<lb />
			should go to the legal heirs of the father. So also under
			<lb />
			clause (b) of sub-Section (2) of Section 15, the property
			<lb />
			inherited by a female Hindu from her husband or her
			<lb />
			father-in-law, shall also under similar circumstances,
			<lb />
			devolve upon the heirs of the husband. It is the source
			<lb />
			from which the property was inherited by the female,
			<lb />
			which is more important for the purpose of devolution of
			<lb />
			her property. We do not think that the fact that a female
			<lb />
			Hindu originally had a limited right and later, acquired
			<lb />
			the full right, in any way, would alter the rules of
			<lb />
			succession given in sub-section 2 of Section 15.&quot;
			<lb />
			31.
			<lb />
			Thous this judgment is of some help to the respondent but is
			<lb />
			not material for adjudicating the present lis.
			<lb />
			32.
			<lb />
			PW6 K.G. Thakur, Advocate is the marginal
			<lb />
			witness to Will in question, he has stated that Atma Ram was
			<lb />
			related to him. He is practicing as an Advocate since the year
			<lb />
			1978 and Atma Ram used to come to him for legal advice. Tulsi
			<lb />
			Devi is second wife of Atma Ram and defendant No.1 Prem
			<lb />
			Lata is his daughter. Atma Ram married Tulsi Devi, as he had
			<lb />
			no children with Rukmani (plaintiff). Atma Ram brought up
			<lb />
			defendant No.1 Prem Lata and paid for her studies etc. and
			<lb />
			thereafter, married her off to Chhavinder Singh. He has stated
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -11/07/2022 23:02:53 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			35
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			that on 16.5.2008, Atma Ram had executed a valid Will
			<lb />
			Ext.DW5/A, in which, he is a marginal witness. The Will was
			<lb />
			scribed by Lekh Raj, Advocate, on the direction of Atma Ram
			<lb />
			and Atma Ram had affixed his thumb impression in presence of
			<lb />
			himself (K.G. Thakur) and other marginal witness Om
			<lb />
			Prakash, Advocate. Further stated that Atma Ram had affixed
			<lb />
			his thumb impression, as because of old age, his hands used to
			<lb />
			tremble and his eye sight was also weak. Atma Ram was in
			<lb />
			sound disposing mind and was in a position to understand his
			<lb />
			good and bad. Thereafter, Atma Ram and himself and other
			<lb />
			marginal witness had appeared before Registrar in the
			<lb />
			Registrar&apos;s office and the Will was again read over and
			<lb />
			explained to Atma Ram, who admitted it to be correct and
			<lb />
			affixed his thumb impression over the same. As per the last
			<lb />
			wish of Atma Ram, his last rights were performed by defendant
			<lb />
			No.2 Ramesh Kumar, who has also been awarded a share in
			<lb />
			the suit land in Will Ext. DW5/B. Earlier also, Atma Ram had
			<lb />
			gifted a part of suit land to defendant No.1, Prem Lata. In
			<lb />
			crossexamination, he has stated that he does not remember as
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -11/07/2022 23:02:53 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			36
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			to what day of the week, it was on 16.5.2008. He had come to
			<lb />
			Manali on that date alongwith Atma Ram, Tulsi Devi and
			<lb />
			Rukmani in his own car. Atma Ram had told him that
			<lb />
			wanted to write a Will and requested him to come to Manali.
			<lb />
			He was not aware as to whether Atma Ram had gone to the
			<lb />
			Bank on that date the will was scribed by Lekh Raj Advocate.
			<lb />
			Lekh Raj, Advocate had initially prepared rough draft of the
			<lb />
			Will and thereafter, the same was got typed on a Computer.
			<lb />
			Thereafter, Lekh Raj, Advocate had read over and explained
			<lb />
			the contents of the Will to Atma Ram in presence of marginal
			<lb />
			witnesses and Atma Ram accepted the same to be correct and
			<lb />
			affixed his thumb impression, because his eye sight was weak.
			<lb />
			He has expressed his ignorance as to whether Atma Ram had
			<lb />
			withdrawn money from the bank on 16.5.2008 and had signed
			<lb />
			the withdrawal voucher. The Will in question was scribed
			<lb />
			between 12.00 noon and 1.00 p.m He has denied that Atma
			<lb />
			Ram did not make Will and it is a forged document.
			<lb />
			33.
			<lb />
			DW2 Chhaivinder Thakur, Advocate is the scribe
			<lb />
			of gift deed Ext.DW2/B, who stated that he had scribed gift
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -11/07/2022 23:02:53 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			37
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			deed as per the directions of Atma Ram and had read over and
			<lb />
			explained it to Atma Ram and Prem Lata and thereafter, the
			<lb />
			document was got registered. In he has
			<lb />
			denied that gift deed is false document. DW3 Atma Ram and
			<lb />
			DW4 Devi Singh are the marginal witnesses to gift deed
			<lb />
			Ext.DW2/B.
			<lb />
			34.
			<lb />
			The fact that earlier Atma Ram had gifted a part
			<lb />
			of suit land to defendant No.1 Prem Lata by way of gift deed
			<lb />
			Ext.DW2/A and mutation number 57 Ext.DW1/E and 58 Ext.
			<lb />
			DW1/F had been attested in this regard is not in dispute. It is
			<lb />
			also not in dispute that the plaintiff has not challenged
			<lb />
			mutation number 57 and 58 respectively.
			<lb />
			35.
			<lb />
			After analyzing the above evidence, it is clear that
			<lb />
			as per the marginal witness PW6, Atma Ram was related to
			<lb />
			him. The Will was scribed by Lekh Raj, Advocate, on the
			<lb />
			direction of Atma Ram and Atma Ram had affixed his thumb
			<lb />
			impression in presence of himself (K.G. Thakur) and other
			<lb />
			marginal witness Om Prakash, Advocate. Further stated that
			<lb />
			Atma Ram had affixed his thumb impression, as because of old
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -11/07/2022 23:02:53 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			38
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			age, his hands used to tremble and his eye sight was also weak.
			<lb />
			Atma Ram was in sound disposing mind and was in a position
			<lb />
			to understand his good and bad. Thereafter, Atma Ram and
			<lb />
			himself and other marginal witness had appeared before
			<lb />
			Registrar in the Registrar&apos;s office and the Will was again read
			<lb />
			over and explained to Atma Ram, who admitted it to be correct
			<lb />
			and affixed his thumb impression over the same. As per the
			<lb />
			last wish of Atma Ram, his last rights were performed by
			<lb />
			defendant No.2 Ramesh Kumar, who has also been awarded a
			<lb />
			share in the suit land in Will Ext. DW5/B. Earlier also, Atma
			<lb />
			Ram had gifted a part of suit land to defendant No.1, Prem
			<lb />
			Lata. In crossexamination, he has stated that he does not
			<lb />
			remember as to what day of the week, it was on 16.5.2008. He
			<lb />
			had come to Manali on that date alongwith Atma Ram, Tulsi
			<lb />
			Devi and Rukmani in his own car. Atma Ram had told him that
			<lb />
			he wanted to recite a Will and requested him to come to
			<lb />
			Manali. He was not aware as to whether Atma Ram had gone
			<lb />
			to the Bank on that date the will was scribed by Lekh Raj
			<lb />
			Advocate. Lekh Raj, Advocate had initially prepared rough
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -11/07/2022 23:02:53 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			39
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			draft of the Will and thereafter, the same was got typed on a
			<lb />
			Computer. Thereafter, Lekh Raj, Advocate had read over and
			<lb />
			explained the contents of the Will to Atma Ram in presence of
			<lb />
			marginal witnesses and Atma Ram accepted the same to be
			<lb />
			correct and affixed his thumb impression, because his eye sight
			<lb />
			was weak. He has expressed his ignorance as to whether Atma
			<lb />
			Ram had withdrawn money from the bank on 16.5.2008 and
			<lb />
			had signed the withdrawal voucher. The Will in question was
			<lb />
			scribed between 12.00 noon and 1.00 p.m He has denied that
			<lb />
			Atma Ram did not make Will and it is a forged document.
			<lb />
			36.
			<lb />
			From the above, it is clear that the judgment
			<lb />
			passed by the learned Courts below are after appreciating the
			<lb />
			facts and law which has come on record correctly and the Will
			<lb />
			dated 16.5.2008, is executed in accordance with the Section 63
			<lb />
			of the Indian Evidence Act and the Substantial Question of law
			<lb />
			is answered accordingly.
			<lb />
			37.
			<lb />
			The Substantial Question of Law No.2 is answered
			<lb />
			holding that the Court below has appreciated the pleadings and
			<lb />
			interpreted the law orally and the documentary evidence
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -11/07/2022 23:02:53 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			40
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			correctly and so this question is answered accordingly.
			<lb />
			38.
			<lb />
			The net result of the above discussion is that
			<lb />
			the appeal, which sans merits, deserves dismissal and is
			<lb />
			accordingly dismissed. However, taking into consideration
			<lb />
			the facts and circumstances of the case, the parties are left
			<lb />
			to bear their own costs.
			<lb />
			39.
			<lb />
			In view of the disposal of the appeal, pending
			<lb />
			application(s) if any, shall also stands disposed of.
			<lb />
			(Chander Bhusan Barowalia)
			<lb />
			Judge
			<lb />
			January 01,2020
			<lb />
			(M. gandhi)
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -11/07/2022 23:02:53 :::CIS
		</note>
	</text>
</tei>
