<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			IN THE HIGH COURT OF HIMACHAL PRADESH AT  SHIMLA
			<lb />
			ON THE 01 DAY OF OCTOBER, 2021
			<lb />
			BEFORE
			<lb />
			HON’BLE MR. JUSTICE CHANDER BHUSAN BAROWALIA,
			<lb />
			JUDGE
			<lb />
			CRIMINAL APPEAL NO.172 of 2021
			<lb />
			Between:­
			<lb />
			ARJUN PATHANIA
			<lb />
			S/O SH. SUBHASH SINGH, AGED ABOUT 22 YEARS,
			<lb />
			R/O VILLAGE SAMRET,
			<lb />
			P.O. BARANDA,
			<lb />
			TEHSIL NURPUR, DISTRICT KANGRA,
			<lb />
			H.P. (ACCUSED)          ...…APPELLANT
			<lb />
			(BY SH. SANJAY  KUMAR SHARMA, ADVOCATE
			<lb />
			WITH MR. RAKESH CHAUHAN, ADVOCATE)
			<lb />
			AND
			<lb />
			STATE OF HIMACHAL PRADESH
			<lb />
			…...RESPONDENT
			<lb />
			(BY SH. ARVIND SHARMA, SH. P.K. BHATTI
			<lb />
			&amp; SH. BHARAT BHUSHAN, ADDITIONAL
			<lb />
			ADVOCATES GENERAL WITH SH. AMIT
			<lb />
			DHUMAL, DEPUTY ADVOCATE GENERAL
			<lb />
			AND  SH. MANOJ BAGGA, ASSISTANT ADVOCATE
			<lb />
			GENERAL FOR THE RESPONDENT/STATE)
			<lb />
			WHETHER APPROVED FOR REPORTING?  Yes.
			<lb />
			This petition coming on for admission this day,
			<lb />
			Hon’ble   Mr.   Justice   Chander   Bhusan   Barowalia,
			<lb />
			delivered the following:
			<lb />
			J U D G M E N T
			<lb />
		</front>
		<body>
			The present appeal has been preferred by the
			<lb />
			appellant/accused/convict   (hereinafter   referred   to   as   “the
			<lb />
			accused”) laying challenge to judgment dated 03.09.2020,
			<lb />
			rendered by learned Special Judge, Kangra at Dharamshala,
			<lb />
			District   Kangra,   H.P.,   in   Sessions   Trial   No.123­
			<lb />
			N/VII/2020/2018, whereby the accused was convicted and
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -11/07/2022 23:56:13 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			2
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			imposed fine of Rs.1000/ upon the accused/appellant for
			<lb />
			the offence punishable under Section 323 of Indian Penal
			<lb />
			Code, 1860 (hereinafter referred to as &quot;IPC&quot;).
			<lb />
			2.
			<lb />
			Leaving fiddling little details, the facts of the
			<lb />
			case can tersely be summarized as under:
			<lb />
			The prosecutrix moved an application to SHO
			<lb />
			Police Station, Nurpur, alleging therein that she is resident of
			<lb />
			village Samrel, Post Office, Baranda, Tehsil Nurpur, District
			<lb />
			Kangra, H.P., aged about 16 years. At about 12.00 noon, she
			<lb />
			was watching television in her house. On that day, there was
			<lb />
			a death in the village and her parents had gone there. In the
			<lb />
			meantime, accused Arjun Kumar came into her room and
			<lb />
			started forcibly teasing her and due to that, she found marks
			<lb />
			on her neck. When the accused was forcibly outraging her
			<lb />
			modesty, she was crying loudly. On her hue and cry, her
			<lb />
			mother came to home and on seeing her mother, the accused
			<lb />
			fled away from there and while the accused was leaving the
			<lb />
			place, he threatened her that if she disclosed anything to
			<lb />
			anyone, then he will kill her. After that, he fled away from the
			<lb />
			spot and her mother called his sister and brotherinlaw and
			<lb />
			alongwith them, she went to Police Station for lodging the
			<lb />
			report. On this information, the formal FIR was registered.
			<lb />
			The victim was sent to the Civil Hospital, Nurpur for obtaining
			<lb />
			the MLC and the doctor disclosed that the injuries are simple
			<lb />
			blunt and during investigation, the Investigating Officer
			<lb />
			2
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -11/07/2022 23:56:13 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			3
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			prepared the spot map, recorded the statements of witnesses
			<lb />
			and statement of victim under Section 164 Cr.P.C was got
			<lb />
			recorded and her date of birth record was obtained from the
			<lb />
			Panchayat and date of birth record of accused was also
			<lb />
			procured. After completion of investigation, the Investigating
			<lb />
			Officer came to the conclusion that the accused has
			<lb />
			committed offences punishable under Sections 452, 354A,
			<lb />
			323, 506 IPC and Section 8 of Protection of Children from
			<lb />
			Sexual Offences Act, 2012.
			<lb />
			3.
			<lb />
			Heard. Learned counsel for the appellant has
			<lb />
			vehemently argued that the learned Court below has failed to
			<lb />
			appreciate the factum of the incidence, which was not at all
			<lb />
			an offence under Section 452, 354A, 323, 506 and under
			<lb />
			Section 8 of the Protection of Children from Sexual Offences
			<lb />
			Act. He has argued that no witness has proved the offence by
			<lb />
			the learned Court below just on the basis of conjectures and
			<lb />
			surmises convicted the present petitioner and sentenced him
			<lb />
			to pay a fine of Rs.1,000/ under Section 323 of the Indian
			<lb />
			Penal Code. He has further argued that no case was proved
			<lb />
			against the accused under Section 323 IPC and his conviction
			<lb />
			under Section 323 IPC is required to be set aside.
			<lb />
			4.
			<lb />
			In reply thereto, the learned Additional Advocate
			<lb />
			General on behalf of the respondent/State has argued that
			<lb />
			the prosecution has proved the case under Section 323 IPC
			<lb />
			beyond reasonable doubt and he has rightly been convicted.
			<lb />
			3
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -11/07/2022 23:56:13 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			4
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			5.In order to appreciate the rival contentions of
			<lb />
			the parties, I have gone through the record carefully.
			<lb />
			6.
			<lb />
			The prosecution, in order to prove its case, has
			<lb />
			examined as many as eight witnesses to bring home the guilt
			<lb />
			of the accused. The statement of the accused, under Section
			<lb />
			313 Cr.P.C., was recorded and he claimed innocence. No
			<lb />
			defence witness was produced by the accused.
			<lb />
			7.
			<lb />
			PW1 is the prosecutrix, who deposed that she
			<lb />
			was studying in 10 th Class in Govt. Senior Secondary School
			<lb />
			Rit, Tehsil Nurpur, District Kangra, H.P. In the month of July,
			<lb />
			she appeared as SOS student in supplementary examination
			<lb />
			and her date of birth is 23.12.2002. She deposed that on
			<lb />
			21.07.2018, she was watching TV around 10:3011:00 a.m.
			<lb />
			Her parents had gone in the village to condole the death and
			<lb />
			during that time, accused came inside her house and when
			<lb />
			she asked the accused why he had come, he pushed her on
			<lb />
			the bed and pressed her throat. Due to pressing of her throat,
			<lb />
			his finger impression were on her throat. She tried to save
			<lb />
			herself. In the meantime, her mother came and the accused
			<lb />
			fled away. While fleeing away, the accused threatened her not
			<lb />
			to disclose this incident to anyone, otherwise he will kill her.
			<lb />
			Then her mother telephonically called her sister and brother
			<lb />
			inlaw, who came after some time and thereafter, they went to
			<lb />
			Police Station, Nurpur, and made a written complaint,
			<lb />
			Ex.PW1/A and she was got medically examined and her MLC
			<lb />
			4
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -11/07/2022 23:56:13 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			5
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			is MarkA. She was produced before the Court where her
			<lb />
			statement under Section 164 Cr.P.C., Ex.PW1/B was
			<lb />
			recorded. In her crossexamination, she has deposed that
			<lb />
			mother of accused used to call her father as Mama and being
			<lb />
			in relation and she and accused are brother and sister. She
			<lb />
			denied that accused used to visit her house due to the above
			<lb />
			stated relation. She further deposed that when the accused
			<lb />
			entered the room, she asked the accused why he had come,
			<lb />
			when he caught hold her from her arm, she slapped him. On
			<lb />
			this, the accused threw her on the bed and pressed her
			<lb />
			throat. The accused had wrapped her hair around her neck
			<lb />
			and pressed it. The complaint, Ex.PW1/A was not written by
			<lb />
			her and she had only signed it. She is not aware as to who
			<lb />
			had written it. She denied that complaint, Ex.PW1/A was
			<lb />
			written at the instance of the police. She admitted that in
			<lb />
			Ex. PW1/A and Ex.PW1/B, it was not specifically written that
			<lb />
			accused had thrown her on the bed. Voluntarily stated that
			<lb />
			she had stated this fact. She denied that she is deposing
			<lb />
			falsely in this regard. She admitted that in Ex. PW1/B, it was
			<lb />
			written that she had quarreled with the accused regarding
			<lb />
			some matter. The matter was that she had asked the accused
			<lb />
			why he had come to her house. She admitted that, firstly she
			<lb />
			slapped the accused and then the accused slapped her and
			<lb />
			wrapped her hair around her neck and nothing else had
			<lb />
			happened. She admitted that the accused had not pressed her
			<lb />
			5
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -11/07/2022 23:56:13 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			6
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			throat with the hands. Voluntarily she has stated that the
			<lb />
			accused had pressed her throat with her hair due to which,
			<lb />
			impression came on her neck. She denied that the accused
			<lb />
			had no intention to tease or sexually assault her. She denied
			<lb />
			that the above incident of her slapping the accused and the
			<lb />
			accused slapping her was in the nature of game played by the
			<lb />
			children, without any intention to tease the female. She
			<lb />
			admitted in her statement, Ex.PW1/B that it was recorded at
			<lb />
			Nurpur Court without any pressure and she had signed Ex.
			<lb />
			PW1/A after going through its contents. She denied that she
			<lb />
			is deposing falsely, due to tutoring by the police.
			<lb />
			8.
			<lb />
			PW2 Sushma Devi deposed that prosecutrix is
			<lb />
			her daughter aged about 16 years. On 21.07.2018, she
			<lb />
			alongwith her husband had gone in the village to condole the
			<lb />
			death and she returned back to home to check the water
			<lb />
			supply. When she entered the gate, the accused was holding
			<lb />
			his Footwears (Chapals) in his hand and fled away by the side
			<lb />
			of their house. She went inside the room of the prosecutrix,
			<lb />
			who was weeping. She inquired from the prosecutrix, who told
			<lb />
			that the accused had quarreled with her and wrapped her
			<lb />
			hair around her neck. Accused could have done anything with
			<lb />
			her. The prosecutrix had threatened the accused that she
			<lb />
			would inform her father about it and then accused had
			<lb />
			wrapped her hair around her neck. The accused is resident of
			<lb />
			their village. She called his mother to her house. The
			<lb />
			6
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			::: Downloaded on -11/07/2022 23:56:13 :::CIS
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			7
			<lb />
			<body>
				mother of the accused requested her not to tell about this
				<lb />
				incident to any other person and she would make the accused
				<lb />
				understand. She telephonically called her daughter Sneha,
				<lb />
				who came alongwith her husband and fatherinlaw.
				<lb />
				Thereafter, prosecutrix alongwith her sister and her husband
				<lb />
				went to the Police Station, Nurpur. The police came on next
				<lb />
				day. The accused had fled away from the house and police
				<lb />
				had called him. In her crossexamination, she admitted that
				<lb />
				the family of the accused is related to them in village
				<lb />
				relationship. The mother of the accused call her husband as
				<lb />
				Mama and they are in visiting terms and this fact was also
				<lb />
				disclosed to the police that accused had fled away from the
				<lb />
				side of the house, when she reached near the gate of her
				<lb />
				house. She had also informed the police that her daughter
				<lb />
				had disclosed her that she threatened the accused that she
				<lb />
				would inform her father about this incident. She had also
				<lb />
				disclosed to the police that she called the mother of accused
				<lb />
				in her house, who requested her not to tell about this incident
				<lb />
				to any other person and she would make the accused
				<lb />
				understand. She is not aware that who had written
				<lb />
				complaint, Ex.PW1/A. She has further deposed that she is not
				<lb />
				aware whether Ex. PW1/A was read over and explained to the
				<lb />
				complainant. Voluntarily deposed that she was in tension at
				<lb />
				that time. She admitted that she was under tension due to
				<lb />
				the impression, which was there in the neck of her daughter.
				<lb />
				7
				<lb />
			</body>
			<note place="footnote">
				::: Downloaded on -11/07/2022 23:56:13 :::CIS
				<lb />
			</note>
			<page>
				8
				<lb />
			</page>
			<body>
				She admitted that her daughter had disclosed her that she
				<lb />
				had slapped the accused and then the accused had also
				<lb />
				slapped her and wrapped her hair around her neck. She
				<lb />
				admitted that, except this nothing else had happened. She
				<lb />
				denied that they had lodged the report only because there was
				<lb />
				impression on the neck of her daughter. She denied that
				<lb />
				being the mother of prosecutrix, she is disposing falsely
				<lb />
				against the accused.
				<lb />
				9.
				<lb />
				PW3 Sh.Ravinder Singh deposed that the
				<lb />
				prosecutrix is his sisterinlaw. On 21.07.2018, they were at
				<lb />
				home and his motherinlaw telephoned him around 12:30
				<lb />
				P.M. that accused had molested the prosecutrix at her home.
				<lb />
				Thereafter, he alongwith his wife, came to inlaws house
				<lb />
				within 510 minutes time and inquired from the prosecutrix,
				<lb />
				who told that the accused had slapped her and also tied her
				<lb />
				hair around her neck. He saw marks on her neck. Thereafter,
				<lb />
				they took the prosecutrix to Police Station, Nurpur and
				<lb />
				complaint, Ex PW1/A was given to the police and his wife also
				<lb />
				accompanied the prosecutrix to Civil Hospital, Nurpur. In
				<lb />
				crossexamination, he has stated that he was married about
				<lb />
				22½ year back and his village is about 67 kilometers away
				<lb />
				from his inlaws house. He is not aware that accused is
				<lb />
				related to his inlaws and that the family of accused was in
				<lb />
				visiting terms with his inlaws. He deposed that he had met
				<lb />
				him once or twice. He denied that the complaint was not
				<lb />
				8
				<lb />
			</body>
			<note place="footnote">
				::: Downloaded on -11/07/2022 23:56:13 :::CIS
				<lb />
			</note>
			<page>
				9
				<lb />
			</page>
			<body>
				written by the prosecutrix, but by the police and they reached
				<lb />
				the Police Station around 2:00 P.M. He further denied that
				<lb />
				after consultation, they lodged false report and made a
				<lb />
				concocted story about the molestation. He denied that the
				<lb />
				prosecutrix was not molested by the accused. He denied that
				<lb />
				the prosecutrix never disclosed to him about the molestation
				<lb />
				by the accused. He denied that being related to the
				<lb />
				prosecutrix, he is deposing falsely.
				<lb />
				10.
				<lb />
				PW4 Dr. Satish Pal, has examined the
				<lb />
				prosecutrix and issued MLC, Ex. PW4/B and prescription
				<lb />
				slip, Ex. PW4/C. In crossexamination, he has denied that the
				<lb />
				police had disclosed the alleged history at the time of medical
				<lb />
				examination. He deposed that the police had written it in the
				<lb />
				application, Ex.PW4/A and before the examination of the
				<lb />
				prosecutrix, he had gone through it. He deposed that if one
				<lb />
				presses the throat of a person with the fingers, then the finger
				<lb />
				impression will not come, but only bruises will appear. It is
				<lb />
				possible that, if the victim resists the injuries being caused to
				<lb />
				her, then the assailant may also have some injuries. It is not
				<lb />
				possible to sustain the aforesaid injury on the throat, if the
				<lb />
				tail of the victim is wrapped around her neck and presses
				<lb />
				hard. In that case, there will be imprinted bruises, around
				<lb />
				the neck. He admitted that except the above noted injuries,
				<lb />
				there was no other injury on the person of the patient and the
				<lb />
				above, injuries could not be sustained by simple scratching as
				<lb />
				9
				<lb />
			</body>
			<note place="footnote">
				::: Downloaded on -11/07/2022 23:56:13 :::CIS
				<lb />
			</note>
			<page>
				10
				<lb />
			</page>
			<body>
				in that case there will be abrasions. There was no injury on
				<lb />
				the back of the neck.
				<lb />
				11.
				<lb />
				PW7 Smt. Saneha, deposed that she came to
				<lb />
				know from her mother regarding the incident and she also
				<lb />
				accompanied the prosecutrix to the Police Station and
				<lb />
				Hospital. In her crossexamination, she admitted that accused
				<lb />
				belonged to their caste, but denied that he related to them.
				<lb />
				There are around 78 houses surrounding her maternal home.
				<lb />
				She denied that due to relations, the accused used to come to
				<lb />
				their house. She stated that he used to come only during
				<lb />
				functions. She denied that her mother used to call the father
				<lb />
				of accused as Mama, in the village relation, he is her Jeth. She
				<lb />
				admitted that at her maternal home, her parents alongwith
				<lb />
				prosecutrix and brother reside. In the Police Station,
				<lb />
				prosecutrix gave the complaint in writing, but denied that
				<lb />
				complaint, Ex PW1/A was not written by the prosecutrix or
				<lb />
				that it was written by the Police official. She admitted that
				<lb />
				the statement of prosecutrix was recorded in the Court of
				<lb />
				learned Magistrate at Nurpur, but she did not accompany her.
				<lb />
				She denied that the prosecutrix had not disclosed anything
				<lb />
				regarding molestation or threatening to her. She denied that
				<lb />
				the accused had not molested the prosecutrix, but only they
				<lb />
				had quarreled just like children. She is not aware that the
				<lb />
				prosecutrix had also slapped the accused. She admitted that
				<lb />
				they are not in talking terms with the family of the accused
				<lb />
				10
				<lb />
			</body>
			<note place="footnote">
				::: Downloaded on -11/07/2022 23:56:13 :::CIS
				<lb />
			</note>
			<page>
				11
				<lb />
			</page>
			<body>
				and prior to this incident, they were in talking terms. She
				<lb />
				denied that being a sister of prosecutrix, she is deposing
				<lb />
				falsely.
				<lb />
				12.
				<lb />
				PW8 SI Prittam Singh, deposed that he
				<lb />
				collected the entire evidence and according to his
				<lb />
				investigation, the accused had committed the offence. In
				<lb />
				crossexamination, admitted that the accused and prosecutrix
				<lb />
				belonged to same caste, but not aware that they are related to
				<lb />
				each other. He is not aware that the family of accused and
				<lb />
				prosecutrix having visiting terms. He is also not aware that
				<lb />
				the complaint, Ex.PW1/A was not written by the victim. He
				<lb />
				deposed that the complaint directly approached the Police
				<lb />
				Station. The statement under Section 164 Cr.P.C of the victim
				<lb />
				was also got recorded from the Court and statement under
				<lb />
				Section 161 Cr.P.C was recorded by the Lady Constable on
				<lb />
				22.07.2018. He denied that Ex.PW1/A and subsequent
				<lb />
				statement of the victim was recorded by tutoring her by the
				<lb />
				police. He admitted that on that day, there was death in the
				<lb />
				village. He denied that firstly the victim slapped the accused
				<lb />
				and then accused slapped her and except it nothing had
				<lb />
				happened. He admitted that the accused wrapped her &apos;Goot&apos;
				<lb />
				(Tail) around her neck. He denied that the accused had no
				<lb />
				intention to tease or molest her and the aforesaid incident of
				<lb />
				slapping by the accused and victim to the accused was in the
				<lb />
				nature of the game played by the children. He denied that
				<lb />
				11
				<lb />
			</body>
			<note place="footnote">
				::: Downloaded on -11/07/2022 23:56:13 :::CIS
				<lb />
			</note>
			<page>
				12
				<lb />
			</page>
			<body>
				mother of the victim had not disclosed that she had seen the
				<lb />
				accused fled away from her house when she came to her
				<lb />
				house and reached near the gate. He is not aware that who
				<lb />
				had conducted the medical examination of the victim. The
				<lb />
				brotherinlaw of the victim and her sister were residing five
				<lb />
				kilometers away from the house of victim. The Police Station
				<lb />
				from the house of the victim is around 18 to 20 kilometers. He
				<lb />
				denied that the brotherinlaw and sister alongwith police
				<lb />
				officials manipulated the prosecution story and made the
				<lb />
				concocted story to implicate the accused in the present case.
				<lb />
				13.
				<lb />
				After going through the entire evidence, the
				<lb />
				injury on the person of the accused, which is stated to be
				<lb />
				caused by the accused/appellant and his conviction under
				<lb />
				Section 323 IPC is only required to be considered at this
				<lb />
				stage.
				<lb />
				14.
				<lb />
				There is no eye witness except the prosecutrix to
				<lb />
				the incidence. She could not say what was the reason and
				<lb />
				what was the intention of the accused in causing injury and
				<lb />
				why the accused had tried to throttle her neck. The victim
				<lb />
				and accused are of 16 to 18 years of age. They are the
				<lb />
				neighbours and in distant relations also. The case of the
				<lb />
				prosecutrix is that the accused tried to molest her, if that is
				<lb />
				so, then why the accused has tried to press her neck. It has
				<lb />
				come in evidence that there was some dispute with respect to
				<lb />
				the water supply and the prosecutrix slapped the accused. As
				<lb />
				12
				<lb />
			</body>
			<note place="footnote">
				::: Downloaded on -11/07/2022 23:56:13 :::CIS
				<lb />
			</note>
			<page>
				13
				<lb />
			</page>
			<body>
				far as pressing of the neck by the accused is concerned, the
				<lb />
				same is not proved as per the medical evidence.
				<lb />
				15.
				<lb />
				PW4, Dr. Satish Pal, in his crossexamination
				<lb />
				has deposed that if one presses the throat of a person with the
				<lb />
				fingers, then the finger impression will not come, but only
				<lb />
				bruises will appear and if the victim resists the injury being
				<lb />
				caused to her, then the assailant may also have some injuries.
				<lb />
				It is not possible to sustain the aforesaid injury on the throat,
				<lb />
				if the tail of the victim is wrapped around her neck and
				<lb />
				pressed hard. He has voluntarily deposed that in that case
				<lb />
				there will be imprinted bruises around the neck. Meaning
				<lb />
				thereby the injury mentioned in the neck is not by wrapping
				<lb />
				the tail around her neck and then pressed it. As per the
				<lb />
				doctor, if one presses the throat of a person with the fingers,
				<lb />
				then the finger impression will not come and only the bruises
				<lb />
				will appear and as per opinion, he has stated that the injury
				<lb />
				in question can be caused on the throat, if a person presses it
				<lb />
				with his fingers and thumb and the victim is resisting it. But
				<lb />
				the victim has nowhere stated that she had resisted while the
				<lb />
				accused wrapped her tail around her neck and according to
				<lb />
				the prosecutrix while she made the statement before the
				<lb />
				learned ACJM, Nurpur, she had deposed that she received an
				<lb />
				impression of tail on her neck, but this fact is not
				<lb />
				corroborated by the doctor, who has deposed that no
				<lb />
				impression was found on the neck and only bruises were
				<lb />
				found, which were simple in nature. In statement under
				<lb />
				13
				<lb />
			</body>
			<note place="footnote">
				::: Downloaded on -23:56:13 :::CIS
				<lb />
			</note>
			<page>
				14
				<lb />
			</page>
			<body>
				Section 313 Cr.P.C., the defence of the accused is totally
				<lb />
				denial.
				<lb />
				16.
				<lb />
				In these circumstances, it is difficult to hold that
				<lb />
				the accused has caused simple injury to the prosecutrix. It
				<lb />
				seems that there was dispute with respect to tap water.
				<lb />
				17.
				<lb />
				In these circumstances, this Court finds that the
				<lb />
				suspicion is there whether the simple injury was caused by
				<lb />
				the accused by pressing the neck of the prosecutrix or it has
				<lb />
				otherwise due to scratching etc. There is no evidence to prove
				<lb />
				conclusively the guilt of the accused under Section 323 IPC.
				<lb />
				The golden rule of the criminal jurisprudence is that,
				<lb />
				prosecution is required to prove the case beyond the shadow
				<lb />
				of reasonable doubt and if two views are possible, the benefit
				<lb />
				of same goes to the accused. Applying the above law in the
				<lb />
				instant case, the prosecution has failed to prove the guilt of
				<lb />
				the accused under Section 323 IPC conclusively and beyond
				<lb />
				shadow of reasonable doubt. Hence, the conviction of the
				<lb />
				accused under Section 323 IPC is required to be set aside.
				<lb />
				18.
				<lb />
				Consequently, the conviction and fine imposed
				<lb />
				upon the accused by the learned Court below under Section
				<lb />
				323 IPC is quashed and set aside.
				<lb />
				19.
				<lb />
				The present appeal is allowed and disposed
				<lb />
				of in the aforesaid terms, so also the pending
				<lb />
				application(s), if any. No order as to costs.
				<lb />
				(Chander Bhusan Barowalia)
				<lb />
				October 01, 2021
				<lb />
				Judge
				<lb />
				(M. gandhi)
				<lb />
			</body>
			<note place="footnote">
				::: Downloaded on -11/07/2022 23:56:13 :::CIS
			</note>
		</page>
	</text>
</tei>
