<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<note place="headnote">
			spm
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			1
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			Appeal-1544-19-Judgment.doc
			<lb />
		</note>
		<front>
			IN THE HIGH COURT OF JUDICATURE AT BOMBAY
			<lb />
			CRIMINAL APPELLATE JURISDICTION
			<lb />
			CRIMINAL APPEAL NO. 1544 OF 2019
			<lb />
			Popat Navasu Bendkoli,
			<lb />
			]
			<lb />
			Age -33 years, Occ: Labourer,
			<lb />
			]
			<lb />
			R/o. Holdar Nagar, Tq. Trambakeshwar,
			<lb />
			]
			<lb />
			Dist. Nashik.
			<lb />
			]
			<lb />
			…..Appellant
			<lb />
			V/s.
			<lb />
			1. The State of Maharashtra
			<lb />
			]
			<lb />
			through Harsul Police Station, Nashik.
			<lb />
			]
			<lb />
			]
			<lb />
			2. Surekha Manglu Bendkoli,
			<lb />
			]
			<lb />
			Age -19 years, Occ: Labourer,
			<lb />
			]
			<lb />
			R/o. Holdar Nagar, Tq. Trambakeshwar,
			<lb />
			]
			<lb />
			Dist. Nashik.
			<lb />
			]
			<lb />
			…..Respondents
			<lb />
			Mr. Aniket Vagal for the Appellant.
			<lb />
			Mr. S. S. Hulke, APP for Respondent No.1-State.
			<lb />
			Ms. Priyanka Chavan for Respondent No.2.
			<lb />
			CORAM
			<lb />
			: A. S. GADKARI, J.
			<lb />
			RESERVED ON
			<lb />
			: 13 th JUNE, 2022.
			<lb />
			PRONOUNCED ON : 12 th JULY, 2022
			<lb />
			JUDGMENT:-
			<lb />
		</front>
		<body>
			Appellant/original Accused No.1 has questioned correctness of
			<lb />
			the Judgment and Order dated 13 th March, 2018 passed in Sessions Case
			<lb />
			No.93 of 2017 by the learned Special Judge (POCSOA), Nashik convicting
			<lb />
			him under Section 366 of Indian Penal Code (for short IPC) and sentenced
			<lb />
			to suffer rigorous imprisonment for five years and to pay fine of Rs.3,000/-
			<lb />
			(Rupees Three Thousand Only), in default of payment of fine to suffer
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			1/9
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="footnote">
			::: Uploaded on -12/07/2022
			<lb />
			::: Downloaded on -13/07/2022 02:55:15 :::
			<lb />
		</note>
		<note place="headnote">
			spm
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			2
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			Appeal-1544-19-Judgment.doc
			<lb />
		</note>
		<body>
			further rigorous imprisonment for three months and for offence committed
			<lb />
			under Section 5(1) read with Section 6 of the Protection of Children from
			<lb />
			Sexual Offences Act, 2012 (for short POCSO Act) and sentenced to suffer
			<lb />
			rigorous imprisonment for ten years and to pay fine of Rs.10,000/-(Rupees
			<lb />
			Ten Thousand Only), in default of payment of fine to further suffer rigorous
			<lb />
			imprisonment for six months.
			<lb />
			2.
			<lb />
			Heard Mr. Aniket Vagal, learned Advocate for the Appellant,
			<lb />
			Ms. Priyanka Chavan, learned Advocate appointed by the High Court Legal
			<lb />
			Services Committee, Mumbai to represent Respondent No.2 (victim) and
			<lb />
			learned APP. Perused entire record.
			<lb />
			3.
			<lb />
			As the victim was minor, aged about 16 years and 11 months
			<lb />
			on the date of commission of offence i.e. on 30 th June, 2016, with a view to
			<lb />
			protect her identity and in consonance with provisions of Section 228(A) of
			<lb />
			IPC and Section 33(7) of the POCSO Act, the facts or any other material
			<lb />
			disclosing her identity are hereinafter avoided.
			<lb />
			4.
			<lb />
			It is the prosecution case that, the Respondent No.2 (victim)
			<lb />
			and her friend who was also a minor, used to go for labour work at Nashik
			<lb />
			in a track jeep of Appellant. They used to return at home by 8.00 p.m.
			<lb />
			every day. That, on 30 th June, 2016, at about 7.00 a.m., Respondent No.2
			<lb />
			(victim) and her friend (victim No.2) went to do labour work at Nashik
			<lb />
			from the jeep of the Appellant, however they did not return till late night.
			<lb />
			Therefore, the father (PW No.3) of the victim and the father of the victim
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			2/9
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="footnote">
			::: Uploaded on -12/07/2022
			<lb />
			::: Downloaded on -13/07/2022 02:55:15 :::
			<lb />
		</note>
		<note place="headnote">
			spm
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			3
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			Appeal-1544-19-Judgment.doc
			<lb />
		</note>
		<body>
			No.2 tried to search them in the vicinity, however they were not traced.
			<lb />
			They continued their search for two days. However, as the said two girls
			<lb />
			were not traced out, he ultimately lodged First Information Report on 2 nd
			<lb />
			July, 2016 with Harsul Police Station, District Nashik bearing Crime No.28
			<lb />
			of 2016 under Section 363, 366 of the IPC and under Section 4 of the
			<lb />
			POCSO Act. After registration of the crime, investigation of the same was
			<lb />
			taken over by PSI Mr. Ghuge. During the course of the investigation it was
			<lb />
			revealed that, the Respondent No.2 along with Appellant were residing at
			<lb />
			village Tokwade and Inde, Taluka Murbad, District Thane, within the
			<lb />
			jurisdiction of Tokwade Police Station. On 22 nd August, 2016, police
			<lb />
			apprehended Appellant and along with Respondent No.2 brought him to
			<lb />
			Harsul Police Station. The medical examination of victim was conducted by
			<lb />
			the Medical Officer of General Hospital, Nashik on 22 nd August, 2016 itself.
			<lb />
			After completion of the investigation, investigating officer submitted final
			<lb />
			report under Section 173(2) of Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (for short
			<lb />
			Cr.P.C.), under Section 366 of IPC and under Section 5(1) read with Section
			<lb />
			6 of the POCSO Act before the special Court.
			<lb />
			5.
			<lb />
			The trial Court took cognizance of the said offences against
			<lb />
			Appellant and accused No.2 Ankush Ananda Mondhe and framed charge
			<lb />
			below Exh.18. The contents of the said charge were read over and
			<lb />
			explained to the accused in vernacular language to which they pleaded not
			<lb />
			guilty and claimed to be tried. To establish its case, the prosecution
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			3/9
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="footnote">
			::: Uploaded on -12/07/2022
			<lb />
			::: Downloaded on -13/07/2022 02:55:15 :::
			<lb />
		</note>
		<note place="headnote">
			spm
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			4
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			Appeal-1544-19-Judgment.doc
			<lb />
		</note>
		<body>
			examined in all four witnesses namely the victim (PW No.1); another victim
			<lb />
			(PW No.2) who had eloped with accused No.2 Ankush Mondhe; Mr. Manglu
			<lb />
			Raghu Bendkoli (PW No.3), father of victim and Mr. Pravin P. Salunke (PW
			<lb />
			No.4), Assistant Police Inspector, investigating officer. The prosecution has
			<lb />
			also proved statement of victim recorded under Section 164 of Cr.P.C.
			<lb />
			through her which is on record at Exh.27.
			<lb />
			The trial Court after recording evidence and hearing learned
			<lb />
			Advocates for the respective parties, has convicted Appellant as noted
			<lb />
			hereinabove by its impugned Judgment and Order dated 13 th March, 2018.
			<lb />
			6.
			<lb />
			Mr. Vagal, learned Advocate for the Appellant submitted that,
			<lb />
			the Appellant has admitted medical reports of Respondent No.2 under
			<lb />
			Section 294 of Cr.P.C. He submitted that, in her medical report, the Medical
			<lb />
			Officer has clearly mentioned in para No.12(c) that Hymen was intact.
			<lb />
			That, the Medical Officer while expressing clinical opinion in para 15(b)
			<lb />
			has stated that, &quot;Not consistent with recent sexual intercourse/assault&quot;. He
			<lb />
			further submitted that, the Appellant has brought on record a vital omission
			<lb />
			from the Respondent No.2 from which it can be safely inferred that, the
			<lb />
			Appellant did not commit an act of &apos;aggravated penetrative sexual assault&apos;
			<lb />
			as defined in Section 5 of the POCSO Act to attract punishment under
			<lb />
			Section 6 of POCSO Act. He submitted that, at the most, offence under
			<lb />
			Section 366 of IPC can be alleged against the Appellant, however in view of
			<lb />
			the categorical opinion expressed by Medical Officer, no offence under
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			4/9
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="footnote">
			::: Uploaded on -12/07/2022
			<lb />
			::: Downloaded on -13/07/2022 02:55:15 :::
			<lb />
		</note>
		<note place="headnote">
			spm
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			5
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			Appeal-1544-19-Judgment.doc
			<lb />
		</note>
		<body>
			Section 6 of POCSO Act has been made out by the prosecution. He
			<lb />
			submitted that, the trial Court has failed to take into consideration these
			<lb />
			aspects and has committed error while convicting the Appellant under
			<lb />
			Section 6 of POCSO Act. He therefore prayed that, the impugned Judgment
			<lb />
			and Order may be set aside and the Appellant may be acquitted.
			<lb />
			7.
			<lb />
			Per contra Ms. Chavan, learned Advocate appointed to
			<lb />
			represent Respondent No.2 and learned APP vehemently opposed the
			<lb />
			Appeal. Ms. Chavan submitted that, the testimony of prosecutrix is fully
			<lb />
			reliable to base conviction solely on the same. In support of her contention,
			<lb />
			she relied on decisions in the case of (i) Mohd. Imran Khan Vs. State
			<lb />
			Government (NCT of Delhi) reported in (2011) 10 SCC 192; (ii) Vijay alias
			<lb />
			Chinee Vs. State of Madhya Pradesh reported in (2010) 8 SCC 191 and (iii)
			<lb />
			State of Uttar Pradesh Vs. Chhotey Lal reported in (2011) 2 SCC 550. She
			<lb />
			further submitted that, conviction can be awarded on the basis of sole
			<lb />
			testimony of the prosecutrix, if Court finds that it is genuine and reliable.
			<lb />
			She therefore submitted that, there are no merits in the Appeal and the
			<lb />
			same may be dismissed.
			<lb />
			Learned APP submitted that, non-rupture of hymen or absence
			<lb />
			of injury on victim&apos;s private parts, does not belie her testimony. That, to
			<lb />
			constitute rape penetration however slight is sufficient. That, opinion of
			<lb />
			doctor cannot throw out an otherwise cogent and trustworthy evidence of
			<lb />
			the prosecutrix. In support of his contention he relied on a decision of the
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			5/9
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="footnote">
			::: Uploaded on -12/07/2022
			<lb />
			::: Downloaded on -13/07/2022 02:55:15 :::
			<lb />
		</note>
		<note place="headnote">
			spm
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			6
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			Appeal-1544-19-Judgment.doc
			<lb />
		</note>
		<body>
			Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court in the case of Ranjit Hazarika Vs. State of Assam
			<lb />
			reported in (1998) 8 SCC 635.
			<lb />
			8.
			<lb />
			Perusal of evidence on record reveals that, PW No.2 (victim
			<lb />
			No.2) did not support prosecution&apos;s case and was declared hostile. In her
			<lb />
			cross-examination by the learned APP, she admitted that, she was having an
			<lb />
			affair with accused No.2 Ankush Mondhe and in the month of June, she and
			<lb />
			Ankush Mondhe decided to ran away and accordingly she joined the
			<lb />
			company of Ankush Mondhe on 30 th June, 2016 and along with him she
			<lb />
			started residing as husband and wife at Thane. She has further stated that,
			<lb />
			she has married with Ankush Mondhe and she has no grievance with
			<lb />
			anybody.
			<lb />
			9.
			<lb />
			PW No.3 i.e. father of the victim has deposed about the fact of
			<lb />
			victim used to go to work at Nashik from the vehicle of Appellant and her
			<lb />
			not returning to home on 30 th June, 2016 and lodgment of crime. He has
			<lb />
			also deposed that, the Respondent No.2 along with other victim girl were
			<lb />
			not found in the village and he had having doubt about the other victim
			<lb />
			joining the company of Ankush Mondhe. PW No.4 Mr. Pravin Salunke,
			<lb />
			Assistant Police Inspector has deposed about the investigation carried out
			<lb />
			by him with respect to present crime i.e. Crime No.28 of 2016 and his
			<lb />
			tracing out of other victim girl along with Ankush Mondhe. He has stated
			<lb />
			that, further investigation was thereafter handed over to original
			<lb />
			investigating officer Mr. Ghuge, who completed the investigation and
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			6/9
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="footnote">
			::: Uploaded on -12/07/2022
			<lb />
			::: Downloaded on -13/07/2022 02:55:15 :::
			<lb />
		</note>
		<note place="headnote">
			spm
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			7
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			Appeal-1544-19-Judgment.doc
			<lb />
		</note>
		<body>
			submitted the charge-sheet.
			<lb />
			10.
			<lb />
			This leads me to deal with the most important deposition in the
			<lb />
			entire case that is of Respondent No.2 (PW No.1) victim. The victim in her
			<lb />
			deposition has stated that, prior to a year, the Appellant took her and her
			<lb />
			friend (victim No.2) to Thane. There he took a room on rent. That, victim
			<lb />
			No.2 and Ankush Mondhe were residing in a separate room and the
			<lb />
			Appellant and Respondent No.2 were residing separately. That, the
			<lb />
			Appellant used to extend threats of serious and dire consequences and
			<lb />
			established physical relations with her. That, she along with Appellant
			<lb />
			stayed there for about a month. During the said period, Appellant
			<lb />
			established physical relations with her on various occasions. She has
			<lb />
			further deposed that, the police from Tokwade Police Station came there
			<lb />
			and took her and Appellant at Police Station. They were thereafter brought
			<lb />
			to Harsul Police Station, where her statement came to be recorded. Her
			<lb />
			medical examination was also conducted. She has further deposed that,
			<lb />
			her statement was recorded by Judicial Magistrate which is at Exh.27. The
			<lb />
			said witness has proved the said exhibit i.e. her statement under Section
			<lb />
			164 recorded by Judicial Magistrate.
			<lb />
			Even in her detailed cross-examination except an omission that
			<lb />
			she did not state before the police that, the Appellant took her under the
			<lb />
			pretext of going to work, took her to Thane and established physical
			<lb />
			relations with her against her will and that he also threatened her with dire
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			7/9
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="footnote">
			::: Uploaded on -12/07/2022
			<lb />
			::: Downloaded on -13/07/2022 02:55:15 :::
			<lb />
		</note>
		<note place="headnote">
			spm
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			8
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			Appeal-1544-19-Judgment.doc
			<lb />
		</note>
		<body>
			consequences, nothing more beneficial to Appellant has been brought on
			<lb />
			record.
			<lb />
			The fact of Appellant established physical relations with
			<lb />
			Respondent No.2 and continued it for a month has not been shaken in her
			<lb />
			cross-examination.
			<lb />
			11.
			<lb />
			Though, the medical report mentions that, Hymen of
			<lb />
			Respondent No.2 was found to be intact and no injuries were found on her
			<lb />
			person and therefore the case of sexual assault is not consistent with recent
			<lb />
			sexual intercourse/assault is concerned, it is the settled position of law and
			<lb />
			as held in the case of Ranjit Hazarika (supra), even if the medical evidence
			<lb />
			does not support the prosecution case, the deposition of prosecutrix cannot
			<lb />
			be brushed aside if it is found to be otherwise reliable and trustworthy. In
			<lb />
			the present case, this Court finds that the testimony of prosecutrix is wholly
			<lb />
			reliable and trustworthy.
			<lb />
			12.
			<lb />
			Section 3(a) of the POCSO Act states that, a person is said to
			<lb />
			&apos;commit penetrative sexual assault&apos; if he penetrates his penis to any extent,
			<lb />
			into the vagina, mouth, urethra or anus of a child or makes the child to do
			<lb />
			so with him or with any other person. Section 5 of the Act defines
			<lb />
			&apos;aggravated penetrative sexual assault&apos;. Section 5(1) mentions about
			<lb />
			penetrative sexual assault on the child more than once or repeatedly. In
			<lb />
			view of the testimony of the victim (PW No.1) it is clear that, the Appellant
			<lb />
			has committed an act as contemplated under Section 3(a) read with Section
			<lb />
			5(1) punishable under Section 6 of the POCSO Act. It is an admitted fact
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			8/9
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="footnote">
			::: Uploaded on -12/07/2022
			<lb />
			::: Downloaded on -13/07/2022 02:55:15 :::
			<lb />
		</note>
		<note place="headnote">
			spm
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			9
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			Appeal-1544-19-Judgment.doc
			<lb />
		</note>
		<body>
			on record that, on the date of the commission of offence i.e. 30 th June,
			<lb />
			2016, age of the prosecutrix was 16 years and 11 months and therefore she
			<lb />
			was a child within the meaning of Section 2(d) of the Act. Appellant forced
			<lb />
			her to join his company from the lawful guardianship of her parents. In
			<lb />
			view thereof, the offence under Section 366 of the IPC and under Section 6
			<lb />
			of POCSO Act is proved by the prosecution.
			<lb />
			13.
			<lb />
			The aforenoted deliberation would lead to draw a safe
			<lb />
			inference that, the Trial Court has not committed any error while convicting
			<lb />
			and sentencing the Appellant by its impugned Judgment and Order. There
			<lb />
			are no merits in Appeal and is accordingly dismissed.
			<lb />
			14.
			<lb />
			Before parting with the Judgment, this Court places on record
			<lb />
			a word of appreciation for the efforts put in by Ms. Chavan, learned
			<lb />
			Advocate appointed through the High Court Legal Services Committee,
			<lb />
			Mumbai for espousing the cause of Respondent No.2, as she was thoroughly
			<lb />
			prepared in the matter and rendered proper assistance to the Court.
			<lb />
			(A.S. GADKARI, J.)
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			9/9
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="footnote">
			::: Uploaded on -12/07/2022
			<lb />
			::: Downloaded on -13/07/2022 02:55:15 :::
		</note>
	</text>
</tei>
