<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<page>
			1/23
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			WP-1415.21.odt-J
			<lb />
		</note>
		<front>
			IN THE HIGH COURT OF JUDICATURE AT BOMBAY
			<lb />
			NAGPUR BENCH, NAGPUR.
			<lb />
			WRIT PETITION NO. 1415 OF 2021
			<lb />
			PETITIONERS :-
			<lb />
			1. Sunil S/o Radhesham Shukla, Aged about
			<lb />
			60 years, Occu: Business, R/o Laxmi-
			<lb />
			narayan Gaurishankar Niwas, Behind
			<lb />
			Ramdevbaba Engineering College, Pension
			<lb />
			Nagar, Nagpur, Tah. &amp; Distt. Nagpur.
			<lb />
			2. Munna @ Gangaprasad S/o Radhesham
			<lb />
			Shukla, Aged about 57 years, Occu: Priest
			<lb />
			&amp; Cultivator, R/o Laxminarayan Mandir,
			<lb />
			Bazar Chouk, Sindi (Rly), Tq. Seloo, Distt.
			<lb />
			Wardha-442105.
			<lb />
			...VERSUS...
			<lb />
			RESPONDENTS :-
			<lb />
			1. State of Maharashtra, through Collector,
			<lb />
			Wardha.
			<lb />
			2. The Sub-Divisional Officer, Wardha, Tah. &amp;
			<lb />
			Distt. Wardha.
			<lb />
			3. The Officer-in-Charge, Jawaharlal Nehru
			<lb />
			Dry Port Project Sindi (Rly), Tah. Seloo,
			<lb />
			Distt. Wardha.
			<lb />
			4. The Tahsildar, Seloo, Tah. Seloo, Distt.
			<lb />
			Wardha.
			<lb />
			5. Durga @ Jyoti W/o Arvindkumar Awasthi,
			<lb />
			Aged about 67 years, Occu: Household, R/o
			<lb />
			Ratan Nagar, Plot No.17, Jyoti Villa
			<lb />
			Mankapur, Nagpur, Tah. &amp; Distt. Nagpur.
			<lb />
			6. Jayashri W/o Vinodkumar Awasthi, Aged
			<lb />
			about 59 years, Occu: Household, R/o Gau
			<lb />
			KHUNTE
			<lb />
			Original Applicant in
			<lb />
			Reference Case before
			<lb />
			Trial Court
			<lb />
			Original Non-applicant
			<lb />
			no.8 in Reference Case
			<lb />
			before Trial Court
			<lb />
			Original Non-applicants
			<lb />
			no.1 to 7 and Original
			<lb />
			Non-applicants no.9 to 15
			<lb />
			in Reference Case before
			<lb />
			Trial Court
			<lb />
		</front>
		<page>
			2/23
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			WP-1415.21.odt-J
			<lb />
		</note>
		<front>
			Anusandhan Vikas Kendra Near Durga
			<lb />
			Mandir, Badkas Chowk, Mahal, Nagpur,
			<lb />
			Tah. &amp; Distt. Nagpur.
			<lb />
			7. Munna @ Gangaprasad S/o Radhesham
			<lb />
			Shukla -Deleted.
			<lb />
			8. Manisha W/o Sunilkumar Mishra, Aged
			<lb />
			about 56 years, Occu: Household, R/o
			<lb />
			Delhi, C/o Jyoti Awasthi, Ratan Nagar, Plot
			<lb />
			No.17, Jyoti Villa Mankapur, Nagpur, Tah.
			<lb />
			&amp; Distt. Nagpur.
			<lb />
			9. Minakshi W/o Manish Tiwari, Aged about
			<lb />
			54 years, Occu: Household, R/o Idgah Hill
			<lb />
			Bhopal (M.P.).
			<lb />
			10.Radhesham S/o Gaurishankar Shukla, Aged
			<lb />
			about 92 years, Occu: Nil, R/o Plot No.110-
			<lb />
			D, Sector Kolar Marg Sarvadharma Colony,
			<lb />
			Bairagd Chichali, Bhopal-462 042 (M.P.).
			<lb />
			11.Shreyansh S/o Gopal Shukla, Aged 29
			<lb />
			years, Occu:Not Known, R/o Sarvadharama
			<lb />
			Colony, Nayapur, Kolar Road, Bhopal.
			<lb />
			12.Savita S/o Gopal Shukla, Aged 49 years,
			<lb />
			Occu: Household, R/o Sarvadharama
			<lb />
			Colony, Nayapur, Kolar Road, Bhopal.
			<lb />
			13.Shanta W/o Ashokrao Petkar, Aged about
			<lb />
			59 years, Occu: Cultivation, R/o Kandhali
			<lb />
			Road, Sindi (Rly), Tah. Seloo, Distt.
			<lb />
			Wardha.
			<lb />
			14.The Allahabad Bank, Nayapur Kolar Road
			<lb />
			Branch, Bhopal (M.P.) through its Branch
			<lb />
			Manager.
			<lb />
		</front>
		<note place="footnote">
			KHUNTE
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			3/23
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			WP-1415.21.odt-J
			<lb />
		</note>
		<front>
			-----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------
			<lb />
			Mr.R.L.Khapre, Sr.Counsel a/b Mr.D.R.Khapre,
			<lb />
			counsel for the petitioners.
			<lb />
			Ms T.H.Khan, AGP for respondent Nos.1, 2 and 4.
			<lb />
			Mr. Abhijit Deshpande, counsel for respondent No.10.
			<lb />
			Mr. Yash Maheshwari, counsel for respondent Nos.11 to 13.
			<lb />
			Mr. Monogya U. Singh, counsel for respondent No.14.
			<lb />
			None for respondent Nos.3, 5, 6, 8 and 9.
			<lb />
			-----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------
			<lb />
			CORAM : MANISH PITALE, J.
			<lb />
			RESERVED ON
			<lb />
			: 16.06.2022.
			<lb />
			PRONOUNCED ON : 0 7 .07.2022.
			<lb />
			J U D G M E N T
			<lb />
		</front>
		<body>
			Heard.
			<lb />
			2.
			<lb />
			Rule. Rule made returnable forthwith. Heard the writ petition
			<lb />
			finally with the consent of the learned counsel appearing for the rival
			<lb />
			parties. Though respondent Nos.3, 5, 6, 8 and 9 were served, they were
			<lb />
			not present in the Court.
			<lb />
			3.
			<lb />
			The petitioners are aggrieved by an order dated 04/02/2021,
			<lb />
			passed by the Court of 2 nd Joint Civil Judge, Senior Division, Wardha,
			<lb />
			whereby an application filed by the respondent No.10 for rejection of
			<lb />
			reference under section 30 of the Land Acquisition Act, 1894 (hereinafter
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			KHUNTE
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			4/23
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note plcae="headnote">
			WP-1415.21.odt-J
			<lb />
		</note>
		<body>
			referred to as &quot;Act&quot;), has been allowed. According to the petitioners,
			<lb />
			once such a reference was made to the aforesaid Civil Court by the
			<lb />
			respondent No.2-Sub-Divisional Officer, it ought to have been decided on
			<lb />
			merits, after recording of evidence and that the said Court erred in
			<lb />
			throwing out the reference at the threshold.
			<lb />
			4.
			<lb />
			In the present case, land located in Mouza Parsodi, Tahsil
			<lb />
			Seloo, District Wardha, was acquired by the respondent-State. The award
			<lb />
			determining compensation payable to the claimant was pronounced on
			<lb />
			29/03/1988 and since the land in question, was registered in the name of
			<lb />
			contesting respondent No.10, i.e. the father of the petitioners, the
			<lb />
			amount of compensation of Rs.22,992/-was disbursed to the respondent
			<lb />
			No.10. There is no dispute about the fact that the said land was
			<lb />
			purchased by the respondent No.10 in the year 1964.
			<lb />
			5.
			<lb />
			At the time when the aforesaid amount of compensation was
			<lb />
			disbursed as per the aforesaid award in the year 2010, and even
			<lb />
			thereafter, no dispute was raised by any person in respect of the
			<lb />
			entitlement of the said respondent for receiving compensation. Later,
			<lb />
			when the acquired land was to be utilized for the benefit of respondent
			<lb />
			No.3 i.e. the Jawaharlal Nehru Dry Port Project at Wardha, it appears that
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			KHUNTE
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			5/23
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			WP-1415.21.odt-J
			<lb />
		</note>
		<body>
			there was some grievance made and demands raised by landowners for
			<lb />
			further payment of amount. On 20/05/2016, the Deputy Secretary of the
			<lb />
			concerned Department of the State of Maharashtra, sent a
			<lb />
			communication to the respondent No.3 and its officials that in view of the
			<lb />
			demands made, and also in the backdrop of the Right to Fair
			<lb />
			Compensation and Transparency in Land Acquisition, Rehabilitation and
			<lb />
			Resettlement Act, 2013, it was decided that further ex gratia
			<lb />
			amount/additional compensation shall be paid to claimants pertaining to
			<lb />
			the said acquisition at Rs.7,00,000/-per acre. Since the respondent
			<lb />
			No.10 was the claimant, who had been paid amount towards
			<lb />
			compensation as per the aforesaid award, steps were taken by the
			<lb />
			concerned Authorities to disburse the enhanced compensation of
			<lb />
			Rs.64,83,750/-into the account of respondent No.10.
			<lb />
			6.
			<lb />
			It is at this stage, that on 05/08/2017, the petitioner No.1
			<lb />
			applied before the Collector, Wardha under section 30 of the Act for
			<lb />
			referring dispute regarding apportionment of the said additional amount,
			<lb />
			to the Civil Court amongst &quot;joint owners&quot;. With reference to the said
			<lb />
			application, the Deputy Collector (Land Acquisition) sent a letter on
			<lb />
			05/09/2017, to the respondent No.2-Sub-Divisional Officer for
			<lb />
			appropriate action and in pursuance thereof, the reference was made to
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			KHUNTE
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			6/23
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			WP-1415.21.odt-J
			<lb />
		</note>
		<body>
			the aforesaid Civil Court under section 30 of the Act, bearing LAC No.46
			<lb />
			of 2017.
			<lb />
			7.
			<lb />
			In this proceeding initiated before the said Civil Court, the
			<lb />
			petitioner No.1 made an application for direction to stop disbursal of the
			<lb />
			amount to the respondent No.10. The Civil Court passed orders and
			<lb />
			issued directions to the concerned Bank as regards disbursal of the
			<lb />
			amount into the account of the respondent No.10.
			<lb />
			8.
			<lb />
			In the said pending proceeding, the respondent No.10 filed an
			<lb />
			application questioning the maintainability of the reference, bearing
			<lb />
			Exhibit-55. It was contended that when the petitioner No.1 moved the
			<lb />
			application before the Collector under section 30 of the Act, the same was
			<lb />
			directly referred to the Civil Court, without even putting the respondent
			<lb />
			No.10 or other parties to notice. It was submitted that acquisition had
			<lb />
			taken place and the award had been pronounced as far back as in the
			<lb />
			year 1988 and the entire compensation was disbursed immediately in
			<lb />
			favour of respondent No.10. There was no objection from any quarters at
			<lb />
			that time and even thereafter and it was further submitted that the
			<lb />
			amount now being distributed was only an ex gratia amount, having no
			<lb />
			connection with the compensation determined under the award and
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note palce="footnote">
			KHUNTE
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			7/23
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			WP-1415.21.odt-J
			<lb />
		</note>
		<body>
			therefore, section 30 of the Act was not applicable. On this basis, it was
			<lb />
			prayed that the application be allowed and the reference be held as not
			<lb />
			maintainable.
			<lb />
			9.
			<lb />
			The petitioner No.1 submitted reply before the Civil Court and
			<lb />
			opposed the said application. By the impugned order dated 04/02/2021,
			<lb />
			the said Civil Court allowed the application, thereby holding that the
			<lb />
			reference was not maintainable. It was held that even the Deputy
			<lb />
			Collector (Land Acquisition) had sent communication dated 27/11/2017,
			<lb />
			withdrawing the reference under section 30 of the Act and therefore, the
			<lb />
			application filed by the respondent No.10 deserved to be allowed.
			<lb />
			10.
			<lb />
			Aggrieved by the said order, the petitioners filed the present
			<lb />
			writ petition. It is significant that the petitioner No.2 was not the
			<lb />
			applicant before the Collector under section 30 of the Act and yet the said
			<lb />
			petitioner chose to join the petitioner No.1 in challenging the impugned
			<lb />
			order. On 22/03/2021, this Court issued notice in the present petition
			<lb />
			and on the question of interim relief, it was found that since the share of
			<lb />
			the petitioners before this Court, came to Rs.13,00,000/-, interim stay
			<lb />
			would be restricted to only the said amount and disbursal of balance
			<lb />
			amount would not be affected. The respondents in the present case
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			KHUNTE
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			8/23
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			WP-1415.21.odt-J
			<lb />
		</note>
		<body>
			entered appearance through counsel. The petition was opposed strongly
			<lb />
			by the respondent No.10, i.e. the father of the petitioners, who was the
			<lb />
			applicant before the Civil Court seeking rejection of the reference as not
			<lb />
			maintainable. The other private respondents, i.e. respondent Nos.5, 6, 8,
			<lb />
			9, 11, 12, and 13 did not oppose the present petition.
			<lb />
			11.
			<lb />
			Mr. R.L. Khapre, learned senior counsel appearing for the
			<lb />
			petitioners, vehemently submitted that the Civil Court committed a grave
			<lb />
			error in allowing the application at Exhibit-55, filed by the respondent
			<lb />
			No.10 and throwing out the reference at the threshold. It was submitted
			<lb />
			that the nature of dispute raised in the present case on behalf of the
			<lb />
			petitioners warranted detailed examination and recording of evidence to
			<lb />
			reach any definitive conclusion. The learned senior counsel referred to
			<lb />
			the provisions of the aforesaid Act, particularly section 30 thereof, to
			<lb />
			emphasize that no limitation is prescribed therein and since the case of
			<lb />
			the petitioners was that cause of action accrued to them only after the
			<lb />
			death of their mother and when the additional compensation was
			<lb />
			determined, the reference under section 30 of the Act was correctly made
			<lb />
			by the Collector and that the same could not have been thrown out at the
			<lb />
			threshold. The learned senior counsel relied upon the judgments of the
			<lb />
			Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court in the case of Dr.G.H. Grant v. The State of Bihar,
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			KHUNTE
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			9/23
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			WP-1415.21.odt-J
			<lb />
		</note>
		<body>
			reported in AIR 1966 SC 237, Sunderlal v. Paramsukhdas and others,
			<lb />
			reported in AIR 1968 SC 366 and Sharda Devi v. State of Bihar, reported
			<lb />
			in AIR 2003 SC 942.
			<lb />
			12.
			<lb />
			It was emphasized that since the interest of the petitioners in
			<lb />
			the apportionment of compensation arose, in the facts of the present
			<lb />
			case, after the death of their mother in the year 2015 and when
			<lb />
			additional compensation was to be disbursed, the petitioners had
			<lb />
			correctly invoked section 30 of the Act. This contention was pressed on
			<lb />
			the assertion of the petitioners that the said land was purchased in 1964,
			<lb />
			only in the name of their father, but from the resources of their mother.
			<lb />
			As long as their mother was alive, they could not have raised any claim
			<lb />
			regarding apportionment, but upon her death in the year 2015, they were
			<lb />
			entitled to raise dispute regarding apportionment of the additional
			<lb />
			compensation. Much emphasis was placed on the observations made by
			<lb />
			the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court regarding entitlement of persons in such a
			<lb />
			situation where the interest arises after award has been pronounced.
			<lb />
			13.
			<lb />
			The learned senior counsel emphasized that the Civil Court
			<lb />
			while passing the impugned order, committed a grave error in proceeding
			<lb />
			on the basis that the Deputy Collector had withdrawn the reference itself.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			KHUNTE
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			10/23
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			WP-1415.21.odt-J
			<lb />
		</note>
		<body>
			It was submitted that once the concerned Deputy Collector had referred
			<lb />
			the dispute under section 30 of the Act to the Civil Court, the said
			<lb />
			Authority had no power to withdraw such a reference.
			<lb />
			It was
			<lb />
			emphasized that if such a power was held to be available to the Collector,
			<lb />
			it would have drastic consequences, because findings rendered by the
			<lb />
			competent Civil Court, confirmed in challenges raised thereto, would
			<lb />
			stand nullified by the Collector simply withdrawing the reference at any
			<lb />
			stage. It was submitted that once the dispute was referred to the Civil
			<lb />
			Court, it had to be disposed of after granting appropriate opportunity to
			<lb />
			the concerned parties to lead evidence in support of their respective
			<lb />
			stands. On this basis, it was submitted that the impugned order deserved
			<lb />
			interference.
			<lb />
			14.
			<lb />
			On the other hand, Mr. Abhijit Deshpande, learned counsel
			<lb />
			appearing for the contesting respondent No.10, submitted that in the
			<lb />
			present case, the petitioner No.1 could not have invoked section 30 of the
			<lb />
			Act at all. By referring to the said provision, it was submitted that an
			<lb />
			application to the Collector for referring a dispute to the Civil Court
			<lb />
			would lie only when the dispute arises as regards apportionment of
			<lb />
			compensation settled under section 11 of the Act. It was emphasized that
			<lb />
			in the present case, the amount sought to be disbursed by the respondent
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			KHUNTE
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			11/23
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			WP-1415.21.odt-J
			<lb />
		</note>
		<body>
			No.3, was only an ex gratia amount, while the compensation determined
			<lb />
			under the award dated 29/03/1988, as per section 11 of the Act was
			<lb />
			already disbursed immediately upon pronouncement of the award. On
			<lb />
			this basis, it was submitted that the application filed by the petitioner
			<lb />
			No.1 itself was stillborn.
			<lb />
			15.
			<lb />
			Apart from this, it was submitted that when the petitioner No.1
			<lb />
			submitted the said application before the Collector, it ought to have been
			<lb />
			ascertained as to whether there could be said to be any dispute as regards
			<lb />
			the apportionment of compensation in the context of an award, for
			<lb />
			reference to the Civil Court. The Collector ought to have put all
			<lb />
			concerned parties, particularly the respondent No.10, i.e. the recorded
			<lb />
			owner of the said property, to notice before proceeding in the matter.
			<lb />
			But, the Collector in the present case mechanically instructed the
			<lb />
			respondent No.2-Sub-Divisional Officer to take appropriate steps leading
			<lb />
			to the reference being registered in the Civil Court. It is for this reason
			<lb />
			that when the reference came to be initiated on 29/09/2017, upon
			<lb />
			realizing the mistake, the Deputy Collector immediately on 27/11/2017,
			<lb />
			communicated to the Civil Court that the reference was being withdrawn.
			<lb />
			Since the reference was withdrawn immediately, it could not be said that
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			KHUNTE
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			12/23
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			WP-1415.21.odt-J
			<lb />
		</note>
		<body>
			such an act on the part of the Deputy Collector was either illegal or
			<lb />
			without jurisdiction.
			<lb />
			16.
			<lb />
			It was further submitted that in any case, the Civil Court was
			<lb />
			enjoined to examine whether the dispute could at all have been referred
			<lb />
			by the Collector under section 30 of the Act. Although some interim
			<lb />
			orders were passed in the reference, the moment the respondent No.10
			<lb />
			filed the aforesaid application at Exhibit-55 for dismissal of the reference
			<lb />
			as not maintainable, the Civil Court correctly analyzed the material on
			<lb />
			record to conclude that such a reference could not be entertained. The
			<lb />
			learned counsel for the respondent No.10 relied upon judgments of the
			<lb />
			Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court in the case of Prayag Upnivesh Awas Evam
			<lb />
			Nirman Sahkari Samiti Ltd. v. Allahabad Vikas Pradhikaran and another,
			<lb />
			reported in AIR 2003 SC 2302 and Meher Rusi Dalal v. Union of India
			<lb />
			and others, reported in (2004) 7 SCC 362 and the judgment of this Court
			<lb />
			in the case of Dattaram Deu Desai and others v. Nirakar Devasthan of
			<lb />
			Palolem, Goa and others, reported in 2003 (3) Mh.L.J. 477 and
			<lb />
			Comunidade of Bambolim v. Manguesh Betu Kankonkar, reported in
			<lb />
			2001 (2) Mh.L.J. 160.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			KHUNTE
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			13/23
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			WP-1415.21.odt-J
			<lb />
		</note>
		<body>
			17.
			<lb />
			Mr. Yash Maheshwari, learned counsel appearing on behalf of
			<lb />
			respondent Nos.11, 12 and 13, submitted that he supported the
			<lb />
			contentions raised on behalf of the respondent No.10 and he further
			<lb />
			submitted that even if no limitation was prescribed under section 30 of
			<lb />
			the said Act, an application for making reference under the said provision
			<lb />
			ought to be made within reasonable time. He also placed reliance on
			<lb />
			judgment of the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court in the case of Meher Rusi Dalal v.
			<lb />
			Union of India (supra).
			<lb />
			18.
			<lb />
			Ms T.H. Khan, learned AGP appeared on behalf of the
			<lb />
			respondent Nos.1, 2 and 4 and supported the impugned order.
			<lb />
			19.
			<lb />
			Heard the learned counsel for the rival parties and perused the
			<lb />
			material on record. In the present case, the Civil Court has proceeded to
			<lb />
			accept the contentions regarding maintainability of the reference raised
			<lb />
			on behalf of respondent No.10 and accordingly, the reference itself has
			<lb />
			been thrown out, without consideration in detail.
			<lb />
			20.
			<lb />
			Before considering other contentions raised on behalf of the
			<lb />
			rival parties, this Court is inclined to consider the contention raised on
			<lb />
			behalf of the petitioners that the Civil Court ought not to have relied
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			KHUNTE
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			14/23
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			WP-1415.21.odt-J
			<lb />
		</note>
		<body>
			upon withdrawal of the reference by the Deputy Collector for holding in
			<lb />
			favour of respondent No.10. In this context, the learned counsel
			<lb />
			appearing for the respondent No.10 submitted that such withdrawal of
			<lb />
			reference could not be said to be either illegal or without jurisdiction,
			<lb />
			firstly, because the withdrawal was almost immediate upon realizing the
			<lb />
			mistake and secondly, if there is a power with an Authority to do
			<lb />
			something, it certainly has the power to undo the same. This Court is of
			<lb />
			the opinion that merely because in the present case, the reference was
			<lb />
			withdrawn by the Deputy Collector within a couple of months of having
			<lb />
			made the same, it cannot be said that such a step was justified because
			<lb />
			the Authority, in the first place, must have the power to withdraw.
			<lb />
			21.
			<lb />
			A reference is made to the Civil Court under section 30 of the
			<lb />
			Act for resolution of dispute pertaining to apportionment of
			<lb />
			compensation. This requires the Collector to reach a conclusion that a
			<lb />
			dispute exists, which cannot be resolved by the Collector and it would
			<lb />
			require determination by the Civil Court. This Court is of the opinion
			<lb />
			that once the Collector concludes that reference of the dispute has to be
			<lb />
			made to the Civil Court and in fact the dispute stands referred, the
			<lb />
			Collector does not retain jurisdiction to withdraw such a reference.
			<lb />
			Accepting the contention of the respondent No.10 is fraught with danger
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			KHUNTE
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			15/23
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			WP-1415.21.odt-J
			<lb />
		</note>
		<body>
			for the reason that if the same is accepted, it would lead to a situation
			<lb />
			where the Collector could annul the findings of the Civil Court, or even
			<lb />
			higher Courts if the order of the Civil Court is challenged, by simply
			<lb />
			withdrawing the reference at any stage. After making the reference, the
			<lb />
			Collector becomes functus officio and it is then for the Civil Court to
			<lb />
			proceed in the matter. Therefore, the Civil Court in the impugned order
			<lb />
			could not have relied upon withdrawal of the reference by the Deputy
			<lb />
			Collector to hold in favour of respondent No.10. The reliance placed by
			<lb />
			the learned counsel appearing for the respondent No.10 on the judgment
			<lb />
			in the case of Prayag Upnivesh Awas Evam Nirman Sahkari Samiti Ltd. v.
			<lb />
			Allahabad Vikas Pradhikaran (supra) is misplaced for the reason that in
			<lb />
			the said judgment, the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court has only held that the
			<lb />
			reference Court cannot widen the scope of its enquiry beyond what is
			<lb />
			referred to it by the Collector. The said judgment in no manner supports
			<lb />
			the contention raised on behalf of the respondent No.10 in the aforesaid
			<lb />
			context.
			<lb />
			22.
			<lb />
			Nonetheless, it is necessary to examine whether the Civil Court,
			<lb />
			in the present case was justified in allowing the application filed by the
			<lb />
			respondent No.10 at Exhibit-55 and in holding that the reference was not
			<lb />
			maintainable. The learned senior counsel appearing for the petitioners
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			KHUNTE
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			16/23
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			WP-1415.21.odt-J
			<lb />
		</note>
		<body>
			emphasized that once the reference was made to the Civil Court under
			<lb />
			section 30 of the Act, there was no power in the Civil Court to throw out
			<lb />
			the reference at the threshold and that the Civil Court was mandated to
			<lb />
			consider the dispute on merits, by asking the parties to lead evidence in
			<lb />
			support of their respective claims. In other words, according to the
			<lb />
			learned senior counsel appearing for the petitioners, the application filed
			<lb />
			by the respondent No.10 could not have been considered by the Civil
			<lb />
			Court.
			<lb />
			23.
			<lb />
			This Court is of the opinion that although the Deputy Collector
			<lb />
			in the present case appears to have mechanically directed the respondent-
			<lb />
			Sub-Divisional Officer to take appropriate steps on the application moved
			<lb />
			by the petitioner No.1 under section 30 of the Act, as a consequence of
			<lb />
			which the reference appears to have been straightaway registered with
			<lb />
			the Civil Court, even if the Deputy Collector had become functus officio
			<lb />
			and the reference could not have been withdrawn, the Civil Court could
			<lb />
			certainly examine as to whether such a reference could be entertained in
			<lb />
			the facts and circumstances of the present case. The Civil Court derives
			<lb />
			jurisdiction not just because the Collector refers the dispute to it, but the
			<lb />
			jurisdiction is derived from the language of section 30 of the Act. The
			<lb />
			said provision reads as follows:
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			KHUNTE
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			17/23
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			WP-1415.21.odt-J
			<lb />
		</note>
		<body>
			&quot;30. Dispute as to apportionment.-When the amount of compensation
			<lb />
			has been settled under section 11, if any dispute arises as to the
			<lb />
			apportionment of the same or any part thereof, or as to the persons to whom
			<lb />
			the same or any part thereof, is payable, the Collector may refer such dispute
			<lb />
			to the decision of the Court.&quot;
			<lb />
			24.
			<lb />
			It is significant that the dispute pertaining to apportionment
			<lb />
			can be referred by the Collector to the decision of the Civil Court when
			<lb />
			such dispute pertains to amount of compensation settled under section 11
			<lb />
			of the Act. This obviously means that the dispute must relate to
			<lb />
			compensation determined under award pronounced under section 11 of
			<lb />
			the Act. In the present case, amount of compensation determined as per
			<lb />
			award under section 11 of the Act, was Rs.22,992/-and the same was
			<lb />
			immediately disbursed, pursuant to the said award dated 29/03/1988. It
			<lb />
			was disbursed to the respondent No.10, being the registered owner of the
			<lb />
			land as found in the land acquisition proceedings undertaken under the
			<lb />
			said Act, on the basis of a registered sale deed of the year 1964, executed
			<lb />
			in the name of respondent No.10. It is an admitted position that there
			<lb />
			was no other recorded owner or claimant. No dispute was ever raised
			<lb />
			when the said amount was disbursed to the respondent No.10, either
			<lb />
			when it was disbursed or even thereafter.
			<lb />
			25.
			<lb />
			The petitioners were both major when the award was
			<lb />
			pronounced in the year 1988 and the amount of compensation was
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			KHUNTE
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			18/23
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			WP-1415.21.odt-J
			<lb />
		</note>
		<body>
			disbursed to their own father, i.e. respondent No.10. Yet, no dispute was
			<lb />
			raised at any point in time.
			<lb />
			26.
			<lb />
			The material on record shows that the respondent No.3 on the
			<lb />
			instructions of the respondent-State Government decided to disburse
			<lb />
			further ex gratia amount to the persons whose lands were acquired in the
			<lb />
			backdrop of certain demands made by certain landowners. It appears
			<lb />
			that the provisions of the Act of 2013 influenced the decision taken by
			<lb />
			the State for granting ex gratia amount. Letter dated 20/05/2016, sent
			<lb />
			by the Deputy Secretary of the concerned Department of the respondent-
			<lb />
			State to the officers of the respondent No.3, records the said backdrop in
			<lb />
			which the ex gratia amount/additional compensation was to be given.
			<lb />
			This Court is of the opinion that such ex gratia amount cannot be said to
			<lb />
			be compensation settled under section 11 of the Act, for section 30
			<lb />
			thereof to be made applicable. The ex gratia amount, which at some
			<lb />
			place is also referred to as additional compensation, can certainly not to
			<lb />
			be categorized as amount of compensation determined and settled under
			<lb />
			section 11 of the Act. Therefore, section 30 of the Act would not apply to
			<lb />
			the said ex gratia amount. The Civil Court was certainly within its
			<lb />
			jurisdiction to examine as to whether such a reference could be
			<lb />
			entertained or not.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			KHUNTE
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			19/23
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			WP-1415.21.odt-J
			<lb />
		</note>
		<body>
			27.
			<lb />
			The other aspect of the matter is, as to whether the petitioners
			<lb />
			could invoke section 30 of the said Act in the year 2017 when the
			<lb />
			acquisition was completed, award was pronounced and the compensation
			<lb />
			was disbursed the respondent No.10 in the year 1988 itself. Although
			<lb />
			there is no specific period of limitation prescribed in section 30 of the
			<lb />
			Act, the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court in the case of Meher Rusi Dalal v. Union
			<lb />
			of India (supra) has held that even if no specific period of limitation is
			<lb />
			prescribed, an application under section 30 of the Act must be made
			<lb />
			within reasonable time. It is further laid down that what is to be
			<lb />
			reasonable time would depend on the facts and circumstances of each
			<lb />
			case and in the facts of the said case before the Court, it was held that
			<lb />
			reasonable time would be the time as specified in section 18 of the Act.
			<lb />
			Applying the aforesaid test of reasonable time, this Court is of the opinion
			<lb />
			that for an acquisition, which was completed in the year 1988, the
			<lb />
			application moved by the petitioner No.1 in the year 2017 was certainly
			<lb />
			not within reasonable time.
			<lb />
			28.
			<lb />
			It is also necessary to refer to the nature of claim raised by the
			<lb />
			petitioners. It is contended on their behalf that the subject land was
			<lb />
			purchased in 1964, only in the name of their father while the source of
			<lb />
			funds was that of their mother. It was claimed that since their mother
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			KHUNTE
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			20/23
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			WP-1415.21.odt-J
			<lb />
		</note>
		<body>
			died in the year 2015, they could not have any cause of action or reason
			<lb />
			to raise any dispute before that and when the said ex gratia amount/
			<lb />
			additional compensation amount was to be disbursed, the cause arose for
			<lb />
			the petitioner No.1 to apply to the Collector under section 30 of the Act.
			<lb />
			Much emphasis was placed on a Will Deed dated 23/09/2013 executed
			<lb />
			by the mother of the petitioners, in support of the aforesaid contention.
			<lb />
			29.
			<lb />
			On this basis, the petitioners claim that since they had made
			<lb />
			out a semblance of case as regards the cause of action and their
			<lb />
			entitlement towards share in the ex gratia amount to be disbursed in the
			<lb />
			year 2017, the Civil Court could not have passed the impugned order to
			<lb />
			throw out the reference at the outset. The petitioners claim that the
			<lb />
			proceeding ought to have travelled its full course and then the Civil Court
			<lb />
			could have reached conclusions in the matter.
			<lb />
			30.
			<lb />
			This Court is of the opinion that the Civil Court was certainly
			<lb />
			entitled to analyze the material on record for reaching a conclusion as to
			<lb />
			whether the reference could be maintained or not. A perusal of the
			<lb />
			impugned order shows that the Civil Court found that the amount in
			<lb />
			question was not compensation as determined under the provisions of the
			<lb />
			Act and the said amount was not available for disbursal pursuant to
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			KHUNTE
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			21/23
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			WP-1415.21.odt-J
			<lb />
		</note>
		<body>
			award pronounced under section 11 of the said Act. Thus, the Civil Court
			<lb />
			applied its mind and found that the petitioners could not raise dispute
			<lb />
			under section 30 of the Act as regards the said ex gratia amount. Having
			<lb />
			reached the said conclusion, the Civil Court was well within its
			<lb />
			jurisdiction to consider whether the reference was at all required to be
			<lb />
			proceeded with. Even if the Civil Court was not right in referring to
			<lb />
			withdrawal of the reference by the Collector, the impugned order shows
			<lb />
			that reference was made to section 11 of the Act and in that backdrop, it
			<lb />
			was found that the ex gratia amount could not be said to be an amount in
			<lb />
			respect of which a dispute could at all be raised under section 30 of the
			<lb />
			Act.
			<lb />
			31.
			<lb />
			The claim made by the petitioners about the manner in which
			<lb />
			the cause of action arose for them is too far-fetched and it certainly did
			<lb />
			not merit any kind of consideration or determination by the Civil Court
			<lb />
			exercising jurisdiction under section 30 of the said Act.
			<lb />
			32.
			<lb />
			Insofar as the judgments on which reliance was placed by the
			<lb />
			learned senior counsel for the petitioners, there can be no quarrel with
			<lb />
			the proposition that section 30 of the Act does not prescribe limitation as
			<lb />
			held by the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court in the case of Dr. G.H. Grant v. The
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			KHUNTE
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			22/23
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			WP-1415.21.odt-J
			<lb />
		</note>
		<body>
			State of Bihar (supra). But as noted above, in the judgment in the case of
			<lb />
			Meher Rusi Dalal v. Union of India (supra), the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court
			<lb />
			itself has held that application under section 30 of the Act ought to be
			<lb />
			moved within reasonable time. As regards the reliance placed on
			<lb />
			Sunderlal v. Paramsukhdas and Sharda Devi v. State of Bihar (supra),
			<lb />
			section 30 of the Act would be available to the petitioners only if they
			<lb />
			could be said to be persons interested in compensation as determined
			<lb />
			under section 11 of the Act. The said judgments cannot be of any
			<lb />
			assistance to the petitioners in the facts and circumstances of the present
			<lb />
			case.
			<lb />
			33.
			<lb />
			In view of the above, this Court is of the opinion that there is
			<lb />
			no substance in the contentions raised on behalf of the petitioners. The
			<lb />
			Civil Court cannot be said to have committed any error in allowing the
			<lb />
			application filed by the respondent No.10 at Exhibit-55 and in dismissing
			<lb />
			the reference under section 30 of the Act. Nonetheless, the petitioners
			<lb />
			may file civil suit, if so advised, as regards their grievance, as indicated in
			<lb />
			judgment of this court in the case of Comunidade of Bambolim v.
			<lb />
			Manguesh Betu Kankonkar (supra). If the petitioners choose to file such a
			<lb />
			civil suit, it would be decided by the competent civil court in accordance
			<lb />
			with law, without being influenced by the observations made herein.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			KHUNTE
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			23/23
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			WP-1415.21.odt-J
			<lb />
		</note>
		<front>
			34.
			<lb />
			Accordingly, the writ petition is dismissed. The interim order
			<lb />
			dated 22/03/2021 is vacated.
			<lb />
			35.
			<lb />
			Pending application(s), if any, is(are) disposed of.
			<lb />
			36.
			<lb />
			Rule stands discharged. No costs.
			<lb />
			JUDGE
			<lb />
			KHUNTE
			<lb />
		</front>
		<note place="footnote">
			Signed By:GHANSHYAM S
			<lb />
			KHUNTE
			<lb />
			Signing Date:07.07.2022 17:18
		</note>
	</text>
</tei>
