<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<note place="headnote">
			901.apeal.593.2018 judge.odt
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			1
			<lb />
		</page>
		<front>
			IN THE HIGH COURT OF JUDICATURE AT BOMBAY
			<lb />
			NAGPUR BENCH, NAGPUR.
			<lb />
			CRIMINAL APPEAL NO. 593 OF 2018
			<lb />
			Siddharth @ Bollywood S/o. Bapurao Meshram
			<lb />
			Convict No.C-9471 detained in Central Prison,
			<lb />
			Nagpur, Aged about 40 yrs, Occ. Labourer,
			<lb />
			R/o. Masters Colony, Wardha, Tahsil &amp;
			<lb />
			District Wardha
			<lb />
			..
			<lb />
			APPELLANT
			<lb />
			...VERSUS...
			<lb />
			1. State of Maharashtra,
			<lb />
			Through P.S.O., Wardha,
			<lb />
			Tah. &amp; Distt. Wardha
			<lb />
			2. XYZ (Victim) Complainant /
			<lb />
			Informant, In Crime 44/2013,
			<lb />
			Registered in Police Station,
			<lb />
			Wardha City, Wardha.
			<lb />
			..
			<lb />
			RESPONDENTS
			<lb />
			-----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------
			<lb />
			Shri R. R. Vyas, Advocate (Appt.) for the appellant
			<lb />
			Shri S. S. Doifode, APP for the respondent No.1
			<lb />
			-----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------
			<lb />
			CORAM : SUNIL B. SHUKRE AND G. A. SANAP , J J .
			<lb />
			RESERVED ON : 22/06/ 20 22
			<lb />
			PRONOUNCED ON : 12/07/2022
			<lb />
			JUDGMENT : (PER : G. A. SANAP, J)
			<lb />
		</front>
		<body>
			1]
			<lb />
			In this appeal, challenge is to the Judgment and order, dated
			<lb />
			15.11.2016, passed by the learned Special Judge, Wardha whereby the
			<lb />
			appellant came to be convicted for the offences punishable under Section
			<lb />
			376 (2)(i), Section 506 of the Indian Penal Code [for short &apos;IPC&apos;] and
			<lb />
			under Section 4 of the Protection of Children from Sexual Offences Act,
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="headnote">
			901.apeal.593.2018 judge.odt
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			2
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			2012 [for short &apos;POCSO Act&apos;] and sentenced to suffer rigorous
			<lb />
			imprisonment for life and to pay fine of Rs.5,000/-and in default of
			<lb />
			payment of fine to suffer rigorous imprisonment for six months under
			<lb />
			Section 376(2)(i) of the IPC and rigorous imprisonment for two years and
			<lb />
			to pay a fine of Rs.1000/-and in default of payment of fine to suffer
			<lb />
			rigorous imprisonment for three months under Section 506 of the Indian
			<lb />
			Penal Code. No separate sentence has been awarded for the offence
			<lb />
			punishable under Section 4 of the POCSO Act.
			<lb />
			2]
			<lb />
			The facts leading to this appeal are as follows:
			<lb />
			In order to hide the identity of the minor girl in this
			<lb />
			Judgment she is referred as &apos;victim&apos;.
			<lb />
			PW-5-Jyoti is the mother of the victim. First Information
			<lb />
			Report was registered on her oral report dated 18.01.2013. PW-5,
			<lb />
			mother of the victim, had reported to the police that the appellant
			<lb />
			Sidharth @ Bollywood Meshram was residing at his sister&apos;s house in the
			<lb />
			same locality. The victim was born on 16.08.2005. At the time of
			<lb />
			incident the victim was studying in 2 nd standard. She has stated in her
			<lb />
			report that on 18.01.2013 in the evening she came to know about the
			<lb />
			incident. She is doing work as a Maid Servant. When she came back
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="headnote">
			901.apeal.593.2018 judge.odt
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			3
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			from her work at 19:00 hours, the women from her locality namely Jangle
			<lb />
			Madam, Kale bai and mother of one Jugal were standing near her house.
			<lb />
			The victim was with them. At that time, Jangle Madam informed her that
			<lb />
			the appellant had committed outrageous act with the victim. Jangle
			<lb />
			Madam in brief narrated the incident to her. The informant took the
			<lb />
			victim to her house. On her inquiry the victim disclosed that 7 days
			<lb />
			before, the appellant on the pretext of giving chocolate took her in his
			<lb />
			house. The appellant shut the door of his house. The appellant told her
			<lb />
			that she had worn her undergarments on a wrong side. The appellant
			<lb />
			removed her undergarment as well as removed his clothes. The appellant
			<lb />
			slept on her body. The appellant touched his private part to the private
			<lb />
			part of the victim. The victim started shouting. The appellant gagged her
			<lb />
			mouth and threatened her not to shout. It is stated that the victim further
			<lb />
			informed PW-5 that the appellant threatened her to repeat the said act if
			<lb />
			the incident was disclosed by the victim to anybody. On the next day in
			<lb />
			the morning i.e. on 19.01.2013 PW-5 with the victim went to the Police
			<lb />
			Station and reported the matter to the police. On the basis of her report,
			<lb />
			crime bearing No. 44 of 2013, for the above offences, came to be
			<lb />
			registered against the appellant. PW-7 Vanmala Pardhi, API, attached to
			<lb />
			Wardha City Police Station conducted the investigation. She sent the
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="headnote">
			901.apeal.593.2018 judge.odt
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			4
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			victim for medical examination. She also sent the appellant, on arrest, for
			<lb />
			medical examination. PW-7 drew the spot panchnama. Various articles
			<lb />
			and blood samples were seized during the investigation. PW-7 recorded
			<lb />
			the statements of the witnesses and on completion of the investigation
			<lb />
			filed the charge-sheet against the appellant in Special Court.
			<lb />
			3]
			<lb />
			The learned Special Judge vide Exh. 3 framed the charge
			<lb />
			against the appellant. The appellant on being explained the contents of
			<lb />
			the Charge pleaded not guilty to the charge. His defence is of total denial.
			<lb />
			In order to bring home guilt of the appellant, the prosecution examined 8
			<lb />
			witnesses. The prosecution tendered documentary evidence. The learned
			<lb />
			Special Judge on consideration of the material on record, found the
			<lb />
			appellant guilty of the above offences and convicted the appellant and
			<lb />
			sentenced him as above. Being aggrieved by this Judgment and order, the
			<lb />
			appellant has come before this Court in appeal.
			<lb />
			4]
			<lb />
			We have heard the learned Advocate for the appellant and
			<lb />
			learned APP for the State. We have perused the record and proceedings.
			<lb />
			5]
			<lb />
			The learned Advocate appearing for the appellant submitted
			<lb />
			that the delay initially in reporting the incident by victim to PW-5 and
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="headnote">
			901.apeal.593.2018 judge.odt
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			5
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			PW-6 and the delay of one day in lodging the actual report has not been
			<lb />
			explained. In the submission of the learned Advocate, considering
			<lb />
			seriousness of the charges, the delay ought to have been explained and in
			<lb />
			the absence of explanation the learned Judge ought to have granted the
			<lb />
			benefit of doubt to the appellant. The learned Advocate further
			<lb />
			submitted that there are material omissions and inconsistencies in the
			<lb />
			evidence of the victim as well as in the evidence of PW-5 mother of the
			<lb />
			victim and PW-6 Mrs Jangle. The learned Advocate submitted that as
			<lb />
			such there is a scope to doubt the credibility of these witnesses. The
			<lb />
			learned Advocate submitted that the evidence of the victim does not
			<lb />
			inspire confidence and therefore, the version of the victim on the point of
			<lb />
			the incident is required to be discarded. The learned Advocate submitted
			<lb />
			that the medical evidence of the examination of the victim does not
			<lb />
			corroborate the evidence of the victim as well as the evidence of PW-5
			<lb />
			and PW-6. In the submission of the learned Advocate for the appellant,
			<lb />
			therefore, in the teeth of such a shaky evidence, the defence of the
			<lb />
			appellant of the false implication becomes probable.
			<lb />
			6]
			<lb />
			The learned APP submitted that the evidence of Medical
			<lb />
			Officer PW-3 Dr. Krushna Shende, who had examined the victim, is
			<lb />
			cogent and reliable. The oral evidence of the medical officer has been
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="headnote">
			901.apeal.593.2018 judge.odt
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			6
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			corroborated by his medical examination report at Exh. 19. The learned
			<lb />
			APP submitted that the history of assault was narrated by victim girl to
			<lb />
			the medical officer PW-3 and it was recorded by PW-3 in Exh. 19. It is
			<lb />
			submitted that the history of assault narrated to an independent witness
			<lb />
			makes the evidence of the victim credible. The learned APP submitted
			<lb />
			that the opinion of the medical officer that the hymen was partially
			<lb />
			ruptured and which indicated the attempt of the intercourse with the
			<lb />
			victim has not at all been shaken. The learned APP submitted that the
			<lb />
			learned Special Judge found the evidence of the victim, as well as the
			<lb />
			evidence of PW-5 and PW-6, on the point of actual occurrence credible.
			<lb />
			In the submission of the learned APP there is no reason to disbelieve and
			<lb />
			discard the evidence of victim and the evidence of PW-5 and PW-6. The
			<lb />
			learned APP submitted that in fact there was no delay, in as much as, the
			<lb />
			victim narrated the incident which had occurred 7 days prior to
			<lb />
			18.01.2013. The learned APP submitted that the PW-5 has placed on
			<lb />
			record the explanation for lodging the report on the next day morning.
			<lb />
			The learned APP submitted that the Judgment and Order passed by the
			<lb />
			learned Special Judge is well reasoned and does not warrant interference.
			<lb />
			7]
			<lb />
			We have minutely perused the evidence of the prosecution
			<lb />
			witnesses. As per the case of prosecution, on the date of the incident, the
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="headnote">
			901.apeal.593.2018 judge.odt
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			7
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			victim was about 7 years old. Exh. 103 is the birth registration certificate
			<lb />
			of the victim. The same has been admitted by the defence Advocate
			<lb />
			before the trial Court. The date of birth mentioned in this certificate is
			<lb />
			16.08.2005. In our view, therefore, this undisputed evidence proves that
			<lb />
			on the date of the incident the victim was 7 yrs 4 months 26 days old. It
			<lb />
			is also not disputed that the appellant was residing at the house of his
			<lb />
			sister in the same locality. It has come in the evidence that there are 5-7
			<lb />
			houses in between the house of the PW-5 and the house of the sister of
			<lb />
			the appellant, where he was resided. There is no dispute about the
			<lb />
			identification of the appellant inasmuch as he was known to the victim
			<lb />
			and to the witnesses before the incident.
			<lb />
			8]
			<lb />
			The perusal of the Judgment of the learned Special Judge
			<lb />
			would show that on minute scrutiny and appreciation of the evidence, the
			<lb />
			learned Judge found the evidence of PW-5 &amp; PW-6 and victim worthy of
			<lb />
			credence. In order to satisfy ourselves about the credibility and reliability
			<lb />
			of the said evidence we have minutely perused the same. The victim has
			<lb />
			categorically stated before the Court about the incident. Her evidence on
			<lb />
			the point of occurrence of the incident is consistent with the one reported
			<lb />
			to the police by PW-5. She has stated that on the date of incident, which
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="headnote">
			901.apeal.593.2018 judge.odt
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			8
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			occurred seven days prior to 18.01.2013, she alongwith other children
			<lb />
			from her neighborhood was playing the game of hide and seek, in front of
			<lb />
			the house of the appellant. She has stated that the appellant came there.
			<lb />
			She has further stated that the appellant called her to his house on the
			<lb />
			pretext of giving chocolate. She went there. The appellant, thereafter,
			<lb />
			closed the door. The appellant told her that she had worn her knickers on
			<lb />
			wrong side. On this pretext, the appellant removed her knickers and slept
			<lb />
			on her person. In her further evidence she has stated that when she cried,
			<lb />
			the appellant gagged her mouth. The appellant after her cries set her free.
			<lb />
			She has stated that the appellant threatened her to repeat the same act, if
			<lb />
			the incident was disclosed to anybody. She has stated that she went to the
			<lb />
			house of PW-6 Jangle Madam and narrated the incident to her. She has
			<lb />
			also deposed that when her mother returned home from work she
			<lb />
			narrated the incident to her.
			<lb />
			9]
			<lb />
			PW-8 is the child witness. Her competence to depose before
			<lb />
			the Court was verified by the learned Judge before recording her
			<lb />
			evidence. On the basis of the some of the admissions given by her, on the
			<lb />
			point of her visits to the Court on 8-10 occasions, it is pointed out that
			<lb />
			PW-8 is the tutored witness and therefore, it would not be safe to rely on
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="headnote">
			901.apeal.593.2018 judge.odt
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			9
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			her testimony. Save and except this material, despite searching cross
			<lb />
			examination, the core of her evidence has not been shaken. She has
			<lb />
			admitted in her cross examination that Jangle Madam is not her class
			<lb />
			teacher or teacher in the School, where she is studying. It has come on
			<lb />
			record in her cross examination that Jangle Madam is residing near to
			<lb />
			their house. She has further stated in her cross examination that on the
			<lb />
			date of incident, her elder sister was also playing with her. In further part
			<lb />
			of her cross examination she has admitted that the appellant often used to
			<lb />
			come to her house. She has denied the suggestion that the quarrel had
			<lb />
			taken place between her father and the appellant. She has denied the
			<lb />
			other suggestions put to her on the point of the incident. As far as the
			<lb />
			aspect of the penetration or intercourse is concerned, this witness has not
			<lb />
			specifically stated about it. She has stated that after removing her knickers
			<lb />
			the appellant slept on her body. In our opinion, the understanding of a
			<lb />
			child of 7 years about such an act needs to be borne in mind. The age of
			<lb />
			the victim at the time of incident was such that she was easily lured by the
			<lb />
			appellant to accompany him on the pretext of giving chocolate to her. In
			<lb />
			her evidence she has categorically stated that after removing her knickers,
			<lb />
			the appellant had removed all his clothes. In our opinion, this is very vital
			<lb />
			aspect, deposed by PW-8. The evidence of PW-8, in our opinion, is
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="headnote">
			901.apeal.593.2018 judge.odt
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			10
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			sufficient to establish the incident as narrated by the victim. The minute
			<lb />
			scrutiny of the evidence of the victim would show that she has narrated
			<lb />
			the incident occurred with her without any exaggeration. If the appellant
			<lb />
			was falsely implicated, as suggested on his behalf, then in that event the
			<lb />
			child witness would have been easily caught unaware on certain relevant
			<lb />
			aspects in her cross examination. Perusal of her cross examination would
			<lb />
			show that she could not be slightly deviated from the core and crux of
			<lb />
			her evidence touching the incident. On minute scrutiny and appreciation
			<lb />
			of her evidence we are satisfied that the possibility of tutoring the child
			<lb />
			witness has been completely ruled out. It is further pertinent to note that
			<lb />
			the parents of the victim girl would have other ways and means to take
			<lb />
			revenge of enmity, if any, they had with the appellant. The parents of the
			<lb />
			victim would not have put the future life and dignity of the victim at stake
			<lb />
			just for the sake of taking revenge.
			<lb />
			10]
			<lb />
			It is to be noted that the PW-6 Sarla Jangle is an independent
			<lb />
			witness. No material has been brought on record in her cross
			<lb />
			examination even to suggest that PW-6 was on inimical terms with the
			<lb />
			appellant or had grudge against the appellant for one reason or the other.
			<lb />
			PW-5 is the mother of the victim. As per the evidence of the victim for
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="headnote">
			901.apeal.593.2018 judge.odt
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			11
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			the first time she narrated the incident to PW-6 Jangle Madam. It would,
			<lb />
			therefore, be necessary to minutely scrutinize her evidence. She has
			<lb />
			stated that the incident took place in January 2013. She has stated that in
			<lb />
			the evening at about 7:00 p.m. when she was standing in front of her
			<lb />
			house with Smt Kale, Smt. Burkunde and Smt. Waghmare, who are also
			<lb />
			residing in the same locality, the victim came there. She has further
			<lb />
			stated that the victim told her the act committed by the appellant. In her
			<lb />
			evidence, PW-6 has specifically stated that victim told her that after
			<lb />
			removing her clothes, the appellant undressed himself and slept over her.
			<lb />
			She has further stated that the victim told her that, thereafter, the
			<lb />
			appellant did something to her private part. She has further stated that
			<lb />
			the victim told her that when she shouted, the appellant gagged her
			<lb />
			mouth and told her not to shout. She has stated after some time the
			<lb />
			mother of the victim PW-5 came there and thereafter, she narrated the
			<lb />
			incident told to her by victim to PW-5. In her cross examination she has
			<lb />
			admitted that the victim was not studying in her school. The victim was
			<lb />
			studying in different primary school. She has stated in her cross
			<lb />
			examination that the appellant is also known as Bollywood kaka. In her
			<lb />
			cross examination, her statement that she is residing near to the house of
			<lb />
			the victim and the house of the appellant is not at all disputed. Perusal of
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="headnote">
			901.apeal.593.2018 judge.odt
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			12
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			her cross examination would show that the mother of the victim used to
			<lb />
			visit her house during her working hours. Her statement was recorded by
			<lb />
			the police. She had narrated all the facts to the police at the time of
			<lb />
			recording of her statement. The perusal of her evidence in entirety would
			<lb />
			show that she is an independent witness. She had no reason to falsely
			<lb />
			implicate the appellant. Perusal of her evidence would show that, being a
			<lb />
			teacher, the victim was knowing her. The victim had trust and faith in
			<lb />
			her. As stated by PW-6, she alongwith other women from the locality was
			<lb />
			standing in front of her house and at that time the victim came there and
			<lb />
			narrated the incident to her in presence of the other women. This fact
			<lb />
			would further indicate that the victim found the PW-6 a reliable and
			<lb />
			trustworthy person to disclose the incident. The learned Judge on
			<lb />
			appreciation of the evidence has accepted the evidence of PW-6, as
			<lb />
			trustworthy and reliable. We do not see any reason to take different view
			<lb />
			on the credibility and reliability of evidence of PW-6 Jangle Madam.
			<lb />
			11]
			<lb />
			PW-5, as stated above, is the mother of the victim. The
			<lb />
			father of the victim is Attorney of one Advocate Mr. Bade at Wardha. An
			<lb />
			attempt has been made in the cross examination of PW-5 to bring on
			<lb />
			record that on the point of consuming liquor there was quarrel between
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="headnote">
			901.apeal.593.2018 judge.odt
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			13
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			the father of the victim and appellant and therefore, to take revenge the
			<lb />
			appellant was falsely implicated. It would be necessary to bear this line of
			<lb />
			cross examination in the mind while appreciating the evidence of PW-5.
			<lb />
			She has stated that the appellant is friend of her husband and therefore, he
			<lb />
			used to come to their house. While narrating her daily routine she has
			<lb />
			stated that she does work as a maid servant at 7-8 houses and comes back
			<lb />
			to her house in the evening after work. She has stated that when she came
			<lb />
			back at 7:00 p.m., she found Jangle Madam, Kale bai and mother of one
			<lb />
			Jugal standing near her house. The victim was also with them. She has
			<lb />
			stated that at that time PW-6 Jangle Madam informed her the outrageous
			<lb />
			act committed by the appellant with the victim. In her evidence she has
			<lb />
			narrated the incident as stated by PW-6. She has further stated that the
			<lb />
			victim informed her that the appellant had touched his private part with
			<lb />
			her private part and when she started shouting the appellant gagged her
			<lb />
			mouth. She has stated that the victim told her that the incident had
			<lb />
			occurred 8 days prior. In her cross examination an attempt has been
			<lb />
			made to point out that on the point of penetration there was a material
			<lb />
			omission in her report as well as in her statement. The omission as can be
			<lb />
			seen from the report at Exh. 33 is on the point of actual use of a word
			<lb />
			&apos;private part&apos;. However, the sum and substance of her report is that there
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="headnote">
			901.apeal.593.2018 judge.odt
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			14
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			was an attempt by the appellant to do some act at her private part on 2-3
			<lb />
			occasions.
			<lb />
			12]
			<lb />
			This witness was subjected to searching cross examination,
			<lb />
			but the same has not made her evidence shaky. In her cross examination
			<lb />
			she has admitted that her husband works as an Attorney with an Advocate
			<lb />
			Mr. Bade and the said Advocate had come to their house on that day.
			<lb />
			The omission as to the private part has been properly recorded by the
			<lb />
			learned Judge. The remaining cross examination would show that she has
			<lb />
			not exaggerated the incident or facts related to incident. Perusal of her
			<lb />
			cross examination would also show that no material has been elicited in
			<lb />
			her cross examination to make the defence of the appellant probable. On
			<lb />
			the contrary, the perusal of her cross examination would show that the
			<lb />
			appellant would come to her house with her husband. This would
			<lb />
			indicate that they were on good terms. In our opinion, this could be one
			<lb />
			of the reasons for the victim to trust the appellant when he lured her to
			<lb />
			his house on the pretext of giving chocolate.
			<lb />
			13]
			<lb />
			The evidence of victim girl, PW-5 Jyoti and the evidence
			<lb />
			independent witness PW-6 Sarla Jangle has not been shaken in the cross
			<lb />
			examination. On minute scrutiny and appreciation of the evidence we
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="headnote">
			901.apeal.593.2018 judge.odt
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			15
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			have not come across any material to discard or disbelieve the said
			<lb />
			evidence. The searching cross examination has not made the said
			<lb />
			evidence shaky and unbelievable. No dent has been caused to the core of
			<lb />
			their evidence on the point of the incident. The evidence is sufficient to
			<lb />
			prove that the appellant indulged in the act narrated by them.
			<lb />
			14]
			<lb />
			In this context, it would be necessary to appreciate the
			<lb />
			evidence of the medical officer. PW-3 Dr. Krushna Shende had examined
			<lb />
			the victim. On examination PW-3 has opined that the hymen of the
			<lb />
			victim was partially ruptured indicating an attempt of intercourse with the
			<lb />
			victim. Exh. 19 is the medical examination report of the victim. A
			<lb />
			perusal of the report would show that the history of the assault or incident
			<lb />
			was recorded by the medical officer, as narrated by the father and victim.
			<lb />
			In cross examination the medical officer has stated that the history of the
			<lb />
			assault or incident was narrated by the victim first and later on by her
			<lb />
			father. He has further admitted that while playing cycle or while playing,
			<lb />
			the hymen can be ruptured. Relying upon this admission, it is submitted
			<lb />
			that the opinion of the medical officer that the victim was subjected to
			<lb />
			attempt of sexual intercourse based on the partially ruptured hymen,
			<lb />
			cannot be relied upon. It is to be noted that the incident of sexual assault
			<lb />
			took place 8 days prior to the examination of the victim. The victim in
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="headnote">
			901.apeal.593.2018 judge.odt
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			16
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			her evidence narrated the actual incident. In our opinion, the evidence of
			<lb />
			the medical officer is a very vital piece of evidence. The same
			<lb />
			corroborates the oral evidence of the victim PW-8, PW-5 &amp; PW-6. The
			<lb />
			victim girl at the time of incident was 7 years old. It is not the defence of
			<lb />
			the appellant that while playing a cycle or due to fall while playing, the
			<lb />
			hymen of the victim got ruptured. The evidence of the medical officer is
			<lb />
			independent. The opinion of the medical officer is based on the
			<lb />
			examination of the victim and the symptoms found by him. Therefore,
			<lb />
			we do not see any reason to discard and disbelieve his evidence.
			<lb />
			15]
			<lb />
			The learned Advocate took us through the evidence of PW-2
			<lb />
			Dr. Jaichand Moon, who had examined the appellant. The report of the
			<lb />
			examination of the appellant given by the PW-2 is at Exh. 16. One of the
			<lb />
			objects behind his medical examination was to get a concrete opinion
			<lb />
			about the capability of the appellant to perform sexual act. PW-2 has
			<lb />
			stated that no opinion was given by him as to whether the appellant could
			<lb />
			perform sexual intercourse or not. He has further stated that he had not
			<lb />
			applied any test on the appellant to come to the conclusion that he is able
			<lb />
			to perform sexual intercourse or not. In our view, this opinion given by
			<lb />
			PW-2 medical officer seems to be without conducting any test on the
			<lb />
			appellant. It is further pertinent to note that the medical officer has not
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="headnote">
			901.apeal.593.2018 judge.odt
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			17
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			given a negative opinion stating that he is not at all capable to perform
			<lb />
			sexual act. If the opinion had been negative then the same would have
			<lb />
			carried some weight. PW-2 had collected his blood as well as his semen
			<lb />
			samples. The perusal of his evidence would show that without
			<lb />
			conducting the proper test the opinion was given. The manner of
			<lb />
			examination of the appellant and the opinion indicate that the PW-2 did
			<lb />
			not take proper care. Be that as it may, since the opinion is not negative,
			<lb />
			the same could not extend any help to the appellant.
			<lb />
			16]
			<lb />
			The other evidence relied upon by the prosecution is of the
			<lb />
			panch witness about the spot panchanama and collection of samples. The
			<lb />
			evidence of the Investigating Officer would show that during the course
			<lb />
			of investigation the seized articles and the samples collected by the
			<lb />
			medical officer PW-2 and PW-3 were forwarded to the CA for analysis.
			<lb />
			The reports of CA have been admitted by the appellant. The CA did not
			<lb />
			detect the semen or blood on the articles seized from the house of the
			<lb />
			appellant. The investigating officer PW-7 has deposed that she drew the
			<lb />
			spot panchnama in presence of the panch witness. The panch witness
			<lb />
			PW-1 to the spot has turned hostile. However, the evidence of the
			<lb />
			investigating officer is sufficient to accept the case of the prosecution that
			<lb />
			after lodging the report, PW-7 paid visit to the spot and on examination
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="headnote">
			901.apeal.593.2018 judge.odt
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			18
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			of the spot drew the spot panchanama. The occurrence of the incident in
			<lb />
			the house of the appellant has been stated by eye witnesses PW-5, PW-6
			<lb />
			and victim PW-8. The investigating officer in her evidence has described
			<lb />
			the spot in great detail. The investigating officer is an independent
			<lb />
			witness. No material has been brought on record in her cross
			<lb />
			examination to suggest the possibility of false implication of the appellant
			<lb />
			in this case.
			<lb />
			17]
			<lb />
			On minute scrutiny and appreciation of the evidence, we
			<lb />
			found that the evidence adduced by the prosecution is sufficient to prove
			<lb />
			the charge. The learned Special Judge has recorded the reasons for
			<lb />
			accepting the evidence adduced by the prosecution. On re-appreciation
			<lb />
			of evidence, we do not see any reason to discard and disbelieve the
			<lb />
			evidence and take a view different from the one taken by the learned
			<lb />
			Special Judge in this case.
			<lb />
			18]
			<lb />
			The learned Advocate for the appellant to substantiate his
			<lb />
			submission placed reliance on the decision in the case of Hari Om @
			<lb />
			Hero .v/s. State of Uttar Pradesh, reported in (2021) 4 SCC 345 and the
			<lb />
			decision of the Division Bench of this Court at Principal Seat Bombay in
			<lb />
			Criminal Appeal No. 1006 of 2019, in the case of Ali Mohammed Shaikh
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="headnote">
			901.apeal.593.2018 judge.odt
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			19
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			.v/s. State of Maharashtra, decided on 14.12.2020, that no reliance can be
			<lb />
			placed on the evidence of PW-8 victim being a child witness, in view of
			<lb />
			the discrepancies on material aspect noticed in her evidence. In the case of
			<lb />
			Hari Om @ Hero (supra) Hon&apos;ble Apex Court has held that in the
			<lb />
			absence of corroboration to the child witness, the evidence of a child
			<lb />
			witness with discrepancies on material aspect cannot be made the basis to
			<lb />
			convict the accused. Same is the view of the Division Bench in the case of
			<lb />
			Ali Mohammed Shaikh (supra). In our opinion, for the reasons recorded
			<lb />
			herein above on the point of credibility of the evidence of child witness
			<lb />
			and the credibility of independent witnesses PW-5 and PW-6 to
			<lb />
			corroborate the evidence of child witness on material aspect, the
			<lb />
			proposition would be of no help and assistance to the case of the
			<lb />
			appellant. In the case before Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court as well as the
			<lb />
			Division bench of this Court there was no corroboration at all to the
			<lb />
			evidence of a child witness. The facts brought on record and the evidence
			<lb />
			of a child witness in those cases was found unreliable. In our opinion, in
			<lb />
			the case in hand, the evidence has been found fully reliable. The
			<lb />
			corroborative evidence available on record lends an assurance to the
			<lb />
			evidence of victim.
			<lb />
			19]
			<lb />
			We, therefore, conclude that on merits there is no substance
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="headnote">
			901.apeal.593.2018 judge.odt
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			20
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			in the appeal. The appeal, therefore, deserves to be dismissed.
			<lb />
			20]
			<lb />
			On the quantum of a sentence, the learned Advocate for the
			<lb />
			appellant pointed out that the incident occurred in January 2013. The
			<lb />
			offence proved against the appellant is under Section 4 of the POCSO Act
			<lb />
			and under Section 376(2)(i) of the IPC. The learned Advocate submitted
			<lb />
			that considering the punishment provided for this offence before
			<lb />
			amendment of Section 4 of the POCSO Act, with effect from
			<lb />
			16.08.2019, the learned Judge was not right in awarding sentence of life
			<lb />
			imprisonment to the appellant. The learned Advocate submitted that the
			<lb />
			appellant was 40 years old at the time of the incident. It is submitted that
			<lb />
			considering his age and other circumstances, the learned Judge ought to
			<lb />
			have taken a lenient view while awarding the sentence. It is seen that no
			<lb />
			separate sentence has been awarded under Section 4 of the POCSO Act.
			<lb />
			Before amendment to Section 4 of the POCSO Act, the punishment
			<lb />
			provided for committing penetrative sexual assault, shall not be less than
			<lb />
			7 years but which may extend to imprisonment for life and shall also be
			<lb />
			liable to fine. Before amendment to Section 376(2)(i) of the IPC, with
			<lb />
			effect from 21.04.2018, the punishment provided for committing
			<lb />
			penetrative sexual assault, on a child below 16 years of age, shall not be
			<lb />
			less than 10 years but which may extend to imprisonment for life, which
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="headnote">
			901.apeal.593.2018 judge.odt
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			21
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			shall mean imprisonment for the remainder of that person&apos;s natural life.
			<lb />
			Section 376-AB has been inserted in the IPC with effect from 21.04.2018
			<lb />
			which provides punishment for rape on a woman under 12 years of age.
			<lb />
			The punishment prescribed is similar to the one prescribed under Section
			<lb />
			4 (2) of the POCSO Act namely imprisonment for a term which shall not
			<lb />
			be less than 20 years, but which may extend to imprisonment for life,
			<lb />
			which shall mean imprisonment for remainder of that person&apos;s natural
			<lb />
			life.
			<lb />
			21]
			<lb />
			In this case, considering the mitigating and aggravating
			<lb />
			circumstances placed on record, in our view, the sentence awarded by the
			<lb />
			learned Judge would be dis-proportionate in the peculiar facts and
			<lb />
			circumstances. In our considered opinion, the rigorous imprisonment for
			<lb />
			a period of 12 years would meet the ends of justice. We, therefore,
			<lb />
			conclude that on the quantum of sentence, the order passed by learned
			<lb />
			Special Judge would be required to be modified.
			<lb />
			22]
			<lb />
			We appreciate the able assistance extended by the learned
			<lb />
			APP Shri S. S. Doifode and learned Advocate Shri R. R. Vyas, at the
			<lb />
			request of this Court.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="headnote">
			901.apeal.593.2018 judge.odt
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			22
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			O RDER
			<lb />
			i]
			<lb />
			Appeal is dismissed with the following modification in the
			<lb />
			substantive sentence.
			<lb />
			ii]
			<lb />
			The sentence of imprisonment for life awarded by the learned
			<lb />
			Special Judge is modified. The appellant is sentenced to suffer rigorous
			<lb />
			imprisonment for 12 years, for the offence punishable under Section
			<lb />
			376(2)(i) of the Indian Penal Code with a benefit of set-off as provided by
			<lb />
			the trial Court.
			<lb />
			iii]
			<lb />
			The fees payable to Shri R. R. Vyas, learned Advocate appointed
			<lb />
			for the appellant from the High Court Legal Services Sub Committee,
			<lb />
			Nagpur, is quantified at Rs.15,000/-.
			<lb />
			The criminal appeal stands disposed of.
			<lb />
			(G. A. SANAP, J.)
			<lb />
			(SUNIL B. SHUKRE, J.)
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="fotnote">
			Namrata
			<lb />
			Signed By:NAMRATA YOGESH
			<lb />
			DHARKAR
			<lb />
			P. A.
			<lb />
			High Court Nagpur
			<lb />
			Signing Date:12.07.2022 16:40
		</note>
	</text>
</tei>
