<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<page>
			1
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			331 apeal352.19(J).odt
			<lb />
		</note>
		<front>
			IN THE HIGH COURT OF JUDICATURE AT BOMBAY
			<lb />
			: NAGPUR BENCH : NAGPUR.
			<lb />
			CRIMINAL APPEAL NO. 352 OF 20 19
			<lb />
			APPELLANT
			<lb />
			: Nivrutti Ninaji Ghule,
			<lb />
			Aged about 56 years, Occu. Labour
			<lb />
			R/o Bhota, Tq. Nandura, Dist. Buldhana.
			<lb />
			VERSUS
			<lb />
			RESPONDENT
			<lb />
			: State of Maharashtra,
			<lb />
			Through The Officer In charge,
			<lb />
			Jalamb Police Station,
			<lb />
			Tq. Shegaon, Dist. Buldhana.
			<lb />
			----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------
			<lb />
			Shri M. L. Chouhan, Advocate (appointed) for the Appellant.
			<lb />
			Shri M. J. Khan, A.P.P. for the respondent / State
			<lb />
			----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------
			<lb />
			CORAM : SUNIL B. SHUKRE and G. A. SANAP, JJ.
			<lb />
			Judgment Reserved on
			<lb />
			: JULY 01, 20 22 .
			<lb />
			Judgment Pronounced on : JULY 12 , 2022
			<lb />
			JUDGMENT : (Per : G. A. SANAP, J.)
			<lb />
		</front>
		<body>
			1.
			<lb />
			In this appeal, challenge is to the judgment and order
			<lb />
			dated 28 th December, 2018 passed by the learned Additional Sessions
			<lb />
			Judge, Khamgaon, Dist. Buldhana, in Sessions Trial No. 45 of 2013,
			<lb />
			whereby the learned Judge has convicted the appellant for the
			<lb />
			offence punishable under Section 302 of the Indian Penal Code and
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			2
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			331 apeal352.19(J).odt
			<lb />
		</note>
		<body>
			sentenced him to suffer imprisonment for life and to pay a fine of
			<lb />
			Rs.500/-. In default of payment of fine, he is ordered to suffer
			<lb />
			rigorous imprisonment for one month.
			<lb />
			2.
			<lb />
			The facts leading to this appeal are as follows :
			<lb />
			The informant (PW1) is the father-in-law of deceased
			<lb />
			Sharda. The incident occurred on 23 rd of April, 2013 around 12.15
			<lb />
			p.m. The appellant is the nephew of the informant. The facts
			<lb />
			recorded in the first information report have unfolded the incident.
			<lb />
			The appellant was raising dispute with the deceased and Shrawan,
			<lb />
			husband of the deceased, for vacating the land. The informant on
			<lb />
			the date of incident went to Khamgaon to see his daughter&apos;s son,
			<lb />
			who was admitted in the hospital. At about 1.00 p.m. Laxman
			<lb />
			Paraskar (PW8) made a phone call to him and informed him that the
			<lb />
			appellant had assaulted his daughter-in-law by axe. Laxman (PW8)
			<lb />
			requested the informant to come back immediately. Informant
			<lb />
			(PW1) came back to his village. He saw that crowed gathered in
			<lb />
			front of the house. He saw his daughter-in-law Sharda was lying in
			<lb />
			the bathroom in a pool of blood. She had sustained injuries on her
			<lb />
			head, neck and on back. The informant went to Jalamb police
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			3
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			331 apeal352.19(J).odt
			<lb />
		</note>
		<body>
			station and lodged the report of incident. On the basis of this report,
			<lb />
			a crime bearing No.21/2013 came to be registered.
			<lb />
			3.
			<lb />
			Santosh Tale (PW13), Assistant Police Inspector,
			<lb />
			attached to Jalamb Police Station, conducted the investigation. He
			<lb />
			visited the spot of the incident and drew the spot panchanama. He
			<lb />
			also held the inquest of the dead body. He collected and seized the
			<lb />
			blood and blood mixed soil samples from the spot. He forwarded the
			<lb />
			dead body to the General Hospital, Khamgaon for post mortem. He
			<lb />
			arrested the appellant and seized the clothes worn by him. The
			<lb />
			appellant during the course of investigation made a confession which
			<lb />
			led to the discovery of axe used by the appellant for commission of
			<lb />
			the crime. The Investigating Officer recorded the statements of the
			<lb />
			witnesses and on completion of the investigation, filed charge-sheet
			<lb />
			in the Court of learned Judicial Magistrate, First Class, Shegaon.
			<lb />
			4.
			<lb />
			Since the case was exclusively triable by the Court of
			<lb />
			Sessions, the learned Magistrate committed the case to the Court of
			<lb />
			learned Additional Sessions Judge, Khamgaon. On committal, the
			<lb />
			learned Additional Sessions Judge framed the Charge at Exhibit-2.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			4
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			331 apeal352.19(J).odt
			<lb />
		</note>
		<body>
			The Charge was read over and explained to the appellant. The
			<lb />
			appellant pleaded not guilty. The defence of the appellant is of total
			<lb />
			denial and false implication in the case.
			<lb />
			5.
			<lb />
			In order to bring home the guilt against the appellant,
			<lb />
			the prosecution examined 13 witnesses. The prosecution relied on
			<lb />
			number of documents. The learned Additional Sessions Judge, on
			<lb />
			consideration of the material on record, found the appellant guilty of
			<lb />
			the offence punishable under Section 302 of the Indian Penal Code
			<lb />
			and sentenced him as above. Being aggrieved by the judgment and
			<lb />
			order of conviction, the appellant is before this Court in appeal.
			<lb />
			6.
			<lb />
			We have heard Shri M. L. Chouhan, learned Advocate
			<lb />
			appointed for the appellant and Shri M. J. Khan, learned Additional
			<lb />
			Public Prosecutor for the State. With their able assistance we have
			<lb />
			gone through the entire record and proceedings.
			<lb />
			7.
			<lb />
			The first plank of the submission of the learned advocate
			<lb />
			for the appellant is that the evidence adduced by the prosecution is
			<lb />
			not sufficient to prove the charge against the appellant. Shri
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			5
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			331 apeal352.19(J).odt
			<lb />
		</note>
		<body>
			Chouhan, learned advocate for the appellant took us through the
			<lb />
			evidence of the witnesses and submitted that there are major
			<lb />
			omissions, contradictions and inconsistencies in the evidence of the
			<lb />
			witnesses examined by the prosecution to prove the actual
			<lb />
			occurrence and the involvement of the appellant in commission of
			<lb />
			the crime. In the submission of the learned advocate for the
			<lb />
			appellant, the learned trial Judge has glossed over all these
			<lb />
			omissions, contradictions and inconsistencies. The learned advocate
			<lb />
			submitted that recovery of the weapon of the offence namely axe at
			<lb />
			the instance of the appellant has not been proved by cogent and
			<lb />
			reliable evidence. The second plank of the submission of the learned
			<lb />
			advocate is that the prosecution has failed to prove that the appellant
			<lb />
			had acted with pre-meditation or pre-planned to commit murder of
			<lb />
			the deceased. In the submission of the learned advocate for the
			<lb />
			appellant, at the most on the basis of the available evidence, the
			<lb />
			knowledge that the injuries inflicted by him would result into death
			<lb />
			of the deceased could be attributed to the appellant. The learned
			<lb />
			advocate submitted that therefore, offence of culpable homicide not
			<lb />
			amounting to murder, punishable under Section 304 Part-II of the
			<lb />
			Indian Penal Code would be made out against the appellant.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			6
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			331 apeal352.19(J).odt
			<lb />
		</note>
		<body>
			8.
			<lb />
			Shri M. J. Khan, learned Additional Public Prosecutor for
			<lb />
			the State submitted that there are two eye-witnesses to the actual
			<lb />
			incident of murder of the deceased at the hands of the appellant.
			<lb />
			The learned APP submitted that the evidence of the eye-witnesses
			<lb />
			despite searching cross-examination has remained unshaken. The
			<lb />
			learned APP submitted that there is other evidence to corroborate the
			<lb />
			evidence of eye-witnesses on the actual involvement of the appellant
			<lb />
			in commission of the crime. The learned APP submitted that the
			<lb />
			appellant had made a confession before the police officer and the
			<lb />
			said confession led to the discovery of weapon namely axe. The
			<lb />
			learned APP submitted that on the clothes worn by the appellant at
			<lb />
			the time of the incident, blood of the deceased was detected. The
			<lb />
			learned APP submitted that the appellant had inflicted three blows
			<lb />
			on vital parts of the body of the deceased and the deceased
			<lb />
			succumbed to those injuries within no time. In the submission of the
			<lb />
			learned APP, the intention of the appellant to commit murder of the
			<lb />
			deceased is writ large. The learned APP submitted that the offence
			<lb />
			of murder has been made out against the appellant.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			7
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			331 apeal352.19(J).odt
			<lb />
		</note>
		<body>
			9.
			<lb />
			We have made minute scrutiny of the evidence to
			<lb />
			appreciate the submissions advanced by the learned advocate for the
			<lb />
			appellant and the learned Additional Public Prosecutor for the State.
			<lb />
			10.
			<lb />
			At the outset, it would be necessary to consider the
			<lb />
			evidence of the Medical Officer who had conducted post mortem of
			<lb />
			the dead body of the deceased. Dr. Sachin Gadekar (PW12) at the
			<lb />
			relevant time was attached to the General Hospital, Khamgaon as a
			<lb />
			Medical Officer. He conducted post mortem of the dead body on 23 rd
			<lb />
			April, 2013. On examination of the dead body, he found following
			<lb />
			external injuries -
			<lb />
			1. There were three deep stab wounds as follows :
			<lb />
			i] Stab wound of size 8 x 3 x 5 cm over the posterior of neck
			<lb />
			with evidence of fracture of cervical spine.
			<lb />
			ii] Stab wound of size 5 x 3 x 3 cm on the right side of upper
			<lb />
			back near 10 th rib.
			<lb />
			iii] Stab wound of size 5.5 x 3 x 3 cm on left side of back at 11 th
			<lb />
			rib.
			<lb />
			2. I could notice following wounds on the skull.
			<lb />
			i] There was evidence of CLW (Contused lacerated wound) on
			<lb />
			right and left parietal region of scalp size 5 x 2 x 2 cm. There
			<lb />
			were evidence of fracture of skull below the aforesaid both
			<lb />
			CLW of size 4 x 2 x 2 cm.
			<lb />
			ii] There was evidence lacerated wound over the left cerebral
			<lb />
			hemisphere with collection of blood inside the skull.
			<lb />
			3] In the thorasic region there was evidence of laceration over
			<lb />
			the left lung of size 3 x 2 x 1 over posterior surface.
			<lb />
			4] In the abdominal cavity there was evidence of laceration of
			<lb />
			both the kidneys approximately at the centre of size 3x2x2 cm
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			8
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			331 apeal352.19(J).odt
			<lb />
		</note>
		<body>
			11.
			<lb />
			Dr. Gadekar (PW12) has opined that the cause of death
			<lb />
			was due to grievous fatal injuries to the vital organs like brain, lungs
			<lb />
			and kidneys. He has stated that the injuries were ante mortem and
			<lb />
			sufficient to cause death. The post mortem report is at Exhibit-62.
			<lb />
			In Column no.21, the Medical Officer has mentioned that the blood
			<lb />
			was preserved as per police request. The clothes on the dead body,
			<lb />
			post mortem report and the blood sample were handed over to a
			<lb />
			Constable. Dr. Gadekar (PW12) has stated that the weapon of
			<lb />
			offence namely axe was sent to him with the queries by the
			<lb />
			Investigating Officer. He has stated that on inspection of the weapon
			<lb />
			and the injuries mentioned in the post mortem report, he opined that
			<lb />
			the injuries found on the body of the deceased could be caused by
			<lb />
			the said weapon. The Medical Officer at the time of his evidence
			<lb />
			identified the axe, which was sent to him for his opinion. Perusal of
			<lb />
			the evidence of the Medical Officer would show that the injuries had
			<lb />
			been caused on the vital parts of the body. The injuries were found
			<lb />
			sufficient to cause death in ordinary course of nature. The injuries
			<lb />
			were ante mortem. The cause of death and nature of death has been
			<lb />
			prima facie established on the basis of his evidence. Besides, there is
			<lb />
			other direct and corroborative evidence in order to come to a
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			9
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			331 apeal352.19(J).odt
			<lb />
		</note>
		<body>
			conclusion that the deceased died homicidal death.
			<lb />
			12.
			<lb />
			The informant (PW1) is not an eye-witness to the
			<lb />
			incident. On the date of the incident he had gone to Shegaon to
			<lb />
			meet his grandson, who was admitted in the hospital. In his
			<lb />
			evidence it has come on record that he received a phone call about
			<lb />
			occurrence of the incident and therefore, he came back to his village.
			<lb />
			He found that the deceased was lying in the bathroom in a pool of
			<lb />
			blood. He found three major injuries on her body. He made enquiry
			<lb />
			with the people gathered on the spot. The eye-witnesses informed
			<lb />
			him about the occurrence of the incident. He, therefore, went to the
			<lb />
			police station and lodged the report.
			<lb />
			13.
			<lb />
			Vikas Ghule (PW2) and Sudam Ghule (PW3) are the two
			<lb />
			eye-witnesses. The learned Additional Sessions Judge found the
			<lb />
			evidence of these two eye-witnesses worth credible and reliable.
			<lb />
			Vilas Ghule (PW2) has deposed that the appellant assaulted the
			<lb />
			deceased by means of an axe. He has stated that on the date of the
			<lb />
			incident at about 11.30 am, he went to the house of Sudam Ghule
			<lb />
			(PW3). He and Sudam were present in his house. Sudam was
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			10
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			331 apeal352.19(J).odt
			<lb />
		</note>
		<body>
			cooking poha. Within 15 minutes of his reaching the house of
			<lb />
			Sudam, they heard the cries &quot;O maa O&quot; (vks ek vks ). After hearing
			<lb />
			the cries, they came out of the house. They saw that the appellant
			<lb />
			was inflicting the blows on Shardabai with an axe. The appellant,
			<lb />
			according to him, inflicted axe blows on waist and neck of the
			<lb />
			deceased. According to him, the incident occurred in the bathroom.
			<lb />
			He has categorically stated that the appellant inflicted three blows
			<lb />
			with an axe on the deceased. He has stated that after witnessing the
			<lb />
			incident he got frightened and rushed to call Shrawan, the husband
			<lb />
			of the deceased. He found Shrawan at a &apos;pan tapri&apos; (kiosk). He
			<lb />
			narrated the incident to him. When they rushed back to the spot,
			<lb />
			they found that the deceased was lying in the bathroom. In his
			<lb />
			evidence, Vilas (PW2) has described the clothes on the person of the
			<lb />
			appellant at the time of the incident. He has stated that after
			<lb />
			inflicting the blows with an axe, the appellant fled from the spot. At
			<lb />
			that time, Sudam (PW3) went inside his house, which is adjoining to
			<lb />
			the house of the appellant. In his cross-examination, he was
			<lb />
			subjected to grueling inquiry. Perusal of his cross-examination would
			<lb />
			show that while answering the relevant questions he has reiterated
			<lb />
			and confirmed the incident. In his cross-examination, one omission
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			11
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			331 apeal352.19(J).odt
			<lb />
		</note>
		<body>
			has been recorded. In order to verify the correct factual opposition,
			<lb />
			we have perused his statement recorded by the police. In his
			<lb />
			statement before the police, he had stated that the appellant gave
			<lb />
			stroke of an axe to Shardabai on her neck, back and waist. We are
			<lb />
			satisfied that his omission was wrongly recorded. He has stated this
			<lb />
			fact to the Investigating Officer at the time of recording his
			<lb />
			statement. He is the close relative of the deceased as well as of the
			<lb />
			appellant. His house is in the vicinity of the spot. No suggestion has
			<lb />
			been given in the cross-examination as to why he has deposed
			<lb />
			against the appellant who is his close relative.
			<lb />
			14.
			<lb />
			Another eye-witness is Sudam Ghule (PW3). In his
			<lb />
			evidence, he has narrated the incident. He has categorically stated
			<lb />
			that when the incident took placed at about 12.00 to 12.15 pm, he
			<lb />
			was cooking poha. They heard the cries &quot;O maa O&quot; (vks ek vks )
			<lb />
			from outside. They came out of the house and saw that the appellant
			<lb />
			was inflicting the blows with an axe on the deceased. Vilas (PW2)
			<lb />
			immediately rushed to call the husband of the deceased. He has
			<lb />
			stated that daughter of deceased namely Anuradha was crying and
			<lb />
			proceeding towards bathroom where her mother was lying. He has
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			12
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			331 apeal352.19(J).odt
			<lb />
		</note>
		<body>
			stated that he picked up Anuradha and brought her to his house.
			<lb />
			The appellant, according to him, was carrying an axe and therefore,
			<lb />
			he closed his door and latched it from inside. He was frightened.
			<lb />
			After some time people gathered on the spot and therefore, he
			<lb />
			opened the door. He has stated that the deceased was lying in a pool
			<lb />
			of blood in the bathroom. PW3 is the uncle of Shrawan. A probing
			<lb />
			cross-examination has been conducted. However not an iota of
			<lb />
			material has been brought on record to dis-lodge this witness from
			<lb />
			the first hand account of the incident narrated by him. This witness
			<lb />
			has categorically stated that Vilas (PW2) was present in his house
			<lb />
			and after hearing the cries of the deceased, they came out and saw
			<lb />
			that the appellant was inflicting blows on the deceased with an axe.
			<lb />
			15.
			<lb />
			The only thing which can go against these two eye-
			<lb />
			witnesses is that after seeing the merciless assault on the deceased,
			<lb />
			they did not bother to intervene and save the deceased. The
			<lb />
			appellant at the time of the incident was 50 years old. It has come
			<lb />
			on record that the appellant was residing alone because his wife had
			<lb />
			left him due to the quarrel. Vilas (PW2) and Sudam (PW3) on the
			<lb />
			date of the incident were below 20 years of age. They have deposed
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			13
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			331 apeal352.19(J).odt
			<lb />
		</note>
		<body>
			that after seeing the brutal attack they got frightened. Vilas (PW2)
			<lb />
			immediately rushed to call the husband of the deceased. Sudam
			<lb />
			(PW3) picked up the daughter of the deceased from the spot when
			<lb />
			he saw that the small girl was proceeding towards the place of the
			<lb />
			incident to see her mother and brought her in his house. In our
			<lb />
			opinion, the brutality of assault by the appellant on the deceased
			<lb />
			could have been a frightful sight for Vilas (PW2) and Sudam (PW3).
			<lb />
			They saw the merciless blows inflicted on the deceased by the
			<lb />
			appellant. They could see depravity of the appellant. In our opinion,
			<lb />
			therefore, their conduct would not weigh against PW2 and PW3 and
			<lb />
			affect their credibility. It is seen that they were natural witnesses.
			<lb />
			Their presence on the spot was natural inasmuch as the place of
			<lb />
			occurrence could be seen from the house of PW3. Both PW2 and
			<lb />
			PW3 have narrated the first hand account of the incident witnessed
			<lb />
			by them. Perusal of their evidence, more particularly their cross-
			<lb />
			examination, would show that not a slightest dent has been caused
			<lb />
			to their credibility. The incident of assault by the appellant with an
			<lb />
			axe on the deceased has been proved on the basis of the evidence of
			<lb />
			these two eye-witnesses. We do not see any reason to discard and
			<lb />
			disbelieve the evidence of these two witnesses.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			14
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			331 apeal352.19(J).odt
			<lb />
		</note>
		<body>
			16.
			<lb />
			The next important witness, who has deposed in the
			<lb />
			case to corroborate the version of Vilas (PW2) and Sudam (PW3), is
			<lb />
			Pankaj Paraskar (PW9). It is the case of the prosecution that after
			<lb />
			brutal attack on the deceased, the appellant fled from the spot with
			<lb />
			the weapon of the offence. Pankaj (PW9) has stated that his father is
			<lb />
			a Police Patil. He has stated that on 23 rd April, 2013 at about 12.30
			<lb />
			to 12.45 pm he was took lunch at his house. His parents had gone to
			<lb />
			Nandura to attend the meeting of Anganwadi work. After completion
			<lb />
			of his lunch, he was sitting in the house. He has stated that the
			<lb />
			appellant came to his house holding an axe stained with blood. The
			<lb />
			appellant made enquiry about his father. He has stated that the
			<lb />
			appellant requested him to take axe in his possession. He has stated
			<lb />
			that he told the appellant that he would not take it and he should go
			<lb />
			to the police station. He has categorically deposed that the appellant
			<lb />
			disclosed to him that he had killed Sharda by axe. He has stated that
			<lb />
			after the appellant left his house, he made a phone call to his father
			<lb />
			and informed him about the incident. It has come on record in his
			<lb />
			cross-examination that his house is at the distance of five minutes
			<lb />
			walk from the house of the informant (PW1). While recording his
			<lb />
			statement by police he has not specifically disclosed that the
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			15
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			331 apeal352.19(J).odt
			<lb />
		</note>
		<body>
			appellant told him that he had killed Sharda. The omission was in
			<lb />
			respect of the name of the deceased. The witness had stated before
			<lb />
			the police that the appellant told him that he killed &quot;vairi&quot;. It is to be
			<lb />
			noted here that the deceased was the wife of the nephew of the
			<lb />
			appellant. It can be seen that in that part of Buldhana district,
			<lb />
			daughter-in-law is called as &quot;vairi&quot;. In view of this, the omission is
			<lb />
			not material. Pankaj (PW9) has narrated in great detail the extra-
			<lb />
			judicial confession made by the appellant to him. It is undisputed
			<lb />
			that the father of Pankaj (PW9) is a Police Patil. The appellant, it
			<lb />
			seems that, after realizing the blunder committed by him, went to
			<lb />
			the house of Police Patil, but the Police Patil was not found at the
			<lb />
			house. His son Pankaj (PW9) was found and the appellant narrated
			<lb />
			killing of the deceased by him with an axe. PW9 saw that the axe
			<lb />
			carried by the appellant was stained with blood. We do not see any
			<lb />
			reason to discard and disbelieve this witness. On appreciation of the
			<lb />
			evidence, possibility of planting this witness to support the case of
			<lb />
			the prosecution has been completely ruled out.
			<lb />
			17.
			<lb />
			Evidence of the eye-witnesses namely Vilas (PW2) and
			<lb />
			Sudam (PW3) has proved the actual incident and the complicity of
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			16
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			331 apeal352.19(J).odt
			<lb />
		</note>
		<body>
			the appellant in commission of crime. This part of the incident and
			<lb />
			conduct of the appellant after the brutal murder has been proved on
			<lb />
			the basis of evidence of Pankaj (PW9). It would, therefore, be
			<lb />
			necessary to consider the other corroborative evidence.
			<lb />
			18.
			<lb />
			The clothes of the deceased were seized. The blood and
			<lb />
			blood mixed soil from the spot were also seized. During the course
			<lb />
			of investigation, the blood sample of the appellant was collected. It
			<lb />
			is the case of the prosecution that after arrest of the appellant, he
			<lb />
			made a confession and on the basis of his confession, an axe was
			<lb />
			recovered. The appellant was arrested on the same day of the
			<lb />
			incident at about 20.45 hours. On his arrest, the clothes namely
			<lb />
			yellow colour payjama and bluish colour sando baniyan were seized.
			<lb />
			The seizure panchanama of the clothes on the person of the
			<lb />
			appellant is at Exhibit-37. The appellant made a confession on 25 th
			<lb />
			of April, 2013 in presence of the panch witnesses and the
			<lb />
			Investigating Officer. Arvind Paraskar (PW7) is the panch witness to
			<lb />
			the memorandum and discovery panchanama.
			<lb />
			19.
			<lb />
			Perusal of the evidence of Arvind Paraskar (PW7) would
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			17
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			331 apeal352.19(J).odt
			<lb />
		</note>
		<body>
			show that on 25 th of April, 2013, he was called by the police to act as
			<lb />
			a panch witness. He has stated that one Murlidhar was another
			<lb />
			panch. He has stated that the appellant had confessed that he would
			<lb />
			point out the place where the weapon (axe) was concealed by him.
			<lb />
			Exhibit-42 is the memorandum panchanama. He has stated that the
			<lb />
			appellant led the panchas and police to an agricultural land of one
			<lb />
			Amol. The appellant in their presence took out an axe from the heap
			<lb />
			of sprinkler pipes. The only discrepancy which has been brought on
			<lb />
			record in his cross-examination was in regard to the timing of
			<lb />
			recording of the memorandum and discovery panchanama. In his
			<lb />
			cross-examination, he has stated that memorandum panchanama
			<lb />
			was prepared after 11.00 a.m., whereas the memorandum
			<lb />
			panchanama would show that it was prepared between 8.25 am and
			<lb />
			8.45 am. He has stated that the discovery panchanama was prepared
			<lb />
			after 11.00 a.m., whereas perusal of the discovery panchanama
			<lb />
			would show that it was commenced at 10.10 am and completed at
			<lb />
			10.45 am. On the basis of difference of timings, it was submitted
			<lb />
			that recovery of the weapon pursuant to the confession of the
			<lb />
			appellant and at the instance of the appellant is doubtful. In our
			<lb />
			opinion, evidence of Arvind (PW7) and evidence of the Investigating
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			18
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			331 apeal352.19(J).odt
			<lb />
		</note>
		<body>
			Officer if read together would show that the discrepancy as to the
			<lb />
			time is not material. There is difference of about two hours in the
			<lb />
			timings mentioned in the panchanamas and as deposed by Arvind
			<lb />
			(PW7) in the Court. The evidence on record would show that the
			<lb />
			axe was found stained with blood. The blood group of the blood
			<lb />
			found on the axe was of group &quot;A&quot;. In the totality of the evidence
			<lb />
			brought on record and in the circumstances, we do not see any
			<lb />
			reason to discard and disbelieve the aspect of recovery of weapon
			<lb />
			axe at the instance of the appellant. Evidence of Pankaj (PW9) to
			<lb />
			whom the appellant wanted to handover the axe stained with blood,
			<lb />
			fully corroborated the evidence of recovery of axe stained with blood.
			<lb />
			20.
			<lb />
			Let us now discuss the other corroborative evidence. The
			<lb />
			Investigating Officer has stated that the articles seized in the crime
			<lb />
			were sent to the Chemical Analyser for analysis. The CA reports are
			<lb />
			at Exhibits-76, 77 and 78. The report Exhibit-76 would show that
			<lb />
			the clothes seized from the body of the deceased and the clothes
			<lb />
			seized from the appellant were found stained with blood of group
			<lb />
			&quot;A&quot;. Similarly, it would show that the blood found on the axe was of
			<lb />
			group &quot;A&quot;. The CA report at Exhibit-77 would show that blood group
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			19
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			331 apeal352.19(J).odt
			<lb />
		</note>
		<body>
			of the appellant is of group &quot;A&quot;. The CA report at Exh.78 would show
			<lb />
			that blood group of the deceased was also of group &quot;A&quot;. On the basis
			<lb />
			of these documentary evidence it is submitted by the learned
			<lb />
			advocate for the appellant that this evidence cannot be used against
			<lb />
			the appellant. We are not prepared to accept this submission. The
			<lb />
			appellant was arrested by the Investigating Officer on the day of the
			<lb />
			incident. There were no bleeding injuries or any injury on the body
			<lb />
			of the appellant at the time of his arrest. It is not suggested in the
			<lb />
			cross-examination of any of the witnesses that the appellant had
			<lb />
			sustained bleeding injury and therefore, the blood found on his
			<lb />
			clothes was his own blood. It is further pertinent to mention that the
			<lb />
			blood of group &quot;A&quot; was detected on the axe. There was no injury on
			<lb />
			the person of the appellant at the time of his arrest. The blood group
			<lb />
			of the deceased was of group &quot;A&quot;. It can, therefore, be stated with
			<lb />
			certainty that the blood detected on the axe was of the deceased.
			<lb />
			This evidence, in our opinion, corroborates the evidence of eye-
			<lb />
			witnesses Vilas (PW2) and Sudam (PW3) and the evidence of Pankaj
			<lb />
			(PW9).
			<lb />
			21.
			<lb />
			On re-appreciation of the entire evidence, we do not see
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			20
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			331 apeal352.19(J).odt
			<lb />
		</note>
		<body>
			any reason to discard and disbelieve the evidence. On the basis of
			<lb />
			the evidence on record, it has been proved that the appellant was the
			<lb />
			author of the injuries sustained by the deceased. The weapon used
			<lb />
			by the deceased for causing injuries has been proved to be an axe.
			<lb />
			The Medical Officer in his evidence has stated that the injuries found
			<lb />
			on the body of the deceased could be caused by an axe. It has come
			<lb />
			on record that the Investigating Officer had forwarded the axe to the
			<lb />
			Medical Officer and obtained his opinion. In this case, therefore, the
			<lb />
			complicity of the appellant in the commission of the crime has been
			<lb />
			proved beyond reasonable doubt.
			<lb />
			22.
			<lb />
			It would now be necessary to deal with the submissions
			<lb />
			advanced by the learned advocate for the appellant on the aspect of
			<lb />
			the actual offence made out against the appellant. In order to seek
			<lb />
			support to his submission that the offence made out against the
			<lb />
			appellant would be culpable homicide not amounting to murder, he
			<lb />
			has placed reliance on three reported decisions, namely :
			<lb />
			1] Ankeri .vs. State of Rajasthan, reported in 1994 AIR 842
			<lb />
			2] Kulesh Mondal .vs. State of West Bengal, reported in
			<lb />
			AIR 2007 SC 3328
			<lb />
			3] Nazir Malitha and others .vs. State of West Bengal, reported in
			<lb />
			2019 All SCR (Cri) 1267
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			21
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			331 apeal352.19(J).odt
			<lb />
		</note>
		<body>
			23.
			<lb />
			We have perused the decisions relied upon by the
			<lb />
			learned advocate for the appellant. The proposition which is culled
			<lb />
			out from the aforesaid decisions is that if the intention of the accused
			<lb />
			either proved or unfolded was not to commit murder but to cause
			<lb />
			some grievous injury, the offence punishable under Section 304 Part-
			<lb />
			II of the Indian Penal Code would get attracted. It is further held
			<lb />
			that if there is direct evidence or some evidence to infer that the act
			<lb />
			was committed in the course of sudden quarrel without any pre-
			<lb />
			meditation, then in that event such an act would fall within
			<lb />
			Explanation -4 of Section 300 of the Indian Penal Code, warranting
			<lb />
			punishment under Section 304 Part-I or Part-II of the Indian Penal
			<lb />
			Code.
			<lb />
			24.
			<lb />
			In this case, the intention of the appellant would be
			<lb />
			required to be gathered from the nature and manner of the assault
			<lb />
			on the deceased by the appellant. Similarly, the weapon used by the
			<lb />
			appellant would also be required to be taken into consideration while
			<lb />
			considering the state of mind of the appellant at the time of the
			<lb />
			incident. It is nobody&apos;s case that the deceased either quarrelled with
			<lb />
			the appellant or insulted him in any manner before the actual
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			22
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			331 apeal352.19(J).odt
			<lb />
		</note>
		<body>
			occurrence of the incident. The informant (PW1) has deposed that
			<lb />
			there was a dispute between the appellant on one hand and the
			<lb />
			deceased and her husband on the other hand on account of vacating
			<lb />
			the land. This fact would show that the appellant wanted the
			<lb />
			deceased and her husband to vacate his land and on that account
			<lb />
			there was a dispute. This, in our view, would be the motive for the
			<lb />
			appellant to commit this brutal crime. The appellant inflicted three
			<lb />
			blows on the vital parts of the body of the deceased. The deceased,
			<lb />
			as can be seen from the evidence of the Medical Officer, died
			<lb />
			instantaneously. The injuries were on vital parts of the body. The
			<lb />
			appellant did not give her a chance to move or defend herself. The
			<lb />
			prosecution has proved the brutality and depravity of the appellant.
			<lb />
			He had preplanned the attack and therefore, he came there with an
			<lb />
			axe. The intention, therefore, of the appellant has been proved to be
			<lb />
			to eliminate the deceased. Therefore, in this case, the offence made
			<lb />
			out is murder of the deceased by the appellant, punishable under
			<lb />
			section 302 of the Indian Penal Code. In the teeth of the available
			<lb />
			evidence, we are not convinced to accept the submission advanced
			<lb />
			by the learned advocate for the appellant that the offence proved in
			<lb />
			this case would be culpable homicide not amounting to murder
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			23
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			331 apeal352.19(J).odt
			<lb />
		</note>
		<body>
			punishable under Section 304 Part-II of the Indian Penal Code.
			<lb />
			25.
			<lb />
			In view of the above, we hold that there is no substance
			<lb />
			in the appeal. The learned Additional Sessions Judge, Khamgaon has
			<lb />
			recorded the cogent reasons in support of his findings. On re-
			<lb />
			appreciation of the evidence, we do not see any reason to take a view
			<lb />
			different from the one taken by the learned Additional Sessions
			<lb />
			Judge. The appeal, therefore, fails. The same is accordingly
			<lb />
			dismissed.
			<lb />
			We appreciate the able assistance extended by learned
			<lb />
			advocate Shri M.L. Chouhan appointed for the appellant by the Court
			<lb />
			and the learned Additional Public Prosecutor for the State.
			<lb />
			Shri M. L. Chouhan, learned advocate appointed for the
			<lb />
			appellant is entitled to receive his fees from the High Court Legal
			<lb />
			Services Sub Committee, Nagpur, which is quantified at Rs.15,000/-.
			<lb />
			(G.A.SANAP, J.)
			<lb />
			(SUNIL B. SHUKRE, J.)
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			Diwale
			<lb />
			Digitally signed byPARAG
			<lb />
			PRABHAKARRAO DIWALE
			<lb />
			Signing Date:12.07.2022
			<lb />
			17:24
		</note>
	</text>
</tei>
