<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<note place="headnote">
			Osk
			<lb />
			Apeal-1129-2018.odt
			<lb />
		</note>
		<front>
			IN THE HIGH COURT OF JUDICATURE AT BOMBAY
			<lb />
			CRIMINAL APPELLATE JURISDICTION
			<lb />
			CRIMINAL APPEAL NO. 1129 OF 2018
			<lb />
			Arun Popatrao Pingale
			<lb />
			]
			<lb />
			Age-56 years,
			<lb />
			]
			<lb />
			Residing at Kivale, Taluka Maval,
			<lb />
			]
			<lb />
			District Pune.
			<lb />
			]
			<lb />
			At present Yerwada Jail.
			<lb />
			]
			<lb />
			… Appellant
			<lb />
			(Accused)
			<lb />
			V/s.
			<lb />
			1. The State of Maharashtra
			<lb />
			]
			<lb />
			At the instance of Senior Police Inspector,
			<lb />
			]
			<lb />
			Vadgaon Maval Police Station,
			<lb />
			]
			<lb />
			District -Pune.
			<lb />
			]
			<lb />
			]
			<lb />
			2. Smt. Chhaya Sharad Bhujade
			<lb />
			]
			<lb />
			Age -Adult, Residing at
			<lb />
			]
			<lb />
			Village -Sangwa, Post Derwadi,
			<lb />
			]
			<lb />
			Taluka -Digras, Dist. Yavatmal,
			<lb />
			]
			<lb />
			Maharashtra. Pin -445 203.
			<lb />
			]
			<lb />
			… Respondents
			<lb />
			Mr.Rajiv Patil, Senior Advocate i/b. Mr.Sachin S. Punde for Appellant.
			<lb />
			Ms.S.S. Kaushik, A.P.P. for Respondent No.1-State.
			<lb />
			Mr.Aditya Bapat for Respondent No.2.
			<lb />
			CORAM : A.S. GADKARI, J.
			<lb />
			RESERVED ON
			<lb />
			: 17 th June 2022.
			<lb />
			PRONOUNCED ON
			<lb />
			: 12 th July 2022.
			<lb />
			JUDGMENT :
			<lb />
		</front>
		<body>
			1.
			<lb />
			Appellant has impugned Judgment and Order dated 1 st
			<lb />
			September 2018 passed by the learned Special Judge, Pune (under POCSO
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			1/9
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			Osk
			<lb />
			Apeal-1129-2018.odt
			<lb />
		</note>
		<body>
			Act) in Special (C) Sessions Case Case No. 23 of 2016 by its Judgment and
			<lb />
			Order dated 1 st September 2018, convicting him under Sections 376 &amp; 506 of
			<lb />
			the Indian Penal Code (for short, &apos;I.P.C.&apos;) and is sentenced to suffer 7 years and
			<lb />
			1 year of rigorous imprisonment on each count respectively and to pay a fine
			<lb />
			of Rs.5,000/-, and is also convicted under Sections 4 &amp; 6 of the Protection of
			<lb />
			Children from Sexual Offences Act, 2012 (for short, &apos;POCSO Act&apos;) and is
			<lb />
			directed to suffer rigorous imprisonment for 7 years and 10 years on each
			<lb />
			count respectively and to pay a fine of Rs.15,000/-. The Trial Court has
			<lb />
			directed that, all the substantive sentences shall run concurrently.
			<lb />
			2.
			<lb />
			Heard Mr.Rajiv Patil, learned Senior Advocate for Appellant,
			<lb />
			Ms.S.S. Kaushik, learned A.P.P. for Respondent No.1-State and Mr.Aditya
			<lb />
			Bapat, learned Advocate appointed to represent Respondent No.2. Perused
			<lb />
			entire record.
			<lb />
			3.
			<lb />
			As the victim was minor on the date of lodgment of crime, with a
			<lb />
			view to protect her identity and in consonance with provisions of Section
			<lb />
			228(A) of I.P.C. &amp; Section 33(7) of P.O.C.S.O. Act, the facts or any other
			<lb />
			material disclosing her identity are hereinafter avoided.
			<lb />
			4.
			<lb />
			It is the prosecution case that, the first informant/victim was a
			<lb />
			minor, then aged approximately 17 years was a native of village Sangwa, Post
			<lb />
			Derwadi, Taluka Digras, District Yavatmal. She along with her parents had
			<lb />
			been to village Kiwale Takva situated near Dehuroad, District Pune for labour
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			2/9
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			Osk
			<lb />
			Apeal-1129-2018.odt
			<lb />
		</note>
		<body>
			work. The prosecutrix along with her parents was staying at a poultry farm
			<lb />
			known as &apos;Gayatri Poultry Farm&apos; owned by Mr.Sunil Deshmukh. Victim girl
			<lb />
			(PW-1) used to call Appellant as &apos; Abaji&apos; and Mr.Sunil Deshmukh as &apos;Mama&apos;.
			<lb />
			Victim was entrusted with the work of taking care of chicks in the poultry
			<lb />
			farm by providing it fodder and water. That, in the month of October 2014, in
			<lb />
			Diwali festival on the day of &apos;Bhaubeej&apos;, the victim girl was providing fodder
			<lb />
			and water to the chicks in the poultry farm in the morning and her parents
			<lb />
			had gone to the brick kiln. At that time, the Appellant came there, gave
			<lb />
			threats of serious consequences and to kill the victim and thereafter
			<lb />
			committed forcible sexual intercourse with her. Appellant committed the said
			<lb />
			act of sexual assault on victim subsequently on atleast two occasions by giving
			<lb />
			threats to kill her. As the victim was frightened, did not disclose the said
			<lb />
			incident to her parents. In the month of April 2015, the victim and her parents
			<lb />
			shifted to village Dohale, Taluka Bhiwandi, District Thane, as her parents were
			<lb />
			not being paid labour charges from the brick kiln owner. As the victim was not
			<lb />
			feeling well on 30 th April 2015, she was taken to Primary Village Center of
			<lb />
			village Padgha, Taluka Bhiwandi, District Thane by her mother. The Medical
			<lb />
			Officer present there, on examination informed that, the victim girl was
			<lb />
			pregnant of about 6 months. The mother of victim therefore made enquiry
			<lb />
			with her, whereupon she disclosed and narrated the incident of rape
			<lb />
			committed by Appellant upon her. The victim along with her mother therefore
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			3/9
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			Osk
			<lb />
			Apeal-1129-2018.odt
			<lb />
		</note>
		<body>
			on 2 nd May 2015 approached Padgha Police Station and lodged First
			<lb />
			Information Report (F.I.R.) against the Appellant. The said F.I.R. was recorded
			<lb />
			by PSI Mr.Shamrao Kale (PW-6), then attached to Padgha Police Station in
			<lb />
			presence of Smt.Manisha Godambe (PW-3), a Member of Mahila Dakshata
			<lb />
			Samittee, Padgha. The Padgha Police Station registered F.I.R. vide C.R. No.
			<lb />
			00/2015 for the offence punishable under Section 376 of I.P.C. and under
			<lb />
			Sections 3 read with Sections 4, 5(J)(2)(3)(l)(q) punishable under Section 6
			<lb />
			of the POCSO Act.
			<lb />
			PSI Shamrao Kale started investigation and got the minor victim
			<lb />
			girl examined from Civil Hospital, Thane. He also collected blood samples for
			<lb />
			DNA test. As the offence had occurred within the jurisdiction of Vadgaon
			<lb />
			Maval Police Station, he forwarded documents of the said crime to the
			<lb />
			Superintendent of Police, Pune (Rural). After receipt of documents, PSI Iqbal
			<lb />
			Shaikh (PW-5) then attached to Vadgaon Maval Police Station numbered the
			<lb />
			said crime as FIR No. 133 of 2015 and conducted further investigation. He
			<lb />
			obtained DNA samples of the victim minor girl, newly born baby of the victim
			<lb />
			girl and the Appellant and sent it for examination to the Forensic Science
			<lb />
			Laboratory. He also produced the victim before the Judicial Magistrate First
			<lb />
			Class for recording her statement (Exh.16) under Section 164 of the Criminal
			<lb />
			Procedure Code (for short, &apos;Cr.P.C.&apos;). After completion of investigation PSI
			<lb />
			Iqbal Shaikh (PW-5) submitted chargesheet.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			4/9
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			Osk
			<lb />
			Apeal-1129-2018.odt
			<lb />
		</note>
		<body>
			5.
			<lb />
			Trial Court framed framed charge below Exh.4. The contents of
			<lb />
			the said were read over and explained to Appellant, to which he pleaded not
			<lb />
			guilty and claimed to be tried. The defence of Appellant was of total denial
			<lb />
			and false implication. In his defence, he stated that the parents of victim had
			<lb />
			availed a loan of Rs.1,20,000/-from the owner of brick kiln and to avoid
			<lb />
			return of it a false case is foisted upon him.
			<lb />
			6.
			<lb />
			The prosecution examined in all 6 witnesses in support of its case,
			<lb />
			namely, (i) Victim (PW-1), (ii) Smt.Bhujade (PW-2), mother of victim, (iii)
			<lb />
			Smt.Manisha Godambe (PW-3), Member of Mahila Dakshata Samitee, Padgha,
			<lb />
			(iv) Mr.Chhabu Waikar (PW-4), a native from the village of Appellant, (v) PSI
			<lb />
			Mr.Iqbal Shaikh (PW-5), Investigating Officer, then attached to Vadgaon Maval
			<lb />
			Police Station and (vi) Mr.Shamrao Kale (PW-6), Police Sub-Inspector, then
			<lb />
			attached to Padgha Police Station, Taluka Bhiwandi, District Thane. The
			<lb />
			Appellant examined Mr.Umesh Kale (DW-1), as a defence witness. The said
			<lb />
			person was working as Branch Manager with Venkateshwara Hatcheries
			<lb />
			Private Limited, Branch Chakan.
			<lb />
			The Trial Court after conducting a full fledged trial has convicted
			<lb />
			and sentenced the Appellant, as noted herein above.
			<lb />
			7.
			<lb />
			Mr.Rajiv Patil, learned Senior Advocate for the Appellant
			<lb />
			submitted that, the prosecution has failed to prove age of the victim being
			<lb />
			minor on the date of alleged incident. That, the prosecution has not
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			5/9
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			Osk
			<lb />
			Apeal-1129-2018.odt
			<lb />
		</note>
		<body>
			ascertained age of the victim, whether she was really minor or major on the
			<lb />
			date of incident. He submitted that, the Trial Court has erred in relying on
			<lb />
			School Leaving Certificate of the victim girl, while reaching to the conclusion
			<lb />
			that the victim was a minor on the date of incident. He submitted that, the
			<lb />
			School Leaving Certificate of victim was not produced with the chargesheet
			<lb />
			and therefore it was an error in producing and proving School Leaving
			<lb />
			Certificate of the victim by the Investigating Officer and accepting it by the
			<lb />
			Trial Court in para No.17 of the impugned Judgment and Order. He submitted
			<lb />
			that, from the provisions of P.O.C.S.O. Act, it is crystal clear that, the
			<lb />
			prosecution is under boundened duty to prove that the victim was a child.
			<lb />
			Unless the prosecution successfully establishes that, the victim was a child as
			<lb />
			contemplated by Section 2(d), a person cannot be convicted for the offence
			<lb />
			punishable under Sections 4 &amp; 6 of the P.O.C.S.O. Act. To buttress his
			<lb />
			submission he placed reliance on the decision of the Division Bench of this
			<lb />
			Court in the case of Ravi Anandrao Gurpude Vs. State of Maharashtra,
			<lb />
			reported in 2017 All MR (Cri.) 1509. He submitted that, as the prosecution
			<lb />
			has failed to prove the age of the victim being minor on the date of incident,
			<lb />
			the conviction of Appellant under the provisions of P.O.C.S.O. Act needs to be
			<lb />
			quashed and set-aside. He submitted that, as far as conviction of the Appellant
			<lb />
			under the provisions of I.P.C. is concerned, it is the case of the Appellant that,
			<lb />
			he has been falsely implicated by the parents of the victim to avoid to make
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			6/9
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			Osk
			<lb />
			Apeal-1129-2018.odt
			<lb />
		</note>
		<body>
			repayment of loan availed by them from the owner of the brick kiln. He
			<lb />
			therefore prayed that, the present Appeal may be allowed by acquitting the
			<lb />
			Appellant from all the charges.
			<lb />
			8.
			<lb />
			Ms.Kaushik, learned A.P.P. and Mr.Bapat, learned Advocate
			<lb />
			appointed to represent Respondent No.2 vehemently opposed the Appeal.
			<lb />
			They submitted that, the medical record produced and proved by PW-5 &amp; PW-
			<lb />
			6 clearly indicates that, the age of the victim as 16 years. They submitted that,
			<lb />
			even the victim in her First Information Report has stated her age as 17 years
			<lb />
			and therefore a clear inference can be drawn that, the prosecutrix was below
			<lb />
			the age of 18 years in the festival of Dewali in the month of October 2014.
			<lb />
			They submitted that, the DNA report which is at Exh.44 clearly mentions that,
			<lb />
			the Appellant is father of the baby delivered by victim. They therefore prayed
			<lb />
			that, the present Appeal may be dismissed.
			<lb />
			9.
			<lb />
			At the outset, it is to be noted here that, in the First Information
			<lb />
			Report the victim has stated her age as about 17 years. In her examination-in-
			<lb />
			chief which was recorded on 29 th July 2017, she has stated her age about 18
			<lb />
			years. It is to be noted here that, after her examination-in-chief was recorded
			<lb />
			on 29 th July 2017, she fell ill and while undergoing treatment expired on 24 th
			<lb />
			August 2017. The Appellant therefore could not cross-examine her. The
			<lb />
			evidence available on record clearly indicates that, the Medical Officer in their
			<lb />
			medical reports have stated age of victim as 16 years on 5 th May 2015 and 6 th
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			7/9
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			Osk
			<lb />
			Apeal-1129-2018.odt
			<lb />
		</note>
		<body>
			May 2015. The Appellant did not raise objection about the age of the victim
			<lb />
			during entire trial. The suggestion given by the Advocate for the Appellant to
			<lb />
			the Investigating Officer (PW-6) that, at the time of commission of offence,
			<lb />
			the victim was major has been denied by him. In his statement recorded under
			<lb />
			Section 313 of Cr.P.C., the Appellant has not disputed the age of the
			<lb />
			prosecutrix. Therefore from the evidence available on record, a safe
			<lb />
			conclusion can be drawn that, the prosecutrix was a child as contemplated
			<lb />
			under Section 2(d) of the P.O.C.S.O. Act in the festival of Diwali in the month
			<lb />
			of October 2014.
			<lb />
			10.
			<lb />
			There is another and most important fact established by the
			<lb />
			prosecution in the present case. PSI Iqbal Shaikh (PW-5) has proved the DNA
			<lb />
			report (Exh.44 colly.) issued by Regional Forensic Science Laboratory, Pune. In
			<lb />
			the said report it is stated that, all the 15 different genetic systems analysed
			<lb />
			with PCR, Arun Popatrao Pingale, i.e. Appellant, matched the obligate
			<lb />
			paternal alleles present in baby of victim. The report therefore opines that,
			<lb />
			the Appellant and victim are concluded to be biological parents of baby of
			<lb />
			victim. The allegation against the Appellant of committing sexual intercourse
			<lb />
			with the victim is thus proved beyond reasonable doubt by the prosecution by
			<lb />
			adopting the advanced scientific methods. The DNA report (Exh.44) has not
			<lb />
			been disputed and/or questioned by the Appellant. There is no cross-
			<lb />
			examination of any of the witnesses about the authenticity or genuineness on
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			8/9
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			Osk
			<lb />
			Apeal-1129-2018.odt
			<lb />
		</note>
		<body>
			the said report. Therefore even the cross-examination of the victim could not
			<lb />
			be conducted due to her unfortunate and untimely demise, the prosecution
			<lb />
			has successfully and beyond reasonable doubt has proved that the Appellant
			<lb />
			had committed sexual intercourse with the victim, who was a child in the
			<lb />
			month of October 2014. The prosecution has therefore proved all the charges
			<lb />
			levelled against the Appellant by leading cogent and convincing evidence in
			<lb />
			that behalf.
			<lb />
			11.
			<lb />
			Perusal of impugned Judgment indicates that, the Trial Court has
			<lb />
			not committed any error while convicting and sentencing the Appellant. There
			<lb />
			are no merits in the Appeal. Appeal is accordingly dismissed.
			<lb />
			[A.S. GADKARI, J.]
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			9/9
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="footnote">
			OMKAR
			<lb />
			SHIVAHAR
			<lb />
			KUMBHAKARN
			<lb />
			Digitally signed
			<lb />
			by OMKAR
			<lb />
			SHIVAHAR
			<lb />
			KUMBHAKARN
			<lb />
			Date:
			<lb />
			2022.07.12
			<lb />
			14:16:14 +0530
		</note>
	</text>
</tei>
