<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			REPORTABLE
			<lb />
			IN THE SUPREME COURT OF INDIA
			<lb />
			CIVIL ORIGINAL/APPELLATE JURISDICTION
			<lb />
			WRIT PETITION (CIVIL) NO. 99 OF 2018
			<lb />
			Swiss Ribbons Pvt. Ltd. &amp; Anr.
			<lb />
			…..Petitioners
			<lb />
			VERSUS
			<lb />
			Union of India &amp; Ors.
			<lb />
			…..Respondents
			<lb />
			WITH
			<lb />
			WRIT PETITION (CIVIL) NO. 100 OF 2018
			<lb />
			WRIT PETITION (CIVIL) NO. 115 OF 2018
			<lb />
			WRIT PETITION (CIVIL) NO. 459 OF 2018
			<lb />
			WRIT PETITION (CIVIL) NO. 598 OF 2018
			<lb />
			WRIT PETITION (CIVIL) NO. 775 OF 2018
			<lb />
			WRIT PETITION (CIVIL) NO. 822 OF 2018
			<lb />
			WRIT PETITION (CIVIL) NO. 849 OF 2018
			<lb />
			WRIT PETITION (CIVIL) NO. 1221 OF 2018
			<lb />
			SPECIAL LEAVE PETITION (CIVIL) NO. 28623 OF 2018
			<lb />
			WRIT PETITION (CIVIL) NO. 37 OF 2019
			<lb />
		</front>
		<note place="footnote">
			Digitally signed by R
			<lb />
			NATARAJAN
			<lb />
			Date: 2019.01.25
			<lb />
			12:26:58 IST
			<lb />
			Reason:
			<lb />
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			1
			<lb />
		</page>
		<front>
			J U D G M E N T
			<lb />
			R.F. Nariman, J.
			<lb />
		</front>
		<body>
			1.
			<lb />
			The present petitions assail the constitutional validity of various
			<lb />
			provisions of the Insolvency and Bankruptcy Code, 2016 [-Insolvency
			<lb />
			Code‖ or -Code‖]. Since we are deciding only questions relating to the
			<lb />
			constitutional validity of the Code, we are not going into the individual
			<lb />
			facts of any case.
			<lb />
			2.
			<lb />
			Shri Mukul Rohatgi, learned Senior Advocate, appearing in Writ
			<lb />
			Petition (Civil) No. 99 of 2018, has first and foremost argued that the
			<lb />
			members of the National Company Law Tribunal [-NCLT‖] and certain
			<lb />
			members of the National Company Law Appellate Tribunal [-NCLAT‖],
			<lb />
			apart from the President, have been appointed contrary to this Court&apos;s
			<lb />
			judgment in Madras Bar Association v. Union of India, (2015) 8
			<lb />
			SCC 583 [-Madras Bar Association (III)‖], and that therefore, this
			<lb />
			being so, all orders that are passed by such members, being passed
			<lb />
			contrary to the judgment of this Court in the aforesaid case, ought to
			<lb />
			be set aside. In any case, even assuming that the de facto doctrine
			<lb />
			would apply to save such orders, it is clear that such members ought to
			<lb />
			be restrained from passing any orders in future. In any case, until a
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			2
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			properly constituted committee, in accordance with the aforesaid
			<lb />
			judgment, reappoints them, they ought not to be allowed to function.
			<lb />
			He also argued that the administrative support for all tribunals should
			<lb />
			be from the Ministry of Law and Justice. However, even today, NCLT
			<lb />
			and NCLAT are functioning under the Ministry of Corporate Affairs.
			<lb />
			This again needs to be corrected immediately. A further technical
			<lb />
			violation also exists in that if the powers of the High Court are taken
			<lb />
			away, the NCLAT, as an appellate forum, should have the same
			<lb />
			convenience and expediency as existed prior to appeals going to the
			<lb />
			NCLAT. Since the NCLAT, as an appellate court, has a seat only at
			<lb />
			New Delhi, this would render the remedy inefficacious inasmuch as
			<lb />
			persons would have to travel from Tamil Nadu, Calcutta, and Bombay
			<lb />
			to New Delhi, whereas earlier, they could have approached the
			<lb />
			respective High Courts in their States. This again is directly contrary to
			<lb />
			Madras Bar Association v. Union of India, (2014) 10 SCC 1
			<lb />
			[-Madras Bar Association (II)‖], and to paragraph 123 in particular.
			<lb />
			Apart from the aforesaid technical objection, Shri Rohatgi assailed the
			<lb />
			legislative scheme that is contained in Section 7 of the Code, stating
			<lb />
			that there is no real difference between financial creditors and
			<lb />
			operational creditors. According to him, both types of creditors would
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			3
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			give either money in terms of loans or money&apos;s worth in terms of goods
			<lb />
			and services. Thus, there is no intelligible differentia between the two
			<lb />
			types of creditors, regard being had to the object sought to be
			<lb />
			achieved by the Code, namely, insolvency resolution, and if that is not
			<lb />
			possible, then ultimately, liquidation. Relying upon Shayara Bano v.
			<lb />
			Union of India, (2017) 9 SCC 1 [-Shayara Bano‖], he argued that
			<lb />
			such classification will not only be discriminatory, but also manifestly
			<lb />
			arbitrary, as under Sections 8 and 9 of the Code, an operational debtor
			<lb />
			is not only given notice of default, but is entitled to dispute the
			<lb />
			genuineness of the claim. In the case of a financial debtor, on the other
			<lb />
			hand, no notice is given and the financial debtor is not entitled to
			<lb />
			dispute the claim of the financial creditor. It is enough that a default as
			<lb />
			defined occurs, after which, even if the claim is disputed and even if
			<lb />
			there be a set-off and counterclaim, yet, the Code gets triggered at the
			<lb />
			behest of a financial creditor, without the corporate debtor being able
			<lb />
			to justify the fact that a genuine dispute is raised, which ought to be left
			<lb />
			for adjudication before ordinary courts and/or tribunals. Shri Rohatgi
			<lb />
			then argued that assuming that a valid distinction exists between
			<lb />
			financial and operational creditors, there is hostile discrimination
			<lb />
			against operational creditors. First and foremost, unless they amount
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			4
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			to 10% of the aggregate of the amount of debt owed, they have no
			<lb />
			voice in the committee of creditors. In any case, Sections 21 and 24 of
			<lb />
			the Code are discriminatory and manifestly arbitrary in that operational
			<lb />
			creditors do not have even a single vote in the committee of creditors
			<lb />
			which has very important functions to perform in the resolution process
			<lb />
			of corporate debtors. Shri Rohatgi then went on to assail the
			<lb />
			establishment of information utilities that are set up under the Code.
			<lb />
			According to him, under Section 210 of the Code, there can be private
			<lb />
			information utilities whose sole object would be to make a profit.
			<lb />
			Further, the said information utility is not only to collect financial data,
			<lb />
			but also to check whether a default has or has not occurred.
			<lb />
			Certification of such agency cannot substitute for adjudication. Thus,
			<lb />
			the certificate of an information utility is in the nature of a preliminary
			<lb />
			decree issued without any hearing and without any process of
			<lb />
			adjudication. Shri Rohatgi next argued that Section 12A of the Code is
			<lb />
			contrary to the directions of this Court in its order in Uttara Foods and
			<lb />
			Feeds Pvt. Ltd. v. Mona Pharmachem, Civil Appeal No. 18520/2017
			<lb />
			[decided on 13.11.2017], and that instead of following the said order,
			<lb />
			Section 12A now derails the settlement process by requiring the
			<lb />
			approval of at least ninety per cent of the voting share of the committee
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			5
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			of creditors. Unbridled and uncanalized power is given to the
			<lb />
			committee of creditors to reject legitimate settlements entered into
			<lb />
			between creditors and the corporate debtors. Shri Rohatgi then argued
			<lb />
			that the resolution professional, having been given powers of
			<lb />
			adjudication under the Code and Regulations, grant of adjudicatory
			<lb />
			power to a non-judicial authority is violative of basic aspects of
			<lb />
			dispensation of justice and access to justice. Lastly, a four-fold attack
			<lb />
			was raised against Section 29A, in particular, clause (c) thereof. First
			<lb />
			and foremost, Shri Rohatgi stated that the vested rights of erstwhile
			<lb />
			promoters to participate in the recovery process of a corporate debtor
			<lb />
			have been impaired by retrospective application of Section 29A.
			<lb />
			Section 29A, in any case, is contrary to the object sought to be
			<lb />
			achieved by the Code, in particular, speedy disposal of the resolution
			<lb />
			process as it will inevitably lead to challenges before the Adjudicating
			<lb />
			Authority and Appellate Authority, which will slow down and delay the
			<lb />
			insolvency resolution process. In particular, so far as Section 29A(c) is
			<lb />
			concerned, a blanket ban on participation of all promoters of corporate
			<lb />
			debtors, without any mechanism to weed out those who are
			<lb />
			unscrupulous and have brought the company to the ground, as against
			<lb />
			persons who are efficient managers, but who have not been able to
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			6
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			pay their debts due to various other reasons, would not only be
			<lb />
			manifestly arbitrary, but also be treating unequals as equals. Also,
			<lb />
			according to Shri Rohatgi, maximization of value of assets is an
			<lb />
			important goal to be achieved in the resolution process. Section 29A is
			<lb />
			contrary to such goal as an erstwhile promoter, who may outbid all
			<lb />
			other applicants and may have the best resolution plan, would be kept
			<lb />
			out at the threshold, thereby impairing the object of maximization of
			<lb />
			value of assets. Another argument that was made was that under
			<lb />
			Section 29A(c), a person&apos;s account may be classified as a non-
			<lb />
			performing asset [-NPA‖] in accordance with the guidelines of the
			<lb />
			Reserve Bank of India [-RBI‖], despite him not being a wilful defaulter.
			<lb />
			Also, the period of one year referred to in clause (c) is again wholly
			<lb />
			arbitrary and without any basis either in rationality or in law. Shri
			<lb />
			Rohatgi then trained his gun on Section 29A(j), and stated that persons
			<lb />
			who may be related parties in the sense that they may be relatives of
			<lb />
			the erstwhile promoters are also debarred, despite the fact that they
			<lb />
			may have no business connection with the erstwhile promoters who
			<lb />
			have been rendered ineligible by Section 29A.
			<lb />
			3.
			<lb />
			Shri K.V. Viswanathan, learned Senior Advocate, appearing in
			<lb />
			Writ Petition No.822 of 2018, strongly supported Shri Rohatgi and
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			7
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			argued the same points with great clarity and with various nuances of
			<lb />
			his own, which will be reflected in our judgment. Followed by Shri
			<lb />
			Viswanathan, Shri A.K. Gupta, Shri Pulkit Deora, Shri Devanshu Sajlan
			<lb />
			and Shri Deepak Joshi also made submissions with particular regard to
			<lb />
			discrimination against operational creditors.
			<lb />
			4.
			<lb />
			As against these submissions, Shri K.K. Venugopal, the learned
			<lb />
			Attorney General for India, and Shri Tushar Mehta, learned Solicitor
			<lb />
			General for India, appearing for the Union of India, and Shri Rakesh
			<lb />
			Dwivedi, learned Senior Advocate, appearing for the Reserve Bank of
			<lb />
			India, countered all the aforesaid submissions. They argued with
			<lb />
			reference to our judgments and Committee Reports that till the
			<lb />
			Insolvency Code was enacted, the regime of previous legislation had
			<lb />
			failed to maximize the value of stressed assets and had focused on
			<lb />
			reviving the corporate debtor with the same erstwhile management. All
			<lb />
			these legislations had failed, as a result of which, the Code was
			<lb />
			enacted to reorganize insolvency resolution of corporate debtors in a
			<lb />
			time bound manner to maximize the value of assets of such person.
			<lb />
			They further argued that there is a paradigm shift from the erstwhile
			<lb />
			management of a corporate debtor being in possession of stressed
			<lb />
			assets to creditors who now assume control from the erstwhile
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			8
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			management and are able to approve resolution plans of other better
			<lb />
			and more efficient managers, which would not only be in the interest of
			<lb />
			the corporate debtor itself but in the interest of all stakeholders,
			<lb />
			namely, all creditors, workers, and shareholders other than
			<lb />
			shareholdings of the erstwhile management. They referred to the
			<lb />
			Statement of Objects and Reasons, the Preamble, and various
			<lb />
			provisions of the Code, and to the Rules and Regulations made
			<lb />
			thereunder, to buttress their submissions. In particular, they referred to
			<lb />
			judgments which mandated a judicial hands-off when it came to laws
			<lb />
			relating to economic regulation. They argued that the legislature must
			<lb />
			get the maximum free play in the joints to experiment and come up
			<lb />
			with solutions to problems that have seemed intractable earlier. In
			<lb />
			particular, in combating the individual points made by the learned
			<lb />
			counsel appearing on behalf of the petitioners, they argued that none
			<lb />
			of the members of the NCLT or the NCLAT had been appointed
			<lb />
			contrary to the judgments of this Court in Union of India v. R. Gandhi,
			<lb />
			President, Madras Bar Association (2010) 11 SCC 1 [-Madras Bar
			<lb />
			Association (I)‖] and Madras Bar Association (III) (supra). They
			<lb />
			referred to affidavits filed before this Court to show that all such
			<lb />
			members had been appointed by a Committee consisting of two
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			9
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			Supreme Court Judges and two bureaucrats, in conformity with the
			<lb />
			aforesaid judgments. When it came to classification between financial
			<lb />
			and operational creditors, they argued that the differentiation between
			<lb />
			the two types of creditors occurs from the nature of the contracts
			<lb />
			entered into with them. Financial contracts involve large sums of
			<lb />
			money given by fewer persons, whereas operational creditors are
			<lb />
			much larger in number and the quantum of dues is generally small.
			<lb />
			Financial creditors have specified repayment schedules and
			<lb />
			agreements which entitle such creditors to recall the loan in totality on
			<lb />
			defaults being made, which the operational creditors do not have.
			<lb />
			Further, financial creditors are, from the start, involved with the
			<lb />
			assessment of viability of corporate debtors and are, therefore, better
			<lb />
			equipped to engage in restructuring of loans as well as reorganization
			<lb />
			of the corporate debtor&apos;s business in the event of financial stress. All
			<lb />
			these differentiae are not only intelligible, but directly relate to the
			<lb />
			objects sought to be achieved by the Code. Insofar as Section 7,
			<lb />
			relatable to financial creditors, and Sections 8 and 9, which relate to
			<lb />
			operational creditors are concerned, it is a fallacy to say that no notice
			<lb />
			is issued to the financial debtor on defaults made, as financial debtors
			<lb />
			are fully aware of the loan structure and the defaults that have been
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			10
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			made. Further, this Court&apos;s judgment in Innoventive Industries Ltd. v.
			<lb />
			ICICI Bank and Anr., (2018) 1 SCC 407 [-Innoventive Industries‖]
			<lb />
			has made it clear that under Section 7(5) of the Code, the Adjudicating
			<lb />
			Authority, in being -satisfied‖ that there is a default, has to issue notice
			<lb />
			to the corporate debtor, hear the corporate debtor, and then adjudicate
			<lb />
			upon the same. The reason why disputes raised by financial debtors
			<lb />
			are not gone into at the stage of triggering the Code is because the
			<lb />
			evidence of financial debts are contained in the documents of
			<lb />
			information utilities, banks, and financial institutions. Disputes which
			<lb />
			may be raised can be raised at the stage of filing of claims once the
			<lb />
			resolution process is underway. Also, by the very nature of financial
			<lb />
			debts, set-off and counterclaims by financial debtors are very rare and,
			<lb />
			in any case, wholly independent of the loan that has been granted to
			<lb />
			them. Insofar as operational creditors having no vote in the committee
			<lb />
			of creditors is concerned, this is because operational creditors are
			<lb />
			typically interested only in getting payment for supply of goods or
			<lb />
			services made by them, whereas financial creditors are typically
			<lb />
			involved in seeing that the entirety of their loan gets repaid, for which
			<lb />
			they are better equipped to go into the viability of corporate
			<lb />
			enterprises, both at the stage of grant of the loan and at the stage of
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			11
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			default. Also, the interests of operational creditors, when a resolution
			<lb />
			plan is to be approved, are well looked-after as the minimum that the
			<lb />
			operational creditors are to be paid is the liquidation value of assets.
			<lb />
			Apart from this, their interests are to be placed at par with the interests
			<lb />
			of financial creditors, and if this is not done, then the Adjudicating
			<lb />
			Authority intervenes to reject or modify resolution plans until the same
			<lb />
			is done. In the 80 cases that have been resolved since the Code has
			<lb />
			come into force, figures were also shown to this Court to indicate that
			<lb />
			not only are the operational creditors paid before the financial creditors
			<lb />
			under the resolution plan, but that the initial recovery of what is owed
			<lb />
			to them is slightly higher than what is owed to financial creditors.
			<lb />
			Insofar as Section 12A is concerned, they argued that once an
			<lb />
			application by a creditor is admitted by the Adjudicating Authority, the
			<lb />
			proceeding becomes a proceeding in rem and is no longer an
			<lb />
			individual proceeding but a collective proceeding. This being the case,
			<lb />
			it is important that when a resolution process is to begin and a
			<lb />
			committee of creditors is formed, it is that committee that is best
			<lb />
			equipped to deal with applications for withdrawal or settlement after
			<lb />
			admission of an insolvency petition. Ninety per cent of such creditors
			<lb />
			have been given this task as once the proceeding is in rem, to halt
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			12
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			such proceeding, which is for the benefit of all creditors generally, can
			<lb />
			only be if all or most of them agree to the same. They argued that the
			<lb />
			resolution professional has no adjudicatory powers under the Code or
			<lb />
			the Regulations, but is only to collate information. Even when he
			<lb />
			exercises his discretion to exercise his best judgment in certain
			<lb />
			situations, he does so administratively, and is subject to an
			<lb />
			adjudicatory body overseeing the same. When it comes to Section 29A
			<lb />
			of the Code, they argued that Section 29A does not disturb any vested
			<lb />
			or existing rights, as a resolution applicant does not have any vested or
			<lb />
			existing rights that can be disturbed, as has been held in ArcelorMittal
			<lb />
			India Private Limited v. Satish Kumar Gupta and Ors., Civil Appeal
			<lb />
			Nos. 9402-9405/2018 [decided on 04.10.2018] [-ArcelorMittal‖].
			<lb />
			Further, merely because this Section relies on antecedent facts for its
			<lb />
			application, does not mean that it is retrospective. Also, Section 29A
			<lb />
			subserves a very important object of the Code, which is to see that
			<lb />
			undesirable persons who are mentioned in all its clauses are rendered
			<lb />
			ineligible to submit resolution plans so that such persons may not
			<lb />
			come into the management of stressed corporate debtors. They also
			<lb />
			argued that Section 29A is not aimed at only persons who have
			<lb />
			committed acts of malfeasance, but also persons who are otherwise
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			13
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			unfit to be put in the saddle of the management of the corporate
			<lb />
			debtor, such as undischarged insolvents and persons who have been
			<lb />
			removed as directors under Section 164 of the Companies Act, 2013
			<lb />
			(for not filing financial statements or annual returns for any continuous
			<lb />
			period of 3 financial years, for example). They further argued that a
			<lb />
			period of one year is sufficient period within which a person, whose
			<lb />
			account has been declared NPA, should clear its dues. They referred
			<lb />
			to the RBI Regulations dealing with NPAs and stated that even before
			<lb />
			a person&apos;s account is declared NPA, a long rope is given for such
			<lb />
			person to clear off its debts. It is only when it does not do so, that its
			<lb />
			account is declared NPA in the first instance. Also, once the said
			<lb />
			guidelines are perused, it is clear that an account, which has been
			<lb />
			NPA for one year, is declared as substandard asset and it is for this
			<lb />
			reason that the one year period is given in Section 29A(c), which is
			<lb />
			based on reason, and is not arbitrary.
			<lb />
			5.
			<lb />
			Shri C.U. Singh, appearing on behalf of the Asset Reconstruction
			<lb />
			Company of India Limited, referred to the pre-existing state of
			<lb />
			legislation before the Code was enacted, and referred in detail to how
			<lb />
			all such legislations had failed to produce the necessary results. He
			<lb />
			also relied upon extracts from the Insolvency Act, 1986 of the United
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			14
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			Kingdom to buttress his point that worldwide, Insolvency Acts have
			<lb />
			moved away from mere liquidation so as to first concentrate on
			<lb />
			reconstruction of corporate debtors. Also, according to him, Section
			<lb />
			29A is not a Section aimed at malfeasance; it is aimed at rendering
			<lb />
			ineligible persons who are undesirable in the widest sense of the term,
			<lb />
			i.e., persons who are unfit to take over the management of a corporate
			<lb />
			debtor.
			<lb />
			PROLOGUE: THE PRE-EXISTING STATE OF THE LAW
			<lb />
			6.
			<lb />
			Having heard the rival contentions, it is important to first clear the
			<lb />
			air on what was the background which led to the enactment of the
			<lb />
			Insolvency Code. The erstwhile regime which led to the enactment of
			<lb />
			the Insolvency Code was discussed by the Bankruptcy Law Reforms
			<lb />
			Committee [-BLRC‖] in its Report dated 04.11.2015 as follows:
			<lb />
			-The current state of the bankruptcy process for firms
			<lb />
			is a highly fragmented framework. Powers of the
			<lb />
			creditor and the debtor under insolvency are provided
			<lb />
			for under different Acts. Given the conflicts between
			<lb />
			creditors and debtors in the resolution of insolvency as
			<lb />
			described in Section 3.2.2, the chances for
			<lb />
			consistency and efficiency in resolution are low when
			<lb />
			rights are separately defined. It is problematic that
			<lb />
			these different laws are implemented in different
			<lb />
			judicial fora. Cases that are decided at the
			<lb />
			tribunal/BIFR often come for review to the High Courts.
			<lb />
			This gives rise to two types of problems in
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			15
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			implementation of the resolution framework. The first
			<lb />
			is the lack of clarity of jurisdiction. In a situation where
			<lb />
			one forum decides on matters relating to the rights of
			<lb />
			the creditor, while another decides on those relating to
			<lb />
			the rights of the debtor, the decisions are readily
			<lb />
			appealed against and either stayed or overturned in a
			<lb />
			higher court. Ideally, if economic value is indeed to be
			<lb />
			preserved, there must be a single forum that hears
			<lb />
			both sides of the case and makes a judgment based
			<lb />
			on both. A second problem exacerbates the problems
			<lb />
			of multiple judicial fora. The fora entrusted with
			<lb />
			adjudicating on matters relating to insolvency and
			<lb />
			bankruptcy may not have the business or financial
			<lb />
			expertise, information or bandwidth to decide on such
			<lb />
			matters. This leads to delays and extensions in
			<lb />
			arriving at an outcome, and increases the vulnerability
			<lb />
			to appeals of the outcome.
			<lb />
			The uncertainty that these problems give rise to shows
			<lb />
			up in case law on matters of insolvency and
			<lb />
			bankruptcy in India. Judicial precedent is set by -case
			<lb />
			law‖ which helps flesh out the statutory laws. These
			<lb />
			may also, in some cases, pronounce new substantive
			<lb />
			law where the statute and precedent are silent. (Ravi,
			<lb />
			2015) reviews judgments of the High Courts on BIFR
			<lb />
			cases, the DRTs and DRATs, as well as a review of
			<lb />
			important judgments of the Supreme Court that have
			<lb />
			had a significant impact on the interpretation of
			<lb />
			existing insolvency legislation. The judgments
			<lb />
			reviewed are those after June 2002 when the
			<lb />
			SARFAESI Act came into effect. It is illustrative of
			<lb />
			both debtor and creditor led process of corporate
			<lb />
			insolvency, and reveals a matrix of fragmented and
			<lb />
			contrary outcomes, rather than coherent and
			<lb />
			consistent, being set as precedents.
			<lb />
			In such an environment of legislative and judicial
			<lb />
			uncertainty, the outcomes on insolvency and
			<lb />
			bankruptcy are poor. World Bank (2014) reports that
			<lb />
			the average time to resolve insolvency is four years in
			<lb />
			India, compared to 0.8 years in Singapore and 1 year
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			16
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			in London. Sengupta and Sharma, 2015 compare the
			<lb />
			number of new cases that file for corporate insolvency
			<lb />
			in the U.K., which has a robust insolvency law, to the
			<lb />
			status of cases registered at the BIFR under SICA,
			<lb />
			1985, as well as those filed for liquidation under
			<lb />
			Companies Act, 1956. They compare this with the
			<lb />
			number of cases files in the UK, and find a significantly
			<lb />
			higher turnover in the cases that are filed and cleared
			<lb />
			through the insolvency process in the UK. If we are to
			<lb />
			bring financing patterns back on track with the global
			<lb />
			norm, we must create a legal framework to make debt
			<lb />
			contracts credible channels of financing.
			<lb />
			This calls for a deeper redesign of the entire resolution
			<lb />
			process, rather than working on strengthening any
			<lb />
			single piece of it. India is not unusual in requiring this.
			<lb />
			In all countries, bankruptcy laws undergo significant
			<lb />
			changes over the period of two decades or more. For
			<lb />
			example, the insolvency resolution framework in the
			<lb />
			UK is the Insolvency Act of 1986, which was
			<lb />
			substantially modified with the Insolvency Act of 2000,
			<lb />
			and the Enterprise Act of 2002. The first Act for
			<lb />
			bankruptcy resolution in the US that lasted for a
			<lb />
			significant time was the Bankruptcy Act of 1889. This
			<lb />
			was followed by the Act of 1938, the Reform Act of
			<lb />
			1978, the Act of 1984, the Act of 1994, a related
			<lb />
			consumer protection Act of 2005. Singapore proposed
			<lb />
			a bankruptcy reform in 2013, while there are significant
			<lb />
			changes that are being proposed in the US and the
			<lb />
			Italian bankruptcy framework this year in 2015.
			<lb />
			Several of these are structural reforms with
			<lb />
			fundamental implications on resolving insolvency….‖
			<lb />
			The BLRC went on to state:
			<lb />
			-[…..] India is one of the youngest republics in the
			<lb />
			world, with a high concentration of the most dynamic
			<lb />
			entrepreneurs. Yet these game changers and growth
			<lb />
			drivers are crippled by an environment that takes
			<lb />
			some of the longest times and highest costs by world
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			17
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			standards to resolve any problems that arise while
			<lb />
			repaying dues on debt. This problem leads to grave
			<lb />
			consequences: India has some of the lowest credit
			<lb />
			compared to the size of the economy. This is a
			<lb />
			troublesome state to be in, particularly for a young
			<lb />
			emerging economy with the entrepreneurial dynamism
			<lb />
			of India.‖
			<lb />
			xxx xxx xxx
			<lb />
			-Speed is of essence for the working of the bankruptcy
			<lb />
			code, for two reasons. First, while the ‗calm period&apos;
			<lb />
			can help keep an organization afloat, without the full
			<lb />
			clarity of ownership and control, significant decisions
			<lb />
			cannot be made. Without effective leadership, the firm
			<lb />
			will tend to atrophy and fail. The longer the delay, the
			<lb />
			more likely it is that liquidation will be the only answer.
			<lb />
			Second, the liquidation value tends to go down with
			<lb />
			time as many assets suffer from a high economic rate
			<lb />
			of depreciation.
			<lb />
			From the viewpoint of creditors, a good realization can
			<lb />
			generally be obtained if the firm is sold as a going
			<lb />
			concern. Hence, when delays induce liquidation, there
			<lb />
			is value destruction. Further, even in liquidation, the
			<lb />
			realization is lower when there are delays. Hence,
			<lb />
			delays cause value destruction. Thus, achieving a
			<lb />
			high recovery rate is primarily about identifying and
			<lb />
			combating the sources of delay.
			<lb />
			This same idea is found in FSLRC&apos;s (Financial Sector
			<lb />
			Legislative Reforms Commission) treatment of the
			<lb />
			failure of financial firms. The most important objective
			<lb />
			in designing a legal framework for dealing with firm
			<lb />
			failure is the need for speed.‖
			<lb />
			The pre-existing scenario has been noticed in some of our judgments.
			<lb />
			In Madras Petrochem Ltd. and Anr. v. Board for Industrial and
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			18
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			Financial Reconstruction and Ors., (2016) 4 SCC 1, this Court
			<lb />
			found:
			<lb />
			-40.……The Eradi Committee Report relating to
			<lb />
			insolvency and winding up of companies dated 31-7-
			<lb />
			2000, observed that out of 3068 cases referred to
			<lb />
			BIFR from 1987 to 2000 all but 1062 cases have been
			<lb />
			disposed of. Out of the cases disposed of, 264 cases
			<lb />
			were revived, 375 cases were under negotiation for
			<lb />
			revival process, 741 cases were recommended for
			<lb />
			winding up, and 626 cases were dismissed as not
			<lb />
			maintainable. These facts and figures speak for
			<lb />
			themselves and place a big question mark on the utility
			<lb />
			of the Sick Industrial Companies (Special Provisions)
			<lb />
			Act, 1985. The Committee further pointed out that
			<lb />
			effectiveness of the Sick Industrial Companies
			<lb />
			(Special Provisions) Act, 1985 as has been pointed out
			<lb />
			earlier, has been severely undermined by reason of
			<lb />
			the enormous delays involved in the disposal of cases
			<lb />
			by BIFR. (See Paras 5.8, 5.9 and 5.15 of the Report.)
			<lb />
			Consequently, the Committee recommended that the
			<lb />
			Sick Industrial Companies (Special Provisions) Act,
			<lb />
			1985 be repealed and the provisions thereunder for
			<lb />
			revival and rehabilitation should be telescoped into the
			<lb />
			structure of the Companies Act, 1956 itself.‖
			<lb />
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
			xxx xxx xxx
			<lb />
			-43.……In fact, another interesting document is the
			<lb />
			Report on Trend and Progress of Banking in India
			<lb />
			2011-2012 for the year ended 30-6-2012 submitted by
			<lb />
			Reserve Bank of India to the Central Government in
			<lb />
			terms of Section 36(2) of the Banking Regulation Act,
			<lb />
			1949. In Table IV.14 the Report provides statistics
			<lb />
			regarding trends in non-performing assets bank-wise,
			<lb />
			group-wise. As per the said Table, the opening
			<lb />
			balance of non-performing assets in public sector
			<lb />
			banks for the year 2011-2012 was Rs 746 billion but
			<lb />
			the closing balance for 2011-2012 was Rs 1172 billion
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			19
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			only. The total amount recovered through the
			<lb />
			Securitisation and Reconstruction of Financial Assets
			<lb />
			and Enforcement of Security Interest Act, 2002 during
			<lb />
			2011-2012 registered a decline compared to the
			<lb />
			previous year, but, even then, the amounts recovered
			<lb />
			under the said Act constituted 70% of the total amount
			<lb />
			recovered. The amounts recovered under the
			<lb />
			Recovery of Debts Due to Banks and Financial
			<lb />
			Institutions Act, 1993 constituted only 28%. All this
			<lb />
			would go to show that the amounts that public sector
			<lb />
			banks and financial institutions have to recover are in
			<lb />
			staggering figures and at long last at least one
			<lb />
			statutory measure has proved to be of some efficacy.
			<lb />
			This Court would be loathe to give such an
			<lb />
			interpretation as would thwart the recovery process
			<lb />
			under the Securitisation and Reconstruction of
			<lb />
			Financial Assets and Enforcement of Security Interest
			<lb />
			Act, 2002 which Act alone seems to have worked to
			<lb />
			some extent at least.‖
			<lb />
			Similarly, in Innoventive Industries (supra), this Court found:
			<lb />
			-13. One of the important objectives of the Code is to
			<lb />
			bring the insolvency law in India under a single unified
			<lb />
			umbrella with the object of speeding up of the
			<lb />
			insolvency process. As per the data available with the
			<lb />
			World Bank in 2016, insolvency resolution in India took
			<lb />
			4.3 years on an average, which was much higher
			<lb />
			when compared with the United Kingdom (1 year),
			<lb />
			USA (1.5 years) and South Africa (2 years). The World
			<lb />
			Bank&apos;s Ease of Doing Business Index, 2015, ranked
			<lb />
			India as country number 135 out of 190 countries on
			<lb />
			the ease of resolving insolvency based on various
			<lb />
			indicia.‖
			<lb />
			Further, this Court in ArcelorMittal (supra) observed:
			<lb />
			-62. Previous legislation, namely, the Sick Industrial
			<lb />
			Companies (Special Provisions) Act, 1985, and the
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			20
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			Recovery of Debts Due to Banks and Financial
			<lb />
			Institutions Act, 1993, which made provision for
			<lb />
			rehabilitation of sick companies and repayment of
			<lb />
			loans availed by them, were found to have completely
			<lb />
			failed. This was taken note of by our judgment
			<lb />
			in Madras Petrochem Ltd. v. Board for Industrial and
			<lb />
			Financial Reconstruction, (2016) 4 SCC 1……‖
			<lb />
			xxx xxx xxx
			<lb />
			-63. These two enactments were followed by the
			<lb />
			Securitization and Reconstruction of Financial Assets
			<lb />
			and Enforcement of Securities Interest Act, 2002. As
			<lb />
			has been noted hereinabove, amounts recovered
			<lb />
			under the said Act recorded improvement over the
			<lb />
			previous two enactments, but this was yet found to be
			<lb />
			inadequate.‖
			<lb />
			JUDICIAL HANDS-OFF QUA ECONOMIC LEGISLATION
			<lb />
			7.
			<lb />
			In the United States, at one point of time, Justice Stephen Field&apos;s
			<lb />
			dissents of the 19 th Century were translated into majority opinions in
			<lb />
			the early 20 th Century. This was referred to as the Lochner era, in
			<lb />
			which the U.S. Supreme Court, over a period of 40 years, consistently
			<lb />
			struck down legislation which was economic in nature as such
			<lb />
			legislation did not, according to the Court, square with property rights.
			<lb />
			As a result, a large number of minimum wage laws, maximum hours of
			<lb />
			work in factories laws, child labour laws, etc. were struck down. The
			<lb />
			result, as is well known, is that President Roosevelt initiated a court-
			<lb />
			packing plan in which he sought to get authorization from Congress to
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			21
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			appoint additional judges to the Supreme Court, who would have then
			<lb />
			overruled the Lochner line of precedents. As it turned out, that became
			<lb />
			unnecessary as Justice Roberts switched his vote so that a 5:4
			<lb />
			majority from 1937 onwards upheld economic legislation. It is important
			<lb />
			to note that the dissents of Justice Holmes and Justice Brandeis now
			<lb />
			became the law. Justice Holmes had, in his dissent in Lochner v. New
			<lb />
			York, 198 U.S. 45 (1905), stated:
			<lb />
			-This case is decided upon an economic theory
			<lb />
			which a large part of the country does not entertain. If
			<lb />
			it were a question whether I agreed with that theory, I
			<lb />
			should desire to study it further and long before
			<lb />
			making up my mind. But I do not conceive that to be
			<lb />
			my duty, because I strongly believe that my agreement
			<lb />
			or disagreement has nothing to do with the right of a
			<lb />
			majority to embody their opinions in law. It is settled by
			<lb />
			various decisions of this court that state constitutions
			<lb />
			and state laws may regulate life in many ways which
			<lb />
			we, as legislators, might think as injudicious, or, if you
			<lb />
			like, as tyrannical, as this, and which, equally with this,
			<lb />
			interfere with the liberty to contract. Sunday laws and
			<lb />
			usury laws are ancient examples. A more modern one
			<lb />
			is the prohibition of lotteries. The liberty of the citizen
			<lb />
			to do as he likes so long as he does not interfere with
			<lb />
			the liberty of others to do the same, which has been a
			<lb />
			shibboleth for some well-known writers, is interfered
			<lb />
			with by school laws, by the Post Office, by every state
			<lb />
			or municipal institution which takes his money for
			<lb />
			purposes thought desirable, whether he likes it or not.
			<lb />
			The Fourteenth Amendment does not enact Mr.
			<lb />
			Herbert Spencer&apos;s Social Statics. The other day, we
			<lb />
			sustained the Massachusetts vaccination law.
			<lb />
			Jacobson v. Massachusetts, 197 U. S. 11. United
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			22
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			States and state statutes and decisions cutting down
			<lb />
			the liberty to contract by way of combination are
			<lb />
			familiar to this court. Northern Securities Co. v. United
			<lb />
			States, 193 U. S. 197. Two years ago, we upheld the
			<lb />
			prohibition of sales of stock on margins or for future
			<lb />
			delivery in the constitution of California. Otis v.
			<lb />
			Parker, 187 U. S. 606. The decision sustaining an
			<lb />
			eight hour law for miners is still recent. Holden v.
			<lb />
			Hardy, 169 U. S. 366. Some of these laws embody
			<lb />
			convictions or prejudices which judges are likely to
			<lb />
			share. Some may not. But a constitution is not
			<lb />
			intended to embody a particular economic theory,
			<lb />
			whether of paternalism and the organic relation of the
			<lb />
			citizen to the State or of laissez faire.
			<lb />
			It is made for people of fundamentally differing
			<lb />
			views, and the accident of our finding certain opinions
			<lb />
			natural and familiar or novel and even shocking ought
			<lb />
			not to conclude our judgment upon the question
			<lb />
			whether statutes embodying them conflict with the
			<lb />
			Constitution of the United States.
			<lb />
			General propositions do not decide concrete
			<lb />
			cases. The decision will depend on a judgment or
			<lb />
			intuition more subtle than any articulate major premise.
			<lb />
			But I think that the proposition just stated, if it is
			<lb />
			accepted, will carry us far toward the end. Every
			<lb />
			opinion tends to become a law. I think that the word
			<lb />
			liberty in the Fourteenth Amendment is perverted
			<lb />
			when it is held to prevent the natural outcome of a
			<lb />
			dominant opinion, unless it can be said that a rational
			<lb />
			and fair man necessarily would admit that the statute
			<lb />
			proposed would infringe fundamental principles as
			<lb />
			they have been understood by the traditions of our
			<lb />
			people and our law. It does not need research to show
			<lb />
			that no such sweeping condemnation can be passed
			<lb />
			upon the statute before us. A reasonable man might
			<lb />
			think it a proper measure on the score of health. Men
			<lb />
			whom I certainly could not pronounce unreasonable
			<lb />
			would uphold it as a first instalment of a general
			<lb />
			regulation of the hours of work. Whether in the latter
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			23
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			aspect it would be open to the charge of inequality I
			<lb />
			think it unnecessary to discuss.‖ 1
			<lb />
			Similarly, in New State Ice Co. v. Liebman, 285 U.S. 262 (1932),
			<lb />
			Justice Brandeis echoed Justice Holmes as follows:
			<lb />
			-The discoveries in physical science, the
			<lb />
			triumphs in invention, attest the value of the process of
			<lb />
			trial and error. In large measure, these advances have
			<lb />
			been due to experimentation. In those fields
			<lb />
			experimentation has, for two centuries, been not only
			<lb />
			free but encouraged. Some people assert that our
			<lb />
			present plight is due, in part, to the limitations set by
			<lb />
			courts upon experimentation in the fields of social and
			<lb />
			economic science; and to the discouragement to which
			<lb />
			proposals for betterment there have been subjected
			<lb />
			otherwise. There must be power in the States and the
			<lb />
			Nation to remould, through experimentation, our
			<lb />
			economic practices and institutions to meet changing
			<lb />
			social and economic needs. I cannot believe that the
			<lb />
			framers of the Fourteenth Amendment, or the States
			<lb />
			which ratified it, intended to deprive us of the power to
			<lb />
			correct the evils of technological unemployment and
			<lb />
			excess productive capacity which have attended
			<lb />
			progress in the useful arts.
			<lb />
			To stay experimentation in things social and
			<lb />
			economic is a grave responsibility. Denial of the right
			<lb />
			to experiment may be fraught with serious
			<lb />
			consequences to the Nation. It is one of the happy
			<lb />
			incidents of the federal system that a single
			<lb />
			courageous State may, if its citizens choose, serve as
			<lb />
			a laboratory; and try novel social and economic
			<lb />
			experiments without risk to the rest of the country. This
			<lb />
			Court has the power to prevent an experiment. We
			<lb />
			may strike down the statute which embodies it on the
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			1 Lochner v. New York, 198 U.S. 45, 75-76 (1905).
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			24
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			ground that, in our opinion, the measure is arbitrary,
			<lb />
			capricious or unreasonable. We have power to do this,
			<lb />
			because the due process clause has been held by the
			<lb />
			Court applicable to matters of substantive law as well
			<lb />
			as to matters of procedure. But in the exercise of this
			<lb />
			high power, we must be ever on our guard, lest we
			<lb />
			erect our prejudices into legal principles. If we would
			<lb />
			guide by the light of reason, we must let our minds be
			<lb />
			bold.‖ 2
			<lb />
			The Lochner doctrine was finally buried in Ferguson v. Skrupa, 372
			<lb />
			U.S. 726 (1962), where the Supreme Court held:
			<lb />
			-Both the District Court in the present case and
			<lb />
			the Pennsylvania court in Stone adopted the
			<lb />
			philosophy of Adams v. Tanner, and cases like it, that
			<lb />
			it is the province of courts to draw on their own views
			<lb />
			as to the morality, legitimacy, and usefulness of a
			<lb />
			particular business in order to decide whether a statute
			<lb />
			bears too heavily upon that business and, by so doing,
			<lb />
			violates due process. Under the system of government
			<lb />
			created by our Constitution, it is up to legislatures, not
			<lb />
			courts, to decide on the wisdom and utility of
			<lb />
			legislation. There was a time when the Due Process
			<lb />
			Clause was used by this Court to strike down laws
			<lb />
			which were thought unreasonable, that is, unwise or
			<lb />
			incompatible with some particular economic or social
			<lb />
			philosophy. In this manner, the Due Process Clause
			<lb />
			was used, for example, to nullify laws prescribing
			<lb />
			maximum hours for work in bakeries, Lochner v. New
			<lb />
			York, 198 U. S. 45 (1905), outlawing -yellow dog‖
			<lb />
			contracts, Coppage v. Kansas, 236 U. S. 1 (1915),
			<lb />
			setting minimum wages for women, Adkins v.
			<lb />
			Children&apos;s Hospital, 261 U. S. 525 (1923), and fixing
			<lb />
			2 New State Ice Co. v. Liebman, 285 U.S. 262, 310-311 (1932).
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			25
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			the weight of loaves of bread, Jay Burns Baking Co. v.
			<lb />
			Bryan, 264 U. S. 504 (1924). This intrusion by the
			<lb />
			judiciary into the realm of legislative value judgments
			<lb />
			was strongly objected to at the time, particularly by Mr.
			<lb />
			Justice Holmes and Mr. Justice Brandeis. Dissenting
			<lb />
			from the Court&apos;s invalidating a state statute which
			<lb />
			regulated the resale price of theatre and other tickets,
			<lb />
			Mr. Justice Holmes said,
			<lb />
			-I think the proper course is to recognize that
			<lb />
			a state Legislature can do whatever it sees fit
			<lb />
			to do unless it is restrained by some express
			<lb />
			prohibition in the Constitution of the United
			<lb />
			States or of the State, and that Courts should
			<lb />
			be careful not to extend such prohibitions
			<lb />
			beyond their obvious meaning by reading into
			<lb />
			them conceptions of public policy that the
			<lb />
			particular Court may happen to entertain.
			<lb />
			And, in an earlier case, he had emphasized that,
			<lb />
			‗The criterion of constitutionality is not whether we
			<lb />
			believe the law to be for the public good&apos; [Adkins v.
			<lb />
			Children&apos;s Hospital, 261 U. S. 525, 567, 570 (1923)
			<lb />
			(dissenting opinion)].
			<lb />
			The doctrine that prevailed in Lochner, Coppage,
			<lb />
			Adkins, Burns, and like cases -that due process
			<lb />
			authorizes courts to hold laws unconstitutional when
			<lb />
			they believe the legislature has acted unwisely -has
			<lb />
			long since been discarded. We have returned to the
			<lb />
			original constitutional proposition that courts do not
			<lb />
			substitute their social and economic beliefs for the
			<lb />
			judgment of legislative bodies, who are elected to pass
			<lb />
			laws. As this Court stated in a unanimous opinion in
			<lb />
			1941, -We are not concerned… with the wisdom,
			<lb />
			need, or appropriateness of the legislation. [Olsen v.
			<lb />
			Nebraska ex rel. Western Reference &amp; Bond Assn.,
			<lb />
			313 U. S. 236, 246 (1941)]‖
			<lb />
			Legislative bodies have broad scope to
			<lb />
			experiment with economic problems, and this Court
			<lb />
			does not sit to, -subject the state to an intolerable
			<lb />
			supervision hostile to the basic principles of our
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			26
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			government and wholly beyond the protection which
			<lb />
			the general clause of the Fourteenth Amendment was
			<lb />
			intended to secure‖ [Sproles v. Binford, 286 U.S. 374,
			<lb />
			388 (1932)]. It is now settled that States -have power
			<lb />
			to legislate against what are found to be injurious
			<lb />
			practices in their internal commercial and business
			<lb />
			affairs, so long as their laws do not run afoul of some
			<lb />
			specific federal constitutional prohibition, or of some
			<lb />
			valid federal law‖ [Lincoln Federal Labor Union, etc. v.
			<lb />
			Northwestern Iron &amp; Metal Co., 335 U.S. 525, 536
			<lb />
			(1949)].
			<lb />
			In the face of our abandonment of the use of the
			<lb />
			-vague contours‖ [Adkins v. Children&apos;s Hospital, 261 U.
			<lb />
			S. 525, 535 (1923)] of the Due Process Clause to
			<lb />
			nullify laws which a majority of the Court believed to be
			<lb />
			economically unwise, reliance on Adams v. Tanner is
			<lb />
			as mistaken as would be adherence to Adkins v.
			<lb />
			Children&apos;s Hospital, overruled by West Coast Hotel Co.
			<lb />
			v. Parrish, 300 U. S. 379 (1937). Not only has the
			<lb />
			philosophy of Adams been abandoned, but also this
			<lb />
			Court, almost 15 years ago, expressly pointed to
			<lb />
			another opinion of this Court as having -clearly
			<lb />
			undermined‖ Adams. [Lincoln Federal Labor Union,
			<lb />
			etc. v. Northwestern Iron &amp; Metal Co., 335 U.S. 525
			<lb />
			(1949)]. We conclude that the Kansas Legislature was
			<lb />
			free to decide for itself that legislation was needed to
			<lb />
			deal with the business of debt adjusting.
			<lb />
			Unquestionably, there are arguments showing that the
			<lb />
			business of debt adjusting has social utility, but such
			<lb />
			arguments are properly addressed to the legislature,
			<lb />
			not to us. We refuse to sit as a -superlegislature to
			<lb />
			weigh the wisdom of legislation,‖ [Day-Brite Lighting,
			<lb />
			Inc., v. Missouri, 342 U.S. 421, 423 (1923)] and we
			<lb />
			emphatically refuse to go back to the time when courts
			<lb />
			used the Due Process Clause -to strike down state
			<lb />
			laws, regulatory of business and industrial conditions,
			<lb />
			because they may be unwise, improvident, or out of
			<lb />
			harmony with a particular school of thought‖
			<lb />
			[Williamson v. Lee Optical Co., 348 U.S. 483, 488
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			27
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			(1955)]. Nor are we able or willing to draw lines by
			<lb />
			calling a law -prohibitory‖ or -regulatory.‖ Whether the
			<lb />
			legislature takes for its textbook Adam Smith, Herbert
			<lb />
			Spencer, Lord Keynes, or some other is no concern of
			<lb />
			ours. The Kansas debt adjusting statute may be wise
			<lb />
			or unwise. But relief, if any be needed, lies not with us,
			<lb />
			but with the body constituted to pass laws for the State
			<lb />
			of Kansas.
			<lb />
			Nor is the statute&apos;s exception of lawyers a denial
			<lb />
			of equal protection of the laws to nonlawyers. Statutes
			<lb />
			create many classifications which do not deny equal
			<lb />
			protection; it is only -invidious discrimination‖ which
			<lb />
			offends the Constitution. The business of debt
			<lb />
			adjusting gives rise to a relationship of trust in which
			<lb />
			the debt adjuster will, in a situation of insolvency, be
			<lb />
			marshalling assets in the manner of a proceeding in
			<lb />
			bankruptcy. The debt adjuster&apos;s client may need
			<lb />
			advice as to the legality of the various claims against
			<lb />
			him remedies existing under state laws governing
			<lb />
			debtor-creditor relationships, or provisions of the
			<lb />
			Bankruptcy Act -advice which a nonlawyer cannot
			<lb />
			lawfully give him. If the State of Kansas wants to limit
			<lb />
			debt adjusting to lawyers, the Equal Protection Clause
			<lb />
			does not forbid it. We also find no merit in the
			<lb />
			contention that the Fourteenth Amendment is violated
			<lb />
			by the failure of the Kansas statute&apos;s title to be as
			<lb />
			specific as appellee thinks it ought to be under the
			<lb />
			Kansas Constitution.‖ 3
			<lb />
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
			8.
			<lb />
			In this country, this Court in R.K. Garg v. Union of India, (1981)
			<lb />
			4 SCC 675 has held:
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			3 Ferguson v. Skrupa, 372 U.S. 726, 728-733 (1962).
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			28
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			-8. Another rule of equal importance is that laws
			<lb />
			relating to economic activities should be viewed with
			<lb />
			greater latitude than laws touching civil rights such as
			<lb />
			freedom of speech, religion etc. It has been said by no
			<lb />
			less a person than Holmes, J., that the legislature
			<lb />
			should be allowed some play in the joints, because it
			<lb />
			has to deal with complex problems which do not admit
			<lb />
			of solution through any doctrinaire or strait-jacket
			<lb />
			formula and this is particularly true in case of
			<lb />
			legislation dealing with economic matters, where,
			<lb />
			having regard to the nature of the problems required to
			<lb />
			be dealt with, greater play in the joints has to be
			<lb />
			allowed to the legislature. The court should feel more
			<lb />
			inclined to give judicial deference to legislative
			<lb />
			judgment in the field of economic regulation than in
			<lb />
			other areas where fundamental human rights are
			<lb />
			involved. Nowhere has this admonition been more
			<lb />
			felicitously expressed than in Morey v. Doud [351 US
			<lb />
			457 : 1 L Ed 2d 1485 (1957)] where Frankfurter, J.,
			<lb />
			said in his inimitable style:
			<lb />
			-In the utilities, tax and economic regulation
			<lb />
			cases, there are good reasons for judicial
			<lb />
			self-restraint if not judicial deference to
			<lb />
			legislative judgment. The legislature after all
			<lb />
			has the affirmative responsibility. The courts
			<lb />
			have only the power to destroy, not to
			<lb />
			reconstruct. When these are added to the
			<lb />
			complexity of economic regulation, the
			<lb />
			uncertainty, the liability to error, the
			<lb />
			bewildering conflict of the experts, and the
			<lb />
			number of times the judges have been
			<lb />
			overruled by events -self-limitation can be
			<lb />
			seen to be the path to judicial wisdom and
			<lb />
			institutional prestige and stability.‖
			<lb />
			The Court must always remember that -legislation is
			<lb />
			directed to practical problems, that the economic
			<lb />
			mechanism is highly sensitive and complex, that many
			<lb />
			problems are singular and contingent, that laws are
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			29
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			not abstract propositions and do not relate to abstract
			<lb />
			units and are not to be measured by abstract
			<lb />
			symmetry‖; -that exact wisdom and nice adaption of
			<lb />
			remedy are not always possible‖ and that -judgment is
			<lb />
			largely a prophecy based on meagre and
			<lb />
			uninterpreted
			<lb />
			experience‖.
			<lb />
			Every
			<lb />
			legislation,
			<lb />
			particularly in economic matters is essentially empiric
			<lb />
			and it is based on experimentation or what one may
			<lb />
			call trial and error method and therefore it cannot
			<lb />
			provide for all possible situations or anticipate all
			<lb />
			possible abuses. There may be crudities and
			<lb />
			inequities in complicated experimental economic
			<lb />
			legislation but on that account alone it cannot be
			<lb />
			struck down as invalid. The courts cannot, as pointed
			<lb />
			out by the United States Supreme Court in Secretary
			<lb />
			of Agriculture v. Central Roig Refining Company [94 L
			<lb />
			Ed 381 : 338 US 604 (1950)] be converted into
			<lb />
			tribunals for relief from such crudities and inequities.
			<lb />
			There may even be possibilities of abuse, but that too
			<lb />
			cannot of itself be a ground for invalidating the
			<lb />
			legislation, because it is not possible for any
			<lb />
			legislature to anticipate as if by some divine
			<lb />
			prescience, distortions and abuses of its legislation
			<lb />
			which may be made by those subject to its provisions
			<lb />
			and to provide against such distortions and abuses.
			<lb />
			Indeed, howsoever great may be the care bestowed
			<lb />
			on its framing, it is difficult to conceive of a legislation
			<lb />
			which is not capable of being abused by perverted
			<lb />
			human ingenuity. The Court must therefore adjudge
			<lb />
			the constitutionality of such legislation by the
			<lb />
			generality of its provisions and not by its crudities or
			<lb />
			inequities or by the possibilities of abuse of any of its
			<lb />
			provisions. If any crudities, inequities or possibilities of
			<lb />
			abuse come to light, the legislature can always step in
			<lb />
			and enact suitable amendatory legislation. That is the
			<lb />
			essence of pragmatic approach which must guide and
			<lb />
			inspire the legislature in dealing with complex
			<lb />
			economic issues.‖
			<lb />
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
			xxx xxx xxx
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			30
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			19. It is true that certain immunities and exemptions
			<lb />
			are granted to persons investing their unaccounted
			<lb />
			money in purchase of Special Bearer Bonds but that is
			<lb />
			an inducement which has to be offered for unearthing
			<lb />
			black money. Those who have successfully evaded
			<lb />
			taxation and concealed their income or wealth despite
			<lb />
			the stringent tax laws and the efforts of the tax
			<lb />
			department are not likely to disclose their unaccounted
			<lb />
			money without some inducement by way of immunities
			<lb />
			and exemptions and it must necessarily be left to the
			<lb />
			legislature to decide what immunities and exemptions
			<lb />
			would be sufficient for the purpose. It would be outside
			<lb />
			the province of the Court to consider if any particular
			<lb />
			immunity or exemption is necessary or not for the
			<lb />
			purpose of inducing disclosure of black money. That
			<lb />
			would depend upon diverse fiscal and economic
			<lb />
			considerations based on practical necessity and
			<lb />
			administrative expediency and would also involve a
			<lb />
			certain amount of experimentation on which the Court
			<lb />
			would be least fitted to pronounce. The Court would
			<lb />
			not have the necessary competence and expertise to
			<lb />
			adjudicate upon such an economic issue. The Court
			<lb />
			cannot possibly assess or evaluate what would be the
			<lb />
			impact of a particular immunity or exemption and
			<lb />
			whether it would serve the purpose in view or not.
			<lb />
			There are so many imponderables that would enter
			<lb />
			into the determination that it would be wise for the
			<lb />
			Court not to hazard an opinion where even economists
			<lb />
			may differ. The Court must while examining the
			<lb />
			constitutional validity of a legislation of this kind, -be
			<lb />
			resilient, not rigid, forward looking, not static, liberal,
			<lb />
			not verbal‖ and the Court must always bear in mind the
			<lb />
			constitutional proposition enunciated by the Supreme
			<lb />
			Court of the United States in Munn v. Illinois [94 US
			<lb />
			13] , namely, -that courts do not substitute their social
			<lb />
			and economic beliefs for the judgment of legislative
			<lb />
			bodies‖. The Court must defer to legislative judgment
			<lb />
			in matters relating to social and economic policies and
			<lb />
			must not interfere, unless the exercise of legislative
			<lb />
			judgment appears to be palpably arbitrary. The Court
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			31
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			should constantly remind itself of what the Supreme
			<lb />
			Court of the United States said in Metropolis Theater
			<lb />
			Company v. City of Chicago [57 L Ed 730 : 228 US 61
			<lb />
			(1912)] :
			<lb />
			-The problems of government are practical
			<lb />
			ones and may justify, if they do not require,
			<lb />
			rough accommodations, illogical it may be,
			<lb />
			and unscientific. But even such criticism
			<lb />
			should not be hastily expressed. What is best
			<lb />
			is not always discernible, the wisdom of any
			<lb />
			choice may be disputed or condemned. Mere
			<lb />
			error of government are not subject to our
			<lb />
			judicial review.‖
			<lb />
			It is true that one or the other of the immunities or
			<lb />
			exemptions granted under the provisions of the Act
			<lb />
			may be taken advantage of by resourceful persons by
			<lb />
			adopting ingenious methods and devices with a view
			<lb />
			to avoiding or saving tax. But that cannot be helped
			<lb />
			because human ingenuity is so great when it comes to
			<lb />
			tax avoidance that it would be almost impossible to
			<lb />
			frame tax legislation which cannot be abused.
			<lb />
			Moreover, as already pointed out above, the trial and
			<lb />
			error method is inherent in every legislative effort to
			<lb />
			deal with an obstinate social or economic issue and if
			<lb />
			it is found that any immunity or exemption granted
			<lb />
			under the Act is being utilized for tax evasion or
			<lb />
			avoidance not intended by the legislature, the Act can
			<lb />
			always be amended and the abuse terminated. We are
			<lb />
			accordingly of the view that none of the provisions of
			<lb />
			the Act is violative of Article 14 and its constitutional
			<lb />
			validity must be upheld.‖
			<lb />
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
			Likewise, in Bhavesh D. Parish v. Union of India, (2000) 5 SCC 471,
			<lb />
			this Court held:
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			32
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			-26. The services rendered by certain informal sectors
			<lb />
			of the Indian economy could not be belittled. However,
			<lb />
			in the path of economic progress, if the informal
			<lb />
			system was sought to be replaced by a more
			<lb />
			organized system, capable of better regulation and
			<lb />
			discipline, then this was an economic philosophy
			<lb />
			reflected by the legislation in question. Such a
			<lb />
			philosophy might have its merits and demerits. But
			<lb />
			these were matters of economic policy. They are best
			<lb />
			left to the wisdom of the legislature and in policy
			<lb />
			matters the accepted principle is that the courts should
			<lb />
			not interfere. Moreover in the context of the changed
			<lb />
			economic scenario the expertise of people dealing with
			<lb />
			the subject should not be lightly interfered with. The
			<lb />
			consequences of such interdiction can have large-
			<lb />
			scale ramifications and can put the clock back for a
			<lb />
			number of years. The process of rationalization of the
			<lb />
			infirmities in the economy can be put in serious
			<lb />
			jeopardy and, therefore, it is necessary that while
			<lb />
			dealing with economic legislations, this Court, while
			<lb />
			not jettisoning its jurisdiction to curb arbitrary action or
			<lb />
			unconstitutional legislation, should interfere only in
			<lb />
			those few cases where the view reflected in the
			<lb />
			legislation is not possible to be taken at all.‖
			<lb />
			xxx xxx xxx
			<lb />
			-30. Before we conclude there is another matter which
			<lb />
			we must advert to. It has been brought to our notice
			<lb />
			that Section 45-S of the Act has been challenged in
			<lb />
			various High Courts and a few of them have granted
			<lb />
			the stay of provisions of Section 45-S. When
			<lb />
			considering an application for staying the operation of
			<lb />
			a piece of legislation, and that too pertaining to
			<lb />
			economic reform or change, then the courts must bear
			<lb />
			in mind that unless the provision is manifestly unjust or
			<lb />
			glaringly unconstitutional, the courts must show judicial
			<lb />
			restraint in staying the applicability of the same. Merely
			<lb />
			because a statute comes up for examination and some
			<lb />
			arguable point is raised, which persuades the courts to
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			33
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			consider the controversy, the legislative will should not
			<lb />
			normally be put under suspension pending such
			<lb />
			consideration. It is now well settled that there is always
			<lb />
			a presumption in favour of the constitutional validity of
			<lb />
			any legislation, unless the same is set aside after final
			<lb />
			hearing and, therefore, the tendency to grant stay of
			<lb />
			legislation relating to economic reform, at the interim
			<lb />
			stage, cannot be understood. The system of checks
			<lb />
			and balances has to be utilized in a balanced manner
			<lb />
			with the primary objective of accelerating economic
			<lb />
			growth rather than suspending its growth by doubting
			<lb />
			its constitutional efficacy at the threshold itself.‖
			<lb />
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
			In DG of Foreign Trade v. Kanak Exports, (2016) 2 SCC 226, this
			<lb />
			Court has held:
			<lb />
			-109. Therefore, it cannot be denied that the
			<lb />
			Government has a right to amend, modify or even
			<lb />
			rescind a particular scheme. It is well settled that in
			<lb />
			complex economic matters every decision is
			<lb />
			necessarily empiric and it is based on experimentation
			<lb />
			or what one may call trial and error method and
			<lb />
			therefore, its validity cannot be tested on any rigid prior
			<lb />
			considerations or on the application of any straitjacket
			<lb />
			formula. In Balco Employees&apos; Union v. Union of India
			<lb />
			[Balco Employees&apos; Union v. Union of India, (2002) 2
			<lb />
			SCC 333], the Supreme Court held that laws, including
			<lb />
			executive action relating to economic activities should
			<lb />
			be viewed with greater latitude than laws touching civil
			<lb />
			rights such as freedom of speech, religion, etc. that the
			<lb />
			legislature should be allowed some play in the joints
			<lb />
			because it has to deal with complex problems which
			<lb />
			do not admit of solution through any doctrine or
			<lb />
			straitjacket formula and this is particularly true in case
			<lb />
			of legislation dealing with economic matters, where
			<lb />
			having regard to the nature of the problems greater
			<lb />
			latitude require to be allowed to the legislature……‖
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			34
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			It is with this background, factual and legal, that the constitutional
			<lb />
			validity of the Insolvency and Bankruptcy Code, 2016 has to be
			<lb />
			viewed.
			<lb />
			THE RAISON D&apos;ÊTRE FOR THE INSOLVENCY AND BANKRUPTCY CODE
			<lb />
			9.
			<lb />
			The Statement of Objects and Reasons for the Code have been
			<lb />
			referred to in Innoventive Industries (supra) which states:
			<lb />
			-12. ……The Statement of Objects and Reasons of the
			<lb />
			Code reads as under:
			<lb />
			-Statement of Objects and Reasons.-There is no
			<lb />
			single law in India that deals with insolvency and
			<lb />
			bankruptcy. Provisions relating to insolvency and
			<lb />
			bankruptcy for companies can be found in the Sick
			<lb />
			Industrial Companies (Special Provisions) Act, 1985,
			<lb />
			the Recovery of Debts Due to Banks and Financial
			<lb />
			Institutions Act, 1993, the Securitisation and
			<lb />
			Reconstruction of Financial Assets and Enforcement
			<lb />
			of Security Interest Act, 2002 and the Companies Act,
			<lb />
			2013. These statutes provide for creation of multiple
			<lb />
			fora such as Board of Industrial and Financial
			<lb />
			Reconstruction (BIFR), Debts Recovery Tribunal
			<lb />
			(DRT) and National Company Law Tribunal (NCLT)
			<lb />
			and their respective Appellate Tribunals. Liquidation of
			<lb />
			companies is handled by the High Courts. Individual
			<lb />
			bankruptcy and insolvency is dealt with under the
			<lb />
			Presidency Towns Insolvency Act, 1909, and the
			<lb />
			Provincial Insolvency Act, 1920 and is dealt with by the
			<lb />
			Courts. The existing framework for insolvency and
			<lb />
			bankruptcy is inadequate, ineffective and results in
			<lb />
			undue delays in resolution, therefore, the proposed
			<lb />
			legislation.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			35
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			2. The objective of the Insolvency and Bankruptcy
			<lb />
			Code, 2015 is to consolidate and amend the laws
			<lb />
			relating to reorganization and insolvency resolution of
			<lb />
			corporate persons, partnership firms and individuals in
			<lb />
			a time-bound manner for maximization of value of
			<lb />
			assets of such persons, to promote entrepreneurship,
			<lb />
			availability of credit and balance the interests of all the
			<lb />
			stakeholders including alteration in the priority of
			<lb />
			payment of government dues and to establish an
			<lb />
			Insolvency and Bankruptcy Fund, and matters
			<lb />
			connected therewith or incidental thereto. An effective
			<lb />
			legal framework for timely resolution of insolvency and
			<lb />
			bankruptcy would support development of credit
			<lb />
			markets and encourage entrepreneurship. It would
			<lb />
			also improve Ease of Doing Business, and facilitate
			<lb />
			more investments leading to higher economic growth
			<lb />
			and development.
			<lb />
			3. The Code seeks to provide for designating NCLT
			<lb />
			and DRT as the Adjudicating Authorities for corporate
			<lb />
			persons and firms and individuals, respectively, for
			<lb />
			resolution of insolvency, liquidation and bankruptcy.
			<lb />
			The Code separates commercial aspects of insolvency
			<lb />
			and bankruptcy proceedings from judicial aspects. The
			<lb />
			Code also seeks to provide for establishment of the
			<lb />
			Insolvency and Bankruptcy Board of India (Board) for
			<lb />
			regulation of insolvency professionals, insolvency
			<lb />
			professional agencies and information utilities. Till the
			<lb />
			Board is established, the Central Government shall
			<lb />
			exercise all powers of the Board or designate any
			<lb />
			financial sector regulator to exercise the powers and
			<lb />
			functions of the Board. Insolvency professionals will
			<lb />
			assist in completion of insolvency resolution,
			<lb />
			liquidation and bankruptcy proceedings envisaged in
			<lb />
			the Code. Information Utilities would collect, collate,
			<lb />
			authenticate and disseminate financial information to
			<lb />
			facilitate such proceedings. The Code also proposes
			<lb />
			to establish a fund to be called the Insolvency and
			<lb />
			Bankruptcy Fund of India for the purposes specified in
			<lb />
			the Code.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			36
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			4. The Code seeks to provide for amendments in the
			<lb />
			Indian Partnership Act, 1932, the Central Excise Act,
			<lb />
			1944, Customs Act, 1962, the Income Tax Act, 1961,
			<lb />
			the Recovery of Debts Due to Banks and Financial
			<lb />
			Institutions Act, 1993, the Finance Act, 1994, the
			<lb />
			Securitisation and Reconstruction of Financial Assets
			<lb />
			and Enforcement of Security Interest Act, 2002, the
			<lb />
			Sick Industrial Companies (Special Provisions) Repeal
			<lb />
			Act, 2003, the Payment and Settlement Systems Act,
			<lb />
			2007, the Limited Liability Partnership Act, 2008, and
			<lb />
			the Companies Act, 2013.
			<lb />
			5. The Code seeks to achieve the above objectives.‖
			<lb />
			(emphasis in original)
			<lb />
			10. The Preamble of the Code states as follows:
			<lb />
			-An Act to consolidate and amend the laws relating to
			<lb />
			reorganization and insolvency resolution of corporate
			<lb />
			persons, partnership firms and individuals in a time-
			<lb />
			bound manner for maximization of value of assets of
			<lb />
			such persons, to promote entrepreneurship, availability
			<lb />
			of credit and balance the interests of all the
			<lb />
			stakeholders including alteration in the order of priority
			<lb />
			of payment of Government dues and to establish an
			<lb />
			Insolvency and Bankruptcy Board of India, and for
			<lb />
			matters connected therewith or incidental thereto.‖
			<lb />
			11. As is discernible, the Preamble gives an insight into what is
			<lb />
			sought to be achieved by the Code. The Code is first and foremost, a
			<lb />
			Code for reorganization and insolvency resolution of corporate debtors.
			<lb />
			Unless such reorganization is effected in a time-bound manner, the
			<lb />
			value of the assets of such persons will deplete. Therefore,
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			37
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			maximization of value of the assets of such persons so that they are
			<lb />
			efficiently run as going concerns is another very important objective of
			<lb />
			the Code. This, in turn, will promote entrepreneurship as the persons in
			<lb />
			management of the corporate debtor are removed and replaced by
			<lb />
			entrepreneurs. When, therefore, a resolution plan takes off and the
			<lb />
			corporate debtor is brought back into the economic mainstream, it is
			<lb />
			able to repay its debts, which, in turn, enhances the viability of credit in
			<lb />
			the hands of banks and financial institutions. Above all, ultimately, the
			<lb />
			interests of all stakeholders are looked after as the corporate debtor
			<lb />
			itself becomes a beneficiary of the resolution scheme -workers are
			<lb />
			paid, the creditors in the long run will be repaid in full, and
			<lb />
			shareholders/investors are able to maximize their investment. Timely
			<lb />
			resolution of a corporate debtor who is in the red, by an effective legal
			<lb />
			framework, would go a long way to support the development of credit
			<lb />
			markets. Since more investment can be made with funds that have
			<lb />
			come back into the economy, business then eases up, which leads,
			<lb />
			overall, to higher economic growth and development of the Indian
			<lb />
			economy. What is interesting to note is that the Preamble does not, in
			<lb />
			any manner, refer to liquidation, which is only availed of as a last resort
			<lb />
			if there is either no resolution plan or the resolution plans submitted are
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			38
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			not up to the mark. Even in liquidation, the liquidator can sell the
			<lb />
			business of the corporate debtor as a going concern. [See
			<lb />
			ArcelorMittal (supra) at paragraph 83, footnote 3].
			<lb />
			12. It can thus be seen that the primary focus of the legislation is to
			<lb />
			ensure revival and continuation of the corporate debtor by protecting
			<lb />
			the corporate debtor from its own management and from a corporate
			<lb />
			death by liquidation. The Code is thus a beneficial legislation which
			<lb />
			puts the corporate debtor back on its feet, not being a mere recovery
			<lb />
			legislation for creditors. The interests of the corporate debtor have,
			<lb />
			therefore, been bifurcated and separated from that of its promoters /
			<lb />
			those who are in management. Thus, the resolution process is not
			<lb />
			adversarial to the corporate debtor but, in fact, protective of its
			<lb />
			interests. The moratorium imposed by Section 14 is in the interest of
			<lb />
			the corporate debtor itself, thereby preserving the assets of the
			<lb />
			corporate debtor during the resolution process. The timelines within
			<lb />
			which the resolution process is to take place again protects the
			<lb />
			corporate debtor&apos;s assets from further dilution, and also protects all its
			<lb />
			creditors and workers by seeing that the resolution process goes
			<lb />
			through as fast as possible so that another management can, through
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			39
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			its entrepreneurial skills, resuscitate the corporate debtor to achieve all
			<lb />
			these ends.
			<lb />
			APPOINTMENT OF MEMBERS OF THE NCLT AND THE NCLAT NOT CONTRARY
			<lb />
			TO THIS COURT&apos;S JUDGMENTS.
			<lb />
			13. Shri Rohatgi has argued that contrary to the judgments in
			<lb />
			Madras Bar Association (I) (supra) and Madras Bar Association (III)
			<lb />
			(supra), Section 412(2) of the Companies Act, 2013 continued on the
			<lb />
			statute book, as a result of which, the two Judicial Members of the
			<lb />
			Selection Committee get outweighed by three bureaucrats.
			<lb />
			14. On 03.01.2018, the Companies Amendment Act, 2017 was
			<lb />
			brought into force by which Section 412 of the Companies Act, 2013
			<lb />
			was amended as follows:
			<lb />
			-412. Selection of Members of Tribunal and
			<lb />
			Appellate Tribunal.-
			<lb />
			xxx xxx xxx
			<lb />
			(2) The Members of the Tribunal and the
			<lb />
			Technical Members of the Appellate Tribunal shall
			<lb />
			be appointed on the recommendation of a
			<lb />
			Selection Committee consisting of-
			<lb />
			(a) Chief Justice of India or his nominee-
			<lb />
			Chairperson;
			<lb />
			(b) a senior Judge of the Supreme Court or
			<lb />
			Chief Justice of High Court-Member;
			<lb />
			(c) Secretary in the Ministry of Corporate
			<lb />
			Affairs-Member; and
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			40
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			(d) Secretary in the Ministry of Law and
			<lb />
			Justice-Member.
			<lb />
			(2-A) Where in a meeting of the Selection
			<lb />
			Committee, there is equality of votes on any
			<lb />
			matter, the Chairperson shall have a casting
			<lb />
			vote.‖
			<lb />
			This was brought into force by a notification dated 09.02.2018.
			<lb />
			However, an additional affidavit has been filed during the course of
			<lb />
			these proceedings by the Union of India. This affidavit is filed by one
			<lb />
			Dr. Raj Singh, Regional Director (Northern Region) of the Ministry of
			<lb />
			Corporate Affairs. This affidavit makes it clear that, acting in
			<lb />
			compliance with the directions of the Supreme Court in the aforesaid
			<lb />
			judgments, a Selection Committee was constituted to make
			<lb />
			appointments of Members of the NCLT in the year 2015 itself. Thus, by
			<lb />
			an Order dated 27.07.2015, (i) Justice Gogoi (as he then was), (ii)
			<lb />
			Justice Ramana, (iii) Secretary, Department of Legal Affairs, Ministry of
			<lb />
			Law and Justice, and (iv) Secretary, Corporate Affairs, were
			<lb />
			constituted as the Selection Committee. This Selection Committee was
			<lb />
			reconstituted on 22.02.2017 to make further appointments. In
			<lb />
			compliance of the directions of this Court, advertisements dated
			<lb />
			10.08.2015 were issued inviting applications for Judicial and Technical
			<lb />
			Members as a result of which, all the present Members of the NCLT
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			41
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			and NCLAT have been appointed. This being the case, we need not
			<lb />
			detain ourselves any further with regard to the first submission of Shri
			<lb />
			Rohatgi.
			<lb />
			NCLAT BENCH ONLY AT DELHI.
			<lb />
			15. It has been argued by Shri Rohatgi that as per our judgment in
			<lb />
			Madras Bar Association (II) (supra), paragraph 123 states as follows:
			<lb />
			-123. We shall first examine the validity of Section 5 of
			<lb />
			the NTT Act. The basis of challenge to the above
			<lb />
			provision has already been narrated by us while
			<lb />
			dealing with the submissions advanced on behalf of
			<lb />
			the petitioners with reference to the fourth contention.
			<lb />
			According to the learned counsel for the petitioners,
			<lb />
			Section 5(2) of the NTT Act mandates that NTT would
			<lb />
			ordinarily have its sittings in the National Capital
			<lb />
			Territory of Delhi. According to the petitioners, the
			<lb />
			aforesaid mandate would deprive the litigating
			<lb />
			assessee the convenience of approaching the
			<lb />
			jurisdictional High Court in the State to which he
			<lb />
			belongs. An assessee may belong to a distant/remote
			<lb />
			State, in which eventuality, he would not merely have
			<lb />
			to suffer the hardship of travelling a long distance, but
			<lb />
			such travel would also entail uncalled for financial
			<lb />
			expense. Likewise, a litigant assessee from a far-flung
			<lb />
			State may find it extremely difficult and inconvenient to
			<lb />
			identify an Advocate who would represent him before
			<lb />
			NTT, since the same is mandated to be ordinarily
			<lb />
			located in the National Capital Territory of Delhi. Even
			<lb />
			though we have expressed the view, that it is open to
			<lb />
			Parliament to substitute the appellate jurisdiction
			<lb />
			vested in the jurisdictional High Courts and constitute
			<lb />
			courts/tribunals to exercise the said jurisdiction, we are
			<lb />
			of the view, that while vesting jurisdiction in an
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			42
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			alternative court/tribunal, it is imperative for the
			<lb />
			legislature to ensure that redress should be available
			<lb />
			with the same convenience and expediency as it was
			<lb />
			prior to the introduction of the newly created
			<lb />
			court/tribunal. Thus viewed, the mandate incorporated
			<lb />
			in Section 5(2) of the NTT Act to the effect that the
			<lb />
			sittings of NTT would ordinarily be conducted in the
			<lb />
			National Capital Territory of Delhi, would render the
			<lb />
			remedy inefficacious, and thus unacceptable in law.
			<lb />
			The instant aspect of the matter was considered by
			<lb />
			this Court with reference to the Administrative
			<lb />
			Tribunals Act, 1985 in S.P. Sampath Kumar case [S.P.
			<lb />
			Sampath Kumar v. Union of India, (1987) 1 SCC 124 :
			<lb />
			(1987) 2 ATC 82] and L. Chandra Kumar case [L.
			<lb />
			Chandra Kumar v. Union of India, (1997) 3 SCC 261 :
			<lb />
			1997 SCC (L&amp;S) 577], wherein it was held that
			<lb />
			permanent Benches needed to be established at the
			<lb />
			seat of every jurisdictional High Court. And if that was
			<lb />
			not possible, at least a Circuit Bench required to be
			<lb />
			established at every place where an aggrieved party
			<lb />
			could avail of his remedy. The position on the above
			<lb />
			issue is no different in the present controversy. For the
			<lb />
			above reason, Section 5(2) of the NTT Act is in clear
			<lb />
			breach of the law declared by this Court.‖
			<lb />
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
			16. The learned Attorney General has assured us that this judgment
			<lb />
			will be followed and Circuit Benches will be established as soon as it is
			<lb />
			practicable. In this view of the matter, we record this submission and
			<lb />
			direct the Union of India to set up Circuit Benches of the NCLAT within
			<lb />
			a period of 6 months from today.
			<lb />
			THE TRIBUNALS ARE FUNCTIONING UNDER THE WRONG MINISTRY
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			43
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			17. Shri Mukul Rohatgi argued that in Madras Bar Association (I)
			<lb />
			(supra), paragraph 120(xii) specifically reads as follows:
			<lb />
			-120 We may tabulate the corrections required to set
			<lb />
			right the defects in Parts I-B and I-C of the Act:
			<lb />
			xxx xxx xxx
			<lb />
			(xii) The administrative support for all Tribunals
			<lb />
			should be from the Ministry of Law and Justice.
			<lb />
			Neither the Tribunals nor their members shall
			<lb />
			seek or be provided with facilities from the
			<lb />
			respective sponsoring or parent Ministries or
			<lb />
			Department concerned.
			<lb />
			xxx xxx xxx‖
			<lb />
			Even though eight years have passed since the date of this judgment,
			<lb />
			the administrative support for these tribunals continues to be from the
			<lb />
			Ministry of Corporate Affairs. This needs to be rectified at the earliest.
			<lb />
			18. However, the learned Attorney General pointed out Article 77(3)
			<lb />
			of the Constitution of India and Delhi International Airport Limited v.
			<lb />
			International Lease Finance Corporation and Ors., (2015) 8 SCC
			<lb />
			446, which state that once rules of business are allocated among
			<lb />
			various Ministries, such allocation is mandatory in nature. According to
			<lb />
			him, therefore, the rules of business, having allocated matters which
			<lb />
			arise under the Insolvency Code to the Ministry of Corporate Affairs,
			<lb />
			are mandatory in nature and have to be followed.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			44
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			19. It is obvious that the rules of business, being mandatory in
			<lb />
			nature, and having to be followed, are to be so followed by the
			<lb />
			executive branch of the Government. As far as we are concerned, we
			<lb />
			are bound by the Constitution Bench judgment in Madras Bar
			<lb />
			Association (I) (supra). This statement of the law has been made
			<lb />
			eight years ago. It is high time that the Union of India follow, both in
			<lb />
			letter and spirit, the judgment of this Court.
			<lb />
			CLASSIFICATION BETWEEN FINANCIAL CREDITOR AND OPERATIONAL
			<lb />
			CREDITOR NEITHER DISCRIMINATORY, NOR ARBITRARY, NOR VIOLATIVE OF
			<lb />
			ARTICLE 14 OF THE CONSTITUTION OF INDIA.
			<lb />
			20. The tests for violation of Article 14 of the Constitution of India,
			<lb />
			when legislation is challenged as being violative of the principle of
			<lb />
			equality, have been settled by this Court time and again. Since equality
			<lb />
			is only among equals, no discrimination results if the Court can be
			<lb />
			shown that there is an intelligible differentia which separates two kinds
			<lb />
			of creditors so long as there is some rational relation between the
			<lb />
			creditors so differentiated, with the object sought to be achieved by the
			<lb />
			legislation. This aspect of Article 14 has been laid down in judgments
			<lb />
			too numerous to cite, from the very inception.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			45
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			21. Another development of the law is that legislation can be struck
			<lb />
			down as being manifestly arbitrary. This has been laid down by the
			<lb />
			recent Constitution Bench decision in Shayara Bano (supra) as
			<lb />
			follows:
			<lb />
			-95. On a reading of this judgment in Natural
			<lb />
			Resources Allocation case [Natural Resources
			<lb />
			Allocation, In re, Special Reference No. 1 of 2012,
			<lb />
			(2012) 10 SCC 1], it is clear that this Court did not
			<lb />
			read McDowell [State of A.P. v. McDowell and Co.,
			<lb />
			(1996) 3 SCC 709] as being an authority for the
			<lb />
			proposition that legislation can never be struck down
			<lb />
			as being arbitrary. Indeed the Court, after referring to
			<lb />
			all the earlier judgments, and Ajay Hasia [Ajay Hasia v.
			<lb />
			Khalid Mujib Sehravardi, (1981) 1 SCC 722 : 1981
			<lb />
			SCC (L&amp;S) 258] in particular, which stated that
			<lb />
			legislation can be struck down on the ground that it is
			<lb />
			-arbitrary‖ under Article 14, went on to conclude that
			<lb />
			-arbitrariness‖ when applied to legislation cannot be
			<lb />
			used loosely. Instead, it broad based the test, stating
			<lb />
			that if a constitutional infirmity is found, Article 14 will
			<lb />
			interdict such infirmity. And a constitutional infirmity is
			<lb />
			found in Article 14 itself whenever legislation is
			<lb />
			-manifestly arbitrary‖ i.e. when it is not fair, not
			<lb />
			reasonable, discriminatory, not transparent, capricious,
			<lb />
			biased, with favouritism or nepotism and not in pursuit
			<lb />
			of promotion of healthy competition and equitable
			<lb />
			treatment. Positively speaking, it should conform to
			<lb />
			norms which are rational, informed with reason and
			<lb />
			guided by public interest, etc.
			<lb />
			96. Another
			<lb />
			Constitution
			<lb />
			Bench
			<lb />
			decision
			<lb />
			in
			<lb />
			Subramanian Swamy v. CBI [Subramanian Swamy v.
			<lb />
			CBI, (2014) 8 SCC 682 : (2014) 6 SCC (Cri) 42 :
			<lb />
			(2014) 3 SCC (L&amp;S) 36] dealt with a challenge to
			<lb />
			Section 6-A of the Delhi Special Police Establishment
			<lb />
			Act, 1946. This section was ultimately struck down as
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			46
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			being discriminatory and hence violative of Article 14.
			<lb />
			A specific reference had been made to the
			<lb />
			Constitution Bench by the reference order in
			<lb />
			Subramanian Swamy v. CBI [Subramanian Swamy v.
			<lb />
			CBI, (2005) 2 SCC 317 : 2005 SCC (L&amp;S) 241] and
			<lb />
			after referring to several judgments including Ajay
			<lb />
			Hasia [Ajay Hasia v. Khalid Mujib Sehravardi, (1981) 1
			<lb />
			SCC 722 : 1981 SCC (L&amp;S) 258], Mardia Chemicals
			<lb />
			[Mardia Chemicals Ltd. v. Union of India, (2004) 4
			<lb />
			SCC 311], Malpe Vishwanath Acharya [Malpe
			<lb />
			Vishwanath Acharya v. State of Maharashtra, (1998) 2
			<lb />
			SCC 1] and McDowell [State of A.P. v. McDowell and
			<lb />
			Co., (1996) 3 SCC 709], the reference, inter alia, was
			<lb />
			as to whether arbitrariness and unreasonableness,
			<lb />
			being facets of Article 14, are or are not available as
			<lb />
			grounds to invalidate a legislation.
			<lb />
			97. After referring to the submissions of the counsel,
			<lb />
			and several judgments on the discrimination aspect of
			<lb />
			Article 14, this Court held: (Subramanian Swamy case
			<lb />
			[Subramanian Swamy v. CBI, (2014) 8 SCC 682 :
			<lb />
			(2014) 6 SCC (Cri) 42 : (2014) 3 SCC (L&amp;S) 36] , SCC
			<lb />
			pp. 721-22, paras 48-49)
			<lb />
			-48. In E.P. Royappa [E.P. Royappa v. State of
			<lb />
			T.N., (1974) 4 SCC 3 : 1974 SCC (L&amp;S) 165] , it
			<lb />
			has been held by this Court that the basic
			<lb />
			principle which informs both Articles 14 and 16
			<lb />
			are equality and inhibition against discrimination.
			<lb />
			This Court observed in para 85 as under: (SCC p.
			<lb />
			38)
			<lb />
			‗85. … From a positivistic point of view,
			<lb />
			equality is antithetic to arbitrariness. In fact
			<lb />
			equality and arbitrariness are sworn enemies;
			<lb />
			one belongs to the rule of law in a republic
			<lb />
			while the other, to the whim and caprice of an
			<lb />
			absolute monarch. Where an act is arbitrary,
			<lb />
			it is implicit in it that it is unequal both
			<lb />
			according to political logic and constitutional
			<lb />
			law and is therefore violative of Article 14,
			<lb />
			and if it affects any matter relating to public
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			47
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			employment, it is also violative of Article 16.
			<lb />
			Articles 14 and 16 strike at arbitrariness in
			<lb />
			State action and ensure fairness and equality
			<lb />
			of treatment.&apos;
			<lb />
			Court&apos;s approach
			<lb />
			49. Where there is challenge to the constitutional
			<lb />
			validity of a law enacted by the legislature, the
			<lb />
			Court must keep in view that there is always a
			<lb />
			presumption of constitutionality of an enactment,
			<lb />
			and a clear transgression of constitutional
			<lb />
			principles must be shown. The fundamental
			<lb />
			nature and importance of the legislative process
			<lb />
			needs to be recognised by the Court and due
			<lb />
			regard and deference must be accorded to the
			<lb />
			legislative process. Where the legislation is
			<lb />
			sought to be challenged as being unconstitutional
			<lb />
			and violative of Article 14 of the Constitution, the
			<lb />
			Court must remind itself to the principles relating
			<lb />
			to the applicability of Article 14 in relation to
			<lb />
			invalidation of legislation. The two dimensions of
			<lb />
			Article 14 in its application to legislation and
			<lb />
			rendering legislation invalid are now well
			<lb />
			recognised and these are: (i) discrimination,
			<lb />
			based on an impermissible or invalid
			<lb />
			classification, and (ii) excessive delegation of
			<lb />
			powers; conferment of uncanalised and unguided
			<lb />
			powers on the executive, whether in the form of
			<lb />
			delegated legislation or by way of conferment of
			<lb />
			authority to pass administrative orders-if such
			<lb />
			conferment is without any guidance, control or
			<lb />
			checks, it is violative of Article 14 of the
			<lb />
			Constitution. The Court also needs to be mindful
			<lb />
			that
			<lb />
			a
			<lb />
			legislation
			<lb />
			does
			<lb />
			not
			<lb />
			become
			<lb />
			unconstitutional merely because there is another
			<lb />
			view or because another method may be
			<lb />
			considered to be as good or even more effective,
			<lb />
			like any issue of social, or even economic policy.
			<lb />
			It is well settled that the courts do not substitute
			<lb />
			their views on what the policy is.‖
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			48
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			xxx xxx xxx
			<lb />
			100. To complete the picture, it is important to note
			<lb />
			that subordinate legislation can be struck down on the
			<lb />
			ground that it is arbitrary and, therefore, violative of
			<lb />
			Article 14 of the Constitution. In Cellular Operators
			<lb />
			Assn. of India v. TRAI [Cellular Operators Assn. of
			<lb />
			India v. TRAI, (2016) 7 SCC 703], this Court referred
			<lb />
			to earlier precedents, and held: (SCC pp. 736-37,
			<lb />
			paras 42-44)
			<lb />
			-Violation of fundamental rights
			<lb />
			42. We have already seen that one of the tests for
			<lb />
			challenging the constitutionality of subordinate
			<lb />
			legislation is that subordinate legislation should
			<lb />
			not be manifestly arbitrary. Also, it is settled law
			<lb />
			that subordinate legislation can be challenged on
			<lb />
			any of the grounds available for challenge against
			<lb />
			plenary legislation. [See Indian Express
			<lb />
			Newspapers (Bombay) (P) Ltd. v. Union of India
			<lb />
			[Indian Express Newspapers (Bombay) (P) Ltd. v.
			<lb />
			Union of India, (1985) 1 SCC 641 : 1985 SCC
			<lb />
			(Tax) 121] , SCC at p. 689, para 75.]
			<lb />
			43. The test of -manifest arbitrariness‖ is well
			<lb />
			explained in two judgments of this Court. In
			<lb />
			Khoday Distilleries Ltd. v. State of Karnataka
			<lb />
			[Khoday Distilleries Ltd. v. State of Karnataka,
			<lb />
			(1996) 10 SCC 304], this Court held: (SCC p. 314,
			<lb />
			para 13)
			<lb />
			‗13. It is next submitted before us that the
			<lb />
			amended Rules are arbitrary, unreasonable
			<lb />
			and cause undue hardship and, therefore,
			<lb />
			violate Article 14 of the Constitution. Although
			<lb />
			the protection of Article 19(1)(g) may not be
			<lb />
			available to the appellants, the Rules must,
			<lb />
			undoubtedly, satisfy the test of Article 14,
			<lb />
			which is a guarantee against arbitrary action.
			<lb />
			However, one must bear in mind that what is
			<lb />
			being challenged here under Article 14 is not
			<lb />
			executive action but delegated legislation.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			49
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			The tests of arbitrary action which apply to
			<lb />
			executive actions do not necessarily apply to
			<lb />
			delegated legislation. In order that delegated
			<lb />
			legislation can be struck down, such
			<lb />
			legislation must be manifestly arbitrary; a law
			<lb />
			which could not be reasonably expected to
			<lb />
			emanate from an authority delegated with the
			<lb />
			law-making power. In Indian Express
			<lb />
			Newspapers (Bombay) (P) Ltd. v. Union of
			<lb />
			India [Indian Express Newspapers (Bombay)
			<lb />
			(P) Ltd. v. Union of India, (1985) 1 SCC 641 :
			<lb />
			1985 SCC (Tax) 121], this Court said that a
			<lb />
			piece of subordinate legislation does not
			<lb />
			carry the same degree of immunity which is
			<lb />
			enjoyed by a statute passed by a competent
			<lb />
			legislature. A subordinate legislation may be
			<lb />
			questioned under Article 14 on the ground
			<lb />
			that it is unreasonable; &quot;unreasonable not in
			<lb />
			the sense of not being reasonable, but in the
			<lb />
			sense that it is manifestly arbitrary‖. Drawing
			<lb />
			a comparison between the law in England
			<lb />
			and in India, the Court further observed that
			<lb />
			in England the Judges would say,
			<lb />
			-Parliament never intended the authority to
			<lb />
			make such rules; they are unreasonable and
			<lb />
			ultra vires‖. In India, arbitrariness is not a
			<lb />
			separate ground since it will come within the
			<lb />
			embargo of Article 14 of the Constitution. But
			<lb />
			subordinate legislation must be so arbitrary
			<lb />
			that it could not be said to be in conformity
			<lb />
			with the statute or that it offends Article 14 of
			<lb />
			the Constitution.&apos;
			<lb />
			44. Also, in Sharma Transport v. State of A.P.
			<lb />
			[Sharma Transport v. State of A.P., (2002) 2 SCC
			<lb />
			188], this Court held: (SCC pp. 203-04, para 25)
			<lb />
			‗25. … The tests of arbitrary action applicable
			<lb />
			to executive action do not necessarily apply
			<lb />
			to delegated legislation. In order to strike
			<lb />
			down a delegated legislation as arbitrary it
			<lb />
			has to be established that there is manifest
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			50
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			arbitrariness. In order to be described as
			<lb />
			arbitrary, it must be shown that it was not
			<lb />
			reasonable and manifestly arbitrary. The
			<lb />
			expression -arbitrarily‖ means: in an
			<lb />
			unreasonable manner, as fixed or done
			<lb />
			capriciously or at pleasure, without adequate
			<lb />
			determining principle, not founded in the
			<lb />
			nature of things, non-rational, not done or
			<lb />
			acting according to reason or judgment,
			<lb />
			depending on the will alone.&apos;‖
			<lb />
			(emphasis in original)
			<lb />
			101. It will be noticed that a Constitution Bench of this
			<lb />
			Court in Indian Express Newspapers (Bombay) (P)
			<lb />
			Ltd. v. Union of India [Indian Express Newspapers
			<lb />
			(Bombay) (P) Ltd. v. Union of India, (1985) 1 SCC 641
			<lb />
			: 1985 SCC (Tax) 121] stated that it was settled law
			<lb />
			that subordinate legislation can be challenged on any
			<lb />
			of the grounds available for challenge against plenary
			<lb />
			legislation. This being the case, there is no rational
			<lb />
			distinction between the two types of legislation when it
			<lb />
			comes to this ground of challenge under Article 14.
			<lb />
			The test of manifest arbitrariness, therefore, as laid
			<lb />
			down in the aforesaid judgments would apply to
			<lb />
			invalidate legislation as well as subordinate legislation
			<lb />
			under Article 14. Manifest arbitrariness, therefore,
			<lb />
			must be something done by the legislature
			<lb />
			capriciously, irrationally and/or without adequate
			<lb />
			determining principle. Also, when something is done
			<lb />
			which is excessive and disproportionate, such
			<lb />
			legislation would be manifestly arbitrary. We are,
			<lb />
			therefore, of the view that arbitrariness in the sense of
			<lb />
			manifest arbitrariness as pointed out by us above
			<lb />
			would apply to negate legislation as well under Article
			<lb />
			14.‖
			<lb />
			This judgment has since been followed in Gopal Jha v. The Hon&apos;ble
			<lb />
			Supreme Court of India, Writ Petition (Civil) No. 745/2018 [decided
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			51
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			on 25.10.2018] (at paragraph 27); Indian Young Lawyers
			<lb />
			Associations and Ors. v. State of Kerala and Ors., Writ Petition
			<lb />
			(Civil) No. 373/2006 [decided on 28.09.2018]; Joseph Shine v. Union
			<lb />
			of India, Writ Petition (Criminal) No. 194/2017 [decided on 27.09.2018]
			<lb />
			(at paragraphs 110, 195, 197); K.S. Puttaswamy v. Union of India,
			<lb />
			Writ Petition (Civil) No. 494/2012 [decided on 26.09.2018] (at
			<lb />
			paragraphs 77, 78, 416, 724, 725, 1160); Navtej Singh Johar and
			<lb />
			Ors. v. Union of India, (2018) 10 SCC 1 (at paragraphs 253, 353,
			<lb />
			411, 637.9); Lok Prahari v. State of Uttar Pradesh and Ors., (2018)
			<lb />
			6 SCC 1 (at paragraph 35); and Nikesh Tarachand Shah v. Union of
			<lb />
			India and Ors., (2018) 11 SCC 1 (at paragraph 23).
			<lb />
			22. Sections 5(7) and 5(8) of the Code define -financial creditor‖ and
			<lb />
			-financial debt‖ as follows:
			<lb />
			-5. Definitions.-In this Part, unless the context
			<lb />
			otherwise requires,-
			<lb />
			xxx xxx xxx
			<lb />
			(7) -financial creditor‖ means any person to whom
			<lb />
			a financial debt is owed and includes a person to
			<lb />
			whom such debt has been legally assigned or
			<lb />
			transferred to;
			<lb />
			(8) -financial debt‖ means a debt along with
			<lb />
			interest, if any, which is disbursed against the
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			52
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			consideration for the time value of money and
			<lb />
			includes-
			<lb />
			(a) money borrowed against the payment of
			<lb />
			interest;
			<lb />
			(b) any amount raised by acceptance under
			<lb />
			any acceptance credit facility or its de-
			<lb />
			materialised equivalent;
			<lb />
			(c) any amount raised pursuant to any note
			<lb />
			purchase facility or the issue of bonds, notes,
			<lb />
			debentures, loan stock or any similar
			<lb />
			instrument;
			<lb />
			(d) the amount of any liability in respect of
			<lb />
			any lease or hire purchase contract which is
			<lb />
			deemed as a finance or capital lease under
			<lb />
			the Indian Accounting Standards or such
			<lb />
			other accounting standards as may be
			<lb />
			prescribed;
			<lb />
			(e) receivables sold or discounted other than
			<lb />
			any receivables sold on non-recourse basis;
			<lb />
			(f) any amount raised under any other
			<lb />
			transaction, including any forward sale or
			<lb />
			purchase agreement, having the commercial
			<lb />
			effect of a borrowing;
			<lb />
			Explanation.-For the purposes of this sub-
			<lb />
			clause,-
			<lb />
			(i) any amount raised from an allottee
			<lb />
			under a real estate project shall be deemed
			<lb />
			to be an amount having the commercial
			<lb />
			effect of a borrowing; and
			<lb />
			(ii) the expressions, -allottee‖ and -real
			<lb />
			estate project‖ shall have the meanings
			<lb />
			respectively assigned to them in clauses
			<lb />
			(d) and (zn) of Section 2 of the Real Estate
			<lb />
			(Regulation and Development) Act, 2016
			<lb />
			(16 of 2016);
			<lb />
			(g) any derivative transaction entered into in
			<lb />
			connection with protection against or benefit
			<lb />
			from fluctuation in any rate or price and for
			<lb />
			calculating the value of any derivative
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			53
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			transaction, only the market value of such
			<lb />
			transaction shall be taken into account;
			<lb />
			(h) any counter-indemnity obligation in
			<lb />
			respect of a guarantee, indemnity, bond,
			<lb />
			documentary letter of credit or any other
			<lb />
			instrument issued by a bank or financial
			<lb />
			institution;
			<lb />
			(i) the amount of any liability in respect of any
			<lb />
			of the guarantee or indemnity for any of the
			<lb />
			items referred to in sub-clauses (a) to (h) of
			<lb />
			this clause;
			<lb />
			xxx xxx xxx‖
			<lb />
			Section 5(20) defines -operational creditor‖ as follows:
			<lb />
			-5. Definitions.-In this Part, unless the context
			<lb />
			otherwise requires,-
			<lb />
			xxx xxx xxx
			<lb />
			(20) -operational creditor‖ means a person to whom
			<lb />
			an operational debt is owed and includes any
			<lb />
			person to whom such debt has been legally
			<lb />
			assigned or transferred;
			<lb />
			xxx xxx xxx‖
			<lb />
			Section 7 of the Code states:
			<lb />
			-7. Initiation of corporate insolvency resolution
			<lb />
			process by financial creditor.-(1) A financial
			<lb />
			creditor either by itself or jointly with other financial
			<lb />
			creditors, or any other person on behalf of the financial
			<lb />
			creditor, as may be notified by the Central
			<lb />
			Government, may file an application for initiating
			<lb />
			corporate insolvency resolution process against a
			<lb />
			corporate debtor before the Adjudicating Authority
			<lb />
			when a default has occurred.
			<lb />
			Explanation.-For the purposes of this sub-section,
			<lb />
			a default includes a default in respect of a financial
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			54
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			debt owed not only to the applicant financial creditor
			<lb />
			but to any other financial creditor of the corporate
			<lb />
			debtor.
			<lb />
			(2) The financial creditor shall make an application
			<lb />
			under sub-section (1) in such form and manner and
			<lb />
			accompanied with such fee as may be prescribed.
			<lb />
			(3) The financial creditor shall, along with the
			<lb />
			application furnish-
			<lb />
			(a) record of the default recorded with the
			<lb />
			information utility or such other record or
			<lb />
			evidence of default as may be specified;
			<lb />
			(b) the name of the resolution professional
			<lb />
			proposed to act as an interim resolution
			<lb />
			professional; and
			<lb />
			(c) any other information as may be specified by
			<lb />
			the Board.
			<lb />
			(4) The Adjudicating Authority shall, within fourteen
			<lb />
			days of the receipt of the application under sub-section
			<lb />
			(2), ascertain the existence of a default from the
			<lb />
			records of an information utility or on the basis of other
			<lb />
			evidence furnished by the financial creditor under sub-
			<lb />
			section (3).
			<lb />
			(5) Where the Adjudicating Authority is satisfied that-
			<lb />
			(a) a default has occurred and the application
			<lb />
			under sub-section (2) is complete, and there is no
			<lb />
			disciplinary proceedings pending against the
			<lb />
			proposed resolution professional, it may, by order,
			<lb />
			admit such application; or
			<lb />
			(b) default has not occurred or the application
			<lb />
			under sub-section (2) is incomplete or any
			<lb />
			disciplinary proceeding is pending against the
			<lb />
			proposed resolution professional, it may, by order,
			<lb />
			reject such application:
			<lb />
			Provided that the Adjudicating Authority shall,
			<lb />
			before rejecting the application under clause (b) of
			<lb />
			sub-section (5), give a notice to the applicant to
			<lb />
			rectify the defect in his application within seven
			<lb />
			days of receipt of such notice from the
			<lb />
			Adjudicating Authority.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			55
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			(6) The corporate insolvency resolution process shall
			<lb />
			commence from the date of admission of the
			<lb />
			application under sub-section (5).
			<lb />
			(7) The Adjudicating Authority shall communicate-
			<lb />
			(a) the order under clause (a) of sub-section (5) to
			<lb />
			the financial creditor and the corporate debtor;
			<lb />
			(b) the order under clause (b) of sub-section (5) to
			<lb />
			the financial creditor, within seven days of
			<lb />
			admission or rejection of such application, as the
			<lb />
			case may be.‖
			<lb />
			23. A perusal of the definition of -financial creditor‖ and -financial
			<lb />
			debt‖ makes it clear that a financial debt is a debt together with
			<lb />
			interest, if any, which is disbursed against the consideration for time
			<lb />
			value of money. It may further be money that is borrowed or raised in
			<lb />
			any of the manners prescribed in Section 5(8) or otherwise, as Section
			<lb />
			5(8) is an inclusive definition. On the other hand, an -operational debt‖
			<lb />
			would include a claim in respect of the provision of goods or services,
			<lb />
			including employment, or a debt in respect of payment of dues arising
			<lb />
			under any law and payable to the Government or any local authority.
			<lb />
			24. A financial creditor may trigger the Code either by itself or jointly
			<lb />
			with other financial creditors or such persons as may be notified by the
			<lb />
			Central Government when a -default‖ occurs. The Explanation to
			<lb />
			Section 7(1) also makes it clear that the Code may be triggered by
			<lb />
			such persons in respect of a default made to any other financial
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			56
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			creditor of the corporate debtor, making it clear that once triggered, the
			<lb />
			resolution process under the Code is a collective proceeding in rem
			<lb />
			which seeks, in the first instance, to rehabilitate the corporate debtor.
			<lb />
			Under Section 7(4), the Adjudicating Authority shall, within the
			<lb />
			prescribed period, ascertain the existence of a default on the basis of
			<lb />
			evidence furnished by the financial creditor; and under Section 7(5),
			<lb />
			the Adjudicating Authority has to be satisfied that a default has
			<lb />
			occurred, when it may, by order, admit the application, or dismiss the
			<lb />
			application if such default has not occurred. On the other hand, under
			<lb />
			Sections 8 and 9, an operational creditor may, on the occurrence of a
			<lb />
			default, deliver a demand notice which must then be replied to within
			<lb />
			the specified period. What is important is that at this stage, if an
			<lb />
			application is filed before the Adjudicating Authority for initiating the
			<lb />
			corporate insolvency resolution process, the corporate debtor can
			<lb />
			prove that the debt is disputed. When the debt is so disputed, such
			<lb />
			application would be rejected.
			<lb />
			25. The argument of learned counsel on behalf of the petitioners is
			<lb />
			that in point of fact, there is no intelligible differentia having relation to
			<lb />
			the objects sought to be achieved by the Code between financial and
			<lb />
			operational creditors and indeed, nowhere in the world has this
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			57
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			distinction been made. The BLRC Report presents what according to it
			<lb />
			is the rationale for the reason to differentiate between financial and
			<lb />
			operational creditors. The Report states as follows:
			<lb />
			-While both types of creditors can trigger the IRP
			<lb />
			under the Code, the evidence presented to trigger
			<lb />
			varies. Since financial creditors have electronic
			<lb />
			records of the liabilities filed in the Information Utilities
			<lb />
			of Section 4.3, incontrovertible event of default on any
			<lb />
			financial credit contract can be readily verifiable by
			<lb />
			accessing this system. The evidence submitted of
			<lb />
			default by the debtor to the operational creditor may be
			<lb />
			in either electronic or physical form, since all
			<lb />
			operational creditors may or may not have electronic
			<lb />
			filings of the debtors&apos; liability. Till such time that the
			<lb />
			Information Utilities are ubiquitous, financial creditors
			<lb />
			may establish default in a manner similar to
			<lb />
			operational creditors.‖
			<lb />
			Similarly, the Insolvency and Bankruptcy Bill in the Notes on Clause 8
			<lb />
			states:
			<lb />
			-Clause 8 lays down the procedure for the initiation of
			<lb />
			the corporate insolvency resolution process by an
			<lb />
			operational creditor. This procedure differs from the
			<lb />
			procedure applicable to financial creditors as
			<lb />
			operational debts (such as trade debts, salary or wage
			<lb />
			claims) tend to be small amounts (in comparison to
			<lb />
			financial debts) or are recurring in nature and may not
			<lb />
			be accurately reflected on the records of information
			<lb />
			utilities at all times. The possibility of disputed debts in
			<lb />
			relation to operational creditors is also higher in
			<lb />
			comparison to financial creditors such as banks and
			<lb />
			financial institutions. Accordingly, the process for
			<lb />
			initiation of the insolvency resolution process differs for
			<lb />
			an operational creditor…… This ensures that
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			58
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			operational creditors, whose debt claims are usually
			<lb />
			smaller, are not able to put the corporate debtor into
			<lb />
			the insolvency resolution process prematurely or
			<lb />
			initiate the process for extraneous considerations. It
			<lb />
			may also facilitate informal negotiations between such
			<lb />
			creditors and the corporate debtor, which may result in
			<lb />
			a restructuring of the debt outside the formal
			<lb />
			proceedings.‖
			<lb />
			However, the Insolvency Law Committee [-ILC‖], in its Report of March
			<lb />
			2018 dealt with debenture holders and fixed deposit holders, who are
			<lb />
			also financial creditors, and are numerous. The Report then went on to
			<lb />
			state:
			<lb />
			-10.6 For certain securities, a trustee or an agent may
			<lb />
			already be appointed as per the terms of the security
			<lb />
			instrument. For example, a debenture trustee would be
			<lb />
			appointed if debentures exceeding 500 have been
			<lb />
			issued [Section 71(5), Companies Act, 2013] or if
			<lb />
			secured debentures are issued [Rule 18(1)(c),
			<lb />
			Companies (Share Capital and Debenture) Rules,
			<lb />
			2014]. Such creditors may be represented through
			<lb />
			such pre-appointed trustees or agents. For other
			<lb />
			classes of creditors which exceed a certain threshold
			<lb />
			in number, like home buyers or security holders for
			<lb />
			whom no trustee or agent has already been appointed
			<lb />
			under a debt instrument or otherwise, an insolvency
			<lb />
			professional (other than the IRP) shall be appointed by
			<lb />
			the NCLT on the request of the IRP. It is to be noted
			<lb />
			that as the agent or trustee or insolvency professional,
			<lb />
			i.e. the authorised representative for the creditors
			<lb />
			discussed above and executors, guarantors, etc. as
			<lb />
			discussed in paragraph 9 of this Report, shall be a part
			<lb />
			of the CoC, they cannot be related parties to the
			<lb />
			corporate debtor in line with the spirit of proviso to
			<lb />
			section 21(2).‖
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			59
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			xxx xxx xxx
			<lb />
			-10.8 In light of the deliberation above, the Committee
			<lb />
			felt that a mechanism requires to be provided in the
			<lb />
			Code to mandate representation in meetings of
			<lb />
			security holders, deposit holders, and all other classes
			<lb />
			of financial creditors which exceed a certain number,
			<lb />
			through an authorised representative. This can be
			<lb />
			done by adding a new provision to section 21 of the
			<lb />
			Code. Such a representative may either be a trustee
			<lb />
			or an agent appointed under the terms of the debt
			<lb />
			agreement of such creditors, otherwise an insolvency
			<lb />
			professional may be appointed by the NCLT for each
			<lb />
			such class of financial creditors. Additionally, the
			<lb />
			representative shall act and attend the meetings on
			<lb />
			behalf of the respective class of financial creditors and
			<lb />
			shall vote on behalf of each of the financial creditor to
			<lb />
			the extent of the voting share of each such creditor,
			<lb />
			and as per their instructions. To ensure adequate
			<lb />
			representation by the authorised representative of the
			<lb />
			financial creditors, a specific provision laying down the
			<lb />
			rights and duties of such authorised representatives
			<lb />
			may be inserted. Further, the requisite threshold for
			<lb />
			the number of creditors and manner of voting may be
			<lb />
			specified by IBBI through regulations to enable
			<lb />
			efficient voting by the representative. Also, regulation
			<lb />
			25 may also be amended to enable voting through
			<lb />
			electronic means such as e-mail, to address any
			<lb />
			technical issues which may arise due to a large
			<lb />
			number of creditors voting at the same time.‖
			<lb />
			Given this Report, the Code was amended and Section 21(6A) and
			<lb />
			21(6B) were added, which are set out hereinbelow:
			<lb />
			-21. Committee of creditors.-
			<lb />
			xxx xxx xxx
			<lb />
			(6-A) Where a financial debt-
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			60
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			(a) is in the form of securities or deposits and the
			<lb />
			terms of the financial debt provide for appointment
			<lb />
			of a trustee or agent to act as authorised
			<lb />
			representative for all the financial creditors, such
			<lb />
			trustee or agent shall act on behalf of such
			<lb />
			financial creditors;
			<lb />
			(b) is owed to a class of creditors exceeding the
			<lb />
			number as may be specified, other than the
			<lb />
			creditors covered under clause (a) or sub-section
			<lb />
			(6), the interim resolution professional shall make
			<lb />
			an application to the Adjudicating Authority along
			<lb />
			with the list of all financial creditors, containing the
			<lb />
			name of an insolvency professional, other than
			<lb />
			the interim resolution professional, to act as their
			<lb />
			authorised representative who shall be appointed
			<lb />
			by the Adjudicating Authority prior to the first
			<lb />
			meeting of the committee of creditors;
			<lb />
			(c) is represented by a guardian, executor or
			<lb />
			administrator, such person shall act as authorised
			<lb />
			representative on behalf of such financial
			<lb />
			creditors,
			<lb />
			and such authorised representative under clause (a) or
			<lb />
			clause (b) or clause (c) shall attend the meetings of the
			<lb />
			committee of creditors, and vote on behalf of each
			<lb />
			financial creditor to the extent of his voting share.
			<lb />
			(6-B) The remuneration payable to the authorised
			<lb />
			representative-
			<lb />
			(i) under clauses (a) and (c) of sub-section (6-A),
			<lb />
			if any, shall be as per the terms of the financial
			<lb />
			debt or the relevant documentation; and
			<lb />
			(ii) under clause (b) of sub-section (6-A) shall be
			<lb />
			as specified which shall form part of the
			<lb />
			insolvency resolution process costs.‖
			<lb />
			Also, Regulations 16A and 16B of the Insolvency and Bankruptcy
			<lb />
			Board of India (Insolvency Resolution Process for Corporate Persons)
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			61
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			Regulations, 2016 [-CIRP Regulations‖] were added, with effect from
			<lb />
			04.07.2018, as follows:
			<lb />
			-16A. Authorised representative.-(1) The interim
			<lb />
			resolution professional shall select the insolvency
			<lb />
			professional, who is the choice of the highest number
			<lb />
			of financial creditors in the class in Form CA received
			<lb />
			under sub-regulation (1) of regulation 12, to act as the
			<lb />
			authorised representative of the creditors of the
			<lb />
			respective class:
			<lb />
			Provided that the choice for an insolvency
			<lb />
			professional to act as authorised representative in
			<lb />
			Form CA received under sub-regulation (2) of
			<lb />
			regulation 12 shall not be considered.
			<lb />
			(2) The interim resolution professional shall apply to
			<lb />
			the Adjudicating Authority for appointment of the
			<lb />
			authorised representatives selected under sub-
			<lb />
			regulation (1) within two days of the verification of
			<lb />
			claims received under sub-regulation (1) of regulation
			<lb />
			12.
			<lb />
			(3) Any delay in appointment of the authorised
			<lb />
			representative for any class of creditors shall not affect
			<lb />
			the validity of any decision taken by the committee.
			<lb />
			(4) The interim resolution professional shall provide
			<lb />
			the list of creditors in each class to the respective
			<lb />
			authorised
			<lb />
			representative
			<lb />
			appointed
			<lb />
			by
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			Adjudicating Authority.
			<lb />
			(5) The interim resolution professional or the resolution
			<lb />
			professional, as the case may be, shall provide an
			<lb />
			updated list of creditors in each class to the respective
			<lb />
			authorised representative as and when the list is
			<lb />
			updated.
			<lb />
			Clarification: The authorised representative shall
			<lb />
			have no role in receipt or verification of claims of
			<lb />
			creditors of the class he represents.
			<lb />
			(6) The interim resolution professional or the resolution
			<lb />
			professional, as the case may be, shall provide
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			62
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			electronic means of communication between the
			<lb />
			authorised representative and the creditors in the
			<lb />
			class.
			<lb />
			(7) The voting share of a creditor in a class shall be in
			<lb />
			proportion to the financial debt which includes an
			<lb />
			interest at the rate of eight per cent per annum unless
			<lb />
			a different rate has been agreed to between the
			<lb />
			parties.
			<lb />
			(8) The authorised representative of creditors in a
			<lb />
			class shall be entitled to receive fee for every meeting
			<lb />
			of the committee attended by him in the following
			<lb />
			manner, namely:
			<lb />
			Number of creditors in
			<lb />
			the class
			<lb />
			Fee per meeting of the
			<lb />
			committee (Rs.)
			<lb />
			10-100
			<lb />
			15,000
			<lb />
			101-1000
			<lb />
			20,000
			<lb />
			More than 1000
			<lb />
			25,000
			<lb />
			(9) The authorised representative shall circulate the
			<lb />
			agenda to creditors in a class and announce the voting
			<lb />
			window at least twenty-four hours before the window
			<lb />
			opens for voting instructions and keep the voting
			<lb />
			window open for at least twelve hours.
			<lb />
			16B. Committee with only creditors in a class.-
			<lb />
			Where the corporate debtor has only creditors in a
			<lb />
			class and no other financial creditor eligible to join the
			<lb />
			committee, the committee shall consist of only the
			<lb />
			authorised representative(s).‖
			<lb />
			26. It is obvious that debenture holders and persons with home
			<lb />
			loans may be numerous and, therefore, have been statutorily dealt
			<lb />
			with by the aforesaid change made in the Code as well as the
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			63
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			Regulations. However, as a general rule, it is correct to say that
			<lb />
			financial creditors, which involve banks and financial institutions, would
			<lb />
			certainly be smaller in number than operational creditors of a corporate
			<lb />
			debtor.
			<lb />
			27. According to us, it is clear that most financial creditors,
			<lb />
			particularly banks and financial institutions, are secured creditors
			<lb />
			whereas most operational creditors are unsecured, payments for
			<lb />
			goods and services as well as payments to workers not being secured
			<lb />
			by mortgaged documents and the like. The distinction between
			<lb />
			secured and unsecured creditors is a distinction which has obtained
			<lb />
			since the earliest of the Companies Acts both in the United Kingdom
			<lb />
			and in this country. Apart from the above, the nature of loan
			<lb />
			agreements with financial creditors is different from contracts with
			<lb />
			operational creditors for supplying goods and services. Financial
			<lb />
			creditors generally lend finance on a term loan or for working capital
			<lb />
			that enables the corporate debtor to either set up and/or operate its
			<lb />
			business. On the other hand, contracts with operational creditors are
			<lb />
			relatable to supply of goods and services in the operation of business.
			<lb />
			Financial contracts generally involve large sums of money. By way of
			<lb />
			contrast, operational contracts have dues whose quantum is generally
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			64
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			less. In the running of a business, operational creditors can be many
			<lb />
			as opposed to financial creditors, who lend finance for the set up or
			<lb />
			working of business. Also, financial creditors have specified repayment
			<lb />
			schedules, and defaults entitle financial creditors to recall a loan in
			<lb />
			totality. Contracts with operational creditors do not have any such
			<lb />
			stipulations. Also, the forum in which dispute resolution takes place is
			<lb />
			completely different. Contracts with operational creditors can and do
			<lb />
			have arbitration clauses where dispute resolution is done privately.
			<lb />
			Operational debts also tend to be recurring in nature and the possibility
			<lb />
			of genuine disputes in case of operational debts is much higher when
			<lb />
			compared to financial debts. A simple example will suffice. Goods that
			<lb />
			are supplied may be substandard. Services that are provided may be
			<lb />
			substandard. Goods may not have been supplied at all. All these qua
			<lb />
			operational debts are matters to be proved in arbitration or in the
			<lb />
			courts of law. On the other hand, financial debts made to banks and
			<lb />
			financial institutions are well-documented and defaults made are easily
			<lb />
			verifiable.
			<lb />
			28. Most importantly, financial creditors are, from the very beginning,
			<lb />
			involved with assessing the viability of the corporate debtor. They can,
			<lb />
			and therefore do, engage in restructuring of the loan as well as
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			65
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			reorganization of the corporate debtor&apos;s business when there is
			<lb />
			financial stress, which are things operational creditors do not and
			<lb />
			cannot do. Thus, preserving the corporate debtor as a going concern,
			<lb />
			while ensuring maximum recovery for all creditors being the objective
			<lb />
			of the Code, financial creditors are clearly different from operational
			<lb />
			creditors and therefore, there is obviously an intelligible differentia
			<lb />
			between the two which has a direct relation to the objects sought to be
			<lb />
			achieved by the Code.
			<lb />
			NOTICE, HEARING, AND SET-OFF OR COUNTERCLAIM QUA FINANCIAL DEBTS.
			<lb />
			29. This Court, in Innoventive Industries (supra) stated as follows:
			<lb />
			-27. The scheme of the Code is to ensure that when a
			<lb />
			default takes place, in the sense that a debt becomes
			<lb />
			due and is not paid, the insolvency resolution process
			<lb />
			begins. Default is defined in Section 3(12) in very wide
			<lb />
			terms as meaning non-payment of a debt once it
			<lb />
			becomes due and payable, which includes non-
			<lb />
			payment of even part thereof or an instalment amount.
			<lb />
			For the meaning of -debt‖, we have to go to Section
			<lb />
			3(11), which in turn tells us that a debt means a liability
			<lb />
			of obligation in respect of a -claim‖ and for the
			<lb />
			meaning of -claim‖, we have to go back to Section 3(6)
			<lb />
			which defines -claim‖ to mean a right to payment even
			<lb />
			if it is disputed. The Code gets triggered the moment
			<lb />
			default is of rupees one lakh or more (Section 4). The
			<lb />
			corporate insolvency resolution process may be
			<lb />
			triggered by the corporate debtor itself or a financial
			<lb />
			creditor or operational creditor. A distinction is made
			<lb />
			by the Code between debts owed to financial creditors
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			66
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			and operational creditors. A financial creditor has been
			<lb />
			defined under Section 5(7) as a person to whom a
			<lb />
			financial debt is owed and a financial debt is defined in
			<lb />
			Section 5(8) to mean a debt which is disbursed against
			<lb />
			consideration for the time value of money. As opposed
			<lb />
			to this, an operational creditor means a person to
			<lb />
			whom an operational debt is owed and an operational
			<lb />
			debt under Section 5(21) means a claim in respect of
			<lb />
			provision of goods or services.
			<lb />
			28. When it comes to a financial creditor triggering the
			<lb />
			process, Section 7 becomes relevant. Under the
			<lb />
			Explanation to Section 7(1), a default is in respect of a
			<lb />
			financial debt owed to any financial creditor of the
			<lb />
			corporate debtor -it need not be a debt owed to the
			<lb />
			applicant financial creditor. Under Section 7(2), an
			<lb />
			application is to be made under sub-section (1) in such
			<lb />
			form and manner as is prescribed, which takes us to
			<lb />
			the Insolvency and Bankruptcy (Application to
			<lb />
			Adjudicating Authority) Rules, 2016. Under Rule 4, the
			<lb />
			application is made by a financial creditor in Form 1
			<lb />
			accompanied by documents and records required
			<lb />
			therein. Form 1 is a detailed form in 5 parts, which
			<lb />
			requires particulars of the applicant in Part I,
			<lb />
			particulars of the corporate debtor in Part II, particulars
			<lb />
			of the proposed interim resolution professional in Part
			<lb />
			III, particulars of the financial debt in Part IV and
			<lb />
			documents, records and evidence of default in Part V.
			<lb />
			Under Rule 4(3), the applicant is to dispatch a copy of
			<lb />
			the application filed with the Adjudicating Authority by
			<lb />
			registered post or speed post to the registered office of
			<lb />
			the corporate debtor. The speed, within which the
			<lb />
			Adjudicating Authority is to ascertain the existence of a
			<lb />
			default from the records of the information utility or on
			<lb />
			the basis of evidence furnished by the financial
			<lb />
			creditor, is important. This it must do within 14 days of
			<lb />
			the receipt of the application. It is at the stage of
			<lb />
			Section 7(5), where the Adjudicating Authority is to be
			<lb />
			satisfied that a default has occurred, that the corporate
			<lb />
			debtor is entitled to point out that a default has not
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			67
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			occurred in the sense that the -debt‖, which may also
			<lb />
			include a disputed claim, is not due. A debt may not be
			<lb />
			due if it is not payable in law or in fact. The moment
			<lb />
			the Adjudicating Authority is satisfied that a default has
			<lb />
			occurred, the application must be admitted unless it is
			<lb />
			incomplete, in which case it may give notice to the
			<lb />
			applicant to rectify the defect within 7 days of receipt of
			<lb />
			a notice from the Adjudicating Authority. Under sub-
			<lb />
			section (7), the Adjudicating Authority shall then
			<lb />
			communicate the order passed to the financial creditor
			<lb />
			and corporate debtor within 7 days of admission or
			<lb />
			rejection of such application, as the case may be.
			<lb />
			29. The scheme of Section 7 stands in contrast with
			<lb />
			the scheme under Section 8 where an operational
			<lb />
			creditor is, on the occurrence of a default, to first
			<lb />
			deliver a demand notice of the unpaid debt to the
			<lb />
			operational debtor in the manner provided in Section
			<lb />
			8(1) of the Code. Under Section 8(2), the corporate
			<lb />
			debtor can, within a period of 10 days of receipt of the
			<lb />
			demand notice or copy of the invoice mentioned in
			<lb />
			sub-section (1), bring to the notice of the operational
			<lb />
			creditor the existence of a dispute or the record of the
			<lb />
			pendency of a suit or arbitration proceedings, which is
			<lb />
			pre-existing-i.e. before such notice or invoice was
			<lb />
			received by the corporate debtor. The moment there is
			<lb />
			existence of such a dispute, the operational creditor
			<lb />
			gets out of the clutches of the Code.
			<lb />
			30. On the other hand, as we have seen, in the case of
			<lb />
			a corporate debtor who commits a default of a financial
			<lb />
			debt, the Adjudicating Authority has merely to see the
			<lb />
			records of the information utility or other evidence
			<lb />
			produced by the financial creditor to satisfy itself that a
			<lb />
			default has occurred. It is of no matter that the debt is
			<lb />
			disputed so long as the debt is -due‖ i.e. payable
			<lb />
			unless interdicted by some law or has not yet become
			<lb />
			due in the sense that it is payable at some future date.
			<lb />
			It is only when this is proved to the satisfaction of the
			<lb />
			Adjudicating Authority that the Adjudicating Authority
			<lb />
			may reject an application and not otherwise.‖
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			68
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			30. Section 3(9)(c) read with Section 214(e) of the Code are
			<lb />
			important and are set out as under:
			<lb />
			-3. Definitions.-In this Code, unless the context
			<lb />
			otherwise requires,-
			<lb />
			xxx xxx xxx
			<lb />
			(9) -core services‖ means services rendered by an
			<lb />
			information utility for-
			<lb />
			xxx xxx xxx
			<lb />
			(c) authenticating and verifying the financial
			<lb />
			information submitted by a person; and
			<lb />
			xxx xxx xxx‖
			<lb />
			-214. Obligations of information utility.-For the
			<lb />
			purposes of providing core services to any person,
			<lb />
			every information utility shall-
			<lb />
			xxx xxx xxx
			<lb />
			(e) get the information received from various
			<lb />
			persons authenticated by all concerned
			<lb />
			parties before storing such information;
			<lb />
			xxx xxx xxx‖
			<lb />
			31. It is clear from these Sections that information in respect of debts
			<lb />
			incurred by financial debtors is easily available through information
			<lb />
			utilities which, under the Insolvency and Bankruptcy Board of India
			<lb />
			(Information Utilities) Regulations, 2017 [-Information Utilities
			<lb />
			Regulations‖], are to satisfy themselves that information provided as
			<lb />
			to the debt is accurate. This is done by giving notice to the corporate
			<lb />
			debtor who then has an opportunity to correct such information.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			69
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			32. Apart from the record maintained by such utility, Form I
			<lb />
			appended to the Insolvency and Bankruptcy (Application to
			<lb />
			Adjudicating Authority) Rules, 2016, makes it clear that the following
			<lb />
			are other sources which evidence a financial debt:
			<lb />
			(a) Particulars of security held, if any, the date of its
			<lb />
			creation, its estimated value as per the creditor;
			<lb />
			(b) Certificate of registration of charge issued by the
			<lb />
			registrar of companies (if the corporate debtor is a
			<lb />
			company);
			<lb />
			(c) Order of a court, tribunal or arbitral panel
			<lb />
			adjudicating on the default;
			<lb />
			(d) Record of default with the information utility;
			<lb />
			(e) Details of succession certificate, or probate of a
			<lb />
			will, or letter of administration, or court decree (as
			<lb />
			may be applicable), under the Indian Succession
			<lb />
			Act, 1925;
			<lb />
			(f) The latest and complete copy of the financial
			<lb />
			contract reflecting all amendments and waivers to
			<lb />
			date;
			<lb />
			(g) A record of default as available with any credit
			<lb />
			information company;
			<lb />
			(h) Copies of entries in a bankers book in accordance
			<lb />
			with the Bankers Books Evidence Act, 1891.
			<lb />
			33. Rule 4 (3) of the aforesaid Rules states as follows:
			<lb />
			-4. Application by financial creditor.-
			<lb />
			xxx xxx xxx
			<lb />
			(3) The applicant shall dispatch forthwith, a
			<lb />
			copy of the application filed with the
			<lb />
			Adjudicating Authority, by registered post or
			<lb />
			speed post to the registered office of the
			<lb />
			corporate debtor.
			<lb />
			xxx xxx xxx‖
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			70
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			Section 420 of the Companies Act, 2013 states as follows:
			<lb />
			-420. Orders of Tribunal.-(1) The Tribunal may,
			<lb />
			after giving the parties to any proceeding before it, a
			<lb />
			reasonable opportunity of being heard, pass such
			<lb />
			orders thereon as it thinks fit.
			<lb />
			(2) The Tribunal may, at any time within two years
			<lb />
			from the date of the order, with a view to rectifying any
			<lb />
			mistake apparent from the record, amend any order
			<lb />
			passed by it, and shall make such amendment, if the
			<lb />
			mistake is brought to its notice by the parties:
			<lb />
			Provided that no such amendment shall be made in
			<lb />
			respect of any order against which an appeal has been
			<lb />
			preferred under this Act.
			<lb />
			(3) The Tribunal shall send a copy of every order
			<lb />
			passed under this section to all the parties concerned.‖
			<lb />
			Rules 11, 34, and 37 of the National Company Law Tribunal Rules,
			<lb />
			2016 [-NCLT Rules‖] state as follows:
			<lb />
			-11. Inherent Powers.-Nothing in these rules shall be
			<lb />
			deemed to limit or otherwise affect the inherent powers
			<lb />
			of the Tribunal to make such orders as may be
			<lb />
			necessary for meeting the ends of justice or to prevent
			<lb />
			abuse of the process of the Tribunal.‖
			<lb />
			xxx xxx xxx
			<lb />
			34. General Procedure.-(1) In a situation not
			<lb />
			provided for in these rules, the Tribunal may, for
			<lb />
			reasons to be recorded in writing, determine the
			<lb />
			procedure in a particular case in accordance with the
			<lb />
			principles of natural justice.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			71
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			(2) The general heading in all proceedings before the
			<lb />
			Tribunal, in all advertisements and notices shall be in
			<lb />
			Form No. NCLT 4.
			<lb />
			(3) Every petition or application or reference shall be
			<lb />
			filed in form as provided in Form No. NCLT 1 with
			<lb />
			attachments thereto accompanied by Form No. NCLT
			<lb />
			2 and in case of an interlocutory application, the same
			<lb />
			shall be filed in Form No. NCLT 1 accompanied by
			<lb />
			such attachments thereto along with Form No. NCLT
			<lb />
			3.
			<lb />
			(4) Every petition or application including interlocutory
			<lb />
			application shall be verified by an affidavit in Form No.
			<lb />
			NCLT 6. Notice to be issued by the Tribunal to the
			<lb />
			opposite party shall be in Form NCLT 5.‖
			<lb />
			xxx xxx xxx
			<lb />
			-37. Notice to Opposite Party.-(1) The Tribunal shall
			<lb />
			issue notice to the respondent to show cause against
			<lb />
			the application or petition on a date of hearing to be
			<lb />
			specified in the Notice. Such notice in Form No. NCLT
			<lb />
			5 shall be accompanied by a copy of the application
			<lb />
			with supporting documents.
			<lb />
			(2) If the respondent does not appear on the date
			<lb />
			specified in the notice in Form No. NCLT 5, the
			<lb />
			Tribunal, after according reasonable opportunity to the
			<lb />
			respondent, shall forthwith proceed ex-parte to
			<lb />
			dispose of the application.
			<lb />
			(3) If the respondent contests to the notice received
			<lb />
			under sub-rule (1), it may, either in person or through
			<lb />
			an authorised representative, file a reply accompanied
			<lb />
			with an affidavit and along with copies of such
			<lb />
			documents on which it relies, with an advance service
			<lb />
			to the petitioner or applicant, to the Registry before the
			<lb />
			date of hearing and such reply and copies of
			<lb />
			documents shall form part of the record.‖
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			72
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			A conjoint reading of all these Rules makes it clear that at the stage of
			<lb />
			the Adjudicating Authority&apos;s satisfaction under Section 7(5) of the
			<lb />
			Code, the corporate debtor is served with a copy of the application filed
			<lb />
			with the Adjudicating Authority and has the opportunity to file a reply
			<lb />
			before the said authority and be heard by the said authority before an
			<lb />
			order is made admitting the said application. What is also of relevance
			<lb />
			is that in order to protect the corporate debtor from being dragged into
			<lb />
			the corporate insolvency resolution process malafide, the Code
			<lb />
			prescribes penalties. Thus, Section 65 of the Code reads as follows:
			<lb />
			-65. Fraudulent or malicious initiation of
			<lb />
			proceedings.-(1) If, any person initiates the
			<lb />
			insolvency
			<lb />
			resolution
			<lb />
			process
			<lb />
			or
			<lb />
			liquidation
			<lb />
			proceedings fraudulently or with malicious intent for
			<lb />
			any purpose other than for the resolution of
			<lb />
			insolvency, or liquidation, as the case may be, the
			<lb />
			Adjudicating Authority may impose upon such person
			<lb />
			a penalty which shall not be less than one lakh rupees,
			<lb />
			but may extend to one crore rupees.
			<lb />
			(2) If, any person initiates voluntary liquidation
			<lb />
			proceedings with the intent to defraud any person, the
			<lb />
			Adjudicating Authority may impose upon such person
			<lb />
			a penalty which shall not be less than one lakh rupees
			<lb />
			but may extend to one crore rupees.‖
			<lb />
			34. Also, punishment is prescribed under Section 75 for furnishing
			<lb />
			false information in an application made by a financial creditor which
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			73
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			further deters a financial creditor from wrongly invoking the provisions
			<lb />
			of Section 7. Section 75 reads as under:
			<lb />
			-75. Punishment for false information furnished in
			<lb />
			application.-Where any person furnishes information
			<lb />
			in the application made under Section 7, which is false
			<lb />
			in material particulars, knowing it to be false or omits
			<lb />
			any material fact, knowing it to be material, such
			<lb />
			person shall be punishable with fine which shall not be
			<lb />
			less than one lakh rupees, but may extend to one
			<lb />
			crore rupees.‖
			<lb />
			35. Insofar as set-off and counterclaim is concerned, a set-off of
			<lb />
			amounts due from financial creditors is a rarity. Usually, financial debts
			<lb />
			point only in one way -amounts lent have to be repaid. However, it is
			<lb />
			not as if a legitimate set-off is not to be considered at all. Such set-off
			<lb />
			may be considered at the stage of filing of proof of claims during the
			<lb />
			resolution process by the resolution professional, his decision being
			<lb />
			subject to challenge before the Adjudicating Authority under Section
			<lb />
			60. Section 60(5)(c) reads as follows:
			<lb />
			-60.
			<lb />
			Adjudicating
			<lb />
			Authority
			<lb />
			for
			<lb />
			corporate
			<lb />
			persons.-
			<lb />
			xxx xxx xxx
			<lb />
			(5) Notwithstanding anything to the contrary contained
			<lb />
			in any other law for the time being in force, the
			<lb />
			National Company Law Tribunal shall have jurisdiction
			<lb />
			to entertain or dispose of-
			<lb />
			xxx xxx xxx
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			74
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			(c) any question of priorities or any question
			<lb />
			of law or facts, arising out of or in relation to
			<lb />
			the insolvency resolution or liquidation
			<lb />
			proceedings of the corporate debtor or
			<lb />
			corporate person under this Code.‖
			<lb />
			36. Equally, counterclaims, by their very definition, are independent
			<lb />
			rights which are not taken away by the Code but are preserved for the
			<lb />
			stage of admission of claims during the resolution plan. Also, there is
			<lb />
			nothing in the Code which interdicts the corporate debtor from pursuing
			<lb />
			such counterclaims in other judicial fora. Form C dealing with
			<lb />
			submission of claims by financial creditors in the CIRP Regulations
			<lb />
			states thus:
			<lb />
			-FORM C
			<lb />
			SUBMISSION OF CLAIM BY FINANCIAL
			<lb />
			CREDITORS
			<lb />
			[Under Regulation 8 of the Insolvency and Bankruptcy
			<lb />
			Board of India (Insolvency Resolution Process for
			<lb />
			Corporate Persons) Regulations, 2016]
			<lb />
			[Date]
			<lb />
			From
			<lb />
			[Name and address of the financial creditor, including
			<lb />
			address of its registered office and principal office]
			<lb />
			To
			<lb />
			The Interim Resolution Professional/Resolution
			<lb />
			Professional,
			<lb />
			[Name of the Insolvency Resolution Professional /
			<lb />
			Resolution Professional]
			<lb />
			[Address as set out in public announcement]
			<lb />
			Subject: Submission of claim and proof of claim.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			75
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			Madam/Sir,
			<lb />
			[Name of the financial creditor], hereby submits this
			<lb />
			claim in respect of the corporate insolvency resolution
			<lb />
			process of [name of corporate debtor]. The details for
			<lb />
			the same are set out below:
			<lb />
			Relevant Particulars
			<lb />
			1
			<lb />
			Name of the financial creditor
			<lb />
			Identification number of the financial
			<lb />
			creditor
			<lb />
			(If an incorporated body, provide
			<lb />
			identification number and proof of
			<lb />
			incorporation. If a partnership or
			<lb />
			individual
			<lb />
			provide
			<lb />
			identification
			<lb />
			records* of all the partners or the
			<lb />
			individual)
			<lb />
			3
			<lb />
			.
			<lb />
			Address and email address of the
			<lb />
			financial creditor for correspondence
			<lb />
			4
			<lb />
			.
			<lb />
			Total amount of claim
			<lb />
			(including any interest as at the
			<lb />
			insolvency commencement date)
			<lb />
			5
			<lb />
			.
			<lb />
			Details of documents by reference to
			<lb />
			which the debt can be substantiated
			<lb />
			6
			<lb />
			.
			<lb />
			Details of how and when debt incurred
			<lb />
			7
			<lb />
			.
			<lb />
			Details of any mutual credit, mutual
			<lb />
			debts, or other mutual dealings
			<lb />
			between the corporate debtor and the
			<lb />
			creditor which may be set-off against
			<lb />
			the claim
			<lb />
			8
			<lb />
			.
			<lb />
			Details of any security held, the value
			<lb />
			of the security, and the date it was
			<lb />
			given
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			76
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			9
			<lb />
			.
			<lb />
			Details of the bank account to which
			<lb />
			the amount of the claim or any part
			<lb />
			thereof can be transferred pursuant to
			<lb />
			a resolution plan
			<lb />
			1
			<lb />
			0
			<lb />
			.
			<lb />
			List of documents attached to this
			<lb />
			claim in order to prove the existence
			<lb />
			and non-payment of claim due to the
			<lb />
			financial creditor
			<lb />
			(Signature of financial creditor or person authorised
			<lb />
			to act on his behalf)
			<lb />
			[Please enclose the authority if this is being
			<lb />
			submitted on behalf of the financial creditor]
			<lb />
			Name in BLOCK LETTERS
			<lb />
			Position with or in relation to creditor
			<lb />
			Address of person signing
			<lb />
			* PAN number, passport, AADHAAR Card or the
			<lb />
			identity card issued by the Election Commission of
			<lb />
			India.
			<lb />
			DECLARATION
			<lb />
			I, [Name of claimant], currently residing at [insert address],
			<lb />
			do hereby declare and state as follows:
			<lb />
			1. [Name of corporate debtor], the corporate
			<lb />
			debtor
			<lb />
			was,
			<lb />
			at
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			insolvency
			<lb />
			commencement date, being the ………… day
			<lb />
			of ………… 20……, actually indebted to me
			<lb />
			for a sum of Rs. [insert amount of claim].
			<lb />
			2. In respect of my claim of the said sum or any
			<lb />
			part thereof, I have relied on the documents
			<lb />
			specified below:
			<lb />
			[Please list the documents relied on as
			<lb />
			evidence of claim].
			<lb />
			3. The said documents are true, valid and
			<lb />
			genuine to the best of my knowledge,
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			77
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			information and belief and no material facts
			<lb />
			have been concealed therefrom.
			<lb />
			4. In respect of the said sum or any part thereof,
			<lb />
			neither I, nor any person, by my order, to my
			<lb />
			knowledge or belief, for my use, had or
			<lb />
			received any manner of satisfaction or
			<lb />
			security whatsoever, save and except the
			<lb />
			following:
			<lb />
			[Please state details of any mutual credit,
			<lb />
			mutual debts, or other mutual dealings
			<lb />
			between the corporate debtor and the
			<lb />
			creditor which may be set-off against the
			<lb />
			claim].
			<lb />
			5. I am/I am not a related party of the corporate
			<lb />
			debtor, as defined under Section 5(24) of the
			<lb />
			Code.
			<lb />
			6. I am eligible to join committee of creditors by
			<lb />
			virtue of proviso to Section 21(2) of the Code
			<lb />
			even though I am a related party of the
			<lb />
			corporate debtor.
			<lb />
			Date:
			<lb />
			Place:
			<lb />
			(Signature of the claimant)
			<lb />
			VERIFICATION
			<lb />
			I, [Name] the claimant hereinabove, do hereby verify
			<lb />
			that the contents of this proof of claim are true and
			<lb />
			correct to my knowledge and belief and no material
			<lb />
			fact has been concealed therefrom.
			<lb />
			Verified at … on this …… day of ………, 20…
			<lb />
			(Signature of claimant)
			<lb />
			[Note: In the case of company or limited liability
			<lb />
			partnership, the declaration and verification shall be
			<lb />
			made by the director/manager/secretary/designated
			<lb />
			partner and in the case of other entities, an officer
			<lb />
			authorised for the purpose by the entity.]‖
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			78
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			37. The trigger for a financial creditor&apos;s application is non-payment of
			<lb />
			dues when they arise under loan agreements. It is for this reason that
			<lb />
			Section 433(e) of the Companies Act, 1956 has been repealed by the
			<lb />
			Code and a change in approach has been brought about. Legislative
			<lb />
			policy now is to move away from the concept of -inability to pay debts‖
			<lb />
			to -determination of default‖. The said shift enables the financial
			<lb />
			creditor to prove, based upon solid documentary evidence, that there
			<lb />
			was an obligation to pay the debt and that the debtor has failed in such
			<lb />
			obligation. Four policy reasons have been stated by the learned
			<lb />
			Solicitor General for this shift in legislative policy. First is predictability
			<lb />
			and certainty. Secondly, the paramount interest to be safeguarded is
			<lb />
			that of the corporate debtor and admission into the insolvency
			<lb />
			resolution process does not prejudice such interest but, in fact,
			<lb />
			protects it. Thirdly, in a situation of financial stress, the cause of default
			<lb />
			is not relevant; protecting the economic interest of the corporate debtor
			<lb />
			is more relevant. Fourthly, the trigger that would lead to liquidation can
			<lb />
			only be upon failure of the resolution process.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			79
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			38. In this context, it is important to differentiate between -claim‖,
			<lb />
			-debt‖ and -default‖. Each of these terms is separately defined as
			<lb />
			follows:
			<lb />
			-3. Definitions.-In this Code, unless the context
			<lb />
			otherwise requires,-
			<lb />
			xxx xxx xxx
			<lb />
			(6) -claim‖ means-
			<lb />
			(a) a right to payment, whether or not such
			<lb />
			right is reduced to judgment, fixed, disputed,
			<lb />
			undisputed, legal, equitable, secured or
			<lb />
			unsecured;
			<lb />
			(b) right to remedy for breach of contract
			<lb />
			under any law for the time being in force, if
			<lb />
			such breach gives rise to a right to payment,
			<lb />
			whether or not such right is reduced to
			<lb />
			judgment, fixed, matured, unmatured,
			<lb />
			disputed, undisputed, secured or unsecured;
			<lb />
			xxx xxx xxx
			<lb />
			(11) -debt‖ means a liability or obligation in respect of
			<lb />
			a claim which is due from any person and includes a
			<lb />
			financial debt and operational debt;
			<lb />
			(12) -default‖ means non-payment of debt when whole
			<lb />
			or any part or instalment of the amount of debt has
			<lb />
			become due and payable and is not paid by the debtor
			<lb />
			or the corporate debtor, as the case may be;
			<lb />
			xxx xxx xxx‖
			<lb />
			Whereas a -claim‖ gives rise to a -debt‖ only when it becomes -due‖, a
			<lb />
			-default‖ occurs only when a -debt‖ becomes -due and payable‖ and is
			<lb />
			not paid by the debtor. It is for this reason that a financial creditor has
			<lb />
			to prove -default‖ as opposed to an operational creditor who merely
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			80
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			-claims‖ a right to payment of a liability or obligation in respect of a
			<lb />
			debt which may be due. When this aspect is borne in mind, the
			<lb />
			differentiation in the triggering of insolvency resolution process by
			<lb />
			financial creditors under Section 7 and by operational creditors under
			<lb />
			Sections 8 and 9 of the Code becomes clear.
			<lb />
			SECTIONS 21 AND 24 AND ARTICLE 14: OPERATIONAL CREDITORS HAVE NO
			<lb />
			VOTE IN THE COMMITTEE OF CREDITORS.
			<lb />
			39. Section 21 of the Code reads as follows:
			<lb />
			-21. Committee of creditors.-(1) The interim
			<lb />
			resolution professional shall after collation of all claims
			<lb />
			received against the corporate debtor and
			<lb />
			determination of the financial position of the corporate
			<lb />
			debtor, constitute a committee of creditors.
			<lb />
			(2) The committee of creditors shall comprise all
			<lb />
			financial creditors of the corporate debtor:
			<lb />
			Provided that a financial creditor or the authorised
			<lb />
			representative of the financial creditor referred to in
			<lb />
			sub-section (6) or sub-section (6-A) or sub-section (5)
			<lb />
			of Section 24, if it is a related party of the corporate
			<lb />
			debtor, shall not have any right of representation,
			<lb />
			participation or voting in a meeting of the committee of
			<lb />
			creditors:
			<lb />
			Provided further that the first proviso shall not apply
			<lb />
			to a financial creditor, regulated by a financial sector
			<lb />
			regulator, if it is a related party of the corporate debtor
			<lb />
			solely on account of conversion or substitution of debt
			<lb />
			into equity shares or instruments convertible into
			<lb />
			equity shares, prior to the insolvency commencement
			<lb />
			date.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			81
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			(3) Subject to sub-sections (6) and (6-A), where the
			<lb />
			corporate debtor owes financial debts to two or more
			<lb />
			financial creditors as part of a consortium or
			<lb />
			agreement, each such financial creditor shall be part of
			<lb />
			the committee of creditors and their voting share shall
			<lb />
			be determined on the basis of the financial debts owed
			<lb />
			to them.
			<lb />
			(4) Where any person is a financial creditor as well as
			<lb />
			an operational creditor,-
			<lb />
			(a) such person shall be a financial creditor to
			<lb />
			the extent of the financial debt owed by the
			<lb />
			corporate debtor, and shall be included in the
			<lb />
			committee of creditors, with voting share
			<lb />
			proportionate to the extent of financial debts
			<lb />
			owed to such creditor;
			<lb />
			(b) such person shall be considered to be an
			<lb />
			operational creditor to the extent of the
			<lb />
			operational debt owed by the corporate
			<lb />
			debtor to such creditor.
			<lb />
			(5) Where an operational creditor has assigned or
			<lb />
			legally transferred any operational debt to a financial
			<lb />
			creditor, the assignee or transferee shall be
			<lb />
			considered as an operational creditor to the extent of
			<lb />
			such assignment or legal transfer.
			<lb />
			(6) Where the terms of the financial debt extended as
			<lb />
			part of a consortium arrangement or syndicated facility
			<lb />
			provide for a single trustee or agent to act for all
			<lb />
			financial creditors, each financial creditor may-
			<lb />
			(a) authorize the trustee or agent to act on his
			<lb />
			behalf in the committee of creditors to the
			<lb />
			extent of his voting share;
			<lb />
			(b) represent himself in the committee of
			<lb />
			creditors to the extent of his voting share;
			<lb />
			(c) appoint an insolvency professional (other
			<lb />
			than the resolution professional) at his own
			<lb />
			cost to represent himself in the committee of
			<lb />
			creditors to the extent of his voting share; or
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			82
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			(d) exercise his right to vote to the extent of
			<lb />
			his voting share with one or more financial
			<lb />
			creditors jointly or severally.
			<lb />
			(6-A) Where a financial debt-
			<lb />
			(a) is in the form of securities or deposits and
			<lb />
			the terms of the financial debt provide for
			<lb />
			appointment of a trustee or agent to act as
			<lb />
			authorised representative for all the financial
			<lb />
			creditors, such trustee or agent shall act on
			<lb />
			behalf of such financial creditors;
			<lb />
			(b) is owed to a class of creditors exceeding
			<lb />
			the number as may be specified, other than
			<lb />
			the creditors covered under clause (a) or sub-
			<lb />
			section (6), the interim resolution professional
			<lb />
			shall make an application to the Adjudicating
			<lb />
			Authority along with the list of all financial
			<lb />
			creditors, containing the name of an
			<lb />
			insolvency professional, other than the
			<lb />
			interim resolution professional, to act as their
			<lb />
			authorised representative who shall be
			<lb />
			appointed by the Adjudicating Authority prior
			<lb />
			to the first meeting of the committee of
			<lb />
			creditors;
			<lb />
			(c) is represented by a guardian, executor or
			<lb />
			administrator, such person shall act as
			<lb />
			authorised representative on behalf of such
			<lb />
			financial creditors,
			<lb />
			and such authorised representative under clause (a) or
			<lb />
			clause (b) or clause (c) shall attend the meetings of
			<lb />
			the committee of creditors, and vote on behalf of each
			<lb />
			financial creditor to the extent of his voting share.
			<lb />
			(6-B) The remuneration payable to the authorised
			<lb />
			representative-
			<lb />
			(i) under clauses (a) and (c) of sub-section
			<lb />
			(6-A), if any, shall be as per the terms of the
			<lb />
			financial debt or the relevant documentation;
			<lb />
			and
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			83
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			(ii) under clause (b) of sub-section (6-A) shall
			<lb />
			be as specified which shall form part of the
			<lb />
			insolvency resolution process costs.
			<lb />
			(7) The Board may specify the manner of voting and
			<lb />
			the determining of the voting share in respect of
			<lb />
			financial debts covered under sub-sections (6) and (6-
			<lb />
			A).
			<lb />
			(8) Save as otherwise provided in this Code, all
			<lb />
			decisions of the committee of creditors shall be taken
			<lb />
			by a vote of not less than fifty-one per cent. of voting
			<lb />
			share of the financial creditors:
			<lb />
			Provided that where a corporate debtor does not
			<lb />
			have any financial creditors, the committee of creditors
			<lb />
			shall be constituted and shall comprise of such
			<lb />
			persons to exercise such functions in such manner as
			<lb />
			may be specified.
			<lb />
			(9) The committee of creditors shall have the right to
			<lb />
			require the resolution professional to furnish any
			<lb />
			financial information in relation to the corporate debtor
			<lb />
			at any time during the corporate insolvency resolution
			<lb />
			process.
			<lb />
			(10) The resolution professional shall make available
			<lb />
			any financial information so required by the committee
			<lb />
			of creditors under sub-section (9) within a period of
			<lb />
			seven days of such requisition.‖
			<lb />
			40. Section 24(3), 24(4), and Section 28, which are also material,
			<lb />
			read as follows:
			<lb />
			-24. Meeting of committee of creditors.-
			<lb />
			xxx xxx xxx
			<lb />
			(3) The resolution professional shall give notice of
			<lb />
			each meeting of the committee of creditors to-
			<lb />
			(a) members of [committee of creditors,
			<lb />
			including the authorised representatives
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			84
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			referred to in sub-sections (6) and (6-A) of
			<lb />
			Section 21 and sub-section (5)];
			<lb />
			(b) members of the suspended Board of
			<lb />
			Directors or the partners of the corporate
			<lb />
			persons, as the case may be;
			<lb />
			(c)
			<lb />
			operational
			<lb />
			creditors
			<lb />
			or
			<lb />
			their
			<lb />
			representatives if the amount of their
			<lb />
			aggregate dues is not less than ten per cent
			<lb />
			of the debt.
			<lb />
			(4) The directors, partners and one representative of
			<lb />
			operational creditors, as referred to in sub-section (3),
			<lb />
			may attend the meetings of committee of creditors, but
			<lb />
			shall not have any right to vote in such meetings:
			<lb />
			Provided that the absence of any such director,
			<lb />
			partner or representative of operational creditors, as
			<lb />
			the case may be, shall not invalidate proceedings of
			<lb />
			such meeting.
			<lb />
			xxx xxx xxx‖
			<lb />
			xxx xxx xxx
			<lb />
			-28. Approval of committee of creditors for certain
			<lb />
			actions.-(1) Notwithstanding anything contained in
			<lb />
			any other law for the time being in force, the resolution
			<lb />
			professional, during the corporate insolvency
			<lb />
			resolution process, shall not take any of the following
			<lb />
			actions without the prior approval of the committee of
			<lb />
			creditors namely-
			<lb />
			(a) raise any interim finance in excess of the
			<lb />
			amount as may be decided by the committee
			<lb />
			of creditors in their meeting;
			<lb />
			(b) create any security interest over the
			<lb />
			assets of the corporate debtor;
			<lb />
			(c) change the capital structure of the
			<lb />
			corporate debtor, including by way of
			<lb />
			issuance of additional securities, creating a
			<lb />
			new class of securities or buying back or
			<lb />
			redemption of issued securities in case the
			<lb />
			corporate debtor is a company;
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			85
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			(d) record any change in the ownership
			<lb />
			interest of the corporate debtor;
			<lb />
			(e) give instructions to financial institutions
			<lb />
			maintaining accounts of the corporate debtor
			<lb />
			for a debit transaction from any such
			<lb />
			accounts in excess of the amount as may be
			<lb />
			decided by the committee of creditors in their
			<lb />
			meeting;
			<lb />
			(f) undertake any related party transaction;
			<lb />
			(g) amend any constitutional documents of
			<lb />
			the corporate debtor;
			<lb />
			(h) delegate its authority to any other person;
			<lb />
			(i) of or permit the disposal of shares
			<lb />
			of any shareholder of the corporate debtor or
			<lb />
			their nominees to third parties;
			<lb />
			(j) make any change in the management of
			<lb />
			the corporate debtor or its subsidiary;
			<lb />
			(k) transfer rights or financial debts or
			<lb />
			operational debts under material contracts
			<lb />
			otherwise than in the ordinary course of
			<lb />
			business;
			<lb />
			(l) make changes in the appointment or terms
			<lb />
			of contract of such personnel as specified by
			<lb />
			the committee of creditors; or
			<lb />
			(m) make changes in the appointment or
			<lb />
			terms of contract of statutory auditors or
			<lb />
			internal auditors of the corporate debtor.
			<lb />
			(2) The resolution professional shall convene a
			<lb />
			meeting of the committee of creditors and seek the
			<lb />
			vote of the creditors prior to taking any of the actions
			<lb />
			under sub-section (1).
			<lb />
			(3) No action under sub-section (1) shall be approved
			<lb />
			by the committee of creditors unless approved by a
			<lb />
			vote of sixty-six per cent of the voting shares.
			<lb />
			(4) Where any action under sub-section (1) is taken by
			<lb />
			the resolution professional without seeking the
			<lb />
			approval of the committee of creditors in the manner
			<lb />
			as required in this section, such action shall be void.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			86
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			(5) The committee of creditors may report the actions
			<lb />
			of the resolution professional under sub-section (4) to
			<lb />
			the Board for taking necessary actions against him
			<lb />
			under this Code. Approval of committee of creditors for
			<lb />
			certain
			<lb />
			41. In this regard, the BLRC Report states:
			<lb />
			-The creditors committee will have the power to decide
			<lb />
			the final solution by majority vote in the negotiations.
			<lb />
			The majority vote requires more than or equal to 75
			<lb />
			percent of the creditors committee by weight of the
			<lb />
			total financial liabilities…… The Committee deliberated
			<lb />
			on who should be on the creditors committee, given
			<lb />
			the power of the creditors committee to ultimately keep
			<lb />
			the entity as a going concern or liquidate it. The
			<lb />
			Committee reasoned that members of the creditors
			<lb />
			committee have to be creditors both with the capability
			<lb />
			to assess viability, as well as to be willing to modify
			<lb />
			terms of existing liabilities in negotiations. Typically,
			<lb />
			operational creditors are neither able to decide on
			<lb />
			matters regarding the insolvency of the entity, nor
			<lb />
			willing to take the risk of postponing payments for
			<lb />
			better future prospects for the entity. The Committee
			<lb />
			concluded that, for the process to be rapid and
			<lb />
			efficient, the Code will provide that the creditors
			<lb />
			committee should be restricted to only the financial
			<lb />
			creditors.‖
			<lb />
			-The second is that any proposed solution must
			<lb />
			explicitly account for the IRP costs and the liabilities of
			<lb />
			the operational creditors within a reasonable period
			<lb />
			from the approval of the solution if it is approved. The
			<lb />
			Committee argues that there must be a
			<lb />
			counterbalance to operational creditors not having a
			<lb />
			vote on the creditors committee. Thus, they concluded
			<lb />
			that the dues of the operational creditors must have
			<lb />
			priority in being paid as an explicit part of the proposed
			<lb />
			solution. This must be ensured by the RP in evaluating
			<lb />
			a proposal before bringing it to the creditors
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			87
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			committee. If there is ambiguity about the coverage of
			<lb />
			the liability in the information memorandum that the
			<lb />
			RP presents to garner solutions, then the RP must
			<lb />
			ensure that this is clearly stated and accounted for in
			<lb />
			the proposed solution.‖
			<lb />
			The Joint Parliamentary Committee Report of April, 2016 [-Joint
			<lb />
			Parliamentary Committee Report‖] on the Insolvency and Bankruptcy
			<lb />
			Code also agreed with these observations but modified Section 24 so
			<lb />
			as to permit operational creditors to be present at the meetings of the
			<lb />
			committee of creditors, albeit without voting rights, if operational
			<lb />
			creditors to 10% or more of the total debts owed by the
			<lb />
			corporate debtor.
			<lb />
			The Joint Parliamentary Committee Report also opined as follows:
			<lb />
			-21. Role of Operational Creditors -Clause 24
			<lb />
			Some of the stakeholders in the memorandum/views
			<lb />
			furnished before the Committee were of the opinion
			<lb />
			that whereas operation creditor has right to make
			<lb />
			application for initiation of corporate insolvency
			<lb />
			resolution process, operational creditors like workmen,
			<lb />
			employees, suppliers have not been given any
			<lb />
			representation in the committee of creditors which is
			<lb />
			pivotal in whole resolution process. In this regard, one
			<lb />
			of the stakeholders has suggested that committee of
			<lb />
			creditors may contain operational creditors as well,
			<lb />
			with some thresholds.
			<lb />
			In this context, while appreciating that the operational
			<lb />
			creditors are important stakeholders in a company, the
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			88
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			Committee took note of the rationale of not including
			<lb />
			operational creditors in the committee of creditors as
			<lb />
			indicated in notes on Clause 21 appended with the Bill
			<lb />
			which states as under:-
			<lb />
			-The committee has to be composed of
			<lb />
			members who have the capability to assess
			<lb />
			the commercial viability of the corporate
			<lb />
			debtor and who are willing to modify the
			<lb />
			terms of the debt contracts in negotiations
			<lb />
			between the creditors and the corporate
			<lb />
			debtor. Operational creditors are typically not
			<lb />
			able to decide on matters relating to
			<lb />
			commercial viability of the corporate debtor,
			<lb />
			nor are they typically willing to take the risk of
			<lb />
			restructuring their debts in order to make the
			<lb />
			corporate debtor a going concern. Similarly,
			<lb />
			financial creditors who are also operational
			<lb />
			creditors will be given representation on the
			<lb />
			committee of creditors only to the extent of
			<lb />
			their financial debts. Nevertheless, in order to
			<lb />
			ensure that the financial creditors do not treat
			<lb />
			the operational creditors unfairly, any
			<lb />
			resolution plan must ensure that the
			<lb />
			operational creditors receive an amount not
			<lb />
			less than the liquidation value of their debt
			<lb />
			(assuming the corporate debtor were to be
			<lb />
			liquidated).
			<lb />
			All decisions of the Committee shall be taken by a vote
			<lb />
			of not less than seventy-five per cent of the voting
			<lb />
			share. In the event there are no financial creditors for a
			<lb />
			corporate debtor, the composition and decision-
			<lb />
			making processes of the corporate debtor shall be
			<lb />
			specified by the Insolvency and Bankruptcy Board.
			<lb />
			The Committee shall also have the power to call for
			<lb />
			information from the resolution professional.‖
			<lb />
			The Committee after due deliberations are of the view
			<lb />
			that, if not voting rights, operational creditors at least
			<lb />
			should have presence in the committee of creditors to
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			89
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			present their views/concerns on important issues
			<lb />
			considered at the meetings so that their
			<lb />
			views/concerns are taken into account by the
			<lb />
			committee of creditors while finalizing the resolution
			<lb />
			plan.‖
			<lb />
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
			The original Insolvency and Bankruptcy Bill did not allow operational
			<lb />
			creditors to attend the committee of creditors at all. This Bill was
			<lb />
			amended whilst in the form of a Bill, the Joint Parliamentary Committee
			<lb />
			deciding as follows:
			<lb />
			-The Committee, therefore, decided to modify clause
			<lb />
			24(3) and (4) as given under:
			<lb />
			Modified Clause 24(3)-
			<lb />
			-The resolution professional shall give notice of each
			<lb />
			meeting of the committee of creditors to-
			<lb />
			(a) members of committee of creditors;
			<lb />
			(b) members of the suspended Board of
			<lb />
			Directors or the partners of the corporate
			<lb />
			persons, as the case may be;
			<lb />
			(c) operational creditors or their representatives
			<lb />
			if the amount of their aggregate dues is not less
			<lb />
			than ten per cent of the debt.‖
			<lb />
			Modified Clause 24(4)-
			<lb />
			-The directors, partners and one representative of
			<lb />
			operational creditors as referred to in sub-section (3),
			<lb />
			may attend the meetings of committee of creditors, but
			<lb />
			shall not have any right to vote in such meetings:
			<lb />
			Provided that the absence of any such director,
			<lb />
			partner or representative of operational creditors, as
			<lb />
			the case may be, shall not invalidate proceedings of
			<lb />
			such meeting.‖
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			90
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			42. What is also of importance is the fact that Expert Committees
			<lb />
			have been set up by the Government to oversee the working of the
			<lb />
			Code. Thus, the report of the Insolvency Law Committee of March,
			<lb />
			2018, after examining the working of the Code, thought it fit not to
			<lb />
			amend the Code so as to give operational creditors the right to vote.
			<lb />
			This was stated as follows:
			<lb />
			-This rationale still holds true, and thus it was deemed
			<lb />
			fit not to amend the constitution of the CoC. Further,
			<lb />
			operational creditors whose aggregate dues are not
			<lb />
			less than ten percent of the debt have a right to attend
			<lb />
			the meetings of the CoC. Also, under the resolution
			<lb />
			plan, they are guaranteed at least the liquidation
			<lb />
			value.‖
			<lb />
			-…The Committee agreed that presently, most of the
			<lb />
			resolution plans are in the process of submission and
			<lb />
			there is no empirical evidence to further the argument
			<lb />
			that operational creditors do not receive a fair share in
			<lb />
			the resolution process under the current scheme of the
			<lb />
			Code. Hence, the Committee decided to continue with
			<lb />
			the present arrangement without making any
			<lb />
			amendments to the Code.‖
			<lb />
			43. Under the Code, the committee of creditors is entrusted with the
			<lb />
			primary responsibility of financial restructuring. They are required to
			<lb />
			assess the viability of a corporate debtor by taking into account all
			<lb />
			available information as well as to evaluate all alternative investment
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			91
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			opportunities that are available. The committee of creditors is required
			<lb />
			to evaluate the resolution plan on the basis of feasibility and viability.
			<lb />
			Thus, Section 30(4) states:
			<lb />
			-30. Submission of resolution plan.-
			<lb />
			xxx xxx xxx
			<lb />
			(4) The committee of creditors may approve a
			<lb />
			resolution plan by a vote of not less than sixty-six per
			<lb />
			cent of voting share of the financial creditors, after
			<lb />
			considering its feasibility and viability, and such other
			<lb />
			requirements as may be specified by the Board:
			<lb />
			Provided that the committee of creditors shall not
			<lb />
			approve a resolution plan, submitted before the
			<lb />
			commencement of the Insolvency and Bankruptcy
			<lb />
			Code (Amendment) Ordinance, 2017, where the
			<lb />
			resolution applicant is ineligible under Section 29A and
			<lb />
			may require the resolution professional to invite a fresh
			<lb />
			resolution plan where no other resolution plan is
			<lb />
			available with it:
			<lb />
			Provided further that where the resolution applicant
			<lb />
			referred to in the first proviso is ineligible under clause
			<lb />
			(c) of Section 29A, the resolution applicant shall be
			<lb />
			allowed by the committee of creditors such period, not
			<lb />
			exceeding thirty days, to make payment of overdue
			<lb />
			amounts in accordance with the proviso to clause (c)
			<lb />
			of Section 29A:
			<lb />
			Provided also that nothing in the second proviso
			<lb />
			shall be construed as extension of period for the
			<lb />
			purposes of the proviso to sub-section (3) of Section
			<lb />
			12, and the corporate insolvency resolution process
			<lb />
			shall be completed within the period specified in that
			<lb />
			sub-section.
			<lb />
			Provided also that the eligibility criteria in Section
			<lb />
			29A as amended by the Insolvency and Bankruptcy
			<lb />
			Code (Amendment) Ordinance, 2018 (Ord. 6 of 2018)
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			92
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			shall apply to the resolution applicant who has not
			<lb />
			submitted resolution plan as on the date of
			<lb />
			commencement of the Insolvency and Bankruptcy
			<lb />
			Code (Amendment) Ordinance, 2018.
			<lb />
			xxx xxx xxx‖
			<lb />
			It is important to bear in mind that once the resolution plan is approved
			<lb />
			by the committee of creditors and thereafter by the Adjudicating
			<lb />
			Authority, the aforesaid plan is binding on all stakeholders as follows:
			<lb />
			-31. Approval of resolution plan.-(1) If the
			<lb />
			Adjudicating Authority is satisfied that the resolution
			<lb />
			plan as approved by the committee of creditors under
			<lb />
			sub-section (4) of Section 30 meets the requirements
			<lb />
			as referred to in sub-section (2) of Section 30, it shall
			<lb />
			by order approve the resolution plan which shall be
			<lb />
			binding on the corporate debtor and its employees,
			<lb />
			members,
			<lb />
			creditors,
			<lb />
			guarantors
			<lb />
			and
			<lb />
			other
			<lb />
			stakeholders involved in the resolution plan:
			<lb />
			Provided that the Adjudicating Authority shall,
			<lb />
			before passing an order for approval of resolution plan
			<lb />
			under this sub-section, satisfy that the resolution plan
			<lb />
			has provisions for its effective implementation.
			<lb />
			xxx xxx xxx‖
			<lb />
			44. Since the financial creditors are in the business of money
			<lb />
			lending, banks and financial institutions are best equipped to assess
			<lb />
			viability and feasibility of the business of the corporate debtor. Even at
			<lb />
			the time of granting loans, these banks and financial institutions
			<lb />
			undertake a detailed market study which includes a techno-economic
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			93
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			valuation report, evaluation of business, financial projection, etc. Since
			<lb />
			this detailed study has already been undertaken before sanctioning a
			<lb />
			loan, and since financial creditors have trained employees to assess
			<lb />
			viability and feasibility, they are in a good position to evaluate the
			<lb />
			contents of a resolution plan. On the other hand, operational creditors,
			<lb />
			who provide goods and services, are involved only in recovering
			<lb />
			amounts that are paid for such goods and services, and are typically
			<lb />
			unable to assess viability and feasibility of business. The BLRC
			<lb />
			Report, already quoted above, makes this abundantly clear.
			<lb />
			45. Quite apart from this, the United Nations Commission on
			<lb />
			International Trade Law, in its Legislative Guide on Insolvency Law
			<lb />
			[-UNCITRAL Guidelines‖] recognizes the importance of ensuring
			<lb />
			equitable treatment to similarly placed creditors and states as follows:
			<lb />
			&quot;Ensuring equitable treatment of similarly situated
			<lb />
			creditors
			<lb />
			7. The objective of equitable treatment is based on the
			<lb />
			notion that, in collective proceedings, creditors with
			<lb />
			similar legal rights should be treated fairly, receiving a
			<lb />
			distribution on their claim in accordance with their
			<lb />
			relative ranking and interests. This key objective
			<lb />
			recognizes that all creditors do not need to be treated
			<lb />
			identically, but in a manner that reflects the different
			<lb />
			bargains they have struck with the debtor. This is less
			<lb />
			relevant as a defining factor where there is no specific
			<lb />
			debt contract with the debtor, such as in the case of
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			94
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			damage claimants (e.g. for environmental damage)
			<lb />
			and tax authorities. Even though the principle of
			<lb />
			equitable treatment may be modified by social policy
			<lb />
			on priorities and give way to the prerogatives
			<lb />
			pertaining to holders of claims or interests that arise,
			<lb />
			for example, by operation of law, it retains its
			<lb />
			significance by 12 UNCITRAL Legislative Guide on
			<lb />
			Insolvency Law ensuring that the priority accorded to
			<lb />
			the claims of a similar class affects all members of the
			<lb />
			class in the same manner. The policy of equitable
			<lb />
			treatment permeates many aspects of an insolvency
			<lb />
			law, including the application of the stay or
			<lb />
			suspension, provisions to set aside acts and
			<lb />
			transactions and recapture value for the insolvency
			<lb />
			estate, classification of claims, voting procedures in
			<lb />
			reorganization and distribution mechanisms. An
			<lb />
			insolvency law should address problems of fraud and
			<lb />
			favouritism that may arise in cases of financial distress
			<lb />
			by providing, for example, that acts and transactions
			<lb />
			detrimental to equitable treatment of creditors can be
			<lb />
			avoided.‖
			<lb />
			46. The NCLAT has, while looking into viability and feasibility of
			<lb />
			resolution plans that are approved by the committee of creditors,
			<lb />
			always gone into whether operational creditors are given roughly the
			<lb />
			same treatment as financial creditors, and if they are not, such plans
			<lb />
			are either rejected or modified so that the operational creditors&apos; rights
			<lb />
			are safeguarded. It may be seen that a resolution plan cannot pass
			<lb />
			muster under Section 30(2)(b) read with Section 31 unless a minimum
			<lb />
			payment is made to operational creditors, being not less than
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			95
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			liquidation value. Further, on 05.10.2018, Regulation 38 has been
			<lb />
			amended. Prior to the amendment, Regulation 38 read as follows:
			<lb />
			-38. Mandatory contents of the resolution plan.-
			<lb />
			(1) A resolution plan shall identify specific sources of
			<lb />
			funds that will be used to pay the-
			<lb />
			(a) insolvency resolution process costs and
			<lb />
			provide that the [insolvency resolution
			<lb />
			process costs, to the extent unpaid, will be
			<lb />
			paid] in priority to any other creditor;
			<lb />
			(b) liquidation value due to operational
			<lb />
			creditors and provide for such payment in
			<lb />
			priority to any financial creditor which shall in
			<lb />
			any event be made before the expiry of thirty
			<lb />
			days after the approval of a resolution plan by
			<lb />
			the Adjudicating Authority; and
			<lb />
			(c) liquidation value due to dissenting
			<lb />
			financial creditors and provide that such
			<lb />
			payment is made before any recoveries are
			<lb />
			made by the financial creditors who voted in
			<lb />
			favour of the resolution plan.‖
			<lb />
			Post amendment, Regulation 38 reads as follows:
			<lb />
			-38. Mandatory contents of the resolution plan.-
			<lb />
			(1) The amount due to the operational creditors under
			<lb />
			a resolution plan shall be given priority in payment
			<lb />
			over financial creditors.
			<lb />
			(1-A) A resolution plan shall include a statement as to
			<lb />
			how it has dealt with the interests of all stakeholders,
			<lb />
			including financial creditors and operational creditors,
			<lb />
			of the corporate debtor.
			<lb />
			xxx xxx xxx‖
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			96
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			47. The aforesaid Regulation further strengthens the rights of
			<lb />
			operational creditors by statutorily incorporating the principle of fair and
			<lb />
			equitable dealing of operational creditors&apos; rights, together with priority
			<lb />
			in payment over financial creditors.
			<lb />
			48. For all the aforesaid reasons, we do not find that operational
			<lb />
			creditors are discriminated against or that Article 14 has been infracted
			<lb />
			either on the ground of equals being treated unequally or on the
			<lb />
			ground of manifest arbitrariness.
			<lb />
			SECTION 12A IS NOT VIOLATIVE OF ARTICLE 14
			<lb />
			49. Section 12A was inserted by the Insolvency and Bankruptcy
			<lb />
			(Second Amendment) Act, 2018 with retrospective effect from
			<lb />
			06.06.2018. It reads as follows:
			<lb />
			-12-A. Withdrawal of application admitted under
			<lb />
			Section 7, 9 or 10.-The Adjudicating Authority may
			<lb />
			allow the withdrawal of application admitted under
			<lb />
			Section 7 or Section 9 or Section 10, on an application
			<lb />
			made by the applicant with the approval of ninety per
			<lb />
			cent voting share of the committee of creditors, in such
			<lb />
			manner as may be specified.‖
			<lb />
			50. The ILC Report of March 2018, which led to the insertion of
			<lb />
			Section 12A, stated as follows:
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			97
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			-29.1 Under rule 8 of the CIRP Rules, the NCLT may
			<lb />
			permit withdrawal of the application on a request by
			<lb />
			the applicant before its admission. However, there is
			<lb />
			no provision in the Code or the CIRP Rules in relation
			<lb />
			to permissibility of withdrawal post admission of a
			<lb />
			CIRP application. It was observed by the Committee
			<lb />
			that there have been instances where on account of
			<lb />
			settlement between the applicant creditor and the
			<lb />
			corporate debtor, judicial permission for withdrawal of
			<lb />
			CIRP was granted [Lokhandwala Kataria Construction
			<lb />
			Pvt. Ltd. v. Ninus Finance &amp; Investment Manager LLP,
			<lb />
			Civil Appeal No. 9279 of 2017; Mothers Pride Dairy
			<lb />
			India Private Limited v. Portrait Advertising and
			<lb />
			Marketing Private Limited, Civil Appeal No. 9286/2017;
			<lb />
			Uttara Foods and Feeds Private Limited v. Mona
			<lb />
			Pharmacem, Civil Appeal No. 18520/2017]. This
			<lb />
			practice was deliberated in light of the objective of the
			<lb />
			Code as encapsulated in the BLRC Report, that the
			<lb />
			design of the Code is based on ensuring that -all key
			<lb />
			stakeholders will participate to collectively assess
			<lb />
			viability. The law must ensure that all creditors who
			<lb />
			have the capability and the willingness to restructure
			<lb />
			their liabilities must be part of the negotiation process.
			<lb />
			The liabilities of all creditors who are not part of the
			<lb />
			negotiation process must also be met in any
			<lb />
			negotiated solution.‖ Thus, it was agreed that once the
			<lb />
			CIRP is initiated, it is no longer a proceeding only
			<lb />
			between the applicant creditor and the corporate
			<lb />
			debtor but is envisaged to be a proceeding involving
			<lb />
			all creditors of the debtor. The intent of the Code is to
			<lb />
			discourage individual actions for enforcement and
			<lb />
			settlement to the exclusion of the general benefit of all
			<lb />
			creditors.
			<lb />
			(emphasis in original)
			<lb />
			29.2 On a review of the multiple NCLT and NCLAT
			<lb />
			judgments in this regard, the consistent pattern that
			<lb />
			emerged was that a settlement may be reached
			<lb />
			amongst all creditors and the debtor, for the purpose
			<lb />
			of a withdrawal to be granted, and not only the
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			98
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			applicant creditor and the debtor. On this basis read
			<lb />
			with the intent of the Code, the Committee
			<lb />
			unanimously agreed that the relevant rules may be
			<lb />
			amended to provide for withdrawal post admission if
			<lb />
			the CoC approves of such action by a voting share of
			<lb />
			ninety per cent. It was specifically discussed that rule
			<lb />
			11 of the National Company Law Tribunal Rules, 2016
			<lb />
			may not be adopted for this aspect of CIRP at this
			<lb />
			stage (as observed by the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court in
			<lb />
			the case of Uttara Foods and Feeds Private Limited v.
			<lb />
			Mona Pharmacem, Civil Appeal No. 18520/2017) and
			<lb />
			even otherwise, as the issue can be specifically
			<lb />
			addressed by amending rule 8 of the CIRP Rules.‖
			<lb />
			51. Before this Section was inserted, this Court, under Article 142,
			<lb />
			was passing orders allowing withdrawal of applications after creditors&apos;
			<lb />
			applications had been admitted by the NCLT or the NCLAT.
			<lb />
			Regulation 30A of the CIRP Regulations states as under:
			<lb />
			-30A. Withdrawal of application.-(1) An application
			<lb />
			for withdrawal under Section 12-A shall be submitted
			<lb />
			to the interim resolution professional or the resolution
			<lb />
			professional, as the case may be, in Form FA of the
			<lb />
			Schedule before issue of invitation for expression of
			<lb />
			interest under Regulation 36A.
			<lb />
			(2) The application in sub-regulation (1) shall be
			<lb />
			accompanied by a bank guarantee towards estimated
			<lb />
			cost incurred for purposes of clauses (c) and (d) of
			<lb />
			Regulation 31 till the date of application.
			<lb />
			(3) The committee shall consider the application made
			<lb />
			under sub-regulation (1) within seven days of its
			<lb />
			constitution or seven days of receipt of the application,
			<lb />
			whichever is later.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			99
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			(4) Where the application is approved by the
			<lb />
			committee with ninety percent voting share, the
			<lb />
			resolution professional shall submit the application
			<lb />
			under sub-regulation (1) to the Adjudicating Authority
			<lb />
			on behalf of the applicant, within three days of such
			<lb />
			approval.
			<lb />
			(5) The Adjudicating Authority may, by order, approve
			<lb />
			the application submitted under sub-regulation (4).‖
			<lb />
			This Court, by its order dated 14.12.2018 in Brilliant Alloys Pvt. Ltd.
			<lb />
			v. Mr. S. Rajagopal &amp; Ors., SLP (Civil) No. 31557/2018, has stated
			<lb />
			that Regulation 30A(1) is not mandatory but is directory for the simple
			<lb />
			reason that on the facts of a given case, an application for withdrawal
			<lb />
			may be allowed in exceptional cases even after issue of invitation for
			<lb />
			expression of interest under Regulation 36A.
			<lb />
			52. It is clear that once the Code gets triggered by admission of a
			<lb />
			creditor&apos;s petition under Sections 7 to 9, the proceeding that is before
			<lb />
			the Adjudicating Authority, being a collective proceeding, is a
			<lb />
			proceeding in rem. Being a proceeding in rem, it is necessary that the
			<lb />
			body which is to oversee the resolution process must be consulted
			<lb />
			before any individual corporate debtor is allowed to settle its claim. A
			<lb />
			question arises as to what is to happen before a committee of creditors
			<lb />
			is constituted (as per the timelines that are specified, a committee of
			<lb />
			creditors can be appointed at any time within 30 days from the date of
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			100
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			appointment of the interim resolution professional). We make it clear
			<lb />
			that at any stage where the committee of creditors is not yet
			<lb />
			constituted, a party can approach the NCLT directly, which Tribunal
			<lb />
			may, in exercise of its inherent powers under Rule 11 of the NCLT
			<lb />
			Rules, 2016, allow or disallow an application for withdrawal or
			<lb />
			settlement. This will be decided after hearing all the concerned parties
			<lb />
			and considering all relevant factors on the facts of each case.
			<lb />
			53. The main thrust against the provision of Section 12A is the fact
			<lb />
			that ninety per cent of the committee of creditors has to allow
			<lb />
			withdrawal. This high threshold has been explained in the ILC Report
			<lb />
			as all financial creditors have to put their heads together to allow such
			<lb />
			withdrawal as, ordinarily, an omnibus settlement involving all creditors
			<lb />
			ought, ideally, to be entered into. This explains why ninety per cent,
			<lb />
			which is substantially all the financial creditors, have to grant their
			<lb />
			approval to an individual withdrawal or settlement. In any case, the
			<lb />
			figure of ninety per cent, in the absence of anything further to show
			<lb />
			that it is arbitrary, must pertain to the domain of legislative policy,
			<lb />
			which has been explained by the Report (supra). Also, it is clear, that
			<lb />
			under Section 60 of the Code, the committee of creditors do not have
			<lb />
			the last word on the subject. If the committee of creditors arbitrarily
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			101
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			rejects a just settlement and/or withdrawal claim, the NCLT, and
			<lb />
			thereafter, the NCLAT can always set aside such decision under
			<lb />
			Section 60 of the Code. For all these reasons, we are of the view that
			<lb />
			Section 12A also passes constitutional muster.
			<lb />
			EVIDENCE PROVIDED BY PRIVATE INFORMATION UTILITIES: ONLY PRIMA FACIE
			<lb />
			EVIDENCE OF DEFAULT
			<lb />
			54. A frontal attack was made by Shri Mukul Rohatgi on the ground
			<lb />
			that private information utilities that have been set up are not governed
			<lb />
			by proper norms. Also, the evidence by way of loan default contained
			<lb />
			in the records of such utility cannot be conclusive evidence of what is
			<lb />
			stated therein. The BLRC Report had stated:
			<lb />
			-Under the present arrangements, considerable time
			<lb />
			can be lost before all parties obtain this information.
			<lb />
			Disputes about these facts can take up years to
			<lb />
			resolve in court…… Hence, the Committee envisions a
			<lb />
			competitive industry of -information utilities‖ who hold
			<lb />
			an array of information about all firms at all times.
			<lb />
			When the IRP commences, within less than a day,
			<lb />
			undisputed and complete information would become
			<lb />
			available to all persons involved in the IRP and thus
			<lb />
			address this source of delay.‖
			<lb />
			55. The setting up of information utilities was preceded by a regime
			<lb />
			of information companies which were referred to as credit information
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			102
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			companies [-CICs‖], as recommended by the Siddiqui Working Group
			<lb />
			in 1999. The Attorney General pointed out, in his written submission,
			<lb />
			that:
			<lb />
			-In 2013, the RBI constituted another Committee under
			<lb />
			the chairmanship of Aditya Puri, MD, HDFC Bank to
			<lb />
			examine reporting formats used by CICs and other
			<lb />
			related issues. The Committee&apos;s report led to the
			<lb />
			standardization of data formats for reporting corporate,
			<lb />
			consumer and MFI data by all credit institutions and
			<lb />
			streamlining the process of data submission by credit
			<lb />
			institutions to CICs. In 2015, all credit institutions were
			<lb />
			directed by RBI to become members of all the CICs
			<lb />
			and submit current and historical data about specified
			<lb />
			borrower to them and to update it regularly.
			<lb />
			The purpose of setting up the above regime of
			<lb />
			information utilities was to reduce information
			<lb />
			asymmetry for improved credit risk assessment and to
			<lb />
			improve recovery processes.
			<lb />
			The setting up of IUs marks a shift in the above
			<lb />
			position as not only is the information with IUs used to
			<lb />
			reduce information asymmetry, but it is also to be
			<lb />
			treated as prima facie evidence of the transaction for
			<lb />
			the purpose of IBC proceedings. This assists in
			<lb />
			improving the timelines for the resolution process.‖
			<lb />
			56. The Information Utilities Regulations, in particular Regulations 20
			<lb />
			and 21, make it clear that on receipt of information of default, an
			<lb />
			information utility shall expeditiously undertake the process of
			<lb />
			authentication and verification of information. Regulations 20 and 21
			<lb />
			read as follows:
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			103
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			-20. Acceptance and receipt of information.-(1) An
			<lb />
			information utility shall accept information submitted by
			<lb />
			a user in Form C of the Schedule.
			<lb />
			(2) On receipt of the information submitted under sub-
			<lb />
			regulation (1), the information utility shall-
			<lb />
			(a) assign a unique identifier to the information,
			<lb />
			including records of debt;
			<lb />
			(b) acknowledge its receipt, and notify the user
			<lb />
			of-
			<lb />
			(i) the unique identifier of the information;
			<lb />
			(ii) the terms and conditions of authentication
			<lb />
			and verification of information; and
			<lb />
			(iii) the manner in which the information may
			<lb />
			be accessed by other parties.
			<lb />
			21. Information of default.-(1) On receipt of
			<lb />
			information of default, an information utility shall
			<lb />
			expeditiously
			<lb />
			undertake
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			processes
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			authentication and verification of the information.
			<lb />
			(2) On completion of the processes of authentication
			<lb />
			and verification under sub-regulation (1), the
			<lb />
			information utility shall communicate the information of
			<lb />
			default, and the status of authentication to registered
			<lb />
			users who are-
			<lb />
			(a) creditors of the debtor who has defaulted;
			<lb />
			(b) parties and sureties, if any, to the debt in
			<lb />
			respect of which the information of default
			<lb />
			has been received.‖
			<lb />
			57. The aforesaid Regulations also make it clear that apart from the
			<lb />
			stringent requirements as to registration of such utility, the moment
			<lb />
			information of default is received, such information has to be
			<lb />
			communicated to all parties and sureties to the debt. Apart from this,
			<lb />
			the utility is to expeditiously undertake the process of authentication
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			104
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			and verification of information, which will include authentication and
			<lb />
			verification from the debtor who has defaulted. This being the case,
			<lb />
			coupled with the fact that such evidence, as has been conceded by the
			<lb />
			learned Attorney General, is only prima facie evidence of default,
			<lb />
			which is rebuttable by the corporate debtor, makes it clear that the
			<lb />
			challenge based on this ground must also fail.
			<lb />
			RESOLUTION PROFESSIONAL HAS NO ADJUDICATORY POWERS.
			<lb />
			58. It is clear from a reading of the Code as well as the Regulations
			<lb />
			that the resolution professional has no adjudicatory powers. Section 18
			<lb />
			of the Code lays down the duties of an interim resolution professional
			<lb />
			as follows:
			<lb />
			-18. Duties of interim resolution professional.-(1)
			<lb />
			The interim resolution professional shall perform the
			<lb />
			following duties, namely-
			<lb />
			(a) collect all information relating to the assets,
			<lb />
			finances and operations of the corporate debtor
			<lb />
			for determining the financial position of the
			<lb />
			corporate debtor, including information relating
			<lb />
			to-
			<lb />
			(i) business operations for the previous two
			<lb />
			years;
			<lb />
			(ii) financial and operational payments for the
			<lb />
			previous two years;
			<lb />
			(iii) list of assets and liabilities as on the
			<lb />
			initiation date; and
			<lb />
			(iv) such other matters as may be specified;
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			105
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			(b) receive and collate all the claims submitted by creditors
			<lb />
			to him, pursuant to the public announcement made under
			<lb />
			Sections 13 and 15;
			<lb />
			(c) constitute a committee of creditors;
			<lb />
			(d) monitor the assets of the corporate debtor and manage
			<lb />
			its operations until a resolution professional is appointed by
			<lb />
			the committee of creditors;
			<lb />
			(e) file information collected with the information utility, if
			<lb />
			necessary; and
			<lb />
			(f) take control and custody of any asset over which the
			<lb />
			corporate debtor has ownership rights as recorded in the
			<lb />
			balance sheet of the corporate debtor, or with information
			<lb />
			utility or the depository of securities or any other registry
			<lb />
			that records the ownership of assets including-
			<lb />
			(i) assets over which the corporate debtor
			<lb />
			has ownership rights which may be located in
			<lb />
			a foreign country;
			<lb />
			(ii) assets that may or may not be in
			<lb />
			possession of the corporate debtor;
			<lb />
			(iii) tangible assets, whether movable or
			<lb />
			immovable;
			<lb />
			(iv) intangible assets including intellectual
			<lb />
			property;
			<lb />
			(v) securities including shares held in any
			<lb />
			subsidiary of the corporate debtor, financial
			<lb />
			instruments, insurance policies;
			<lb />
			(vi) assets subject to the determination of
			<lb />
			ownership by a court or authority;
			<lb />
			(g) to perform such other duties as may be
			<lb />
			specified by the Board.
			<lb />
			Explanation.-For the purposes of this
			<lb />
			section, the term -assets‖ shall not include
			<lb />
			the following, namely-
			<lb />
			(a) assets owned by a third party in
			<lb />
			possession of the corporate debtor held
			<lb />
			under
			<lb />
			trust
			<lb />
			or
			<lb />
			under
			<lb />
			contractual
			<lb />
			arrangements including bailment;
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			106
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			(b) assets of any Indian or foreign subsidiary
			<lb />
			of the corporate debtor; and
			<lb />
			(c) such other assets as may be notified by
			<lb />
			the Central Government in consultation with
			<lb />
			any financial sector regulator.‖
			<lb />
			59. Under the CIRP Regulations, the resolution professional has to
			<lb />
			vet and verify claims made, and ultimately, determine the amount of
			<lb />
			each claim as follows:
			<lb />
			-10. Substantiation of claims.-The interim
			<lb />
			resolution professional or the resolution professional,
			<lb />
			as the case may be, may call for such other evidence
			<lb />
			or clarification as he deems fit from a creditor for
			<lb />
			substantiating the whole or part of its claim.‖
			<lb />
			xxx xxx xxx
			<lb />
			-12. Submission of proof of claims.-(1) Subject to
			<lb />
			sub-regulation (2), a creditor shall submit claim with
			<lb />
			proof on or before the last date mentioned in the public
			<lb />
			announcement.
			<lb />
			(2) A creditor, who fails to submit claim with proof
			<lb />
			within the time stipulated in the public announcement,
			<lb />
			may submit the claim with proof to the interim
			<lb />
			resolution professional or the resolution professional,
			<lb />
			as the case may be, on or before the ninetieth day of
			<lb />
			the insolvency commencement date.
			<lb />
			(3) Where the creditor in sub-regulation (2) is a
			<lb />
			financial creditor under regulation 8, it shall be
			<lb />
			included in the committee from the date of admission
			<lb />
			of such claim:
			<lb />
			Provided that such inclusion shall not affect the
			<lb />
			validity of any decision taken by the committee prior to
			<lb />
			such inclusion.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			107
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			13. Verification of claims.-(1) The interim resolution
			<lb />
			professional or the resolution professional, as the case
			<lb />
			may be, shall verify every claim, as on the insolvency
			<lb />
			commencement date, within seven days from the last
			<lb />
			date of the receipt of the claims, and thereupon
			<lb />
			maintain a list of creditors containing names of
			<lb />
			creditors along with the amount claimed by them, the
			<lb />
			amount of their claims admitted and the security
			<lb />
			interest, if any, in respect of such claims, and update
			<lb />
			it.
			<lb />
			(2) The list of creditors shall be -
			<lb />
			(a) available for inspection by the persons
			<lb />
			who submitted proofs of claim;
			<lb />
			(b) available for inspection by members,
			<lb />
			partners, directors and guarantors of the
			<lb />
			corporate debtor;
			<lb />
			(c) displayed on the website, if any, of the
			<lb />
			corporate debtor;
			<lb />
			(d) filed with the Adjudicating Authority; and
			<lb />
			(e) presented at the first meeting of the
			<lb />
			committee.
			<lb />
			14. Determination of amount of claim.-(1) Where
			<lb />
			the amount claimed by a creditor is not precise due to
			<lb />
			any contingency or other reason, the interim resolution
			<lb />
			professional or the resolution professional, as the case
			<lb />
			may be, shall make the best estimate of the amount of
			<lb />
			the claim based on the information available with him.
			<lb />
			(2) The interim resolution professional or the resolution
			<lb />
			professional, as the case may be, shall revise the
			<lb />
			amounts of claims admitted, including the estimates of
			<lb />
			claims made under sub-regulation (1), as soon as may
			<lb />
			be practicable, when he comes across additional
			<lb />
			information warranting such revision.‖
			<lb />
			It is clear from a reading of these Regulations that the resolution
			<lb />
			professional is given administrative as opposed to quasi-judicial
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			108
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			powers. In fact, even when the resolution professional is to make a
			<lb />
			-determination‖ under Regulation 35A, he is only to apply to the
			<lb />
			Adjudicating Authority for appropriate relief based on the determination
			<lb />
			made as follows:
			<lb />
			-35A. Preferential and other transactions.-(1) On
			<lb />
			or before the seventy-fifth day of the insolvency
			<lb />
			commencement date, the resolution professional shall
			<lb />
			form an opinion whether the corporate debtor has
			<lb />
			been subjected to any transaction covered under
			<lb />
			sections 43, 45, 50 or 66.
			<lb />
			(2) Where the resolution professional is of the opinion
			<lb />
			that the corporate debtor has been subjected to any
			<lb />
			transactions covered under sections 43, 45, 50 or 66,
			<lb />
			he shall make a determination on or before the one
			<lb />
			hundred and fifteenth day of the insolvency
			<lb />
			commencement date, under intimation to the Board.
			<lb />
			(3) Where the resolution professional makes a
			<lb />
			determination under sub-regulation (2), he shall apply
			<lb />
			to the Adjudicating Authority for appropriate relief on or
			<lb />
			before the one hundred and thirty-fifth day of the
			<lb />
			insolvency commencement date.
			<lb />
			60. As opposed to this, the liquidator, in liquidation proceedings
			<lb />
			under the Code, has to consolidate and verify the claims, and either
			<lb />
			admit or reject such claims under Sections 38 to 40 of the Code.
			<lb />
			Sections 41 and 42, by way of contrast between the powers of the
			<lb />
			liquidator and that of the resolution professional, are set out
			<lb />
			hereinbelow:
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			109
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			-41. Determination of valuation of claims.-The
			<lb />
			liquidator shall determine the value of claims admitted
			<lb />
			under Section 40 in such manner as may be specified
			<lb />
			by the Board.
			<lb />
			42. Appeal against the decision of liquidator.-A
			<lb />
			creditor may appeal to the Adjudicating Authority
			<lb />
			against the decision of the liquidator accepting or
			<lb />
			rejecting the claims within fourteen days of the receipt
			<lb />
			of such decision.‖
			<lb />
			It is clear from these Sections that when the liquidator -determines‖ the
			<lb />
			value of claims admitted under Section 40, such determination is a
			<lb />
			-decision‖, which is quasi-judicial in nature, and which can be appealed
			<lb />
			against to the Adjudicating Authority under Section 42 of the Code.
			<lb />
			61. Unlike the liquidator, the resolution professional cannot act in a
			<lb />
			number of matters without the approval of the committee of creditors
			<lb />
			under Section 28 of the Code, which can, by a two-thirds majority,
			<lb />
			replace one resolution professional with another, in case they are
			<lb />
			unhappy with his performance. Thus, the resolution professional is
			<lb />
			really a facilitator of the resolution process, whose administrative
			<lb />
			functions are overseen by the committee of creditors and by the
			<lb />
			Adjudicating Authority.
			<lb />
			CONSTITUTIONAL VALIDITY OF SECTION 29A.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			110
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			62. Section 29A reads as follows:
			<lb />
			-29A. Persons not eligible to be resolution
			<lb />
			applicant.-A person shall not be eligible to submit a
			<lb />
			resolution plan, if such person, or any other person
			<lb />
			acting jointly or in concert with such person-
			<lb />
			(a) is an undischarged insolvent;
			<lb />
			(b) is a wilful defaulter in accordance with the
			<lb />
			guidelines of the Reserve Bank of India issued
			<lb />
			under the Banking Regulation Act, 1949 (10 of
			<lb />
			1949);
			<lb />
			(c) at the time of submission of the resolution plan
			<lb />
			has an account,] or an account of a corporate
			<lb />
			debtor under the management or control of such
			<lb />
			person or of whom such person is a promoter,
			<lb />
			classified as non-performing asset in accordance
			<lb />
			with the guidelines of the Reserve Bank of India
			<lb />
			issued under the Banking Regulation Act, 1949
			<lb />
			(10 of 1949) or the guidelines of a financial sector
			<lb />
			regulator issued under any other law for the time
			<lb />
			being in force, and at least a period of one year
			<lb />
			has lapsed from the date of such classification till
			<lb />
			the date of commencement of the corporate
			<lb />
			insolvency resolution process of the corporate
			<lb />
			debtor:
			<lb />
			Provided that the person shall be eligible to
			<lb />
			submit a resolution plan if such person makes
			<lb />
			payment of all overdue amounts with interest
			<lb />
			thereon and charges relating to non-performing
			<lb />
			asset accounts before submission of resolution
			<lb />
			plan:
			<lb />
			Provided further that nothing in this clause shall
			<lb />
			apply to a resolution applicant where such
			<lb />
			applicant is a financial entity and is not a related
			<lb />
			party to the corporate debtor.
			<lb />
			Explanation I.-For the purposes of this
			<lb />
			proviso, the expression -related party‖ shall not
			<lb />
			include a financial entity, regulated by a financial
			<lb />
			sector regulator, if it is a financial creditor of the
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			111
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			corporate debtor and is a related party of the
			<lb />
			corporate debtor solely on account of conversion
			<lb />
			or substitution of debt into equity shares or
			<lb />
			instruments convertible into equity shares, prior to
			<lb />
			the insolvency commencement date.
			<lb />
			Explanation II.-For the purposes of this
			<lb />
			clause, where a resolution applicant has an
			<lb />
			account, or an account of a corporate debtor
			<lb />
			under the management or control of such person
			<lb />
			or of whom such person is a promoter, classified
			<lb />
			as non-performing asset and such account was
			<lb />
			acquired pursuant to a prior resolution plan
			<lb />
			approved under this Code, then, the provisions of
			<lb />
			this clause shall not apply to such resolution
			<lb />
			applicant for a period of three years from the date
			<lb />
			of approval of such resolution plan by the
			<lb />
			Adjudicating Authority under this Code;
			<lb />
			(d) has been convicted for any offence punishable
			<lb />
			with imprisonment-
			<lb />
			(i) for two years or more under any Act
			<lb />
			specified under the Twelfth Schedule; or
			<lb />
			(ii) for seven years or more under any other
			<lb />
			law for the time being in force:
			<lb />
			Provided that this clause shall not apply to a
			<lb />
			person after the expiry of a period of two years
			<lb />
			from the date of his release from imprisonment:
			<lb />
			Provided further that this clause shall not apply
			<lb />
			in relation to a connected person referred to in
			<lb />
			clause (iii) of Explanation I;
			<lb />
			(e) is disqualified to act as a director under the
			<lb />
			Companies Act, 2013 (18 of 2013):
			<lb />
			Provided that this clause shall not apply in relation
			<lb />
			to a connected person referred to in clause (iii) of
			<lb />
			Explanation I;
			<lb />
			(f) is prohibited by the Securities and Exchange
			<lb />
			Board of India from trading in securities or
			<lb />
			accessing the securities markets;
			<lb />
			(g) has been a promoter or in the management or
			<lb />
			control of a corporate debtor in which a
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			112
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			preferential transaction, undervalued transaction,
			<lb />
			extortionate credit transaction or fraudulent
			<lb />
			transaction has taken place and in respect of
			<lb />
			which an order has been made by the
			<lb />
			Adjudicating Authority under this Code:
			<lb />
			Provided that this clause shall not apply if a
			<lb />
			preferential transaction, undervalued transaction,
			<lb />
			extortionate credit transaction or fraudulent
			<lb />
			transaction has taken place prior to the
			<lb />
			acquisition of the corporate debtor by the
			<lb />
			resolution applicant pursuant to a resolution plan
			<lb />
			approved under this Code or pursuant to a
			<lb />
			scheme or plan approved by a financial sector
			<lb />
			regulator or a court, and such resolution applicant
			<lb />
			has not otherwise contributed to the preferential
			<lb />
			transaction, undervalued transaction, extortionate
			<lb />
			credit transaction or fraudulent transaction;
			<lb />
			(h) has executed a guarantee in favour of a
			<lb />
			creditor in respect of a corporate debtor against
			<lb />
			which an application for insolvency resolution
			<lb />
			made by such creditor has been admitted under
			<lb />
			this Code and such guarantee has been invoked
			<lb />
			by the creditor and remains unpaid in full or part;
			<lb />
			(i) is subject to any disability, corresponding to
			<lb />
			clauses (a) to (h), under any law in a jurisdiction
			<lb />
			outside India; or
			<lb />
			(j) has a connected person not eligible under
			<lb />
			clauses (a) to (i).
			<lb />
			Explanation I.-For the purposes of this clause,
			<lb />
			the expression -connected person‖ means-
			<lb />
			(i) any person who is the promoter or in the
			<lb />
			management or control of the resolution
			<lb />
			applicant; or
			<lb />
			(ii) any person who shall be the promoter or
			<lb />
			in management or control of the business of
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			corporate
			<lb />
			debtor
			<lb />
			during
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			implementation of the resolution plan; or
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			113
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			(iii) the holding company, subsidiary
			<lb />
			company, associate company or related party
			<lb />
			of a person referred to in clauses (i) and (ii):
			<lb />
			Provided that nothing in clause (iii) of
			<lb />
			Explanation I shall apply to a resolution
			<lb />
			applicant where such applicant is a financial
			<lb />
			entity and is not a related party of the
			<lb />
			corporate debtor:
			<lb />
			Provided further that the expression
			<lb />
			-related party‖ shall not include a financial
			<lb />
			entity, regulated by a financial sector
			<lb />
			regulator, if it is a financial creditor of the
			<lb />
			corporate debtor and is a related party of the
			<lb />
			corporate debtor solely on account of
			<lb />
			conversion or substitution of debt into equity
			<lb />
			shares or instruments convertible into equity
			<lb />
			shares,
			<lb />
			prior
			<lb />
			to
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			insolvency
			<lb />
			commencement date;
			<lb />
			Explanation II.-For the purposes of this
			<lb />
			section, -financial entity‖ shall mean the following
			<lb />
			entities which meet such criteria or conditions as
			<lb />
			the Central Government may, in consultation with
			<lb />
			the financial sector regulator, notify in this behalf,
			<lb />
			namely-
			<lb />
			(a) a scheduled bank;
			<lb />
			(b) any entity regulated by a foreign central
			<lb />
			bank or a securities market regulator or other
			<lb />
			financial sector regulator of a jurisdiction
			<lb />
			outside India which jurisdiction is compliant
			<lb />
			with the Financial Action Task Force
			<lb />
			Standards and is a signatory to the
			<lb />
			International Organisation of Securities
			<lb />
			Commissions Multilateral Memorandum of
			<lb />
			Understanding;
			<lb />
			(c) any investment vehicle, registered foreign
			<lb />
			institutional investor, registered foreign
			<lb />
			portfolio investor or a foreign venture capital
			<lb />
			investor, where the terms shall have the
			<lb />
			meaning assigned to them in regulation 2 of
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			114
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			the Foreign Exchange Management (Transfer
			<lb />
			or Issue of Security by a Person Resident
			<lb />
			Outside India) Regulations, 2017 made under
			<lb />
			the Foreign Exchange Management Act,
			<lb />
			1999 (42 of 1999);
			<lb />
			(d) an asset reconstruction company
			<lb />
			registered with the Reserve Bank of India
			<lb />
			under Section 3 of the Securitisation and
			<lb />
			Reconstruction of Financial Assets and
			<lb />
			Enforcement of Security Interest Act, 2002
			<lb />
			(54 of 2002);
			<lb />
			(e) an Alternate Investment Fund registered
			<lb />
			with the Securities and Exchange Board of
			<lb />
			India;
			<lb />
			(f) such categories of persons as may be
			<lb />
			notified by the Central Government.‖
			<lb />
			63. This Section was first introduced by the Insolvency and
			<lb />
			Bankruptcy Code (Amendment) Ordinance, 2017, which amended the
			<lb />
			Insolvency and Bankruptcy Code on 23.11.2017. The Finance Minister
			<lb />
			while moving the Amendment Bill stated as follows:
			<lb />
			-The core and the soul of this new Ordinance is really
			<lb />
			Clause 5, which is Section 29A of the original Bill. I
			<lb />
			may just explain that once a company goes into the
			<lb />
			resolution process, then applications would be invited
			<lb />
			with regard to the potential resolution proposals as far
			<lb />
			as the company is concerned or the enterprise is
			<lb />
			concerned. Now a number of ineligibility clauses were
			<lb />
			not there in the original Act, and, therefore, Clause
			<lb />
			29A introduces those who are not eligible to apply. For
			<lb />
			instance, there is a clause with regard to an
			<lb />
			undischarged insolvent who is not eligible to apply; a
			<lb />
			person who has been disqualified under the
			<lb />
			Companies Act to act as a Director cannot apply; and
			<lb />
			a person who is prohibited under the SEBI Act cannot
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			115
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			apply. So these are statutory disqualifications. And,
			<lb />
			there is also a disqualification in clause (c) with regard
			<lb />
			to those who are corporate debtors and who, as on the
			<lb />
			date of the application making a bid, do not
			<lb />
			operationalize the account by paying the interest itself,
			<lb />
			i.e., you cannot say that I have an NPA. I am not
			<lb />
			making the account operational. The accounts will
			<lb />
			continue to be NPAs and yet I am going to apply for
			<lb />
			this. Effectively, this clause will mean that those, who
			<lb />
			are in management and on account of whom this
			<lb />
			insolvent or the non-performing asset has arisen, will
			<lb />
			now try and say, I do not discharge any of the
			<lb />
			outstanding debts in terms of making the accounts
			<lb />
			operational, and yet I would like to apply and get the
			<lb />
			same enterprise back at a discounted value, for this is
			<lb />
			not the object of this particular Act itself. So clause 5
			<lb />
			has been brought in with that purpose in mind.‖
			<lb />
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
			The Statement of Objects and Reasons for the aforesaid amendment
			<lb />
			states:
			<lb />
			-2. The provisions for insolvency resolution and
			<lb />
			liquidation of a corporate person in the Code did not
			<lb />
			restrict or bar any person from submitting a resolution
			<lb />
			plan or participating in the acquisition process of the
			<lb />
			assets of a company at the time of liquidation.
			<lb />
			Concerns have been raised that persons who, with
			<lb />
			their misconduct contributed to defaults of companies
			<lb />
			or are otherwise undesirable, may misuse this
			<lb />
			situation due to lack of prohibition or restrictions to
			<lb />
			participate in the resolution or liquidation process, and
			<lb />
			gain or regain control of the corporate debtor. This
			<lb />
			may undermine the processes laid down in the Code
			<lb />
			as the unscrupulous person would be seen to be
			<lb />
			rewarded at the expense of creditors. In addition, in
			<lb />
			order to check that the undesirable persons who may
			<lb />
			have submitted their resolution plans in the absence of
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			116
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			such a provision, responsibility is also being entrusted
			<lb />
			on the committee of creditors to give a reasonable
			<lb />
			period to repay overdue amounts and become
			<lb />
			eligible.‖
			<lb />
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
			This Court has held in ArcelorMittal (supra):
			<lb />
			-27. A purposive interpretation of Section 29A,
			<lb />
			depending both on the text and the context in which
			<lb />
			the provision was enacted, must, therefore, inform our
			<lb />
			interpretation of the same. We are concerned in the
			<lb />
			present matter with sub-clauses (c), (f), (i) and (j)
			<lb />
			thereof.
			<lb />
			28. It will be noticed that the opening lines of Section
			<lb />
			29A contained in the Ordinance of 2017 are different
			<lb />
			from the opening lines of Section 29A as contained in
			<lb />
			the Amendment Act of 2017. What is important to note
			<lb />
			is that the phrase -persons acting in concert‖ is
			<lb />
			conspicuous by its absence in the Ordinance of 2017.
			<lb />
			The concepts of -promoter‖, -management‖ and
			<lb />
			-control‖ which were contained in the opening lines of
			<lb />
			Section 29A under the Ordinance have now been
			<lb />
			transferred to sub-clause (c) in the Amendment Act of
			<lb />
			2017. It is, therefore, important to note that the
			<lb />
			Amendment Act of 2017 opens with language which is
			<lb />
			of wider import than that contained in the Ordinance of
			<lb />
			2017, evincing an intention to rope in all persons who
			<lb />
			may be acting in concert with the person submitting a
			<lb />
			resolution plan.
			<lb />
			29. The opening lines of Section 29A of the
			<lb />
			Amendment Act refer to a de facto as opposed to a de
			<lb />
			jure position of the persons mentioned therein. This is
			<lb />
			a typical instance of a -see through provision‖, so that
			<lb />
			one is able to arrive at persons who are actually in
			<lb />
			-control‖, whether jointly, or in concert, with other
			<lb />
			persons. A wooden, literal, interpretation would
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			117
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			obviously not permit a tearing of the corporate veil
			<lb />
			when it comes to the -person‖ whose eligibility is to be
			<lb />
			gone into. However, a purposeful and contextual
			<lb />
			interpretation, such as is the felt necessity of
			<lb />
			interpretation of such a provision as Section 29A,
			<lb />
			alone governs. For example, it is well settled that a
			<lb />
			shareholder is a separate legal entity from the
			<lb />
			company in which he holds shares. This may be true
			<lb />
			generally speaking, but when it comes to a corporate
			<lb />
			vehicle that is set up for the purpose of submission of
			<lb />
			a resolution plan, it is not only permissible but
			<lb />
			imperative for the competent authority to find out as to
			<lb />
			who are the constituent elements that make up such a
			<lb />
			company. In such cases, the principle laid down
			<lb />
			in Salomon v. A Salomon and Co. Ltd. [1897] AC
			<lb />
			22 will not apply. For it is important to discover in such
			<lb />
			cases as to who are the real individuals or entities who
			<lb />
			are acting jointly or in concert, and who have set up
			<lb />
			such a corporate vehicle for the purpose of submission
			<lb />
			of a resolution plan.‖
			<lb />
			Similarly in Chitra Sharma v. Union of India, Writ Petition (Civil) No.
			<lb />
			744 of 2017 [decided on 09.08.2018], this Court observed as follows:
			<lb />
			-31. Parliament has introduced Section 29A into the
			<lb />
			IBC with a specific purpose. The provisions of Section
			<lb />
			29A are intended to ensure that among others,
			<lb />
			persons responsible for insolvency of the corporate
			<lb />
			debtor do not participate in the resolution process......‖
			<lb />
			-32. …… The Court must bear in mind that Section
			<lb />
			29A has been enacted in the larger public interest and
			<lb />
			to facilitate effective corporate governance. Parliament
			<lb />
			rectified a loophole in the Act which allowed a back-
			<lb />
			door entry to erstwhile managements in the CIRP.
			<lb />
			Section 30 of the IBC, as amended, also clarifies that
			<lb />
			a resolution plan of a person who is ineligible under
			<lb />
			Section 29A will not be considered by the CoC……‖
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			118
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			RETROSPECTIVE APPLICATION
			<lb />
			64. It is settled law that a statute is not retrospective merely because
			<lb />
			it affects existing rights; nor is it retrospective merely because a part of
			<lb />
			the requisites for its action is drawn from a time antecedent to its
			<lb />
			passing [See State Bank&apos;s Staff Union (Madras Circle) v. Union of
			<lb />
			India and Ors., (2005) 7 SCC 584 (at paragraph 21)]. In ArcelorMittal
			<lb />
			(supra), this Court has observed that a resolution applicant has no
			<lb />
			vested right for consideration or approval of its resolution plan as
			<lb />
			follows:
			<lb />
			-79. Take the next stage under Section 30. A
			<lb />
			Resolution Professional has presented a resolution
			<lb />
			plan to the committee of creditors for its approval, but
			<lb />
			the committee of creditors does not approve such plan
			<lb />
			after considering its feasibility and viability, as the
			<lb />
			requisite vote of not less than 66% of the voting share
			<lb />
			of the financial creditors is not obtained. As has been
			<lb />
			mentioned hereinabove, the first proviso to Section
			<lb />
			30(4) furnishes the answer, which is that all that can
			<lb />
			happen at this stage is to require the Resolution
			<lb />
			Professional to invite a fresh resolution plan within the
			<lb />
			time limits specified where no other resolution plan is
			<lb />
			available with him. It is clear that at this stage again no
			<lb />
			application before the Adjudicating Authority could be
			<lb />
			entertained as there is no vested right or fundamental
			<lb />
			right in the resolution applicant to have its resolution
			<lb />
			plan approved, and as no adjudication has yet taken
			<lb />
			place.‖
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			119
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			65. This being the case, it is clear that no vested right is taken away
			<lb />
			by application of Section 29A. However, Shri Viswanathan pointed out
			<lb />
			the judgments in Ritesh Agarwal and Anr. v. SEBI and Ors., (2008)
			<lb />
			8 SCC 205 (at paragraph 25), K.S. Paripoornan v. State of Kerala
			<lb />
			and Ors., (1994) 5 SCC 593 (at paragraphs 60-66), Darshan Singh v.
			<lb />
			Ram Pal Singh and Anr., 1992 Supp (1) SCC 191 (at paragraph 35),
			<lb />
			Pyare Lal Sharma v. Managing Director and Ors., (1989) 3 SCC
			<lb />
			448 (at paragraph 21), P.D. Aggarwal and Ors. v. State of U.P. and
			<lb />
			Ors., (1987) 3 SCC 622 (at paragraph 18), and Govind Das and Ors.
			<lb />
			v. Income Tax Officer and Anr., (1976) 1 SCC 906 (at paragraphs 6
			<lb />
			and 11), to argue that if a Section operates on an antecedent set of
			<lb />
			facts, but affects a vested right, it can be held to be retrospective, and
			<lb />
			unless the legislature clearly intends such retrospectivity, the Section
			<lb />
			should not be construed as such. Each of these judgments deals with
			<lb />
			different situations in which penal and other enactments interfere with
			<lb />
			vested rights, as a result of which, they were held to be prospective in
			<lb />
			nature. However, in our judgment in ArcelorMittal (supra), we have
			<lb />
			already held that resolution applicants have no vested right to be
			<lb />
			considered as such in the resolution process. Shri Mukul Rohatgi,
			<lb />
			however, argued that this judgment is distinguishable as no question of
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			120
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			constitutional validity arose in this case, and no issue as to the vested
			<lb />
			right of a promoter fell for consideration. We are of the view that the
			<lb />
			observations made in ArcelorMittal (supra) directly arose on the facts
			<lb />
			of the case in order to oust the Ruias as promoters from the pale of
			<lb />
			consideration of their resolution plan, in which context, this Court held
			<lb />
			they had no vested right to be considered as resolution applicants.
			<lb />
			Accordingly, we follow the aforesaid judgment. Since a resolution
			<lb />
			applicant who applies under Section 29A(c) has no vested right to
			<lb />
			apply for being considered as a resolution applicant, this point is of no
			<lb />
			avail.
			<lb />
			SECTION 29A(C) NOT RESTRICTED TO MALFEASANCE
			<lb />
			66. According to learned counsel for the petitioners, Section 29A(c)
			<lb />
			treats unequals as equals. A good erstwhile manager cannot be
			<lb />
			lumped with a bad erstwhile manager. Where an erstwhile manager is
			<lb />
			not guilty of malfeasance or of acting contrary to the interests of the
			<lb />
			corporate debtor, there is no reason why he should not be permitted to
			<lb />
			take part in the resolution process. After all, say the counsel for the
			<lb />
			petitioners, maximization of value of the assets of the corporate debtor
			<lb />
			is an important objective to be achieved by the Code. Keeping out
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			121
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			good erstwhile managers from the resolution process would go
			<lb />
			contrary to this objective.
			<lb />
			67. This objection by the petitioners was countered by the learned
			<lb />
			Attorney General and Solicitor General, stating that the various clauses
			<lb />
			of Section 29A would show that a person need not be a criminal in
			<lb />
			order to be kept out of the resolution process. For example, under
			<lb />
			Section 29A(a), it is clear that a person may be an undischarged
			<lb />
			insolvent for no fault of his. Equally, under Section 29A(e), a person
			<lb />
			may be disqualified to act as a director under the Companies Act,
			<lb />
			2013, say, where he has not furnished the necessary financial
			<lb />
			statements on time [see Section 164(2)(a) 4 of the Companies Act,
			<lb />
			2013].
			<lb />
			4 -164. Disqualifications for appointment of director.-
			<lb />
			xxx xxx xxx
			<lb />
			(2) No person who is or has been a director of a company which-
			<lb />
			(a) has not filed financial statements or annual returns for any continuous
			<lb />
			period of three financial years; or
			<lb />
			(b) has failed to repay the deposits accepted by it or pay interest thereon or
			<lb />
			to redeem any debentures on the due date or pay interest due thereon or
			<lb />
			pay any dividend declared and such failure to pay or redeem continues for
			<lb />
			one year or more,
			<lb />
			shall be eligible to be re-appointed as a director of that company or appointed in
			<lb />
			other company for a period of five years from the date on which the said company
			<lb />
			fails to do so:
			<lb />
			Provided that where a person is appointed as a director of a company which is in
			<lb />
			default of clause (a) or clause (b), he shall not incur the disqualification for a period
			<lb />
			of six months from the date of his appointment.
			<lb />
			xxx xxx xxx‖
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			122
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			68. The learned counsel for some of the petitioners have also argued
			<lb />
			that the proviso to Section 35(1)(f) that was added by the Insolvency
			<lb />
			and Bankruptcy Code (Amendment) Act, 2017 [dated 19.01.2018] with
			<lb />
			retrospective effect from 23.11.2017 is manifestly arbitrary and
			<lb />
			violative of Article 14 of the Constitution of India. The proviso to
			<lb />
			Section 35(1)(f) reads as follows:
			<lb />
			-35. Powers and duties of liquidator.-(1) Subject to
			<lb />
			the directions of the Adjudicating Authority, the
			<lb />
			liquidator shall have the following powers and duties,
			<lb />
			namely:-
			<lb />
			xxx xxx xxx
			<lb />
			(f) subject to Section 52, to sell the
			<lb />
			immovable and movable property and
			<lb />
			actionable claims of the corporate debtor in
			<lb />
			liquidation by public auction or private
			<lb />
			contract, with power to transfer such property
			<lb />
			to any person or body corporate, or to sell the
			<lb />
			same in parcels in such manner as may be
			<lb />
			specified:
			<lb />
			Provided that the liquidator shall not sell
			<lb />
			the immovable and movable property or
			<lb />
			actionable claims of the corporate debtor in
			<lb />
			liquidation to any person who is not eligible to
			<lb />
			be a resolution applicant.
			<lb />
			xxx xxx xxx‖
			<lb />
			69. According to the learned counsel for the petitioners, when
			<lb />
			immovable and movable property is sold in liquidation, it ought to be
			<lb />
			sold to any person, including persons who are not eligible to be
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			123
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			resolution applicants as, often, it is the erstwhile promoter who alone
			<lb />
			may purchase such properties piecemeal by public auction or by
			<lb />
			private contract. The same rationale that has been provided earlier in
			<lb />
			this judgment will apply to this proviso as well -there is no vested right
			<lb />
			in an erstwhile promoter of a corporate debtor to bid for the immovable
			<lb />
			and movable property of the corporate debtor in liquidation. Further,
			<lb />
			given the categories of persons who are ineligible under Section 29A,
			<lb />
			which includes persons who are malfeasant, or persons who have
			<lb />
			fallen foul of the law in some way, and persons who are unable to pay
			<lb />
			their debts in the grace period allowed, are further, by this proviso,
			<lb />
			interdicted from purchasing assets of the corporate debtor whose
			<lb />
			debts they have either wilfully not paid or have been unable to pay.
			<lb />
			The legislative purpose which permeates Section 29A continues to
			<lb />
			permeate the Section when it applies not merely to resolution
			<lb />
			applicants, but to liquidation also. Consequently, this plea is also
			<lb />
			rejected.
			<lb />
			THE ONE-YEAR PERIOD IN SECTION 29A(C) AND NPAS
			<lb />
			70. It is clear that Section 29A goes to eligibility to submit a
			<lb />
			resolution plan. A wilful defaulter, in accordance with the guidelines of
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			124
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			the RBI, would be a person who though able to pay, does not pay. An
			<lb />
			NPA, on the other hand, refers to the account belonging to a person
			<lb />
			that is declared as such under guidelines issued by the RBI. It is
			<lb />
			important at this juncture to advert to the aforesaid guidelines. The
			<lb />
			RBI&apos;s Master Circular on Prudential Norms on Income Recognition,
			<lb />
			Asset Classification and Provisioning pertaining to Advances dated
			<lb />
			01.07.2015 [-RBI Master Circular‖] consolidates instructions issued
			<lb />
			upto 30.06.2015 on NPAs. Clause 2.1 defines NPAs as under:
			<lb />
			-2. DEFINITIONS
			<lb />
			2.1 Non-performing Assets
			<lb />
			2.1.1 An asset, including a leased asset, becomes
			<lb />
			non-performing when it ceases to generate income
			<lb />
			for the bank.
			<lb />
			2.1.2 A non-performing asset (NPA) is a loan or an
			<lb />
			advance where;
			<lb />
			i.
			<lb />
			interest and/ or instalment of principal
			<lb />
			remain overdue for a period of more than
			<lb />
			90 days in respect of a term loan,
			<lb />
			ii. the account remains ‗out of order&apos; as
			<lb />
			indicated at paragraph 2.2 below, in
			<lb />
			respect of an Overdraft/Cash Credit
			<lb />
			(OD/CC),
			<lb />
			iii. the bill remains overdue for a period of
			<lb />
			more than 90 days in the case of bills
			<lb />
			purchased and discounted,
			<lb />
			iv. the instalment of principal or interest
			<lb />
			thereon remains overdue for two crop
			<lb />
			seasons for short duration crops,
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			125
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			v. the instalment of principal or interest
			<lb />
			thereon remains overdue for one crop
			<lb />
			season for long duration crops,
			<lb />
			vi. the amount of liquidity facility remains
			<lb />
			outstanding for more than 90 days, in
			<lb />
			respect of a securitization transaction
			<lb />
			undertaken in terms of guidelines on
			<lb />
			securitization dated February 1, 2006.
			<lb />
			vii. in respect of derivative transactions, the
			<lb />
			overdue
			<lb />
			receivables
			<lb />
			representing
			<lb />
			positive mark-to-market value of a
			<lb />
			derivative contract, if these remain
			<lb />
			unpaid for a period of 90 days from the
			<lb />
			specified due date for payment.
			<lb />
			2.1.3 In case of interest payments, banks should,
			<lb />
			classify an account as NPA only if the interest due
			<lb />
			and charged during any quarter is not serviced fully
			<lb />
			within 90 days from the end of the quarter.
			<lb />
			2.1.4 In addition, an account may also be classified
			<lb />
			as NPA in terms of paragraph 4.2.4 of this Master
			<lb />
			Circular.‖
			<lb />
			Clause 4 of the RBI Master Circular deals with asset classification as
			<lb />
			follows:
			<lb />
			-4. ASSET CLASSIFICATION
			<lb />
			4.1 Categories of NPAs
			<lb />
			Banks are required to classify non-performing
			<lb />
			assets further into the following three categories
			<lb />
			based on the period for which the asset has
			<lb />
			remained non-performing and the realisability of
			<lb />
			the dues:
			<lb />
			 Substandard Assets
			<lb />
			 Doubtful Assets
			<lb />
			 Loss Assets
			<lb />
			4.1.1 Substandard Assets
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			126
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			With effect from March 31, 2005, a substandard
			<lb />
			asset would be one, which has remained NPA for a
			<lb />
			period less than or equal to 12 months. Such an
			<lb />
			asset will have well defined credit weaknesses that
			<lb />
			jeopardize the liquidation of the debt and are
			<lb />
			characterized by the distinct possibility that the
			<lb />
			banks will sustain some loss, if are not
			<lb />
			corrected.
			<lb />
			4.1.2 Doubtful Assets
			<lb />
			With effect from March 31, 2005, an asset would
			<lb />
			be classified as doubtful if it has remained in the
			<lb />
			substandard category for a period of 12 months. A
			<lb />
			loan classified as doubtful has all the weaknesses
			<lb />
			inherent in assets that were classified as sub-
			<lb />
			standard, with the added characteristic that the
			<lb />
			weaknesses make collection or liquidation in full -
			<lb />
			on the basis of currently known facts, conditions
			<lb />
			and values -highly questionable and improbable.
			<lb />
			4.1.3 Loss Assets
			<lb />
			A loss asset is one where loss has been identified
			<lb />
			by the bank or internal or external auditors or the
			<lb />
			RBI inspection but the amount has not been written
			<lb />
			off wholly. In other words, such an asset is
			<lb />
			considered uncollectible and of such little value
			<lb />
			that its continuance as a bankable asset is not
			<lb />
			warranted although there may be some salvage or
			<lb />
			recovery value.
			<lb />
			xxx xxx xxx‖
			<lb />
			71. What is clear from the aforesaid circular is that accounts are
			<lb />
			declared NPA only if defaults made by a corporate debtor are not
			<lb />
			resolved (for example, interest on and/or instalment of the principal
			<lb />
			remaining overdue for a period of more than 90 days in respect of a
			<lb />
			term loan). Post declaration of such NPA, what is clear is that a
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			127
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			substandard asset would then be NPA which has remained as such for
			<lb />
			a period of twelve months. In short, a person is a defaulter when an
			<lb />
			instalment and/or interest on the principal remains overdue for more
			<lb />
			than three months, after which, account is declared NPA. During the
			<lb />
			period of one year thereafter, since it is now classified as a
			<lb />
			substandard asset, this grace period is given to such person to pay off
			<lb />
			the debt. this grace period, it is clear that such person can bid
			<lb />
			along with other resolution applicants to manage the corporate debtor.
			<lb />
			What is important to bear in mind is also the fact that, prior to this one-
			<lb />
			year-three-month period, banks and financial institutions do not declare
			<lb />
			the accounts of corporate debtors to be NPAs. As a matter of practice,
			<lb />
			they first try and resolve disputes with the corporate debtor, after
			<lb />
			which, the corporate debtor&apos;s account is declared NPA. As a matter of
			<lb />
			legislative policy therefore, quite apart from malfeasance, if a person is
			<lb />
			unable to repay a loan taken, in whole or in part, within this period of
			<lb />
			one year and three months (which, in any case, is after an earlier
			<lb />
			period where the corporate debtor and its financial creditors sit
			<lb />
			together to resolve defaults that continue), it is stated to be ineligible to
			<lb />
			become a resolution applicant. The reason is not far to see. A person
			<lb />
			who cannot service a debt for the aforesaid period is obviously a
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			128
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			person who is ailing itself. The saying of Jesus comes to mind --if the
			<lb />
			blind lead the blind, both shall fall into the ditch.‖ The legislative policy,
			<lb />
			therefore, is that a person who is unable to service its own debt
			<lb />
			beyond the grace period referred to above, is unfit to be eligible to
			<lb />
			become a resolution applicant. This policy cannot be found fault with.
			<lb />
			Neither can the period of one year be found fault with, as this is a
			<lb />
			policy matter decided by the RBI and which emerges from its Master
			<lb />
			Circular, as during this period, an NPA is classified as a substandard
			<lb />
			asset. The ineligibility attaches only after this one year period is over
			<lb />
			as the NPA now gets classified as a doubtful asset.
			<lb />
			72. The Committee set up by the Government to oversee the
			<lb />
			working of the Code has, in its Report of March 2018, also considered
			<lb />
			this aspect of the matter and has opined as follows:
			<lb />
			-14.8 In regards to the disqualification under clause (c)
			<lb />
			for having an NPA account, it was also stated to the
			<lb />
			Committee that the time period for existence of the
			<lb />
			NPA account must be increased from one year to
			<lb />
			three years. The reason provided was that a downturn
			<lb />
			in a typical business cycle was most likely to extend
			<lb />
			over a year. However, in the absence of any concrete
			<lb />
			data, the Committee felt that there is no conclusive
			<lb />
			way to determine what the ideal time period for
			<lb />
			existence of an NPA should be for the disqualification
			<lb />
			to apply. The Committee felt that the Code was a
			<lb />
			relatively new legislation and therefore, it would be
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			129
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			prudent to wait and allow industry experience to
			<lb />
			emerge for a few years before any amendment is
			<lb />
			made to the NPA holding period under section 29A(c).
			<lb />
			In relation to applicability of section 29A(c), the
			<lb />
			Committee also discussed that it must be clarified that
			<lb />
			the disqualification pursuant to section 29A(c) shall be
			<lb />
			applicable if such NPA accounts are held by the
			<lb />
			resolution applicant or its connected persons at the
			<lb />
			time of submission of the resolution plan to the RP.‖
			<lb />
			(emphasis in original)
			<lb />
			RELATED PARTY
			<lb />
			73. A constitutional challenge has been raised against Section 29A(j)
			<lb />
			read with the definition of -related party‖. -Related party‖ is defined in
			<lb />
			the Code as follows:
			<lb />
			-5. Definitions.-In this Part, unless the context
			<lb />
			otherwise requires,-
			<lb />
			xxx xxx xxx
			<lb />
			(24) -related party‖, in relation to a corporate debtor,
			<lb />
			means-
			<lb />
			(a) a director or partner of the corporate debtor or
			<lb />
			a relative of a director or partner of the corporate
			<lb />
			debtor;
			<lb />
			(b) a key managerial personnel of the corporate
			<lb />
			debtor or a relative of a key managerial personnel
			<lb />
			of the corporate debtor;
			<lb />
			(c) a limited liability partnership or a partnership
			<lb />
			firm in which a director, partner, or manager of the
			<lb />
			corporate debtor or his relative is a partner;
			<lb />
			(d) a private company in which a director, partner
			<lb />
			or manager of the corporate debtor is a director
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			130
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			and holds along with his relatives, more than two
			<lb />
			per cent of its share capital;
			<lb />
			(e) a public company in which a director, partner
			<lb />
			or manager of the corporate debtor is a director
			<lb />
			and holds along with relatives, more than two per
			<lb />
			cent of its paid-up share capital;
			<lb />
			(f) anybody corporate whose board of directors,
			<lb />
			managing director or manager, in the ordinary
			<lb />
			course of business, acts on the advice, directions
			<lb />
			or instructions of a director, partner or manager of
			<lb />
			the corporate debtor;
			<lb />
			(g) any limited liability partnership or a partnership
			<lb />
			firm whose partners or employees in the ordinary
			<lb />
			course of business, acts on the advice, directions
			<lb />
			or instructions of a director, partner or manager of
			<lb />
			the corporate debtor;
			<lb />
			(h) any person on whose advice, directions or
			<lb />
			instructions, a director, partner or manager of the
			<lb />
			corporate debtor is accustomed to act;
			<lb />
			(i) a body corporate which is a holding, subsidiary
			<lb />
			or an associate company of the corporate debtor,
			<lb />
			or a subsidiary of a holding company to which the
			<lb />
			corporate debtor is a subsidiary;
			<lb />
			(j) any person who controls more than twenty per
			<lb />
			cent of voting rights in the corporate debtor on
			<lb />
			account of ownership or a voting agreement;
			<lb />
			(k) any person in whom the corporate debtor
			<lb />
			controls more than twenty per cent of voting rights
			<lb />
			on account of ownership or a voting agreement;
			<lb />
			(l) any person who can control the composition of
			<lb />
			the board of directors or corresponding governing
			<lb />
			body of the corporate debtor;
			<lb />
			(m) any person who is associated with the
			<lb />
			corporate debtor on account of-
			<lb />
			(i) participation in policy-making processes of
			<lb />
			the corporate debtor; or
			<lb />
			(ii) having more than two directors in common
			<lb />
			between the corporate debtor and such
			<lb />
			person; or
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			131
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			(iii) interchange of managerial personnel
			<lb />
			between the corporate debtor and such
			<lb />
			person; or
			<lb />
			(iv)
			<lb />
			provision
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			essential
			<lb />
			technical
			<lb />
			information to, or from, the corporate debtor;
			<lb />
			(24A) -related party‖, in relation to an individual,
			<lb />
			means-
			<lb />
			(a) a person who is a relative of the individual or a
			<lb />
			relative of the spouse of the individual;
			<lb />
			(b) a partner of a limited liability partnership, or a
			<lb />
			limited liability partnership or a partnership firm, in
			<lb />
			which the individual is a partner;
			<lb />
			(c) a person who is a trustee of a trust in which
			<lb />
			the beneficiary of the trust includes the individual,
			<lb />
			or the terms of the trust confers a power on the
			<lb />
			trustee which may be exercised for the benefit of
			<lb />
			the individual;
			<lb />
			(d) a private company in which the individual is a
			<lb />
			director and holds along with his relatives, more
			<lb />
			than two per cent. of its share capital;
			<lb />
			(e) a public company in which the individual is a
			<lb />
			director and holds along with relatives, more than
			<lb />
			two per cent. of its paid-up share capital;
			<lb />
			(f) a body corporate whose board of directors,
			<lb />
			managing director or manager, in the ordinary
			<lb />
			course of business, acts on the advice, directions
			<lb />
			or instructions of the individual;
			<lb />
			(g) a limited liability partnership or a partnership
			<lb />
			firm whose partners or employees in the ordinary
			<lb />
			course of business, act on the advice, directions
			<lb />
			or instructions of the individual;
			<lb />
			(h) a person on whose advice, directions or
			<lb />
			instructions, the individual is accustomed to act;
			<lb />
			(i) a company, where the individual or the
			<lb />
			individual along with its related party, own more
			<lb />
			than fifty per cent. of the share capital of the
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			132
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			company or controls the appointment of the board
			<lb />
			of directors of the company.
			<lb />
			Explanation.-For the purposes of this clause,-
			<lb />
			(a) -relative‖, with reference to any person,
			<lb />
			means anyone who is related to another, in the
			<lb />
			following manner, namely-
			<lb />
			(i) members of a Hindu Undivided Family,
			<lb />
			(ii) husband,
			<lb />
			(iii) wife,
			<lb />
			(iv) father,
			<lb />
			(v) mother,
			<lb />
			(vi) son,
			<lb />
			(vii) daughter,
			<lb />
			(viii) son&apos;s daughter and son,
			<lb />
			(ix) daughter&apos;s daughter and son,
			<lb />
			(x) grandson&apos;s daughter and son,
			<lb />
			(xi) granddaughter&apos;s daughter and son,
			<lb />
			(xii) brother,
			<lb />
			(xiii) sister,
			<lb />
			(xiv) brother&apos;s son and daughter,
			<lb />
			(xv) sister&apos;s son and daughter,
			<lb />
			(xvi) father&apos;s father and mother,
			<lb />
			(xvii) mother&apos;s father and mother,
			<lb />
			(xviii) father&apos;s brother and sister,
			<lb />
			(xix) mother&apos;s brother and sister, and
			<lb />
			(b) wherever the relation is that of a son,
			<lb />
			daughter, sister or brother, their spouses shall
			<lb />
			also be included;‖
			<lb />
			74. What is argued by the petitioners is that the mere fact that
			<lb />
			somebody happens to be a relative of an ineligible person cannot be
			<lb />
			good enough to oust such person from becoming a resolution
			<lb />
			applicant, if he is otherwise qualified. We were urged, by Shri
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			133
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			Viswanathan in particular, to apply the doctrine of nexus that is well
			<lb />
			known and that has been applied by this Court in several judgments in
			<lb />
			other legal contexts, more particularly, in Attorney General for India
			<lb />
			and Ors. v. Amratlal Prajivandas and Ors., (1994) 5 SCC 54.
			<lb />
			Paragraph 44 reads as under:
			<lb />
			-44. It is contended by the counsel for the petitioners
			<lb />
			that extending the provisions of SAFEMA to the
			<lb />
			relatives, associates and other ‗holders&apos; is again a
			<lb />
			case of overreaching or of over-breadth, as it may be
			<lb />
			called -a case of excessive regulation. It is submitted
			<lb />
			that the relatives or associates of a person falling
			<lb />
			under clause (a) or clause (b) of Section 2(2) of
			<lb />
			SAFEMA may have acquired properties of their own,
			<lb />
			may be by illegal means but there is no reason why
			<lb />
			those properties be forfeited under SAFEMA just
			<lb />
			because they are related to or are associates of the
			<lb />
			detenu or convict, as the case may be. It is pointed out
			<lb />
			that the definition of ‗relative&apos; in Explanation (2) and of
			<lb />
			‗associates&apos; in Explanation (3) are so wide as to bring
			<lb />
			in a person even distantly related or associated with
			<lb />
			the convict/detenu, within the net of SAFEMA, and
			<lb />
			once he comes within the net, all his illegally acquired
			<lb />
			properties can be forfeited under the Act. In our
			<lb />
			opinion, the said contention is based upon a
			<lb />
			misconception. SAFEMA is directed towards forfeiture
			<lb />
			of -illegally acquired properties‖ of a person falling
			<lb />
			under clause (a) or clause (b) of Section 2(2). The
			<lb />
			relatives and associates are brought in only for the
			<lb />
			purpose of ensuring that the illegally acquired
			<lb />
			properties of the convict or detenu, acquired or kept in
			<lb />
			their names, do not escape the net of the Act. It is a
			<lb />
			well-known fact that persons indulging in illegal
			<lb />
			activities screen the properties acquired from such
			<lb />
			illegal activity in the names of their relatives and
			<lb />
			associates. Sometimes they transfer such properties
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			134
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			to them, may be, with an intent to transfer the
			<lb />
			ownership and title. In fact, it is immaterial how such
			<lb />
			relative or associate holds the properties of
			<lb />
			convict/detenu -whether as a benami or as a mere
			<lb />
			name-lender or as a bona fide transferee for value or
			<lb />
			in any other manner. He cannot claim those properties
			<lb />
			and must surrender them to the State under the Act.
			<lb />
			Since he is a relative or associate, as defined by the
			<lb />
			Act, he cannot put forward any defence once it is
			<lb />
			proved that that property was acquired by the detenu
			<lb />
			-whether in his own name or the name of his
			<lb />
			relatives and associates. It is to counteract the several
			<lb />
			devices that are or may be adopted by persons
			<lb />
			mentioned in clauses (a) and (b) of Section 2(2) that
			<lb />
			their relatives and associates mentioned in clauses (c)
			<lb />
			and (d) of the said sub-section are also brought within
			<lb />
			the purview of the Act. The fact of their holding or
			<lb />
			possessing the properties of convict/detenu furnishes
			<lb />
			the link between the convict/detenu and his relatives
			<lb />
			and associates. Only the properties of the
			<lb />
			convict/detenu are sought to be forfeited, wherever
			<lb />
			they are. The idea is to reach his properties in
			<lb />
			whosoever&apos;s name they are kept or by whosoever they
			<lb />
			are held. The independent properties of relatives and
			<lb />
			friends, which are not traceable to the convict/detenu,
			<lb />
			are not sought to be forfeited nor are they within the
			<lb />
			purview of SAFEMA [ That this was the object of the
			<lb />
			Act is evident from para 4 of the preamble which
			<lb />
			states: -And whereas such persons have in many
			<lb />
			cases been holding the properties acquired by them
			<lb />
			through such gains in the names of their relatives,
			<lb />
			associates and confidants.‖ We are not saying that the
			<lb />
			preamble can be utilized for restricting the scope of the
			<lb />
			Act, we are only referring to it to ascertain the object of
			<lb />
			the enactment and to reassure ourselves that the
			<lb />
			construction placed by us accords with the said
			<lb />
			object.] . We may proceed to explain what we say.
			<lb />
			Clause (c) speaks of a relative of a person referred to
			<lb />
			in clause (a) or clause (b) (which speak of a convict or
			<lb />
			a detenu). Similarly, clause (d) speaks of associates of
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			135
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			such convict or detenu. If we look to Explanation (3)
			<lb />
			which specifies who the associates referred to in
			<lb />
			clause (d) are, the matter becomes clearer.
			<lb />
			‗Associates&apos; means -(i) any individual who had been
			<lb />
			or is residing in the residential premises (including
			<lb />
			outhouses) of such person [‗such person&apos; refers to the
			<lb />
			convict or detenu, as the case may be, referred to in
			<lb />
			clause (a) or clause (b)]; (ii) any individual who had
			<lb />
			been or is managing the affairs or keeping the
			<lb />
			accounts of such convict/detenu; (iii) any association
			<lb />
			of persons, body of individuals, partnership firm or
			<lb />
			private company of which such convict/detenu had
			<lb />
			been or is a member, partner or director; (iv) any
			<lb />
			individual who had been or is a member, partner or
			<lb />
			director of an association of persons, body of
			<lb />
			individuals, partnership firm or private company
			<lb />
			referred to in clause (iii) at any time when such person
			<lb />
			had been or is a member, partner or director of such
			<lb />
			association of persons, body of individuals, partnership
			<lb />
			firm or private company; (v) any person who had been
			<lb />
			or is managing the affairs or keeping the accounts of
			<lb />
			any association of persons, body of individuals,
			<lb />
			partnership firm or private company referred to in
			<lb />
			clause (iii); (vi) the trustee of any trust where (a) the
			<lb />
			trust has been created by such convict/detenu; or (b)
			<lb />
			the value of the assets contributed by such
			<lb />
			convict/detenu to the trust amounts, on the date of
			<lb />
			contribution not less than 20% of the value of the
			<lb />
			assets of the trust on that date; and (vii) where the
			<lb />
			competent authority, for reasons to be recorded in
			<lb />
			writing, considers that any properties of such
			<lb />
			convict/detenu are held on his behalf by any other
			<lb />
			person, such other person. It would thus be clear that
			<lb />
			the connecting link or the nexus, as it may be called, is
			<lb />
			the holding of property or assets of the convict/detenu
			<lb />
			or traceable to such detenu/convict. Section 4 is
			<lb />
			equally relevant in this context. It declares that -as
			<lb />
			from the commencement of this Act, it shall not be
			<lb />
			lawful for any person to whom this Act applies to hold
			<lb />
			any illegally acquired property either by himself or
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			136
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			through any other person on his behalf‖. All such
			<lb />
			property is liable to be forfeited. The language of this
			<lb />
			section is indicative of the ambit of the Act. Clauses (c)
			<lb />
			and (d) in Section 2(2) and the Explanations (2) and
			<lb />
			(3) occurring therein shall have to be construed and
			<lb />
			understood in the light of the overall scheme and
			<lb />
			purpose of the enactment. The idea is to forfeit the
			<lb />
			illegally acquired properties of the convict/detenu
			<lb />
			irrespective of the fact that such properties are held by
			<lb />
			or kept in the name of or screened in the name of any
			<lb />
			relative or associate as defined in the said two
			<lb />
			Explanations. The idea is not to forfeit the independent
			<lb />
			properties of such relatives or associates which they
			<lb />
			may have acquired illegally but only to reach the
			<lb />
			properties of the convict/detenu or properties traceable
			<lb />
			to him, wherever they are, ignoring all the transactions
			<lb />
			with respect to those properties. By way of illustration,
			<lb />
			take a case where a convict/detenu purchases a
			<lb />
			property in the name of his relative or associate -it
			<lb />
			does not matter whether he intends such a person to
			<lb />
			be a mere name-lender or whether he really intends
			<lb />
			that such person shall be the real owner and/or
			<lb />
			possessor thereof -or gifts away or otherwise
			<lb />
			transfers his properties in favour of any of his relatives
			<lb />
			or associates, or purports to sell them to any of his
			<lb />
			relatives or associates -in all such cases, all the said
			<lb />
			transactions will be ignored and the properties forfeited
			<lb />
			unless the convict/detenu or his relative/associate, as
			<lb />
			the case may be, establishes that such property or
			<lb />
			properties are not -illegally acquired properties‖ within
			<lb />
			the meaning of Section 3(c). In this view of the matter,
			<lb />
			there is no basis for the apprehension that the
			<lb />
			independently acquired properties of such relatives
			<lb />
			and associates will also be forfeited even if they are in
			<lb />
			no way connected with the convict/detenu. So far as
			<lb />
			the holders (not being relatives and associates)
			<lb />
			mentioned in Section 2(2)(e) are concerned, they are
			<lb />
			dealt with on a separate footing. If such person proves
			<lb />
			that he is a transferee in good faith for consideration,
			<lb />
			his property -even though purchased from a
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			137
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			convict/detenu -is not liable to be forfeited. It is
			<lb />
			equally necessary to reiterate that the burden of
			<lb />
			establishing that the properties mentioned in the show-
			<lb />
			cause notice issued under Section 6, and which are
			<lb />
			held on that date by a relative or an associate of the
			<lb />
			convict/detenu, are not the illegally acquired properties
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			convict/detenu,
			<lb />
			lies
			<lb />
			upon
			<lb />
			such
			<lb />
			relative/associate. He must establish that the said
			<lb />
			property has not been acquired with the monies or
			<lb />
			assets provided by the detenu/convict or that they in
			<lb />
			fact did not or do not belong to such detenu/convict.
			<lb />
			We do not think that Parliament ever intended to say
			<lb />
			that the properties of all the relatives and associates,
			<lb />
			may be illegally acquired, will be forfeited just because
			<lb />
			they happen to be the relatives or associates of the
			<lb />
			convict/detenu. There ought to be the connecting link
			<lb />
			between those properties and the convict/detenu, the
			<lb />
			burden of disproving which, as mentioned above, is
			<lb />
			upon the relative/associate. In this view of the matter,
			<lb />
			the apprehension and contention of the petitioners in
			<lb />
			this behalf must be held to be based upon a mistaken
			<lb />
			premise. The bringing in of the relatives and
			<lb />
			associates or of the persons mentioned in clause (e) of
			<lb />
			Section 2(2) is thus neither discriminatory nor
			<lb />
			incompetent apart from the protection of Article 31-B.‖
			<lb />
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
			75. We are of the view that persons who act jointly or in concert with
			<lb />
			others are connected with the business activity of the resolution
			<lb />
			applicant. Similarly, all the categories of persons mentioned in Section
			<lb />
			5(24A) show that such persons must be -connected‖ with the
			<lb />
			resolution applicant within the meaning of Section 29A(j). This being
			<lb />
			the case, the said categories of persons who are collectively
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			138
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			mentioned under the caption -relative‖ obviously need to have a
			<lb />
			connection with the business activity of the resolution applicant. In the
			<lb />
			absence of showing that such person is -connected‖ with the business
			<lb />
			of the activity of the resolution applicant, such person cannot possibly
			<lb />
			be disqualified under Section 29A(j). All the categories in Section
			<lb />
			29A(j) deal with persons, natural as well as artificial, who are
			<lb />
			connected with the business activity of the resolution applicant. The
			<lb />
			expression -related party‖, therefore, and -relative‖ contained in the
			<lb />
			definition Sections must be read noscitur a sociis with the categories of
			<lb />
			persons mentioned in Explanation I, and so read, would include only
			<lb />
			persons who are connected with the business activity of the resolution
			<lb />
			applicant.
			<lb />
			76. An argument was also made that the expression -connected
			<lb />
			person‖ in Explanation I, clause (ii) to Section 29A(j) cannot possibly
			<lb />
			refer to a person who may be in management or control of the
			<lb />
			business of the corporate debtor in future. This would be arbitrary as
			<lb />
			the explanation would then apply to an indeterminate person. This
			<lb />
			contention also needs to be repelled as Explanation I seeks to make it
			<lb />
			clear that if a person is otherwise covered as a -connected person‖,
			<lb />
			this provision would also cover a person who is in management or
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			139
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			control of the business of the corporate debtor during the
			<lb />
			implementation of a resolution plan. Therefore, any such person is not
			<lb />
			indeterminate at all, but is a person who is in the saddle of the
			<lb />
			business of the corporate debtor either at an anterior point of time or
			<lb />
			even during implementation of the resolution plan. This disposes of all
			<lb />
			the contentions raising questions as to the constitutional validity of
			<lb />
			Section 29A(j).
			<lb />
			EXEMPTION OF MICRO, SMALL, AND MEDIUM ENTERPRISES FROM SECTION
			<lb />
			29A
			<lb />
			77. The ILC Report of March 2018 found that micro, small, and
			<lb />
			medium enterprises form the foundation of the economy and are key
			<lb />
			drivers
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			employment,
			<lb />
			production,
			<lb />
			economic
			<lb />
			growth,
			<lb />
			entrepreneurship, and financial inclusion.
			<lb />
			78. Section 7 of the Micro, Small and Medium Enterprises
			<lb />
			Development Act, 2006 classifies enterprises depending upon whether
			<lb />
			they manufacture or produce goods, or are engaged in providing and
			<lb />
			rendering services as micro, small, or medium, depending upon certain
			<lb />
			investments made, as follows:
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			140
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			-7.
			<lb />
			Classification
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			enterprises.-(1)
			<lb />
			Notwithstanding anything contained in Section 11-B of
			<lb />
			the Industries (Development and Regulation) Act,
			<lb />
			1951 (65 of 1951), the Central Government may, for
			<lb />
			the purposes of this Act, by notification and having
			<lb />
			regard to the provisions of sub-sections (4) and (5),
			<lb />
			classify any class or classes of enterprises, whether
			<lb />
			proprietorship, Hindu undivided family, associations of
			<lb />
			persons, co-operative society, partnership firm,
			<lb />
			company or undertaking, by whatever name called,-
			<lb />
			(a) in the case of the enterprises engaged in the
			<lb />
			manufacture or production of goods pertaining to
			<lb />
			any industry specified in the First Schedule to the
			<lb />
			Industries (Development and Regulation) Act,
			<lb />
			1951 (65 of 1951), as-
			<lb />
			(i) a micro enterprise, where the investment
			<lb />
			in plant and machinery does not exceed
			<lb />
			twenty-five lakh rupees;
			<lb />
			(ii) a small enterprise, where the investment
			<lb />
			in plant and machinery is more than twenty-
			<lb />
			five lakh rupees but does not exceed five
			<lb />
			crore rupees; or
			<lb />
			(iii) a medium enterprise, where the
			<lb />
			investment in plant and machinery is more
			<lb />
			than five crore rupees but does not exceed
			<lb />
			ten crore rupees;
			<lb />
			(b) in the case of the enterprises engaged in
			<lb />
			providing or rendering of services, as-
			<lb />
			(i) a micro enterprise, where the investment
			<lb />
			in equipment does not exceed ten lakh
			<lb />
			rupees;
			<lb />
			(ii) a small enterprise, where the investment
			<lb />
			in equipment is more than ten lakh rupees
			<lb />
			but does not exceed two crore rupees; or
			<lb />
			(iii) a medium enterprise, where the
			<lb />
			investment in equipment is more than two
			<lb />
			crore rupees but does not exceed five crore
			<lb />
			rupees.
			<lb />
			xxx xxx xxx‖
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			141
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			79. The ILC Report of 2018 exempted these industries from Section
			<lb />
			29A(c) and 29A(h) of the Code, their rationale for doing so being
			<lb />
			contained in paragraph 27.4 of the Report, which reads as follows:
			<lb />
			-27.4 Regarding the first issue, the Code is clear that
			<lb />
			default of INR one lakh or above triggers the right of a
			<lb />
			financial creditor or an operational creditor to file for
			<lb />
			insolvency. Thus, the financial creditor or operational
			<lb />
			creditors of MSMEs may take it to insolvency under
			<lb />
			the Code. However, given that MSMEs are the
			<lb />
			bedrock of the Indian economy, and the intent is not to
			<lb />
			push them into liquidation and affect the livelihood of
			<lb />
			employees and workers of MSMEs, the Committee
			<lb />
			sought it fit to explicitly grant exemptions to corporate
			<lb />
			debtors which are MSMEs by permitting a promoter
			<lb />
			who is not a wilful defaulter, to bid for the MSME in
			<lb />
			insolvency. The rationale for this relaxation is that a
			<lb />
			business of an MSME attracts interest primarily from a
			<lb />
			promoter of an MSME and may not be of interest to
			<lb />
			other resolution applicants.‖
			<lb />
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
			80. Thus, the rationale for excluding such industries from the
			<lb />
			eligibility criteria laid down in Section 29A(c) and 29A(h) is because
			<lb />
			qua such industries, other resolution applicants may not be
			<lb />
			forthcoming, which then will inevitably lead not to resolution, but to
			<lb />
			liquidation. Following upon the Insolvency Law Committee&apos;s Report,
			<lb />
			Section 240A has been inserted in the Code with retrospective effect
			<lb />
			from 06.06.2018 as follows:
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			142
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			-240-A. Application of this Code to micro, small
			<lb />
			and medium enterprises.-(1) Notwithstanding
			<lb />
			anything to the contrary contained in this Code, the
			<lb />
			provisions of clauses (c) and (h) of Section 29A shall
			<lb />
			not apply to the resolution applicant in respect of
			<lb />
			corporate insolvency resolution process of any micro,
			<lb />
			small and medium enterprises.
			<lb />
			(2) Subject to sub-section (1), the Central Government
			<lb />
			may, in the public interest, by notification, direct that
			<lb />
			any of the provisions of this Code shall-
			<lb />
			(a) not apply to micro, small and medium
			<lb />
			enterprises; or
			<lb />
			(b) apply to micro, small and medium
			<lb />
			enterprises, with such modifications as may
			<lb />
			be specified in the notification.
			<lb />
			(3) A draft of every notification proposed to be issued
			<lb />
			under sub-section (2), shall be laid before each House
			<lb />
			of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of
			<lb />
			thirty days which may be comprised in one session or
			<lb />
			in two or more successive sessions.
			<lb />
			(4) If both Houses agree in disapproving the issue of
			<lb />
			notification or both Houses agree in making any
			<lb />
			modification in the notification, the notification shall not
			<lb />
			be issued or shall be issued only in such modified form
			<lb />
			as may be agreed upon by both the Houses, as the
			<lb />
			case may be.
			<lb />
			(5) The period of thirty days referred to in sub-section
			<lb />
			(3) shall not include any period during which the
			<lb />
			House referred to in sub-section (4) is prorogued or
			<lb />
			adjourned for more than four consecutive days.
			<lb />
			(6) Every notification issued under this section shall be
			<lb />
			laid, as soon as may be after it is issued, before each
			<lb />
			House of Parliament.
			<lb />
			Explanation.-For the purposes of this section, the
			<lb />
			expression -micro, small and medium enterprises‖
			<lb />
			means any class or classes of enterprises classified as
			<lb />
			such under sub-section (1) of Section 7 of the Micro,
			<lb />
			Small and Medium Enterprises Development Act, 2006
			<lb />
			(27 of 2006).‖
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			143
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			81. It can thus be seen that when the Code has worked hardship to a
			<lb />
			class of enterprises, the Committee constituted by the Government, in
			<lb />
			overseeing the working of the Code, has been alive to such problems,
			<lb />
			and the Government in turn has followed the recommendations of the
			<lb />
			Committee in enacting Section 240A. This is an important instance of
			<lb />
			how the executive continues to monitor the application of the Code,
			<lb />
			and exempts a class of enterprises from the application of some of its
			<lb />
			provisions in deserving cases. This and other amendments that are
			<lb />
			repeatedly being made to the Code, and to subordinate legislation
			<lb />
			made thereunder, based upon Committee Reports which are looking
			<lb />
			into the working of the Code, would also show that the legislature is
			<lb />
			alive to serious anomalies that arise in the working of the Code and
			<lb />
			steps in to rectify them.
			<lb />
			SECTION 53 OF THE CODE DOES NOT VIOLATE ARTICLE 14.
			<lb />
			82. An argument has been made by counsel appearing on behalf of
			<lb />
			the petitioners that in the event of liquidation, operational creditors will
			<lb />
			never get anything as they rank below all other creditors, including
			<lb />
			other unsecured creditors who happen to be financial creditors. This,
			<lb />
			according to them, would render Section 53 and in particular, Section
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			144
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			53(1)(f) discriminatory and manifestly arbitrary and thus, violative of
			<lb />
			Article 14 of the Constitution of India.
			<lb />
			Section 53(1) reads as follows:
			<lb />
			-53. Distribution of assets.-(1) Notwithstanding
			<lb />
			anything to the contrary contained in any law enacted
			<lb />
			by the Parliament or any State Legislature for the time
			<lb />
			being in force, the proceeds from the sale of the
			<lb />
			liquidation assets shall be distributed in the following
			<lb />
			order of priority and within such period and in such
			<lb />
			manner as may be specified, namely-
			<lb />
			(a) the insolvency resolution process costs and
			<lb />
			the liquidation costs paid in full;
			<lb />
			(b) the following debts which shall rank equally
			<lb />
			between and among the following-
			<lb />
			(i) workmen&apos;s dues for the period of twenty-
			<lb />
			four months preceding the liquidation
			<lb />
			commencement date; and
			<lb />
			(ii) debts owed to a secured creditor in the
			<lb />
			event such secured creditor has relinquished
			<lb />
			security in the manner set out in Section 52;
			<lb />
			(c) wages and any unpaid dues owed to
			<lb />
			employees other than workmen for the period of
			<lb />
			twelve months preceding the liquidation
			<lb />
			commencement date;
			<lb />
			(d) financial debts owed to unsecured creditors;
			<lb />
			(e) the following dues shall rank equally between
			<lb />
			and among the following:-
			<lb />
			(i) any amount due to the Central
			<lb />
			Government and the State Government
			<lb />
			including the amount to be received on
			<lb />
			account of the Consolidated Fund of India
			<lb />
			and the Consolidated Fund of a State, if any,
			<lb />
			in respect of the whole or any part of the
			<lb />
			period of two years preceding the liquidation
			<lb />
			commencement date;
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			145
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			(ii) debts owed to a secured creditor for any
			<lb />
			amount unpaid following the enforcement of
			<lb />
			security interest;
			<lb />
			(f) any remaining debts and dues;
			<lb />
			(g) preference shareholders, if any; and
			<lb />
			(h) equity shareholders or partners, as the case
			<lb />
			may be.
			<lb />
			xxx xxx xxx‖
			<lb />
			83. The BLRC Report, which led to the enactment of the Insolvency
			<lb />
			Code, in dealing with this aspect of the matter, has stated:
			<lb />
			-The Committee has recommended to keep the right of
			<lb />
			the Central and State Government in the distribution
			<lb />
			waterfall in liquidation at a priority below the unsecured
			<lb />
			financial creditors in addition to all kinds of secured
			<lb />
			creditors for promoting the availability of credit and
			<lb />
			developing a market for unsecured financing (including
			<lb />
			the development of bond markets). In the long run, this
			<lb />
			would increase the availability of finance, reduce the
			<lb />
			cost of capital, promote entrepreneurship and lead to
			<lb />
			faster economic growth. The government also will be
			<lb />
			the beneficiary of this process as economic growth will
			<lb />
			increase revenues. Further, efficiency enhancement
			<lb />
			and consequent greater value capture through the
			<lb />
			proposed insolvency regime will bring in additional
			<lb />
			gains to both the economy and the exchequer.‖
			<lb />
			xxx xxx xxx
			<lb />
			-For the remaining creditors who participate in the
			<lb />
			collective action of Liquidation, the Committee debated
			<lb />
			on the waterfall of liabilities that should hold in
			<lb />
			Liquidation in the new Code. Across different
			<lb />
			jurisdictions, the observation is that secured creditors
			<lb />
			have first priority on the realizations, and that these
			<lb />
			are typically paid out net of the costs of insolvency
			<lb />
			resolution and Liquidation. In order to bring the
			<lb />
			practices in India in-line with the global practice, and to
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			146
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			ensure that the objectives of this proposed Code is
			<lb />
			met, the Committee recommends that the waterfall in
			<lb />
			Liquidation should be as follows:
			<lb />
			1. Costs of IRP and liquidation.
			<lb />
			2. Secured creditors and Workmen dues capped
			<lb />
			up to three months from the start of IRP.
			<lb />
			3. Employees capped up to three months.
			<lb />
			4. Dues to unsecured financial creditors, debts
			<lb />
			payable to workmen in respect of the period
			<lb />
			beginning twelve months before the liquidation
			<lb />
			commencement date and ending three months
			<lb />
			before the liquidation commencement date;
			<lb />
			5. Any amount due to the State Government and
			<lb />
			the Central Government in respect of the whole or
			<lb />
			any part of the period of two years before the
			<lb />
			liquidation commencement date; any debts of the
			<lb />
			secured creditor for any amount unpaid following
			<lb />
			the enforcement of security interest
			<lb />
			6. Remaining debt
			<lb />
			7. Surplus to shareholders.‖
			<lb />
			84. It will be seen that the reason for differentiating between financial
			<lb />
			debts, which are secured, and operational debts, which are unsecured,
			<lb />
			is in the relative importance of the two types of debts when it comes to
			<lb />
			the object sought to be achieved by the Insolvency Code. We have
			<lb />
			already seen that repayment of financial debts infuses capital into the
			<lb />
			economy inasmuch as banks and financial institutions are able, with
			<lb />
			the money that has been paid back, to further lend such money to
			<lb />
			other entrepreneurs for their businesses. This rationale creates an
			<lb />
			intelligible differentia between financial debts and operational debts,
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			147
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			which are unsecured, which is directly related to the object sought to
			<lb />
			be achieved by the Code. In any case, workmen&apos;s dues, which are also
			<lb />
			unsecured debts, have traditionally been placed above most other
			<lb />
			debts. Thus, it can be seen that unsecured debts are of various kinds,
			<lb />
			and so long as there is some legitimate interest sought to be protected,
			<lb />
			having relation to the object sought to be achieved by the statute in
			<lb />
			question, Article 14 does not get infracted. For these reasons, the
			<lb />
			challenge to Section 53 of the Code must also fail.
			<lb />
			EPILOGUE
			<lb />
			85. The Insolvency Code is a legislation which deals with economic
			<lb />
			matters and, in the larger sense, deals with the economy of the country
			<lb />
			as a whole. Earlier experiments, as we have seen, in terms of
			<lb />
			legislations having failed, ‗trial&apos; having led to repeated ‗errors&apos;,
			<lb />
			ultimately led to the enactment of the Code. The experiment contained
			<lb />
			in the Code, judged by the generality of its provisions and not by so-
			<lb />
			called crudities and inequities that have been pointed out by the
			<lb />
			petitioners, passes constitutional muster. To stay experimentation in
			<lb />
			things economic is a grave responsibility, and denial of the right to
			<lb />
			experiment is fraught with serious consequences to the nation. We
			<lb />
			have also seen that the working of the Code is being monitored by the
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			148
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			Central Government by Expert Committees that have been set up in
			<lb />
			this behalf. Amendments have been made in the short period in which
			<lb />
			the Code has operated, both to the Code itself as well as to
			<lb />
			subordinate legislation made under it. This process is an ongoing
			<lb />
			process which involves all stakeholders, including the petitioners.
			<lb />
			86. We are happy to note that in the working of the Code, the flow of
			<lb />
			financial resource to the commercial sector in India has increased
			<lb />
			exponentially as a result of financial debts being repaid. Approximately
			<lb />
			3300 cases have been disposed of by the Adjudicating Authority based
			<lb />
			on out-of-court settlements between corporate debtors and creditors
			<lb />
			which themselves involved claims amounting to over INR 1,20,390
			<lb />
			crores. Eighty cases have since been resolved by resolution plans
			<lb />
			being accepted. Of these eighty cases, the liquidation value of sixty-
			<lb />
			three such cases is INR 29,788.07 crores. However, the amount
			<lb />
			realized from the resolution process is in the region of INR 60,000
			<lb />
			crores, which is over 202% of the liquidation value. As a result of this,
			<lb />
			the Reserve Bank of India has come out with figures which reflect
			<lb />
			these results. Thus, credit that has been given by banks and financial
			<lb />
			institutions to the commercial sector (other than food) has jumped up
			<lb />
			from INR 4952.24 crores in 2016-2017, to INR 9161.09 crores in 2017-
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			149
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			2018, and to INR 13195.20 crores for the first six months of 2018-
			<lb />
			2019. Equally, credit flow from non-banks has gone up from INR
			<lb />
			6819.93 crores in 2016-2017, to INR 4718 crores for the first six
			<lb />
			months of 2018-2019. Ultimately, the total flow of resources to the
			<lb />
			commercial sector in India, both bank and non-bank, and domestic and
			<lb />
			foreign (relatable to the non-food sector) has gone up from a total of
			<lb />
			INR 14530.47 crores in 2016-2017, to INR 18469.25 crores in 2017-
			<lb />
			2018, and to INR 18798.20 crores in the first six months of 2018-2019.
			<lb />
			These figures show that the experiment conducted in enacting the
			<lb />
			Code is proving to be largely successful. The defaulter&apos;s paradise is
			<lb />
			lost. In its place, the economy&apos;s rightful position has been regained.
			<lb />
			The result is that all the petitions will now be disposed of in terms of
			<lb />
			this judgment. There will be no order as to costs.
			<lb />
			……………………J.
			<lb />
			(R.F. Nariman)
			<lb />
			……………………J.
			<lb />
			New Delhi
			<lb />
			(Navin Sinha)
			<lb />
			January 25, 2019
		</body>
		<page>
			150
			<lb />
		</page>
	</text>
</tei>
