<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			REPORTABLE
			<lb />
			IN THE SUPREME COURT OF INDIA
			<lb />
			CIVIL APPELLATE JURISDICTION
			<lb />
			CIVIL APPEAL NO. 810 OF 2021
			<lb />
			(ARISING OUT OF SLP(CIVIL) NO.15982 OF 2020
			<lb />
			AMWAY INDIA ENTERPRISES PVT. LTD.
			<lb />
			… APPELLANT
			<lb />
			VERSUS
			<lb />
			RAVINDRANATH RAO SINDHIA &amp; ANR.
			<lb />
			… RESPONDENTS
			<lb />
			J U D G M E N T
			<lb />
			R.F. Nariman, J.
			<lb />
		</front>
		<body>
			1.
			<lb />
			Leave granted.
			<lb />
			2.
			<lb />
			This appeal arises out of a petition filed under Section 11(6) of the
			<lb />
			Arbitration and Conciliation Act, 1996 [&quot;Arbitration Act&quot;] by the
			<lb />
			respondents in the Delhi High Court for appointment of a sole arbitrator.
			<lb />
			The brief facts of the case are noted in the impugned order dated
			<lb />
			03.12.2020 thus:
			<lb />
			&quot;2. The facts of the case, as noted from the petition are, in the
			<lb />
			year 1998, the petitioners were appointed as Distributor for
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			<lb />
			Digitally signed by
			<lb />
			Jayant Kumar Arora
			<lb />
			Date: 2021.03.04
			<lb />
			16:01:48 IST
			<lb />
			Reason:
			<lb />
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			1
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			respondent for undertaking sale, distribution and marketing of
			<lb />
			its products in India and were registered as Amway Business
			<lb />
			Owner (ABO)/ Amway Direct Seller (ADS), in the name of the
			<lb />
			sole proprietorship &apos;Sindhia Enterprises&apos; with ABO No. 141935.
			<lb />
			According to the petitioners, they have set up a vast Line of
			<lb />
			Sponsorship in the respondent Company, and nurtured and
			<lb />
			supported close to 1500 ADSs, who have now set up their own
			<lb />
			networks, and are in the category of Silver/ Gold/ Platinum/
			<lb />
			Sapphire/ Emerald. From 2015, the renewal process for existing
			<lb />
			ADSs became automatic, each year, without payment of any
			<lb />
			fee. The respondent issued a Code of Ethics and Rules of
			<lb />
			Conduct in 2015 to govern the terms of the relationship
			<lb />
			between the respondent and the ADSs. The respondent also
			<lb />
			started promoting registration of Preferred Customers (PCs)
			<lb />
			directly through the respondent&apos;s website, as customers of the
			<lb />
			concerned ADS.
			<lb />
			3. On the requirement of the respondent, necessary documents
			<lb />
			were executed by the petitioners including contract for
			<lb />
			distributorship, setting out the terms and conditions of the
			<lb />
			distributorship, and to inter alia confirm the Code of Ethics and
			<lb />
			Rules of Conduct, Legal Entity Authorisation Form (LEAF) etc.
			<lb />
			Since then, the contract of the petitioners has been renewed
			<lb />
			from time to time. The petitioners recorded client volume/sales
			<lb />
			from their ABO account. The petitioners have also received
			<lb />
			income on the sales generated by them for the months of
			<lb />
			January to March, 2019 by the respondent. However, in April,
			<lb />
			2019, upon logging into the respondent&apos;s website, the
			<lb />
			petitioners noted that they could not access their ABO account,
			<lb />
			or view their LoS. They could only access their account as a
			<lb />
			PC. Accordingly, between April, 2019 and December, 2019, the
			<lb />
			petitioners raised a query with their Major Accounts Manager,
			<lb />
			who informed them that their account had been reclassified as
			<lb />
			a &apos;PC&apos; account, since they have not complied with the criteria of
			<lb />
			are corded re-sale related purchase in the last 12 months. The
			<lb />
			petitioners learnt that this was a criteria in the fresh set of Terms
			<lb />
			and Conditions issued by the respondent in December, 2016,
			<lb />
			which was mandatorily required to be accepted by all ADSs, by
			<lb />
			clicking on the &apos;By clicking here you agree to abide by the new
			<lb />
			Terms &amp; Conditions&apos; button, immediately upon logging in on the
			<lb />
			respondent&apos;s website, to proceed further to their account.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			2
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			<lb />
			According to the petitioner, this requirement was never
			<lb />
			communicated to the petitioners in the past, nor was any notice
			<lb />
			of termination issued by the respondent. This criterion is also in
			<lb />
			violation of the Direct Selling Guidelines dated September 09,
			<lb />
			2016.
			<lb />
			4. The petitioners made repeated requests to restore their ABO
			<lb />
			account. The petitioners attempted to resolve the aforesaid
			<lb />
			disputes and differences amicably by mutual discussions with
			<lb />
			the representatives of the respondent from April till December,
			<lb />
			2019. However, the respondent has failed to consider the
			<lb />
			petitioners&apos; request for restoration of their ADS account. On
			<lb />
			June 26, 2020, the petitioners referred the matter for redressal
			<lb />
			and review to Mr. Jon Sherk, Vice President and Deputy
			<lb />
			General Counsel of Amway Global in January, 2020. The
			<lb />
			petitioners were communicated about the rejection of their
			<lb />
			request for restoration of their ADS account on June 26, 2020.
			<lb />
			According to the petitioners, the respondent has now, with
			<lb />
			effect from July, 2020 notified a new Code of Ethics &amp; Rules of
			<lb />
			Conduct wherein the respondent has now been given benefit of
			<lb />
			a 2 year period for establishing sales, in accordance with the
			<lb />
			DSG, and carved a provision for restoration of the ADS
			<lb />
			account. Accordingly, the petitioners caused issuance of notice
			<lb />
			invoking arbitration dated July 28, 2020 to the respondent
			<lb />
			invoking the arbitration clause, Clause 12 of the Terms and
			<lb />
			Conditions enclosed with the Amway Direct Seller Application
			<lb />
			Form (Form-SA-88-ID), which is reproduced as under:
			<lb />
			&quot;12. Dispute Settlement. The parties shall
			<lb />
			endeavour to settle any dispute or difference arising
			<lb />
			out of or in connection with the Direct Seller
			<lb />
			Contract through mutual discussions within 30 days
			<lb />
			of such dispute arising. The Direct Seller agrees
			<lb />
			that in the event it is not satisfied by any decision of
			<lb />
			Amway, or in the event that any issue raised by the
			<lb />
			Direct Seller has remained unresolved for a period
			<lb />
			of more than two months, and / or during the
			<lb />
			subsistence of this agreement or upon or after its
			<lb />
			termination, any issue or dispute that the Direct
			<lb />
			Seller may have regarding the interpretation or
			<lb />
			operation of the clauses of this arrangement or any
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			3
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			issues arising there from shall be referred to
			<lb />
			Grievance Redressal Committee set up by the
			<lb />
			company. Any dispute, difference or claim
			<lb />
			remaining unresolved post reference to the
			<lb />
			Grievance Redressal committee discussions shall
			<lb />
			be submitted to binding arbitration under the
			<lb />
			provisions of the Indian Arbitration and Conciliation
			<lb />
			Act, 1996. The venue of such arbitration shall be at
			<lb />
			New Delhi and the award of the Arbitrator shall be
			<lb />
			final and binding on all Parties. Subject to the
			<lb />
			above, courts at New Delhi shall alone have
			<lb />
			jurisdiction in relation to the Direct Seller Contract
			<lb />
			and matters connected here to.&quot;
			<lb />
			5. The respondent replied vide letter dated August 20, 2020
			<lb />
			wherein the respondent communicated that the name of the
			<lb />
			Arbitrator as recommended by the petitioners was not
			<lb />
			acceptable by it and sought time to respond with the name of
			<lb />
			another Arbitrator. However, the respondent has till the filing of
			<lb />
			the petition failed to issue any follow up reply further to its reply
			<lb />
			dated August 20, 2020 even after expiry of 30 days&apos; time.&quot;
			<lb />
			3.
			<lb />
			The main plea taken by the learned counsel appearing on behalf of
			<lb />
			the appellant, Amway India Enterprises Pvt. Ltd., in the Delhi High Court
			<lb />
			was that a petition before the High Court is not maintainable as the dispute
			<lb />
			relates to an international commercial arbitration, being covered by Section
			<lb />
			2(1)(f)(i) of the Arbitration Act inasmuch as the respondents are husband
			<lb />
			and wife who are both nationals of and habitually resident in the United
			<lb />
			States of America. This plea was turned down by the impugned judgment
			<lb />
			stating:
			<lb />
			&quot;23. Even the judgment of the Supreme Court in the case of
			<lb />
			TDM Infrastructure (P) Ltd. v. UE Development India (P)
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			4
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			Ltd., (2008) 14 SCC 271 is not applicable in the facts of this
			<lb />
			case, which have been noted above. Rather, the learned
			<lb />
			counsel for the petitioners is justified in relying upon the
			<lb />
			judgment in the case of Larsen &amp; Toubro Ltd. -SCOMI
			<lb />
			Engineering Bhd v. MMRDA, (2019) 2 SCC 271, wherein the
			<lb />
			Supreme Court was concerned with a consortium consisting of
			<lb />
			an Indian company and a foreign company and the Court took
			<lb />
			note of the fact that the office of an unincorporated entity, i.e.
			<lb />
			the consortium, being in Mumbai, as one of the factors for
			<lb />
			arriving at the conclusion that the arbitration proceedings would
			<lb />
			not be international commercial arbitration. No doubt a sole
			<lb />
			proprietorship has no separate legal identity but in the case in
			<lb />
			hand, two individuals, husband and wife, by joining together as
			<lb />
			a proprietorship have taken a single Distributorship. The Code
			<lb />
			of Ethics and Rules of Conduct issued by the respondent under
			<lb />
			Clause 3.17.1 contemplates and recognises that a husband
			<lb />
			and wife shall operate their Distributorship as single entity. The
			<lb />
			proprietorship is an association or body of individuals with
			<lb />
			central management in India.
			<lb />
			24. The plea of Ms. Kumar that the petitioners being individuals
			<lb />
			and habitual residents of USA, the case shall be covered by
			<lb />
			Section 2 (1) (f) (i) of the Act of 1996 is not appealing in view of
			<lb />
			my conclusion in the above paragraph.&quot;
			<lb />
			4.
			<lb />
			It was held that since the central management and control of this
			<lb />
			association or body of individuals is exercised only in India under Section
			<lb />
			2(1)(f)(iii), the dispute is not an international commercial arbitration, as a
			<lb />
			result of which the High Court has jurisdiction under Section 11(6) to
			<lb />
			appoint an arbitrator. Justice Brijesh Sethi, a retired Judge of the Delhi High
			<lb />
			Court was, therefore, appointed as sole arbitrator.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			5
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			Shri Parag Tripathi, learned Senior Advocate appearing on behalf of
			<lb />
			the appellant, has argued that his predecessor&apos;s plea in the High Court was
			<lb />
			incorrectly turned down in that this case is really governed by Section 2(1)
			<lb />
			(f)(i) and not by Section 2(1)(f)(iii). Once it is found that a party to an
			<lb />
			arbitration agreement is an individual who is a national of, or habitually
			<lb />
			resident in, any country other than India, it is not necessary to go to any
			<lb />
			other sub-clauses of Section 2(1)(f), and as it is clear that the respondents,
			<lb />
			who applied to the High Court under Section 11(6), are individuals who are
			<lb />
			nationals of and habitually resident in the USA, would fall under Section
			<lb />
			2(1)(f)(i), the High Court would have no jurisdiction, such petition having to
			<lb />
			be filed only under Section 11(6) read with Section 11(9) to the Supreme
			<lb />
			Court.
			<lb />
			6.
			<lb />
			Ms. Manmeet Arora, learned counsel appearing on behalf of the
			<lb />
			respondents, has supported the judgment under appeal, and has referred
			<lb />
			to various documents which, according to her, make it clear that the
			<lb />
			respondents, husband and wife, would have to be pigeonholed under
			<lb />
			&quot;association or body of individuals&quot; under Section 2(1)(f)(iii) and not under
			<lb />
			Section 2(1)(f)(i).
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			6
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			7.
			<lb />
			The question lies in a very narrow compass. As rightly contended by
			<lb />
			Ms. Arora, the documentary evidence in this case would be decisive of
			<lb />
			whether the requirements of sub-clause (i) to Section 2(1)(f) have been
			<lb />
			met, in which case it is unnecessary to go to sub-clause (iii), as under
			<lb />
			Section 2(1)(f), &quot;at least one of the parties&quot; must fall under sub-clauses (i)
			<lb />
			to (iv) of Section 2(1)(f).
			<lb />
			8.
			<lb />
			In a document entitled &quot;Code of Ethics of Amway Direct Sellers&quot;,
			<lb />
			under &quot;Rules of Conduct&quot;, it is stipulated as follows:
			<lb />
			&quot;2.1.17 Legal Entity Authorisation Form&quot; (LEAF) means the
			<lb />
			document that must, in addition to the Direct Seller Contract, be
			<lb />
			completed by a Direct Seller required to or electing to operate
			<lb />
			an Amway Business in the name of an applicable legal entity.&quot;
			<lb />
			xxx xxx xxx
			<lb />
			&quot;3.1 Application and Starter Guide: In order to be considered
			<lb />
			for an Amway distributorship, an individual(s) must, in
			<lb />
			his/her/their own name(s) or on behalf of a legal entity, submit a
			<lb />
			signed, completed Direct Seller Application(in Form SA-88-ID),
			<lb />
			together with all required supporting documentation.
			<lb />
			A distributorship may be taken up in individual capacity or as a
			<lb />
			sole proprietorship concern, partnership firm or company.
			<lb />
			Amway reserves the right to require that Applicants having Non-
			<lb />
			Resident Indian (NRI), Person of Indian Origin (PIO) or
			<lb />
			Overseas Citizen of India (OCI) status operate distributorships
			<lb />
			via certain types of legal entities.&quot;
			<lb />
			xxx xxx xxx
			<lb />
			&quot;3.14 Legal Entity Distributorships: A Direct Seller may own
			<lb />
			and operate his or her Distributorship as a sole proprietary
			<lb />
			concern or registered partnership firm or limited liability
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			7
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			company (LLC), provided it complies with certain requirements
			<lb />
			and conditions. …&quot;
			<lb />
			xxx xxx xxx
			<lb />
			&quot;3.14.5 The sole business of the legal entity must be the
			<lb />
			operation of an Amway Distributorship. No other business may
			<lb />
			be conducted by such an entity.&quot;
			<lb />
			xxx xxx xxx
			<lb />
			&quot;3.17 Husband and Wife Distributorships: If both husband
			<lb />
			and wife wish to become Direct Sellers, they must be
			<lb />
			sponsored together for a single Distributorship. Husbands and
			<lb />
			wives may not be sponsored in different Lines of Sponsorship.
			<lb />
			Husbands and wives may not sponsor each other. If one
			<lb />
			spouse is already a Direct Seller, the other spouse, upon
			<lb />
			electing to become a Direct Seller, must join the same
			<lb />
			Distributorship as his or her spouse.
			<lb />
			3.17.1 A husband and wife shall operate their Distributorship as
			<lb />
			a single entity. Therefore, each is held accountable for the
			<lb />
			actions of the other so far as the Rules of Conduct are
			<lb />
			concerned regardless of whether a husband or wife is active in
			<lb />
			the distributorship or not.&quot;
			<lb />
			xxx xxx xxx
			<lb />
			&quot;4.13 Franchises and Territories: No Direct Seller shall
			<lb />
			represent to anyone that there are exclusive franchises or
			<lb />
			territories available under the Amway Sales and Marketing
			<lb />
			Plan.
			<lb />
			No Direct Seller shall represent that he or she, or anyone else
			<lb />
			has the authority to grant, sell, assign, or transfer such
			<lb />
			franchises or to assign or designate territories. No Direct Seller
			<lb />
			or Sponsor may state or imply that he or she has a given
			<lb />
			territory, nor that any other Direct Seller is operating outside his
			<lb />
			territory.
			<lb />
			Amway Direct Sellers have no territorial limits. They can
			<lb />
			operate anywhere within India.&quot;
			<lb />
			xxx xxx xxx
			<lb />
			&quot;4.16 Exporting Amway Products: Amway Direct Sellers must
			<lb />
			sell Amway products and/or sponsor prospective Amway Direct
			<lb />
			Sellers within India only. No Direct Seller may export, or
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			8
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			knowingly sell to others who exports, Amway Products from
			<lb />
			India, or from any other country in which Amway has
			<lb />
			established operations, into any country regardless of whether
			<lb />
			or not Amway is doing business in that country.
			<lb />
			For important legal reasons, including trade names and
			<lb />
			trademark protections; local laws on product registration,
			<lb />
			packaging, labelling ingredient content and formulation, product
			<lb />
			liability; customs and tax laws; and literature content or
			<lb />
			language requirements. Amway must limit the resale of Amway
			<lb />
			Products by Direct Sellers to only other Direct Sellers or retail
			<lb />
			customers located within country in which the Direct Seller
			<lb />
			legitimately buys the Amway Products and is authorised to do
			<lb />
			business. The term &quot;products&quot; includes, without limitation, all
			<lb />
			literature, sales aids, and any other items obtained by a Direct
			<lb />
			Seller from Amway or from his sponsor or Platinum.
			<lb />
			4.16.1 Exporting Rule: Personal Use
			<lb />
			Globally, Amway&apos;s Rules and Commercial Principles include
			<lb />
			prohibitions on exporting and importing Amway products from
			<lb />
			one market to another. Amway Direct Sellers may, however,
			<lb />
			take Amway products across borders for personal use, with the
			<lb />
			following limitations:
			<lb />
			 The Amway Direct Seller is visiting another country and
			<lb />
			personally places the product order in that country.
			<lb />
			 The Amway Direct Seller physically picks up/receives the
			<lb />
			products in one country and personally carries the products
			<lb />
			to another country. There may be no couriers, shipping
			<lb />
			companies, or freight forwarders involved.
			<lb />
			 If the Amway Direct Seller has a Multiple Business in the
			<lb />
			country visited, the order cannot be placed as a customer
			<lb />
			order for an overseas customer.
			<lb />
			 The products are for the Amway Direct Sellers personal use
			<lb />
			only.
			<lb />
			 The products may not be resold, distributed, or given away
			<lb />
			under any circumstances.
			<lb />
			 The products ordered must not be available in the Amway
			<lb />
			Direct Seller&apos;s home market.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			9
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			 Durables (e.g. water treatment systems, air treatment
			<lb />
			systems) may not be carried from one market to another
			<lb />
			under any circumstances.
			<lb />
			 The Amway Direct Seller order must not be for more than a
			<lb />
			reasonable amount of product: under 300 USD annually.
			<lb />
			 The personal use exclusion may not be used as a business-
			<lb />
			building strategy.&quot;
			<lb />
			9.
			<lb />
			In what is referred to as the &quot;Legal Entity Authorisation Form&quot;, what
			<lb />
			was filled up was &quot;Legal Entity Authorisation Form: Sole Proprietor&quot;. The
			<lb />
			said form which was filled in by the respondents reads as follows:
			<lb />
			&quot;LEGAL ENTITY AUTHORISATION FORM:
			<lb />
			SOLE PROPRIETORSHIP
			<lb />
			Where an Amway Independent Business (&quot;Amway Business&quot;)
			<lb />
			will be operated in India via a Sole Proprietorship (the &quot;Entity&quot;)
			<lb />
			held by a Resident Indian, Non-Resident Indian (&quot;NRI&quot;), Person
			<lb />
			of Indian Origin (&quot;PIO&quot;) or Overseas Citizen of India (&quot;OCI&quot;), the
			<lb />
			Sole Proprietorship must, through the sole proprietor (the &quot;Sole
			<lb />
			Proprietor&quot;), complete this Legal Entity Authorisation Form for
			<lb />
			Amway Business Owners (the &quot;Entity Agreement&quot;) and submit
			<lb />
			it to Amway India Enterprises Pvt. Ltd. (&quot;AIE&quot;). The Sole
			<lb />
			Proprietor must agree to remain and ensure that the Entity
			<lb />
			remains in full compliance with the Rules of Conduct for Amway
			<lb />
			Business Owners. This Entity Agreement shall become effective
			<lb />
			if and when AlE signs the completed form. This Entity
			<lb />
			Agreement incorporated into and forms an integral part of the
			<lb />
			Amway Distributor Agreement, which includes any and all
			<lb />
			documents incorporated therein (the &quot;ABO Contract&quot;). In the
			<lb />
			event of any conflict, the terms and conditions of this Entity
			<lb />
			Agreement shall prevail.
			<lb />
			xxx xxx xxx
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			10
			<lb />
		</page>
		<page>
			11
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			&quot;5. The Sole Proprietor agrees that :
			<lb />
			A. The sole purpose of the Entity is to own and operate the
			<lb />
			Amway Business identified above, unless AIE expressly allows
			<lb />
			the Entity to own and operate more than one Amway business.
			<lb />
			Neither the Entity nor the Sole Proprietor will own or operate
			<lb />
			any other business or business interest.
			<lb />
			xxx xxx xxx
			<lb />
			C. Any NRI, PIO or OCl investment in the Entity, if and as
			<lb />
			applicable, has been made on a non-repatriatable basis in
			<lb />
			accordance with applicable foreign exchange laws of India.
			<lb />
			xxx xxx xxx
			<lb />
			G. The Entity shall, in accordance with the laws of India and for
			<lb />
			all matters connected to the Amway Business, exclusively use a
			<lb />
			duly authorised Indian rupee bank account which, if applicable,
			<lb />
			operates on a non-repatriatable basis.
			<lb />
			H. The Sole Proprietor shall be responsible for his or her, and
			<lb />
			the Entity&apos;s, compliance with the Amway Rules of Conduct and
			<lb />
			the applicable laws with respect to the operation of the Amway
			<lb />
			Business by the Entity, including foreign exchange laws. Any
			<lb />
			violation of the aforesaid entitles AIE to terminate the ABO
			<lb />
			Contract and the Entity Agreement.
			<lb />
			xxx xxx xxx&quot;
			<lb />
			10. Under &quot;authorised signature&quot;, the entity&apos;s name was filled in as
			<lb />
			Sindhia Enterprises and the proprietor was filled in as Ravindranath Rao
			<lb />
			Sindhia (respondent no. 1 herein). This was done pursuant to an
			<lb />
			application again filed in a printed form, given by the appellant to the
			<lb />
			respondents, which reads as follows:
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			12
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			11. A reading of the application form as filled in, together with the Code of
			<lb />
			Ethics, would show that a distributorship may be taken up either in
			<lb />
			individual capacity, a sole proprietorship concern, partnership firm, or
			<lb />
			company. When it comes to a husband and wife&apos;s distributorship, they are
			<lb />
			entitled not to two, but to a single distributorship, it being made clear under
			<lb />
			clause 3.17 of the Code of Ethics that they are to operate only as a single
			<lb />
			entity. The form that was filled in made it clear that the respondents applied
			<lb />
			to become a distributor as a sole proprietorship, it being made clear that
			<lb />
			the husband, Ravindranath Rao Sindhia, was the sole proprietor / &quot;primary
			<lb />
			applicant&quot;, the wife, Indumathi Sindhia, being a &quot;co-applicant&quot;.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			13
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			12. However, Ms. Arora argued, from a reading of the Code of Ethics and
			<lb />
			correspondence between the parties, that there was no international flavour
			<lb />
			whatsoever to the transaction as the business that is to be conducted can
			<lb />
			be conducted only in India, an exception being made only for personal use
			<lb />
			under clause 4.16.1. Most importantly, the address of the so-called sole
			<lb />
			proprietorship in all the correspondence between the parties was the
			<lb />
			address of the Bangalore office of the sole proprietorship.
			<lb />
			13. Ms. Arora also strongly relied upon the judgment of this Court in
			<lb />
			Larsen &amp; Toubro Ltd.-SCOMI Engineering Bhd v. MMRDA, (2019) 2
			<lb />
			SCC 271. This Court was concerned with an agreement between the
			<lb />
			MMRDA, an Indian company, and a consortium of Larsen and Toubro, an
			<lb />
			Indian company together with Scomi Engineering Bhd, a Malaysian
			<lb />
			company. The argument that was pressed in the appeal before this Court
			<lb />
			was that since a Malaysian company was involved, it would be a body
			<lb />
			corporate which is incorporated in a country other than India, which would
			<lb />
			attract the provisions of Section 2(1)(f)(ii) of the Arbitration Act. This Court
			<lb />
			repelled the aforesaid argument, stating:
			<lb />
			&quot;9. Under the general conditions of contract, the &quot;contractor&quot;, in
			<lb />
			Clause 1.1.2.3 is defined as meaning an individual, firm,
			<lb />
			company, corporation, joint venture or Consortium, whether
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			14
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			incorporated or not. &quot;Bidder&quot; is also defined under Clause
			<lb />
			1.1.2.10 as meaning an individual, firm, company, corporation,
			<lb />
			joint venture or Consortium which could submit a bid. What is
			<lb />
			important to notice is that the contract was signed by the
			<lb />
			employer viz. MMRDA and by the contractor under the head
			<lb />
			sub-clauses (A) and (B) in which L&amp;T India signed as &apos;A&apos; and
			<lb />
			Scomi Engineering Bhd has signed as &apos;B&apos;. When we come to
			<lb />
			the consortium agreement that is entered into between the
			<lb />
			Indian company and the Malaysian company as aforestated, we
			<lb />
			find in the definition clause that &quot;Consortium&quot; shall mean L&amp;T
			<lb />
			and Scomi Engineering Bhd, acting in collaboration, for the
			<lb />
			purpose of this agreement and shall be called &quot;the L&amp;T-SEB&quot;
			<lb />
			Consortium &quot;unincorporated&quot;. The contract is defined in Sub-
			<lb />
			Clause 6 as meaning, &quot;the contract to be entered by the
			<lb />
			Consortium with the employer for the execution of the Project&quot;.
			<lb />
			Under Sub-Clause 7, &quot;the lead Member of the Consortium&quot; or
			<lb />
			&quot;Consortium Leader&quot; shall mean L&amp;T, that is, the Indian
			<lb />
			Company. Under Sub-Clause 8, the &quot;Supervisory Board&quot;
			<lb />
			(hereinafter referred to as &quot;the SB&quot;) shall mean a Board
			<lb />
			constituted under Clause 11 of the GCC. When we come to
			<lb />
			Clause 11.2, it is clear that the Members of this Supervisory
			<lb />
			Board will consist of four members, two appointed by each
			<lb />
			Member. One of the Members nominated by the Consortium
			<lb />
			leader and agreed to by all members shall then act as the
			<lb />
			Chairman of the Supervisory Board, which is, by Clause 11.5,
			<lb />
			to decide on various matters relating to the execution of the
			<lb />
			contract. Clause 21.1(g) provides that the Consortium leader
			<lb />
			shall lead all arbitration proceedings.
			<lb />
			xxx xxx xxx
			<lb />
			11. It is important, at this juncture, to refer to an order made by
			<lb />
			the High Court of Bombay dated 20-10-2016 [L&amp;T
			<lb />
			Ltd. v. MMRDA, 2016 SCC OnLine Bom 13348] which, as has
			<lb />
			been stated earlier, arises between the self-same parties, under
			<lb />
			the same contract. An interim award made by the arbitrators
			<lb />
			qua different claims arising under the same contract had made
			<lb />
			it clear that the claim could be filed only in the name of the
			<lb />
			Consortium and not separately, as was contended by Shri
			<lb />
			Jain&apos;s client. The preliminary issue framed on this count was
			<lb />
			&quot;whether the claimants are entitled to file this claim as Claimant
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			15
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			1 and Claimant 2 or only as the Consortium of L&amp;T and Scomi
			<lb />
			Engineering Bhd?&quot; The High Court of Bombay agreed with the
			<lb />
			interim award of the arbitrators, and held as follows: (L&amp;T Ltd.
			<lb />
			case [L&amp;T Ltd. v. MMRDA, 2016 SCC OnLine Bom 13348] ,
			<lb />
			SCC OnLine Bom para 10)
			<lb />
			&quot;10. Considering the terms and conditions of the
			<lb />
			contract as well as the decision cited by Mr. Ankhad,
			<lb />
			in my opinion, in the facts and circumstances of the
			<lb />
			present case, it is not open for the petitioners to rely
			<lb />
			upon their independent identities while dealing with
			<lb />
			the respondent and that they will have to deal with
			<lb />
			the respondent as a Consortium only. Therefore,
			<lb />
			there is no infirmity in the impugned order. For the
			<lb />
			same reason the present petition as filed would also
			<lb />
			not been maintainable. Hence, the same is
			<lb />
			dismissed.&quot;
			<lb />
			12. Shri Gopal Jain did not dispute the fact that this judgment
			<lb />
			was final inter-partes as no appeal has been preferred.
			<lb />
			Therefore, to stress the fact that it pertains only to &quot;this claim&quot;
			<lb />
			and would therefore, not apply to a different set of claims under
			<lb />
			the arbitration clause is not an argument that appeals to us.
			<lb />
			13. It is clear, as has been held by the judgment [L&amp;T Ltd v.
			<lb />
			MMRDA, 2016 SCC OnLine Bom 13348] of the High Court of
			<lb />
			Bombay, and which is binding inter-partes, that it is not open for
			<lb />
			the petitioner to rely upon their status as independent
			<lb />
			entities while dealing with the respondent and they will have to
			<lb />
			deal with the respondent as a Consortium only.
			<lb />
			14. This being the case, it is clear that the unincorporated
			<lb />
			&quot;association&quot; referred to in Section 2(1)(f)(iii) would be attracted
			<lb />
			on the facts of this case and not Section 2(1)(f)(ii) as the
			<lb />
			Malaysian body cannot be referred to as an independent entity
			<lb />
			following the judgment [L&amp;T Ltd. v. MMRDA, 2016 SCC OnLine
			<lb />
			Bom 13348] of the High Court of Bombay.
			<lb />
			xxx xxx xxx
			<lb />
			18. This being the case, coupled with the fact, as correctly
			<lb />
			argued by Shri Divan, that the Indian company is the lead
			<lb />
			partner, and that the Supervisory Board constituted under the
			<lb />
			consortium agreement makes it clear that the lead partner really
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			16
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			has the determining voice in that it appoints the Chairman of
			<lb />
			the said Board (undoubtedly, with the consent of other
			<lb />
			members); and the fact that the Consortium&apos;s office is in
			<lb />
			Wadala, Mumbai as also that the lead member shall lead the
			<lb />
			arbitration proceedings, would all point to the fact that the
			<lb />
			central management and control of this Consortium appears to
			<lb />
			be exercised in India and not in any foreign nation.&quot;
			<lb />
			14. This case is distinguishable on facts, inasmuch as a final judgment
			<lb />
			between the parties made it clear that it would not be open for the
			<lb />
			consortium to rely upon their status as independent entities while dealing
			<lb />
			with MMRDA. This being the case, the consortium was held to be an
			<lb />
			association of persons falling under Section 2(1)(f)(iii), and that since the
			<lb />
			lead member is to lead arbitral proceedings, the central management and
			<lb />
			control of the consortium being exercised by Larsen and Toubro in India, it
			<lb />
			was held that Section 2(1)(f)(iii) would not be attracted on the facts of that
			<lb />
			case.
			<lb />
			15. By way of contrast, we have seen how the respondents have
			<lb />
			themselves applied to become distributors of Amway products in India as a
			<lb />
			sole proprietorship concern under the relevant forms issued by the
			<lb />
			appellant, read with the Code of Ethics referred to hereinabove. In Ashok
			<lb />
			Transport Agency v. Awadhesh Kumar, (1998) 5 SCC 567, this Court
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			17
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			has clearly held that a sole proprietary concern is equated with the
			<lb />
			proprietor of the business as follows:
			<lb />
			&quot;6. A partnership firm differs from a proprietary concern owned
			<lb />
			by an individual. A partnership is governed by the provisions of
			<lb />
			the Indian Partnership Act, 1932. Though a partnership is not a
			<lb />
			juristic person but Order XXX Rule 1 CPC enables the partners
			<lb />
			of a partnership firm to sue or to be sued in the name of the
			<lb />
			firm. A proprietary concern is only the business name in which
			<lb />
			the proprietor of the business carries on the business. A suit by
			<lb />
			or against a proprietary concern is by or against the proprietor
			<lb />
			of the business. In the event of the death of the proprietor of a
			<lb />
			proprietary concern, it is the legal representatives of the
			<lb />
			proprietor who alone can sue or be sued in respect of the
			<lb />
			dealings of the proprietary business. The provisions of Rule 10
			<lb />
			of Order XXX which make applicable the provisions of Order
			<lb />
			XXX to a proprietary concern, enable the proprietor of a
			<lb />
			proprietary business to be sued in the business names of his
			<lb />
			proprietary concern. The real party who is being sued is the
			<lb />
			proprietor of the said business. The said provision does not
			<lb />
			have the effect of converting the proprietary business into a
			<lb />
			partnership firm. The provisions of Rule 4 of Order XXX have
			<lb />
			no application to such a suit as by virtue of Order XXX Rule 10
			<lb />
			the other provisions of Order XXX are applicable to a suit
			<lb />
			against the proprietor of proprietary business &quot;insofar as the
			<lb />
			nature of such case permits&quot;. This means that only those
			<lb />
			provisions of Order XXX can be made applicable to proprietary
			<lb />
			concern which can be so made applicable keeping in view the
			<lb />
			nature of the case.
			<lb />
			7. In the present case A.C. Basu, Proprietor of Ashok Transport
			<lb />
			Agency, had died before the date of the institution of the suit
			<lb />
			and on the date of the institution of the suit, the proprietary
			<lb />
			concern was not in existence. Only the legal representatives of
			<lb />
			A.C. Basu could be sued with regard to any cause of action
			<lb />
			arising against A.C. Basu in connection with the proprietary
			<lb />
			business. We find it difficult to understand how the provisions of
			<lb />
			Rule 4 Order XXX CPC, could be extended to such a case.&quot;
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			18
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			16. In this view of the matter, the argument that there is no international
			<lb />
			flavour to the transaction between the parties has no legs to stand on.
			<lb />
			Indeed, an analysis of Section 2(1)(f) would show that whatever be the
			<lb />
			transaction between the parties, if it happens to be entered into between
			<lb />
			persons, at least one of whom is either a foreign national, or habitually
			<lb />
			resident in, any country other than India; or by a body corporate which is
			<lb />
			incorporated in any country other than India; or by the Government of a
			<lb />
			foreign country, the arbitration becomes an international commercial
			<lb />
			arbitration notwithstanding the fact that the individual, body corporate, or
			<lb />
			government of a foreign country referred to in Section 2(1)(f) carry on
			<lb />
			business in India through a business office in India. This being the case, it
			<lb />
			is clear that the Delhi High Court had no jurisdiction to appoint an arbitrator
			<lb />
			in the facts of this case.
			<lb />
			17. Ms. Arora made an impassioned plea to this Court to use its power
			<lb />
			under Article 142 of the Constitution to straightaway appoint an arbitrator,
			<lb />
			now that the matter is before this Court. We are afraid we cannot
			<lb />
			countenance such a suggestion as the respondents would have to now
			<lb />
			follow the drill of Section 11(6) read with Section 11(9) of the Arbitration
			<lb />
			Act.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			19
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			18. The appeal is allowed, and the judgment under appeal is set aside.
			<lb />
			…………………………J.
			<lb />
			(R.F. Nariman)
			<lb />
			…………………………J.
			<lb />
			(B.R. Gavai)
			<lb />
			New Delhi;
			<lb />
			March 04, 2021.
			<lb />
			20
		</body>
		<page>
			20
			<lb />
		</page>
	</text>
</tei>
