<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			THE HIGH COURT OF DELHI AT NEW DELHI
			<lb />
			Judgment delivered on : 03.07.2007
			<lb />
			CRL.REV.P.255/2000
			<lb />
			SMT SARASWATI AND OTHERS Petitioners
			<lb />
			- versus -
			<lb />
			SHRI SHIV SHANKAR AND OTHERS ...Respondent
			<lb />
			Advocates who appeared in this case:
			<lb />
			For the Petitioners : Mr K.S. Bindra, Sr Advocate with
			<lb />
			Mr Manjeet Singh Ahluwalia.
			<lb />
			For the Respondents : Mr Mohit Mathur.
			<lb />
			CORAM:-
			<lb />
			HONBLE MR JUSTICE BADAR DURREZ AHMED
			<lb />
			<lb />
			CORAM:-
			<lb />
			HON&apos;BLE MR JUSTICE BADAR DURREZ AHMED
			<lb />
			1. Whether Reporters of local papers may be allowed
			<lb />
			to see the judgment? Yes
			<lb />
			2. To be referred to the Reporter or not? Yes
			<lb />
			3. Whether the judgment should be reported in Digest? Yes
			<lb />
			BADAR DURREZ AHMED, J
			<lb />
		</front>
		<body>
			1. This criminal revision petition has been filed on behalf of the
			<lb />
			complainant party against an order of acquittal passed by the learned
			<lb />
			Additional Sessions Judge, Delhi on 01.04.2000. The State has chosen not to
			<lb />
			file an appeal against the said order of acquittal. By virtue of the impugned
			<lb />
			judgment and order dated 01.04.2000 all the accused – Shiv Shankar,
			<lb />
			Virender, Narender, Ashok Kumar and Satya Prakash (Respondent Nos 1 to 5
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			page 1 of 11
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="footnote">
			CRL.REV.P. 255/2000
		</note>
		<body>
			herein) were acquitted, after giving them the benefit of doubt, in respect of the
			<lb />
			offences punishable under Sections 308 / 452 / 506 / 323 /325 /34 IPC arising
			<lb />
			out of FIR No.298/92 registered at Police Station Narela.
			<lb />
			2. As per the challan filed in the case, on 03.11.1992 the statement
			<lb />
			of Smt Saraswati (petitioner No.1 herein) was recorded to the effect that she
			<lb />
			resided at 1573, Pana Maumpur, Delhi with her parents and was a student of
			<lb />
			class XII. That on that date at about 4.20 p.m. she was present at her said
			<lb />
			house when her neighbours Shiv Shankar, Virender and Ashok Kumar entered
			<lb />
			the house and started beating her. It was further stated that they dragged her
			<lb />
			out of the house and that her mother Smt Omwati (petitioner No.3 herein) and
			<lb />
			her aunt Smt Krishna (petitioner No.4 herein) came to her rescue. In the
			<lb />
			meanwhile, Narender arrived at the scene with iron rods, jelli, sword and lathi
			<lb />
			and handed the same to the others who used the same to assault the three
			<lb />
			women. It was also stated that when her father Surat Singh (petitioner No.2
			<lb />
			herein) returned from duty, Shiv Shankar exhorted the others that he should
			<lb />
			also be killed and that he would manage the affairs. On such exhortation all
			<lb />
			the accused persons started beating Surat Singh as well. It was stated that
			<lb />
			Surat Singh received serious head injuries and fell down on the ground and
			<lb />
			that he also received injuries on his entire body. It was also stated that Smt
			<lb />
			Krishna also received head injuries. Smt Omwati was also stated to have
			<lb />
			received injuries. It was mentioned that the assailants had caused injuries due
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			CRL.REV.P. 255/2000
		</note>
		<page>
			page 2 of 11
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			to old enmity and that after assaulting and beating the members of the
			<lb />
			complainant party, the accused left the scene and Shiv Shankar proclaimed
			<lb />
			that this was sufficient for the time being and that they would kill the entire
			<lb />
			family in future. On the basis of this statement of Smt Saraswati, the police
			<lb />
			registered the case. Since the offence of Section 308 IPC was also involved,
			<lb />
			the case was committed for trial to the court of Sessions. Charges had been
			<lb />
			framed against the accused under Sections 452/308/323/325/506/34 IPC.
			<lb />
			Since the accused pleaded not guilty, the matter went up for trial. 15
			<lb />
			prosecution witnesses were examined. The witnesses of importance were
			<lb />
			PW3 (Saraswati), PW4 (Surat Singh), PW5 (Omwati) and PW6 (Krishna).
			<lb />
			All of whom were members of the complainant party. PW7 Ram Chander
			<lb />
			deposed about the arrest of the accused persons as also with regard to the
			<lb />
			preparation of the site plan. PW13 Dr Ashok Tyagi and PW15 Dr Anil Sahni
			<lb />
			deposed with regard to the MLC of Omwati.
			<lb />
			3. The learned Additional Sessions Judge discussed the evidence of
			<lb />
			all the witnesses and came to the conclusion that the prosecution was unable
			<lb />
			to prove its case. It gave the benefit of doubt to the accused and acquitted
			<lb />
			them of all the charges.
			<lb />
			4. The learned counsel for the petitioners pointed out that the trial
			<lb />
			court did not return any finding with regard to the offences punishable under
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			CRL.REV.P. 255/2000
		</note>
		<page>
			page 3 of 11
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			Sections 308 and 506 IPC. With regard to the offences punishable under
			<lb />
			Sections 323/325 IPC, the learned counsel appearing on behalf of the
			<lb />
			petitioners submitted that the trial court completely misdirected itself in
			<lb />
			holding that, firstly, the injuries were simple and not grevious and secondly, in
			<lb />
			coming to the conclusion that since only an offence punishable under Section
			<lb />
			323 IPC was involved, the same being non-cognizable, the investigation
			<lb />
			conducted by the police without obtaining an order from the Magistrate was
			<lb />
			illegal and, therefore, the accused could not be convicted for the offence under
			<lb />
			Section 323 IPC. The exact manner in which the trial court considered this
			<lb />
			issue is as under:
			<lb />
			“The doctors had opined the injuries received by Surat
			<lb />
			Singh, Saraswati and Krishna to be simple caused by blunt
			<lb />
			object which makes out only the offence under sec.323
			<lb />
			IPC which is a non-cognizable offence. It is settled law
			<lb />
			that the police will have to obtain an order from the
			<lb />
			concerned Metropolitan Magistrate under Section.155(2)
			<lb />
			Cr.P.C. and in the absence of such order, the
			<lb />
			investigation, if any, conducted by the police in respect of
			<lb />
			that offence is illegal. In the present case, the police has
			<lb />
			not obtained any such order from the Magistrate. As such
			<lb />
			the investigation conducted by the police in respect of an
			<lb />
			offence punishable under Sec.323 IPC, anon-cognizable
			<lb />
			offence, is illegal and as such accused persons cannot be
			<lb />
			convicted for the offence under Sec.323 IPC.”
			<lb />
			5. It was contended by the learned counsel for the petitioners that
			<lb />
			this is clearly contrary to the provisions of Section 155(4) of the Code of
			<lb />
			Criminal Procedure, 1973 which reads as under:
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			CRL.REV.P. 255/2000
		</note>
		<page>
			page 4 of 11
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			“155 (4) Where a case relates to two or more offences of
			<lb />
			which at least one is cognizable, the case shall be deemed
			<lb />
			to be a cognizable case, notwithstanding that the other
			<lb />
			offences are non-cognizable.”
			<lb />
			6. Since there were other offences other than Section 323 and the
			<lb />
			other offences were cognizable, by virtue of Section 155(4) of the Code of
			<lb />
			Criminal Procedure, 1973, the case was deemed to be cognizable case.
			<lb />
			Therefore, according to the learned counsel for the petitioners the
			<lb />
			investigation conducted by the police could not have been held to be illegal.
			<lb />
			Consequently, it was submitted that the accused could not have been acquitted
			<lb />
			under Section 323 IPC merely on this ground.
			<lb />
			7. It was also contended on behalf of the learned counsel for the
			<lb />
			petitioners that the trial court completely ignored Exhibit PW13/B (MLC of
			<lb />
			Omwati) which was in the handwriting of Dr. Ashok Tyagi (PW13) which
			<lb />
			indicated that the nature of injury on Smt Omwati was grevious. In the
			<lb />
			presence of such a recording on the MLC in the hand writing of PW13
			<lb />
			himself, it could not have been held by the trial court that no grevious injury
			<lb />
			was caused. The learned counsel for the petitioners also contended that there
			<lb />
			was also no finding with regard to the offence under Section 452 IPC.
			<lb />
			8. The learned counsel appearing on behalf of the respondents
			<lb />
			advanced submissions in support of the impugned order passed by the trial
			<lb />
			court.
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			CRL.REV.P. 255/2000
		</note>
		<page>
			page 5 of 11
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			9. With regard to the submission that there is no finding in respect of
			<lb />
			Section 452 IPC, I find that this is not correct. The trial court has specifically
			<lb />
			examined this issue with regard to the question of place of occurrence. In this
			<lb />
			context, the trial court examined the deposition of PW8 (Chander Singh) as
			<lb />
			well as PW7 (Ram Chander). According to the testimony of PW8 (Chander
			<lb />
			Singh), the place of occurrence was near the Chowk Chauda and not in the
			<lb />
			house of the complainant. The trial court observed that even PW3 Saraswati
			<lb />
			had admitted in her cross-examination that the incident had taken place in
			<lb />
			Chowk Chauda in front of her house. It is on the basis of this, that the trial
			<lb />
			court concluded that this proves that the accused persons had not tresspassed
			<lb />
			into the house of the complainant as alleged and, therefore, there could be no
			<lb />
			conviction of the accused persons for the offence punishable under Section
			<lb />
			452 IPC. This is a clear finding recorded by the trial court negating
			<lb />
			conviction under Section 452 IPC. In this context, the trial court also noted
			<lb />
			that the site plan had been prepared at the instance of the PW7 (Ram Chander)
			<lb />
			who was not even present on the spot at the time of the incident as admitted by
			<lb />
			him in his deposition. Consequently, the trial court, and in my view, correctly
			<lb />
			held that this fact creates a serious dent in the prosecution case and makes the
			<lb />
			site plan doubtful.
			<lb />
			10. With regard to the submission that the trial court had erred in
			<lb />
			recording that the investigation was illegal, I am of the view that the learned
			<lb />
			counsel for the petitioners is right. At the time when the police was
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			CRL.REV.P. 255/2000
		</note>
		<page>
			page 6 of 11
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			confronted with the case, the alleged offences included cognizable as well as
			<lb />
			non-cognizable offences. That being the case, Section 155(4) of the Code of
			<lb />
			Criminal Procedure, 1973 would be applicable and the entire case would have
			<lb />
			to be deemed to be cognizable one. In such eventuality it was open to the
			<lb />
			police to investigate without obtaining any order from a Magistrate.
			<lb />
			Consequently, the trial court was in error in holding that the investigation
			<lb />
			conducted by the police in respect of the offence under section 323 IPC was
			<lb />
			illegal.
			<lb />
			11. Having so held, does it mean that the order of acquittal has to be
			<lb />
			set aside and re-trial has to be ordered?
			<lb />
			12. Before I examine this question, it would be relevant to also
			<lb />
			consider the related question that no specific findings have been returned with
			<lb />
			respect to the offences under Sections 308/506 IPC. I find that while there is
			<lb />
			no specific discussion of these offences there is a general discussion
			<lb />
			throughout the impugned judgment with regard to the incident itself. The
			<lb />
			conclusion arrived at by the trial court is that there was great doubt as to
			<lb />
			whether the incident occurred at all and as to whether the accused persons
			<lb />
			were involved in the same. The trial court took note of the fact that the first
			<lb />
			call that had been received by the police about an alleged incident was in
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			CRL.REV.P. 255/2000
		</note>
		<page>
			page 7 of 11
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			respect of a quarrel amongst ladies as indicated by PW9 Lady H.C. Sheela. It
			<lb />
			is in this context that the trial court observed :-
			<lb />
			“It is surprising that inspite of the admitted fact that the
			<lb />
			quarrel was going on between the ladyfolk not a single
			<lb />
			lady is an accused in the present case.”
			<lb />
			13. Apart from this, the trial court also observed that the presence of
			<lb />
			Virender and Ashok Kumar at the scene was also doubtful if not entirely ruled
			<lb />
			out because of their presence at their respective places of work. In sum, it
			<lb />
			could be said that the trial court acquitted the accused on the basis of (i) the
			<lb />
			place of occurrence being uncertain; (ii) injuries being simple, therefore, the
			<lb />
			investigation was bad (this aspect has already been discussed above); (iii)
			<lb />
			accused Virender and Ashok Kumar were not present on the scene and were
			<lb />
			on duty; (iv) there were serious contradictions in the depositions of the
			<lb />
			prosecution witnesses; (v) it had been alleged that a group of people had
			<lb />
			gathered at the time of the incident but not a single independent public witness
			<lb />
			had been examined and all the witnesses of the incident were interested
			<lb />
			witnesses; (vi) the weapons allegedly used did not match the injuries; (vii)
			<lb />
			there was previous enmity between the complainant party and the accused;
			<lb />
			and (viii) there was great delay in the recording of the statements of the
			<lb />
			injured.
			<lb />
			CRL.R
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			CRL.REV.P. 255/2000
		</note>
		<page>
			page 8 of 11
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			14. For all these reasons, the trial court came to the conclusion that
			<lb />
			there was enough doubt to acquit the accused. It is clear that the powers of
			<lb />
			the High Court in exercise of its revisional jurisdiction in respect of a revision
			<lb />
			petition filed by a private party against an order of acquittal is very limited.
			<lb />
			The revisional court does not function as a court of appeal and cannot
			<lb />
			reappraise evidence. It cannot also interfere with an order of acquittal unless
			<lb />
			it is an exceptional case of some procedural irregularity or overlooking of
			<lb />
			material evidence or misreading of the same which is manifest and which
			<lb />
			results in flagrant miscarriage of justice. These principles are well settled by
			<lb />
			the Supreme court in various decisions starting from D Stephens v Nosibolla :
			<lb />
			AIR 1951 SC 196. The other decisions being K Chinnaswamy Reddy v State
			<lb />
			of Andhra Pradesh &amp; Another : AIR 1962 SC 1788; Mahendra Pratap
			<lb />
			Singh v Sarju Singh : (1968) 2 SCR 287; Ramu v Jagannath : 1995 SCC
			<lb />
			(Cri) 181; Vimal Singh v Khuman Singh &amp; another : 1998 SCC (CRI) 1574
			<lb />
			; Hydru v State of Kerala : (2004) 13 SCC 374.
			<lb />
			15. Keeping these principles in mind, this court has to consider as to
			<lb />
			whether the incorrect findings of the trial court to the effect that the police
			<lb />
			investigation was illegal would call for interference with the impugned order.
			<lb />
			It must be remembered that the well settled principles are that not only must
			<lb />
			there be manifest illegality or glaring defect in the procedure but there must
			<lb />
			also have been a flagrant miscarriage of justice. I have examined this matter
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			CRL.REV.P. 255/2000
		</note>
		<page>
			page 9 of 11
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			in great detail and have considered all aspects particularly as some findings of
			<lb />
			the trial court are not correct as already pointed out above. If it is assumed
			<lb />
			that the police investigation was legal, which it was, then clearly the offence
			<lb />
			under Section 323 IPC ought to have been discussed by the trial court. That
			<lb />
			was not done. But the trial court discussed in general as to whether the
			<lb />
			accused were at all involved in the incident. The trial court came to the
			<lb />
			conclusion that the PWs 3 to 6 were not entirely reliable as they were
			<lb />
			interested witnesses. There was admitted previous enmity between two
			<lb />
			groups. The trial court also came to the conclusion that the place of
			<lb />
			occurrence itself was indeterminate. The trial court also concluded that
			<lb />
			Virender and Ashok Kumar could not have been present on the scene at the
			<lb />
			time of the alleged incident. The delay with regard to the recording of the
			<lb />
			statements of the injured was also considered as a material factor by the trial
			<lb />
			court in concluding that there was doubt as to whether the accused were at all
			<lb />
			involved in the incident. So, although it may be established that this was not a
			<lb />
			case of merely simple injuries but also of a grevious injuries, it does not in
			<lb />
			any way go to fill in the gap of linking the accused with the said injuries.
			<lb />
			16. Considering the matter in this light I find that although there are
			<lb />
			errors in the trial court judgment, it has not resulted in any miscarriage of
			<lb />
			justice. Therefore, no interference with the impugned judgment is called for.
			<lb />
			This revision petition is dismissed.
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			CRL.REV.P. 255/2000
		</note>
		<page>
			page 10 of 11
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			BADAR DURREZ AHMED (JUDGE)
			<lb />
			July 03, 2007
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			CRL.REV.P. 255/2000
		</note>
		<page>
			page 10 of 11
			<lb />
		</page>
	</text>
</tei>
