<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			Reportable
			<lb />
			IN THE SUPREME COURT OF INDIA
			<lb />
			CIVIL ORIGINAL JURISDICTION
			<lb />
			Writ Petition (C) No 961 of 2021
			<lb />
			Neil Aurelio Nunes &amp; Ors.
			<lb />
			....Petitioners
			<lb />
			Versus
			<lb />
			Union of India &amp; Ors.
			<lb />
			.... Respondents
			<lb />
			With
			<lb />
			Writ Petition (C) No 967 of 2021
			<lb />
			With
			<lb />
			Writ Petition (C) No 1002 of 2021
			<lb />
			With
			<lb />
			Writ Petition (C) No 1021 of 2021
			<lb />
			And With
			<lb />
			Writ Petition (C) No 1105 of 2021
			<lb />
		</front>
		<note place="footnote">
			Digitally signed by
			<lb />
			Sanjay Kumar
			<lb />
			Date: 2022.01.07
			<lb />
			15:01:43 IST
			<lb />
			Reason:
			<lb />
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
		</note>
		<front>
			O R D E R
			<lb />
			Dr Dhananjaya Y Chandrachud, J
			<lb />
		</front>
		<page>
			1
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			1
			<lb />
			There is a challenge, in this batch of petitions under Article 32 of the
			<lb />
			Constitution, to a notice which was issued by the Directorate General of Health
			<lb />
			Services in the Union Ministry of Health and Family Welfare on 29 July 2021. The
			<lb />
			notice implements a 27 per cent reservation for Other Backward Classes 1 (non-creamy
			<lb />
			layer) and a 10 per cent reservation for the Economically Weaker Section, 2 while filling
			<lb />
			up 15 per cent undergraduate and 50 per cent post-graduate 3 All India Quota 4 seats in
			<lb />
			pursuance of the National Eligibility cum Entrance Test 5 . The notice takes effect from
			<lb />
			the current admission year, 2021-2022. The petitioners are doctors who appeared in
			<lb />
			the NEET-PG 2021 examination.
			<lb />
			2
			<lb />
			The petitions were instituted on 24 August 2021 to challenge the validity of the
			<lb />
			notice dated 29 July 2021. Notice was issued by this Court on 6 September 2021. The
			<lb />
			NEET-PG results were announced on 28 September 2021. Arguments were heard in
			<lb />
			part on 7 October 2021. It was argued that there cannot be any reservation for the
			<lb />
			OBC and EWS category in the AIQ seats in NEET-PG and that the criteria for the
			<lb />
			determination of the EWS category notified by O.M 36039/1/2019 6 was unconstitutional.
			<lb />
			By an order dated 21 October 2021, this Court sought clarifications in regard to the
			<lb />
			criteria provided by the OM of 2019 of using Rs 8 lakhs as the cut -off income limit for
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			1 &quot;OBC&quot;
			<lb />
			2 &quot;EWS&quot;
			<lb />
			3 &quot;PG&quot;
			<lb />
			4 &quot;AIQ&quot;
			<lb />
			5 &quot;NEET&quot;
			<lb />
			6 &quot;OM 2019&quot;
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			2
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			identifying EWS. Two weeks were granted to the Union Government to file an affidavit
			<lb />
			in this regard. When the batch was taken up for hearing on 21 October 2021, the Union
			<lb />
			Government had not filed the affidavit. The ASG, Mr KM Nataraj informed this Court
			<lb />
			that an affidavit will be filed within two days. By an order dated 21 October 2021, this
			<lb />
			Court then formulated issues requiring the Union Government to disclose the rationale
			<lb />
			for the adoption of the criteria used to identify the EWS. On 25 October 2021, the Union
			<lb />
			Government of its own accord deferred the counselling due to the pendency of the
			<lb />
			petitions. Thereafter, the Union Government filed an affidavit justifying the EWS criteria
			<lb />
			on 26 October 2021 stating that the criteria was adopted after due deliberation within
			<lb />
			the Ministry of Social Justice and Empowerment and all the concerned stakeholders.
			<lb />
			3
			<lb />
			When the matter was listed for hearing on 28 October 2021, the Solicitor General
			<lb />
			sought an adjournment and requested that the petitions be heard after Diwali. On 25
			<lb />
			November 2021, this Court was informed by the Solicitor General that the Union
			<lb />
			Government has taken a considered decision to revisit the criteria for determining the
			<lb />
			EWS and requested four weeks to complete this exercise, which was acceded to by
			<lb />
			this Court. The Union Government formed a Committee 7 on 30 November 2021 to
			<lb />
			review the criteria for identifying EWS. The Committee submitted its report on 31
			<lb />
			December 2021. Thereafter, the Union Government filed an affidavit before this Court
			<lb />
			accepting the recommendations of the Committee including the recommendation that
			<lb />
			the existing criteria for identifying EWS be retained for the present admission year
			<lb />
			2021-2022.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			7 &quot;Pandey Committee&quot;
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			3
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			4
			<lb />
			The petitions were taken up for urgent hearing by this Court on 5 January 2022
			<lb />
			after a request was made by the Solicitor General. It was submitted on behalf of the
			<lb />
			Union Government that the OBC and EWS reservation (with the old criteria according to
			<lb />
			OM 2019) be allowed to be implemented for the current admission year of 2021.
			<lb />
			5
			<lb />
			We have heard Mr, Arvind Datar, Mr Shyam Divan and Mr Anand Grover, Senior
			<lb />
			Counsel and Mr Shrirang Choudary, Ms. Archana Pathak Dave, Mr Apoorva Karol, Mr
			<lb />
			Subodh Patil and Mr Varun Thakur for the doctors and intervenors challenging the
			<lb />
			validity of the reservations for OBC and EWS categories. On the other side, we heard
			<lb />
			Mr Tushar Mehta, Solicitor General, Mr. Nataraj, Additional Solicitor General, Mr P
			<lb />
			Wilson for the Dravida Munnetra Kazhagam, Mr Mariarputham for the State of Tamil
			<lb />
			Nadu, and Mr Biju and Mr. Shashank Ratnoo for the intervenors.
			<lb />
			6
			<lb />
			The submissions which have been urged before this Court over a span of two
			<lb />
			days necessitate a detailed interim order on the applicability of the EWS criteria as
			<lb />
			notified by OM 2019 for NEET-PG 2021. The formulation of the reasons in the interim
			<lb />
			order on the EWS reservation would take some time. The validity of the OBC
			<lb />
			reservation in the AIQ seats in NEET-PG and NEET-UG is upheld for reasons to follow.
			<lb />
			In the meantime, there is an urgent need to commence the process of Counselling. We
			<lb />
			are hence issuing the following operative directions at this stage :
			<lb />
			7 (i)
			<lb />
			We accept the recommendation of the Pandey Committee that the
			<lb />
			criteria which have been stipulated in OM 2019 be used for 2021-2022
			<lb />
			in order to ensure that the admission process is not dislocated;
			<lb />
			(ii)
			<lb />
			Counselling on the basis of NEET-PG 2021 and NEET-UG 2021 shall
			<lb />
			be conducted by giving effect to the reservation as provided by the
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			4
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			notice dated 29 July 2021, including the 27 per cent reservation for the
			<lb />
			OBC category and 10 per cent reservation for EWS category in the AIQ
			<lb />
			seats;
			<lb />
			(iii)
			<lb />
			The criteria for the determination of the EWS notified by OM 2019 shall
			<lb />
			be used for identifying the EWS category for candidates who appeared
			<lb />
			for the NEET-PG 2021 and NEET-UG 2021examinations;
			<lb />
			(iv)
			<lb />
			The validity of the criteria determined by the Pandey Committee for
			<lb />
			identification of EWS would prospectively for the future be subject to the
			<lb />
			final result of the petitions; and
			<lb />
			(v)
			<lb />
			The petitions shall be listed for final hearing on the validity of the EWS
			<lb />
			criteria as recommended by the Pandey Committee in the third week of
			<lb />
			March 2022.
			<lb />
			8
			<lb />
			Reasons shall follow.
			<lb />
			….…….…………………………...............................J.
			<lb />
			[Dr Dhananjaya Y Chandrachud]
			<lb />
			….…….…………………………...............................J.
			<lb />
			[AS Bopanna]
			<lb />
			New Delhi;
			<lb />
			January 07, 2022
		</body>
		<page>
			5
			<lb />
		</page>
	</text>
</tei>
