<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			via Video-conferencing
			<lb />
			$~34
			<lb />
			*
			<lb />
			IN THE HIGH COURT OF DELHI AT NEW DELHI
			<lb />
			Date of decision: 22 nd September 2020
			<lb />
			+
			<lb />
			BAIL APPL. 1559/2020
			<lb />
			DHARMANDER SINGH @ SAHEB
			<lb />
			.....Petitioner/Applicant.
			<lb />
			Through : Ms. Vagisha Kochar, Advocate.
			<lb />
			versus
			<lb />
			THE STATE (GOVT. OF NCT, DELHI)
			<lb />
			..... Respondent
			<lb />
			Through : Mr. Neelam Sharma, APP for State.
			<lb />
			Complainant/Prosecutrix in-person
			<lb />
			along with I.O./W/S.I. Anil Sharma.
			<lb />
			CORAM:
			<lb />
			HON&apos;BLE MR. JUSTICE ANUP JAIRAM BHAMBHANI
			<lb />
			J U D G M E N T
			<lb />
			ANUP JAIRAM BHAMBHANI, J.
			<lb />
		</front>
		<body>
			The applicant, who is stated to be about 24 years of age, is an accused
			<lb />
			in case FIR No. 471/2018 dated 14.10.2018 registered under sections
			<lb />
			323/343/363/366A/376/506 IPC read with sections 6/21 of the Protection of
			<lb />
			Children from Sexual Offences Act 2012 (&apos;POCSO Act&apos;, for short) at PS:
			<lb />
			Hari Nagar ; and has been in judicial custody since 17.11.2018.
			<lb />
			2.
			<lb />
			By way of the present application under section 439 of the Code of
			<lb />
			Criminal Procedure, 1973 (&apos;Cr. P.C.&apos;, for short), the applicant seeks
			<lb />
			regular bail.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			BAIL APPL. No. 1559/2020
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page
			<lb />
			1 of 45
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			3.
			<lb />
			Briefly, the factual backdrop that has led to filing of the subject FIR is
			<lb />
			that the applicant and the complainant/prosecutrix became friends
			<lb />
			through Facebook about 02 years back in 2016, which friendship, it is
			<lb />
			alleged, culminated in physical intimacy between the two.
			<lb />
			4.
			<lb />
			The FIR recites that the applicant made physical relations with the
			<lb />
			complainant at his residence and also made a video of the act;
			<lb />
			whereafter, the allegation goes, the applicant started calling the
			<lb />
			complainant to his house time-and-again to engage in physical
			<lb />
			relations. It is further alleged that on 25.04.2018, when the
			<lb />
			complainant was visiting her village, the applicant called her back
			<lb />
			threatening that if she did not return, he would share the video made
			<lb />
			on social media and upload it on the internet. The complainant says
			<lb />
			that thereupon she boarded the train back from her village on
			<lb />
			09.05.2018 and returned to the applicant on 10.05.2018. She further
			<lb />
			says that the applicant forced the complainant to live with him in a
			<lb />
			certain house; and when the complainant called her family members
			<lb />
			to come and meet her, the applicant started pressurising the
			<lb />
			complainant for marriage.
			<lb />
			5.
			<lb />
			It is further alleged that on 15.05.2018, the applicant married the
			<lb />
			complainant in his own house in the presence of his mother; and
			<lb />
			thereafter, forcibly kept the complainant there for about a month-and-
			<lb />
			a-half. Thereafter, the complainant alleges that she called her parents
			<lb />
			to the applicant&apos;s house and returned with them to her maternal home
			<lb />
			on 25.06.2018. It is further the complainant&apos;s case that again on
			<lb />
			27.06.2018, the applicant threatened the complainant to return to him,
			<lb />
			whereupon she came back and stayed with him for about 05 days until
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			BAIL APPL. No. 1559/2020
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page
			<lb />
			2 of 45
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			03.07.2018, when her mother and aunt came to the applicant&apos;s place
			<lb />
			and the applicant sent her off.
			<lb />
			6.
			<lb />
			The FIR records other allegations as well, the essence of which is that
			<lb />
			the applicant threatened the complainant to return to him from time-
			<lb />
			to-time; and that, when she refused, he uploaded the complainant&apos;s
			<lb />
			photograph as his display-picture on WhatsApp and threatened to
			<lb />
			embarrass her.
			<lb />
			7.
			<lb />
			There is also an allegation in the FIR that on 13.10.2018 the applicant
			<lb />
			took the complainant on his &apos;scooty&apos;; and thereafter diverted towards
			<lb />
			a flyover, stopped the &apos;scooty&apos; and asked the complainant to disrobe,
			<lb />
			at which point he also hit her.
			<lb />
			8.
			<lb />
			On these allegations, the FIR was registered on 14.10.2018;
			<lb />
			whereupon the applicant was arrested on 17.11.2018.
			<lb />
			9.
			<lb />
			Notice in this application was issued on 06.07.2020.
			<lb />
			10. Status report dated 21.07.2020 has been filed by the State.
			<lb />
			11. Nominal roll dated 21.07.2020 has also been received from the Jail
			<lb />
			Superintendent.
			<lb />
			12. Since the matter concerned an allegation under section 376 IPC read
			<lb />
			with sections 6/21 of the POCSO Act, intimation under section
			<lb />
			439(1A) Cr.P.C. and Delhi High Court Practice Directions dated
			<lb />
			24.09.2019 was sent to the complainant; in response to which the
			<lb />
			complainant appeared along with Investigating Officer/W/S.I. Anil
			<lb />
			Sharma and was heard on the bail application.
			<lb />
			13. In her statement dated 16.10.2018 recorded under section 164 Cr.P.C.,
			<lb />
			the complainant has, in substance, supported the allegations made in
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			BAIL APPL. No. 1559/2020
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page
			<lb />
			3 of 45
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			the FIR while giving some additional details. What is noteworthy
			<lb />
			however is that in her supplementary statement dated 14.10.2018
			<lb />
			recorded under section 161 Cr.P.C., the complainant says that at the
			<lb />
			time she was getting married to the applicant at his house, both the
			<lb />
			complainant and the applicant had told the applicant&apos;s mother that her
			<lb />
			age was 19 years, so that the mother would not disallow them to get
			<lb />
			married; and she further states that the applicant&apos;s mother believed
			<lb />
			them since she is old and uneducated. An extract of the relevant
			<lb />
			portion of supplementary statement dated 14.10.2018 is as under :
			<lb />
			14. In MLC dated 14.10.2018 however, the complainant&apos;s age is recorded
			<lb />
			as 17 years.
			<lb />
			15. Subsequently, charge-sheet dated 15.12.2018 was filed in the matter
			<lb />
			and charges were framed on 06.04.2019. Although initially a co-
			<lb />
			accused, the applicant&apos;s mother was discharged in the matter at that
			<lb />
			stage.
			<lb />
			16. The complainant&apos;s examination-in-chief was recorded in-part on
			<lb />
			11.10.2019, in which the complainant has disclosed her age as 18
			<lb />
			years as on 26.07.2019.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			BAIL APPL. No. 1559/2020
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page
			<lb />
			4 of 45
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			17. Some parts of the complainant&apos;s deposition that are relevant for
			<lb />
			purposes of deciding the present bail application are as under :
			<lb />
			18. The examination-in-chief was deferred inter alia because the
			<lb />
			applicant&apos;s mobile phone, which is alleged to contain the
			<lb />
			complainant&apos;s objectionable photos and videos, was to be produced;
			<lb />
			but was pending forensic examination by the Forensic Science
			<lb />
			Laboratory. This court is informed that subsequently a supplementary
			<lb />
			charge sheet has also been filed based on the FSL report.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			BAIL APPL. No. 1559/2020
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page
			<lb />
			5  of 45
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			19. Ms. Vagisha Kochar, learned counsel appearing for the applicant has
			<lb />
			essentially submitted that the allegations in the FIR, and subsequently
			<lb />
			in the charge-sheet, show that the applicant and the complainant were
			<lb />
			in a consensual relationship for a prolonged period of time; that the
			<lb />
			complainant was fully and voluntarily involved in such relationship
			<lb />
			inasmuch as she even lied to the applicant&apos;s mother as regards her age
			<lb />
			at the time when the applicant married her at his house; that on the
			<lb />
			applicant&apos;s beckoning, the complainant readily returned to him several
			<lb />
			times and stayed with him for several days; that it is accordingly
			<lb />
			evident that the relationship was voluntary even on the complainant&apos;s
			<lb />
			part and there was no culpable coercion in the relationship.
			<lb />
			20. Counsel further submits, that in any case, since the investigation is
			<lb />
			complete and the charge-sheet in the matter has been filed way-back
			<lb />
			in December 2018 and a supplementary charge-sheet has also now
			<lb />
			been filed, nothing further remains to be done in the matter that would
			<lb />
			justify keeping the applicant in judicial custody any longer.
			<lb />
			21. Ms. Kochar has also argued that in fact a major portion of the
			<lb />
			complaint&apos;s examination-in-chief also stands recorded; and that her
			<lb />
			remaining deposition including cross-examination, would have been
			<lb />
			complete by now, had it not been for the truncated functioning of
			<lb />
			courts by reason of the prevailing coronavirus pandemic. It is
			<lb />
			submitted that especially in the present times, when evidence is still
			<lb />
			not being recorded in courts by reason of the pandemic, there is no
			<lb />
			likelihood that trial will be completed anytime soon and therefore the
			<lb />
			applicant&apos;s detention in custody is unwarranted and unfair.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			BAIL APPL. No. 1559/2020
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page
			<lb />
			6 of 45
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			22. Opposing the grant of bail, Ms. Neelam Sharma, learned APP
			<lb />
			appearing for the State has contended that, as the record clearly
			<lb />
			shows, the complainant was minor and that therefore the question of
			<lb />
			the physical relationship being consensual does not arise. She
			<lb />
			contends that it is admitted by the applicant that he repeatedly
			<lb />
			engaged in sexual intercourse with the complainant which only makes
			<lb />
			the position worse; and that the story that the parties married each
			<lb />
			other in the presence of the applicant&apos;s mother is again of no legal
			<lb />
			consequence, since the complainant was minor.
			<lb />
			23. Ms. Sharma submits that in the supplementary charge-sheet filed in
			<lb />
			the matter, based on the FSL report on the contents of the applicant&apos;s
			<lb />
			cell phone, it has also been alleged that the applicant had taken
			<lb />
			objectionable photographs and videos of the complainant, which was
			<lb />
			obviously against her consent or will.
			<lb />
			24. Ms. Sharma invites attention to the complainant&apos;s deposition recorded
			<lb />
			on 11.10.2019 again, in which she emphasises that the complainant
			<lb />
			has stated the following :
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			BAIL APPL. No. 1559/2020
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page
			<lb />
			7 of 45
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			25. Ms. Sharma also stresses the point that since charges have already
			<lb />
			been framed in the matter, section 29 of the POCSO Act will apply
			<lb />
			with full vigour, whereby the court must presume the applicant to be
			<lb />
			guilty of the offences charged till he proves otherwise; and bail must
			<lb />
			not be given.
			<lb />
			26. In the course of the video-conference hearing, the court has interacted
			<lb />
			with the complainant, to elicit her stand in the matter; and, in gist, the
			<lb />
			complainant has supported her stand taken in her deposition before
			<lb />
			the trial court and has opposed grant of bail.
			<lb />
			27. Counsel for the applicant as also for the State have also been heard at
			<lb />
			length on the law, especially on the scope and application of sections
			<lb />
			29, 30 and 31 of the POCSO Act. Their submissions have been
			<lb />
			included and considered in the discussion that appears below.
			<lb />
			28. At this point a quick recapitulation of the basic tenets and principles
			<lb />
			of bail would be useful.
			<lb />
			29. While the precept &apos;bail is the rule and jail is the exception&apos; was
			<lb />
			originally crafted as a mantra, this court notes with consternation that
			<lb />
			this phrase has, more often than not, been reduced to mere empty
			<lb />
			platitude, which is repeated often but almost never applied.
			<lb />
			30. In Jeetendra vs. State of Madhya Pradesh &amp; Anr. , the Supreme
			<lb />
			1
			<lb />
			Court has reiterated this mantra in the following words :
			<lb />
			&quot;7. Having heard learned counsel for the parties as well as the counsel
			<lb />
			representing the complainant, we are satisfied that the appellant deserves
			<lb />
			to be enlarged on bail. The High Court ought to have kept in view that
			<lb />
			&apos;Bail is rule and jail is exception&apos;. There is no gainsaying that bail should
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			2020 SCC OnLine SC 334
			<lb />
			1
		</note>
		<note place="footnote">
			<lb />
			BAIL APPL. No. 1559/2020
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page of
			<lb />
			8 45
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			not be granted or rejected in a mechanical manner as it concerns the
			<lb />
			liberty of a person. In peculiar circumstances of this case where closure
			<lb />
			report was filed twice, the High Court ought not to have declined bail only
			<lb />
			because the trial court was yet to accept the said report. Further, the
			<lb />
			examination of witnesses would depend upon the fate of 2nd closure
			<lb />
			report. Considering the nature of allegations attributed to the appellant
			<lb />
			and the period he has already spent in custody, we are satisfied that he
			<lb />
			deserves to be released on bail forthwith.&quot;
			<lb />
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
			31. The legal dispensation relating to bail in the Cr.P.C. is contained
			<lb />
			essentially in sections 437 and 439. While in section 437 Cr.P.C. the
			<lb />
			Legislature has imposed certain qualifications and conditions on the
			<lb />
			grant of bail by &apos;a Court other than a High Court or Court of Session&apos;,
			<lb />
			under section 439 Cr.P.C. the power of the High Court or the Sessions
			<lb />
			Court to grant bail is wider.
			<lb />
			32. Discussing the powers under sections 437 and 439 Cr. P.C. in
			<lb />
			Gurcharan Singh &amp; Ors vs. State (Delhi Administration) , the
			<lb />
			2
			<lb />
			Supreme Court had this to say :
			<lb />
			&quot;24. Section 439(1) Cr. P.C. of the new Code, on the other hand, confers
			<lb />
			special powers on the High Court or the Court of Session in respect of
			<lb />
			bail. Unlike under Section 437(1) there is no ban imposed under Section
			<lb />
			439(1), Cr. P.C. against granting of bail by the High Court or the Court of
			<lb />
			Session to persons accused of an offence punishable with death or
			<lb />
			imprisonment for life. It is, however, legitimate to suppose that the High
			<lb />
			Court or the Court of Session will be approached by an accused only after
			<lb />
			he has failed before the Magistrate and after the investigation has
			<lb />
			progressed throwing light on the evidence and circumstances implicating
			<lb />
			the accused. Even so, the High Court or the Court of Session will have to
			<lb />
			exercise its judicial discretion in considering the question of granting of
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			(1978) 1 SCC 118
			<lb />
			2
			<lb />
		</note>
		<note place="footnote">
			BAIL APPL. No. 1559/2020
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page of
			<lb />
			9 45
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			bail under Section 439(1) Cr. P.C. of the new Code. The overriding
			<lb />
			considerations in granting bail to which we adverted to earlier and which
			<lb />
			are common both in the case of Section 437(1) and Section 439(1), Cr.
			<lb />
			P.C. of the new Code are the nature and gravity of the circumstances in
			<lb />
			which the offence is committed; the position and the status of the accused
			<lb />
			with reference to the victim and the witnesses; the likelihood, of the
			<lb />
			accused fleeing from justice; of repeating the offence; of jeopardising his
			<lb />
			own life being faced with a grim prospect of possible conviction in the
			<lb />
			case; of tampering with witnesses; the history of the case as well as of its
			<lb />
			investigation and other relevant grounds which, in view of so many
			<lb />
			valuable factors, cannot be exhaustively set out.&quot;
			<lb />
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
			33. In Sundeep Kumar Bafna vs. State of Maharashtra &amp; Anr. , the
			<lb />
			3
			<lb />
			Supreme Court has clarified:
			<lb />
			&quot;8. …. Cr.P.C. severely curtails the powers of the Magistrate while
			<lb />
			leaving that of the Court of Session and the High Court untouched and
			<lb />
			unfettered. It appears to us that this is the only logical conclusion that can
			<lb />
			be arrived at on a conjoint consideration of Sections 437 and 439 Cr.P.C.
			<lb />
			Obviously, in order to complete the picture so far as concerns the powers
			<lb />
			and limitations thereto of the Court of Session and the High Court, Section
			<lb />
			439 would have to be carefully considered. .... &quot;
			<lb />
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
			34. While the amplitude and power under section 439 Cr.P.C. is wide, it
			<lb />
			would be trite to say that the wider the power and discretion, the more
			<lb />
			the need for its judicious and non-arbitrary exercise. Observing that
			<lb />
			the power to grant bail must be exercised in a judicious manner and
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			(2014) 16 SCC 623
			<lb />
			3
			<lb />
		</note>
		<note place="footnote">
			BAIL APPL. No. 1559/2020
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page
			<lb />
			10 of45
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			not as a matter of course, in Mahipal vs. Rajesh Kumar &amp; Anr. , the
			<lb />
			4
			<lb />
			Supreme Court observes thus :
			<lb />
			&quot;12. The determination of whether a case is fit for the grant of bail
			<lb />
			involves the balancing of numerous factors, among which the nature of
			<lb />
			the offence, the severity of the punishment and a prima facie view of the
			<lb />
			involvement of the accused are important. No straitjacket formula exists
			<lb />
			for courts to assess an application for the grant or rejection of bail. At the
			<lb />
			stage of assessing whether a case is fit for the grant of bail, the court is
			<lb />
			not required to enter into a detailed analysis of the evidence on record to
			<lb />
			establish beyond reasonable doubt the commission of the crime by the
			<lb />
			accused. That is a matter for trial. However, the Court is required to
			<lb />
			examine whether there is a prima facie or reasonable ground to believe
			<lb />
			that the accused had committed the offence and on a balance of the
			<lb />
			considerations involved, the continued custody of the accused subserves
			<lb />
			the purpose of the criminal justice system. Where bail has been granted
			<lb />
			by a lower court, an appellate court must be slow to interfere and ought to
			<lb />
			be guided by the principles set out for the exercise of the power to set
			<lb />
			aside bail.
			<lb />
			* * * * * *
			<lb />
			&quot;14. The provision for an accused to be released on bail touches upon the
			<lb />
			liberty of an individual. It is for this reason that this Court does not
			<lb />
			ordinarily interfere with an order of the High Court granting bail.
			<lb />
			However, where the discretion of the High Court to grant bail has been
			<lb />
			exercised without the due application of mind or in contravention of the
			<lb />
			directions of this Court, such an order granting bail is liable to be set
			<lb />
			aside. The Court is required to factor, amongst other things, a prima facie
			<lb />
			view that the accused had committed the offence, the nature and gravity of
			<lb />
			the offence and the likelihood of the accused obstructing the proceedings
			<lb />
			of the trial in any manner or evading the course of justice. The provision
			<lb />
			for being released on bail draws an appropriate balance between public
			<lb />
			interest in the administration of justice and the protection of individual
			<lb />
			liberty pending adjudication of the case. However, the grant of bail is to
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			(2020) 2 SCC 118
			<lb />
			4
			<lb />
		</note>
		<note place="footnote">
			BAIL APPL. No. 1559/2020
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page
			<lb />
			11 of 45
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			be secured within the bounds of the law and in compliance with the
			<lb />
			conditions laid down by this Court. It is for this reason that a court must
			<lb />
			balance numerous factors that guide the exercise of the discretionary
			<lb />
			power to grant bail on a case-by-case basis. Inherent in this determination
			<lb />
			is whether, on an analysis of the record, it appears that there is a prima
			<lb />
			facie or reasonable cause to believe that the accused had committed the
			<lb />
			crime. It is not relevant at this stage for the court to examine in detail the
			<lb />
			evidence on record to come to a conclusive finding.&quot;
			<lb />
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
			35. However, when the offences alleged are inter alia under the POCSO
			<lb />
			Act, as in the present case, another very significant factor requires to
			<lb />
			be factored in and addressed.
			<lb />
			36. While ordinarily there is a &apos;presumption of innocence&apos; vis-a-vis an
			<lb />
			accused, section 29 of the POCSO Act reverses this position. Section
			<lb />
			29 of the POCSO Act creates a &apos;presumption of guilt&apos; on the part of
			<lb />
			the accused if he is prosecuted for committing, abetting or attempting
			<lb />
			certain offences. Section 29 reads as under :
			<lb />
			&quot;29. Presumption as to certain offences.-Where a person is prosecuted
			<lb />
			for committing or abetting or attempting to commit any offence under
			<lb />
			Sections 3, 5, 7 and Section 9 of this Act, the Special Court shall presume,
			<lb />
			that such person has committed or abetted or attempted to commit the
			<lb />
			offence, as the case may be unless the contrary is proved.&quot;
			<lb />
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
			37. In the context of section 29, two other provisions of the POCSO Act
			<lb />
			which also need attention are sections 30 and 31 of that statute, which
			<lb />
			are extracted hereinbelow for ease of reference :
			<lb />
			&quot;30. Presumption of culpable mental state.-(1) In any prosecution for
			<lb />
			any offence under this Act which requires a culpable mental state on the
			<lb />
			part of the accused, the Special Court shall presume the existence of
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			BAIL APPL. No. 1559/2020
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page
			<lb />
			12  of 45
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			such mental state but it shall be a defence for the accused to prove the
			<lb />
			fact that he had no such mental state with respect to the act charged as an
			<lb />
			offence in that prosecution.
			<lb />
			(2) For the purposes of this section, a fact is said to be proved only when
			<lb />
			the Special Court believes it to exist beyond reasonable doubt and not
			<lb />
			merely when its existence is established by a preponderance of probability.
			<lb />
			Explanation.-In this section, &quot;culpable mental state&quot; includes intention,
			<lb />
			motive, knowledge of a fact and the belief in, or reason to believe, a fact.
			<lb />
			&quot;31. Application of Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 to proceedings
			<lb />
			before a Special Court.-Save as otherwise provided in this Act, the
			<lb />
			provisions of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974) (including
			<lb />
			the provisions as to bail and bonds) shall apply to the proceedings before
			<lb />
			a Special Court and for the purposes of the said provisions, the Special
			<lb />
			Court shall be deemed to be a Court of Sessions and the person
			<lb />
			conducting a prosecution before a Special Court, shall be deemed to be a
			<lb />
			Public Prosecutor.&quot;
			<lb />
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
			38. Section 30 therefore stipulates that in a prosecution under the POCSO
			<lb />
			Act, where the offence requires the existence of a culpable mental
			<lb />
			state, the court is to presume the existence of such culpable mental
			<lb />
			state on the part of the accused, while of course giving to the accused
			<lb />
			the right to rebut it beyond reasonable doubt. Again therefore, there is
			<lb />
			a presumption of culpability coupled with the right of the accused to
			<lb />
			rebut such presumption.
			<lb />
			39. Insofar as section 31 is concerned, it brings into play the provisions of
			<lb />
			the Cr.P.C provided there is no specific provision otherwise with
			<lb />
			regard to a procedural matter in the POCSO Act. Section 31 is of
			<lb />
			special significance since there is no specific provision relating to bail
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			BAIL APPL. No. 1559/2020
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page
			<lb />
			13  of 45
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			in the POCSO Act, unlike say, section 37 in the Narcotic Drugs &amp;
			<lb />
			Psychotropic Substances Act 1985 (&apos;NDPS Act&apos; for short). Section 31
			<lb />
			accordingly provides that if the POCSO Act is silent in respect of a
			<lb />
			procedural matter, the proceeding before a Special Court dealing with
			<lb />
			offences under the POCSO Act shall be governed by the Cr.P.C. Ergo,
			<lb />
			the provisions relating to bail contained in the Cr.P.C. apply squarely
			<lb />
			to proceedings under the POCSO Act. Furthermore, since section 31
			<lb />
			says that a Special Court appointed under the POCSO Act is deemed
			<lb />
			to be a Court of Sessions under the Cr.P.C., the provisions of section
			<lb />
			439 Cr.P.C. for grant of bail, as briefly discussed above, would govern
			<lb />
			such proceedings before the Special Court.
			<lb />
			40. Now, the POCSO Act was enacted to specifically address sexual
			<lb />
			offences against children and to establish Special Courts for trial of
			<lb />
			such offences. In this connection, the Parliamentary Standing
			<lb />
			Committee on Human Resource Development of the Rajya Sabha
			<lb />
			rendered its 240 th Report on the Protection of Children from Sexual
			<lb />
			Offences Bill 2011, which report gives an insight into the thought
			<lb />
			process, rationale and reasoning that went into incorporation of
			<lb />
			various provisions in that statute. For purposes of the present
			<lb />
			discussion, apropos the reason for incorporating a reverse burden
			<lb />
			provision in section 29 of the POCSO Act, the Parliamentary Standing
			<lb />
			Committee had the following to say in para 1.12 of its report :
			<lb />
			&quot;1.12 ……Secondly, keeping in view the low conviction rate of sexual
			<lb />
			offences against children, a presumption has been provided in the Bill that
			<lb />
			the accused in case of sexual assault has committed the offence unless
			<lb />
			proved contrary. It was mentioned that such a provision already existed in
			<lb />
			our law. Sections 113A and 114A of the Indian Evidence Act already create
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			BAIL APPL. No. 1559/2020
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page
			<lb />
			14 of 45
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			presumptions in two situations, cruelty for dowry and for rape.
			<lb />
			Vulnerability of the victims and the difficulty in collecting the evidence
			<lb />
			were the two factors leading to such a provision being incorporated in the
			<lb />
			Bill. Misuse of such a provision had also been taken care of by including a
			<lb />
			safeguard therein.&quot;
			<lb />
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
			41. In view of the above prefatory discussion, the questions that arise for
			<lb />
			consideration are :
			<lb />
			i. Since section 29 says &quot;(w)here a person is prosecuted&quot; for
			<lb />
			committing an offence inter alia under sections 3, 5, 7 and 9,
			<lb />
			the special court &quot;shall presume&quot; an accused to be guilty, when
			<lb />
			can a person be said to be prosecuted ?
			<lb />
			ii. Since section 29 says &quot;unless the contrary is proved&quot;, when
			<lb />
			does a person get the chance to disprove his presumptive guilt ?
			<lb />
			iii. When and at what stage does the &apos;presumption of guilt&apos; as
			<lb />
			engrafted in section 29 get triggered ? and
			<lb />
			iv. Does the presumption apply only at the stage of trial or does it
			<lb />
			also apply when a bail plea is being considered ?
			<lb />
			v. Does the applicability or rigour of section 29 depend on
			<lb />
			whether a bail plea is being considered before or after charges
			<lb />
			have been framed ?
			<lb />
			42. The term &apos;prosecution&apos; is defined in the Oxford Advanced Learner&apos;s
			<lb />
			Dictionary as follows :
			<lb />
			&quot;prosecution (noun) -the process of trying to prove in court that
			<lb />
			somebody is guilty of a crime; the process of being officially charged with
			<lb />
			a crime in court.&quot;
			<lb />
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			BAIL APPL. No. 1559/2020
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page
			<lb />
			15 of 45
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			43. &apos;Prosecution&apos; in its legal connotation is defined in the Black&apos;s Law
			<lb />
			Dictionary 8 th Ed. as follows :
			<lb />
			&quot;prosecution. 1. The commencement and carrying out of any action or
			<lb />
			scheme &lt;the prosecution of a long, bloody war&gt;.2. A criminal proceeding
			<lb />
			in which an accused person is tried &lt;the conspiracy trial involved the
			<lb />
			prosecution of seven defendants&gt;. -Also termed criminal prosecution.&quot;
			<lb />
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
			44. Notably, the terms &apos;prosecution&apos; or &apos;prosecuted&apos; have neither been
			<lb />
			defined in the POCSO Act nor in the Cr.P.C. As explained later in this
			<lb />
			judgment, the phrase &quot;person is prosecuted&quot; appearing in section 29
			<lb />
			actually refers to the stage when trial commences. To that extent the
			<lb />
			word &quot;prosecuted&quot; has been used in the sense of &quot;tried&quot;. But when
			<lb />
			does &apos;trial&apos; commence ?
			<lb />
			45. Now, in Hardeep Singh vs. State of Punjab &amp; Ors. , the Supreme
			<lb />
			5
			<lb />
			Court overruled an earlier view that trial commences on cognizance
			<lb />
			being taken and held that trial commences only once charges are
			<lb />
			framed. The following observation of the Supreme Court in Hardeep
			<lb />
			Singh (supra) is important :
			<lb />
			&quot;38. In view of the above, the law can be summarised to the effect that as
			<lb />
			&quot;trial&quot; means determination of issues adjudging the guilt or the
			<lb />
			innocence of a person, the person has to be aware of what is the case
			<lb />
			against him and it is only at the stage of framing of the charges that the
			<lb />
			court informs him of the same, the &quot;trial&quot; commences only on charges
			<lb />
			being framed. Thus, we do not approve the view taken by the courts that
			<lb />
			in a criminal case, trial commences on cognizance being taken.&quot;
			<lb />
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			(2014) 3 SCC 92
			<lb />
			5
			<lb />
		</note>
		<note place="footnote">
			BAIL APPL. No. 1559/2020
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page
			<lb />
			<lb />
			16 of 45
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			46. It is important to recall that cognizance is taken of the &apos;offence&apos; and
			<lb />
			not of the &apos;offender&apos;; and it has been consistently so held by the
			<lb />
			Supreme Court. A brief reference on this point may be made to
			<lb />
			Prasad Shrikant Purohit vs. State of Maharashtra &amp; Anr. , in which
			<lb />
			6
			<lb />
			the Supreme Court refers to an earlier decision in the following
			<lb />
			words:
			<lb />
			&quot;71. Reliance was then placed upon the decision in Fakhruddin Ahmad, in
			<lb />
			particular para 17. The said para 17 reads as under: (SCC p. 163)
			<lb />
			&quot;17. Nevertheless, it is well settled that before a Magistrate can be
			<lb />
			said to have taken cognizance of an offence, it is imperative that he
			<lb />
			must have taken notice of the accusations and applied his mind to
			<lb />
			the allegations made in the complaint or in the police report or the
			<lb />
			information received from a source other than a police report, as the
			<lb />
			case may be, and the material filed therewith. It needs little
			<lb />
			emphasis that it is only when the Magistrate applies his mind and is
			<lb />
			satisfied that the allegations, if proved, would constitute an offence
			<lb />
			and decides to initiate proceedings against the alleged offender, that
			<lb />
			it can be positively stated that he has taken cognizance of the
			<lb />
			offence. Cognizance is in regard to the offence and not the
			<lb />
			offender.&quot;
			<lb />
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
			Even here this Court has stated in uncontroverted terms that once the
			<lb />
			Magistrate applies his mind to the offence alleged and decides to initiate
			<lb />
			proceedings against the alleged offender, it can be stated that he has taken
			<lb />
			cognizance of the offence and by way of reiteration, it is further stated that
			<lb />
			cognizance is in regard to the offence and not the offender. This decision,
			<lb />
			therefore, reinforces the position that cognizance is mainly of the offence
			<lb />
			and not the offender.&quot;
			<lb />
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			(2015) 7 SCC 440
			<lb />
			6
			<lb />
		</note>
		<note place="footnote">
			BAIL APPL. No. 1559/2020
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page
			<lb />
			17  of 45
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			47. At the stage of taking cognizance, a court may take cognizance of the
			<lb />
			offence vis-a-vis one accused but not against another. Since upto the
			<lb />
			stage of cognizance, it is the offence and not the offender that is
			<lb />
			subject matter of proceedings before court, it cannot be said that upto
			<lb />
			the stage of cognizance, an accused is being prosecuted. As a sequitur
			<lb />
			therefore, a person must be deemed to be prosecuted only when trial
			<lb />
			commences against the accused, which, as the Supreme Court has
			<lb />
			held in Hardeep Singh (supra), happens only after charges are
			<lb />
			framed.
			<lb />
			48. This aspect has also been usefully discussed by the Gauhati High
			<lb />
			Court in Bhupen Kalita vs. State of Assam where the Gauhati High
			<lb />
			7
			<lb />
			Court has this is to say :
			<lb />
			&quot;60. Several views, however, have been taken by various courts as to when
			<lb />
			a prosecution can be said to commence. The following are the some of the
			<lb />
			views.
			<lb />
			(i) Prosecution starts with registration of FIR or complaint before
			<lb />
			the Magistrate.
			<lb />
			(ii) Prosecution is initiated when the Magistrate/Court takes
			<lb />
			cognizance of the offence.
			<lb />
			(iii) Prosecution commences with filing of charge sheet/challan/
			<lb />
			investigation report by the police.
			<lb />
			(iv) Prosecution commences with framing of charges by the court.
			<lb />
			* * * * *
			<lb />
			&quot;64. As to the meaning of trial, when an accused prosecuted, the Hon&apos;ble
			<lb />
			Supreme Court explained the same elaborately in Hardeep Singh v. State
			<lb />
			of Punjab, (2014) 3 SCC 92 : (2014) 2 SCC (Cri) 86. The Hon&apos;ble
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			2020 SCC OnLine Gau 2230
			<lb />
			7
			<lb />
		</note>
		<note place="footnote">
			BAIL APPL. No. 1559/2020
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page
			<lb />
			18 of 45
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			Supreme Court in the said case overruled the view that trial commences
			<lb />
			on cognizance being taken.
			<lb />
			&quot;65. It was held that &quot;trial&quot; means determination of issues for adjudging
			<lb />
			the guilt or the innocence of a person after making the person aware of
			<lb />
			what is the case against him, and it is only at the stage of framing of the
			<lb />
			charges that the court informs him of the same. Thus, &quot;trial&quot; commences
			<lb />
			only on charges being framed.
			<lb />
			* * * * * *
			<lb />
			&quot;67. It is to be noted that neither the POCSO Act nor the CrPC defines as
			<lb />
			to the meaning of the words &quot;prosecuted&quot; and when a prosecution can be
			<lb />
			said to commence. Under the circumstances, as to when a person is
			<lb />
			prosecuted or when the prosecution commences has to be understood in
			<lb />
			the context of the Act and the provisions of the CrPC. As discussed above,
			<lb />
			it can be said that that a trial commences not from the date of filing of FIR
			<lb />
			or the charge-sheet or taking of cognizance by the court but from the stage
			<lb />
			of framing of charge. Prosecution can thus be said to commence from that
			<lb />
			stage when the court starts applying its mind regarding the culpability of
			<lb />
			the accused, that is, when the proper judicial consideration of the guilt or
			<lb />
			otherwise of the accused begins.&quot;
			<lb />
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
			49. The question of when the presumption of guilt gets triggered has been
			<lb />
			addressed by the Supreme Court in the context of the NDPS Act and
			<lb />
			by various other High Courts in POCSO cases, holding that such
			<lb />
			presumption comes into play only when the prosecution has
			<lb />
			established facts that form the basis of the presumption. Relevant
			<lb />
			extracts of the opinion of the Supreme Court and the view taken by
			<lb />
			the High Courts on this point are :
			<lb />
			a. In Noor Aga vs. State of Punjab &amp; Anr. , while dealing with a
			<lb />
			8
			<lb />
			case under the NDPS Act, the Supreme Court has held :
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			(2008) 16 SCC 417
			<lb />
			8
			<lb />
		</note>
		<note place="footnote">
			BAIL APPL. No. 1559/2020
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page
			<lb />
			19 of 45
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			&quot;57. It is also necessary to bear in mind that superficially a case
			<lb />
			may have an ugly look and thereby, prima facie, shaking the
			<lb />
			conscience of any court but it is well settled that suspicion,
			<lb />
			however high it may be, can under no circumstances, be held to be
			<lb />
			a substitute for legal evidence.
			<lb />
			&quot;58. Sections 35 and 54 of the Act, no doubt, raise presumptions
			<lb />
			with regard to the culpable mental state on the part of the accused
			<lb />
			as also place the burden of proof in this behalf on the accused; but a
			<lb />
			bare perusal of the said provision would clearly show that
			<lb />
			presumption would operate in the trial of the accused only in the
			<lb />
			event the circumstances contained therein are fully satisfied. An
			<lb />
			initial burden exists upon the prosecution and only when it stands
			<lb />
			satisfied, would the legal burden shift. Even then, the standard of
			<lb />
			proof required for the accused to prove his innocence is not as high
			<lb />
			as that of the prosecution. Whereas the standard of proof required to
			<lb />
			prove the guilt of the accused on the prosecution is &quot;beyond all
			<lb />
			reasonable doubt&quot; but it is &quot;preponderance of probability&quot; on the
			<lb />
			accused. If the prosecution fails to prove the foundational facts so as
			<lb />
			to attract the rigours of Section 35 of the Act, the actus reus which is
			<lb />
			possession of contraband by the accused cannot be said to have
			<lb />
			been established.
			<lb />
			&quot;59. With a view to bring within its purview the requirements of
			<lb />
			Section 54 of the Act, element of possession of the contraband was
			<lb />
			essential so as to shift the burden on the accused. The provisions
			<lb />
			being exceptions to the general rule, the generality thereof would
			<lb />
			continue to be operative, namely, the element of possession will have
			<lb />
			to be proved beyond reasonable doubt.
			<lb />
			&quot;60. Whether the burden on the accused is a legal burden or an
			<lb />
			evidentiary burden would depend on the statute in question. The
			<lb />
			purport and object thereof must also be taken into consideration in
			<lb />
			determining the said question. It must pass the test of the doctrine of
			<lb />
			proportionality. The difficulties faced by the prosecution in certain
			<lb />
			cases may be held to be sufficient to arrive at an opinion that the
			<lb />
			burden on the accused is an evidentiary burden and not merely a
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			BAIL APPL. No. 1559/2020
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page
			<lb />
			20  of 45
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			legal burden. The trial must be fair. The accused must be provided
			<lb />
			w i t h o p p o r t u n i t i e s t o e f f e c t i v e l y d e f e n d h i m s e l f .
			<lb />
			In Sheldrake v. Director of Public Prosecutions it was stated in the
			<lb />
			9
			<lb />
			following terms: (WLR pp. 988-89, para 21)
			<lb />
			&quot;21. From this body of authority certain principles may be
			<lb />
			derived. The overriding concern is that a trial should be fair,
			<lb />
			and the presumption of innocence is a fundamental right
			<lb />
			directed to that end. The Convention does not outlaw
			<lb />
			presumptions of fact or law but requires that these should be
			<lb />
			kept within reasonable limits and should not be arbitrary. It is
			<lb />
			open to States to define the constituent elements of a criminal
			<lb />
			offence, excluding the requirement of mens rea. But the
			<lb />
			substance and effect of any presumption adverse to a
			<lb />
			d e f e n d a n t m u s t b e e x a m i n e d , a n d m u s t b e
			<lb />
			reasonable. Relevant to any judgment on reasonableness or
			<lb />
			proportionality will be the opportunity given to the defendant
			<lb />
			to rebut the presumption, maintenance of the rights of the
			<lb />
			defence, flexibility in application of the presumption, retention
			<lb />
			by the court of a power to assess the evidence, the importance
			<lb />
			of what is at stake and the difficulty which a prosecutor may
			<lb />
			face in the absence of a presumption. Security concerns do not
			<lb />
			absolve member States from their duty to observe basic
			<lb />
			standards of fairness. The justifiability of any infringement of
			<lb />
			the presumption of innocence cannot be resolved by any rule
			<lb />
			of thumb, but on examination of all the facts and
			<lb />
			circumstances of the particular provision as applied in the
			<lb />
			particular case.&quot;
			<lb />
			(emphasis added)&quot;
			<lb />
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			(2005) 1 AC 264
			<lb />
			9
			<lb />
		</note>
		<note place="footnote">
			BAIL APPL. No. 1559/2020
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page
			<lb />
			21 of 45
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			b. In Sahid Hossain Biswas vs. State of West Bengal , the
			<lb />
			10
			<lb />
			Calcutta High Court has held as under:
			<lb />
			&quot;23. A conjoint reading of the statutory provision in the light of the
			<lb />
			definitions, as aforesaid, would show that in a prosecution under the
			<lb />
			POCSO Act an accused is to prove &apos;the contrary&apos;, that is, he has to
			<lb />
			prove that he has not committed the offence and he is innocent. It is
			<lb />
			trite law that negative cannot be proved [see Sait Tarajee
			<lb />
			Khimchand v. Yelamarti Satyam ]. In order to prove a contrary
			<lb />
			11
			<lb />
			fact, the fact whose opposite is sought to be established must be
			<lb />
			proposed first. It is, therefore, an essential prerequisite that the
			<lb />
			foundational facts of the prosecution case must be established by
			<lb />
			leading evidence before the aforesaid statutory presumption is
			<lb />
			triggered in to shift the onus on the accused to prove the contrary.
			<lb />
			&quot;24. Once the foundation of the prosecution case is laid by leading
			<lb />
			legally admissible evidence, it becomes incumbent on the accused to
			<lb />
			establish from the evidence on record that he has not committed the
			<lb />
			offence or to show from the circumstances of a particular case that a
			<lb />
			man of ordinary prudence would most probably draw an inference of
			<lb />
			innocence in his favour. The accused may achieve such an end by
			<lb />
			leading defence evidence or by discrediting prosecution witnesses
			<lb />
			through effective cross-examination or by exposing the patent
			<lb />
			absurdities or inherent infirmities in their version by an analysis of
			<lb />
			the special features of the case. However, the aforesaid statutory
			<lb />
			presumption cannot be read to mean that the prosecution version is
			<lb />
			to be treated as gospel truth in every case. The presumption does not
			<lb />
			take away the essential duty of the Court to analyse the evidence on
			<lb />
			record in the light of the special features of a particular case, eg.
			<lb />
			patent absurdities or inherent infirmities in the prosecution version
			<lb />
			or existence of entrenched enmity between the accused and the
			<lb />
			victim giving rise to an irresistible inference of falsehood in the
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			2017 SCC OnLine Cal 5023
			<lb />
			10
		</note>
		<note place="footnote">
			<lb />
			(1972) 4 SCC 562, Para-15
			<lb />
			11
			<lb />
		</note>
		<note place="footnote">
			BAIL APPL. No. 1559/2020
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page
			<lb />
			22  of 45
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			prosecution case while determining whether the accused has
			<lb />
			discharged his onus and established his innocence in the given facts
			<lb />
			of a case. To hold otherwise, would compel the Court to
			<lb />
			mechanically accept the mere ipse dixit of the prosecution and give a
			<lb />
			stamp of judicial approval to every prosecution, howsoever, patently
			<lb />
			absurd or inherently improbable it may be.&quot;
			<lb />
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
			c. In Navin Dhaniram Baraiye vs. The State of Maharashtra ,
			<lb />
			12
			<lb />
			the Bombay High Court has held as under:
			<lb />
			&quot;18. A perusal of the above quoted provision does show that it is for
			<lb />
			the accused to prove the contrary and in case he fails to do so, the
			<lb />
			presumption would operate against him leading to his conviction
			<lb />
			under the provisions of the POCSO Act. It cannot be disputed that
			<lb />
			no presumption is absolute and every presumption is rebuttable. It
			<lb />
			cannot be countenanced that the presumption under Section 29 of
			<lb />
			the POCSO Act is absolute. It would come into operation only when
			<lb />
			the prosecution is first able to establish facts that would form the
			<lb />
			foundation for the presumption under Section 29 of the POCSO Act
			<lb />
			to operate. Otherwise, all that the prosecution would be required to
			<lb />
			do is to file a charge sheet against the accused under the provisions
			<lb />
			of the said Act and then claim that the evidence of the prosecution
			<lb />
			witnesses would have to be accepted as gospel truth and further that
			<lb />
			the entire burden would be on the accused to prove to the contrary.
			<lb />
			Such a position of law or interpretation of the presumption under
			<lb />
			Section 29 of the POCSO Act cannot be accepted as it would clearly
			<lb />
			violate the constitutional mandate that no person shall be deprived
			<lb />
			of liberty except in accordance with procedure established by law.&quot;
			<lb />
			* * * * * *
			<lb />
			&quot;24. The above quoted views of the Courts elucidate the position of
			<lb />
			law insofar as presumption under Section 29 of the POCSO Act is
			<lb />
			concerned. It becomes clear that although the provision states that
			<lb />
			the Court shall presume that the accused has committed the offence
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			2018 SCC OnLine Bom 1281
			<lb />
			12
			<lb />
		</note>
		<note place="footnote">
			BAIL APPL. No. 1559/2020
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page
			<lb />
			23 of 45
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			for which he is charged under the POCSO Act, unless the contrary is
			<lb />
			proved, the presumption would operate only upon the prosecution
			<lb />
			first proving foundational facts against the accused, beyond
			<lb />
			reasonable doubt. Unless the prosecution is able to prove
			<lb />
			foundational facts in the context of the allegations made against the
			<lb />
			accused under the POCSO Act, the presumption under Section 29 of
			<lb />
			the said Act would not operate against the accused. Even if the
			<lb />
			prosecution establishes such facts and the presumption is raised
			<lb />
			against the accused, he can rebut the same either by discrediting
			<lb />
			prosecution witnesses through cross-examination demonstrating
			<lb />
			that the prosecution case is improbable or absurd or the accused
			<lb />
			could lead evidence to prove his defence, in order to rebut the
			<lb />
			presumption. In either case, the accused is required to rebut the
			<lb />
			presumption on the touchstone of preponderance of probability.&quot;
			<lb />
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
			d. In Joy V.S. vs. State of Kerala , the Kerala High Court has
			<lb />
			13
			<lb />
			observed as under:
			<lb />
			&quot;10. This court is not oblivious to Section 29 of the Act which
			<lb />
			contains a legislative mandate that the court shall presume
			<lb />
			commission of the offences by the accused unless the contrary is
			<lb />
			proved. Section 29 of the Act states that where a person is
			<lb />
			prosecuted for committing or abetting or attempting to commit any
			<lb />
			offence under Sections 3, 5, 7 and 9 of the Act, the Special Court
			<lb />
			shall presume, that such person has committed or abetted or
			<lb />
			attempted to commit the offence, as the case may be, unless the
			<lb />
			contrary is proved. The court shall take into consideration the
			<lb />
			presumption under Section 29 of the Act while dealing with an
			<lb />
			application for bail filed by a person who is accused of the aforesaid
			<lb />
			offences under the Act (See State of Bihar v. Rajballav Prasad,
			<lb />
			(2017) 2 SCC 178 : AIR 2017 SC 630).
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			2019 SCC OnLine Ker 783
			<lb />
			13
			<lb />
		</note>
		<note place="footnote">
			BAIL APPL. No. 1559/2020
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page
			<lb />
			24 of 45
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			&quot;11. However, the statutory presumption under Section 29 of the Act
			<lb />
			does not mean that the prosecution version has to be accepted as
			<lb />
			gospel truth in every case. The presumption does not mean that the
			<lb />
			court cannot take into consideration the special features of a
			<lb />
			particular case. Patent absurdities or inherent infirmities or
			<lb />
			improbabilities in the prosecution version may lead to an irresistible
			<lb />
			inference of falsehood in the prosecution case. The presumption
			<lb />
			would come into play only when the prosecution is able to bring on
			<lb />
			record facts that would form the foundation for the presumption.
			<lb />
			Otherwise, all that the prosecution would be required to do is to
			<lb />
			raise some allegations against the accused and to claim that the
			<lb />
			case projected by it is true. The courts must be on guard to see that
			<lb />
			the application of the presumption, without adverting to essential
			<lb />
			facts, shall not lead to any injustice. The presumption under Section
			<lb />
			29 of the Act is not absolute. The statutory presumption would get
			<lb />
			activated or triggered only if the prosecution proves the essential
			<lb />
			basic facts. If the accused is able to create serious doubt on the
			<lb />
			veracity of the prosecution case or the accused brings on record
			<lb />
			materials which would render the prosecution version highly
			<lb />
			improbable, the presumption would get weakened. As held by the
			<lb />
			Apex Court in Siddharam Satlingappa Mhetre v. State of
			<lb />
			Maharashtra , frivolity in prosecution should always be
			<lb />
			14
			<lb />
			considered and in the event of there being some doubt as to the
			<lb />
			genuineness of the prosecution, in the normal course of events, the
			<lb />
			accused is entitled to an order of anticipatory bail. No inflexible
			<lb />
			guidelines or straitjacket formula can be provided for grant or
			<lb />
			refusal of anticipatory bail. It should necessarily depend on facts
			<lb />
			and circumstances of each case in consonance with the legislative
			<lb />
			intention.&quot;
			<lb />
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
			50. Drawing from the verdict of the Supreme Court and the views taken
			<lb />
			by the various High Courts in the above cases, in essence, the position
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			(2011) 1 SCC 694
			<lb />
			14
			<lb />
		</note>
		<note place="footnote">
			BAIL APPL. No. 1559/2020
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page
			<lb />
			25 of 45
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			is that to rebut a presumption, first, the presumptive proposition must
			<lb />
			itself be formulated based on relevant and credible material ; and
			<lb />
			second, the accused must know what presumption he has to rebut. It is
			<lb />
			not enough to say that the accused has been implicated by the police
			<lb />
			on charges under sections 3, 5, 7, and/or 9 of the POSCO Act. At the
			<lb />
			very least, the charges should have been framed by court against the
			<lb />
			accused under one or more of those sections for the presumption to
			<lb />
			arise; and mere implication by the police is not enough.
			<lb />
			51. Only when the trial court frames charges, does it form a prima facie
			<lb />
			opinion that there is a case for the accused to answer and defend. At
			<lb />
			the stage of framing charges, the trial court may decide not to frame
			<lb />
			charges against an accused under any of the sections mentioned in
			<lb />
			section 29 but under some other provision; or, it may not frame
			<lb />
			charges against all accused persons under those sections. So, the
			<lb />
			presumption under section 29 cannot arise before charges are framed.
			<lb />
			52. If the presumption of guilt is taken to arise even before charges are
			<lb />
			framed, say when a court is considering a bail application, then the
			<lb />
			court will have to afford to the accused an opportunity to prove that he
			<lb />
			has not committed the offence; which would require the court to
			<lb />
			conduct a mini-trial, even when it is only considering a bail plea.
			<lb />
			What then would remain to be done during the trial itself ? In the
			<lb />
			opinion of this court it is not the purport of section 29 that a mini-trial
			<lb />
			should be conducted at the stage of deciding a bail application. No
			<lb />
			such concept is known to law. Requiring production and analysis of
			<lb />
			evidence to form an opinion on the merits of the allegations; and to
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			BAIL APPL. No. 1559/2020
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page
			<lb />
			26 of 45
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			express a view on such evidence, is certainly not within the remit of a
			<lb />
			court considering a bail plea.
			<lb />
			53. Since reasoning is the soul of every adjudicatory process, if a court
			<lb />
			were to give reasons and express an opinion as to whether an accused
			<lb />
			had succeeded or failed to rebut the presumption of guilt when
			<lb />
			hearing a bail plea, even if on a prima facie consideration, it would
			<lb />
			prejudice the trial itself.
			<lb />
			54. Let us consider section 29 from another perspective. Let us assume
			<lb />
			that the presumption of guilt contained in section 29 applies from the
			<lb />
			stage of registration of the FIR itself. Let us assume that an accused is
			<lb />
			told that the moment an FIR under the specific provisions indicated in
			<lb />
			section 29 is registered, he is presumed to be guilty; and then let us
			<lb />
			tell him that he, of course, has a right to rebut the presumption. Would
			<lb />
			the court then allow the accused to marshal defence evidence even
			<lb />
			before charges are framed at the stage of considering his bail plea ?
			<lb />
			To demand that an accused lead defence evidence even before charges
			<lb />
			are framed and even before prosecution evidence is led, would be
			<lb />
			anathema to fundamental criminal jurisprudence. It would be
			<lb />
			anathema to his right of silence. It would also be anathema to the
			<lb />
			principle that the prosecution must first establish the foundational
			<lb />
			facts constituting the charge, as held by the Supreme Court and the
			<lb />
			High Courts in the decisions cited above. Besides, by invoking the
			<lb />
			presumption of guilt under section 29 before charges are framed, we
			<lb />
			would be enforcing only a half-portion of section 29, viz. the
			<lb />
			presumption of guilt, while ignoring the remaining half, viz. by not
			<lb />
			affording to the accused the opportunity to rebut the presumption.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			BAIL APPL. No. 1559/2020
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page
			<lb />
			27 of 45
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			Would such interpretation or application of section 29 pass
			<lb />
			constitutional muster ?
			<lb />
			55. In a long line of decisions after Maneka Gandhi vs. Union of India
			<lb />
			&amp; Anr. , the Supreme Court has consistently held that &apos;law&apos; as
			<lb />
			15
			<lb />
			interpreted under Article 21 of the Constitution is more than mere
			<lb />
			&apos;lex&apos;; and that it implies due process, both procedural and substantive.
			<lb />
			It has been held that unless the law depriving a person of his life or
			<lb />
			personal liberty is reasonable, just and fair, it would not pass
			<lb />
			constitutional muster ; and that it is not enough for the law to provide
			<lb />
			any procedure or only a semblance of procedure.
			<lb />
			56. Following this sacrosanct constitutional principle, in its recent
			<lb />
			decision in Nikesh Tarachand Shah vs. Union of India &amp; Anr. ,
			<lb />
			16
			<lb />
			while striking down section 45 of the Prevention of Money
			<lb />
			Laundering Act 2002 as being unconstitutional since it inter alia
			<lb />
			imposed a condition that before granting bail the court must be
			<lb />
			satisfied that there are reasonable grounds for believing that the
			<lb />
			accused is not guilty of the offence, our Supreme Court had this to
			<lb />
			say:
			<lb />
			&quot;24. Article 21 is the Ark of the Covenant so far as the Fundamental
			<lb />
			Rights Chapter of the Constitution is concerned. It deals with nothing less
			<lb />
			sacrosanct than the rights of life and personal liberty of the citizens of
			<lb />
			India and other persons. It is the only article in the Fundamental Rights
			<lb />
			Chapter (along with Article 20) that cannot be suspended even in an
			<lb />
			emergency [see Article 359(1) of the Constitution]. At present, Article 21
			<lb />
			is the repository of a vast number of substantive and procedural rights
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			(1978) 1 SCC 248
			<lb />
			15
			<lb />
		</note>
		<note place="footnote">
			(2018) 11 SCC 1
			<lb />
			16
			<lb />
		</note>
		<note place="footnote">
			BAIL APPL. No. 1559/2020
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			28 45
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			post Maneka Gandhi v. Union of India. Thus, in Rajesh Kumar at pp.
			<lb />
			17
			<lb />
			724-26, this Court held: (SCC paras 56-63)
			<lb />
			* * * * *
			<lb />
			58. This epoch-making decision in Maneka Gandhi has substantially
			<lb />
			infused the concept of due process in our constitutional
			<lb />
			jurisprudence whenever the court has to deal with a question
			<lb />
			affecting life and liberty of citizens or even a person. Krishna Iyer, J.
			<lb />
			giving a concurring opinion in Maneka Gandhi elaborated, in his
			<lb />
			inimitable style, the transition from the phase of the rule of law to
			<lb />
			due process of law. The relevant statement of law given by the
			<lb />
			learned Judge is quoted below: (SCC p. 337, para 81)
			<lb />
			&apos;81. … &quot;Procedure established by law&quot;, with its lethal
			<lb />
			potentiality, will reduce life and liberty to a precarious plaything
			<lb />
			if we do not ex necessitate import into those weighty words an
			<lb />
			adjectival rule of law, civilised in its soul, fair in its heart and
			<lb />
			fixing those imperatives of procedural protection absent which
			<lb />
			the processual tail will wag the substantive head. Can the sacred
			<lb />
			essence of the human right to secure which the struggle for
			<lb />
			liberation, with &quot;do or die&quot; patriotism, was launched be sapped
			<lb />
			by formalistic and pharisaic prescriptions, regardless of essential
			<lb />
			standards? An enacted apparition is a constitutional illusion.
			<lb />
			Processual justice is writ patently on Article 21. It is too grave to
			<lb />
			be circumvented by a black letter ritual processed through the
			<lb />
			legislature.&apos;
			<lb />
			* * * * *
			<lb />
			62. Until the decision was rendered in Maneka Gandhi, Article 21
			<lb />
			was viewed by this Court as rarely embodying the Diceyian concept
			<lb />
			of the rule of law that no one can be deprived of his personal liberty
			<lb />
			by an executive action unsupported by law. If there was a law which
			<lb />
			provided some sort of a procedure it was enough to deprive a person
			<lb />
			of his life or personal liberty. In this connection, if we refer to the
			<lb />
			example given by S.R. Das, J. in his judgment in A.K. Gopalan that
			<lb />
			18
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note plcae="footnote">
			<lb />
			(2011) 13 SCC 706
			<lb />
			17
			<lb />
		</note>
		<note place="footnote">
			AIR 1950 SC 27 : (1950) 51 Cri LJ 1383
			<lb />
			18
			<lb />
		</note>
		<note place="footnote">
			BAIL APPL. No. 1559/2020
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page
			<lb />
			29 of 45
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			if the law provided the Bishop of Rochester &quot;be boiled in oil&quot; it
			<lb />
			would be valid under Article 21. But after the decision in Maneka
			<lb />
			Gandhi which marks a watershed in the development of
			<lb />
			constitutional law in our country, this Court, for the first time, took
			<lb />
			the view that Article 21 affords protection not only against the
			<lb />
			executive action but also against the legislation which deprives a
			<lb />
			person of his life and personal liberty unless the law for
			<lb />
			deprivation is reasonable, just and fair. And it was held that the
			<lb />
			concept of reasonableness runs like a golden thread through the
			<lb />
			entire fabric of the Constitution and it is not enough for the law to
			<lb />
			provide some semblance of a procedure. The procedure for
			<lb />
			depriving a person of his life and personal liberty must be
			<lb />
			eminently just, reasonable and fair and if challenged before the
			<lb />
			court it is for the court to determine whether such procedure is
			<lb />
			reasonable, just and fair and if the court finds that it is not so, the
			<lb />
			court will strike down the same.
			<lb />
			63. Therefore, &quot;law&quot; as interpreted under Article 21 by this Court
			<lb />
			is more than mere &quot;lex&quot;. It implies a due process, both
			<lb />
			procedurally and substantively.&quot;
			<lb />
			* * * * * *
			<lb />
			&quot;43. ..... In fact, the presumption of innocence, which is attached to any
			<lb />
			person being prosecuted of an offence, is inverted by the conditions
			<lb />
			specified in Section 45, whereas for grant of ordinary bail the
			<lb />
			presumption of innocence attaches, after which the various factors set
			<lb />
			out in para 18 of the judgment are to be looked at. Under Section 45, the
			<lb />
			Court must be satisfied that there are reasonable grounds to believe that
			<lb />
			the person is not guilty of such offence and that he is not likely to commit
			<lb />
			any offence while on bail.&quot;
			<lb />
			* * * * *
			<lb />
			&quot;46. We must not forget that Section 45 is a drastic provision which turns
			<lb />
			on its head the presumption of innocence which is fundamental to a person
			<lb />
			accused of any offence. Before application of a section which makes
			<lb />
			drastic inroads into the fundamental right of personal liberty guaranteed
			<lb />
			by Article 21 of the Constitution of India, we must be doubly sure that such
			<lb />
			provision furthers a compelling State interest for tackling serious crime.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			BAIL APPL. No. 1559/2020
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page
			<lb />
			30 of 45
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			Absent any such compelling State interest, the indiscriminate application
			<lb />
			of the provisions of Section 45 will certainly violate Article 21 of the
			<lb />
			Constitution. Provisions akin to Section 45 have only been upheld on the
			<lb />
			ground that there is a compelling State interest in tackling crimes of an
			<lb />
			extremely heinous nature.&quot;
			<lb />
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
			57. Furthermore, looking at the issue from the supervening perspective of
			<lb />
			the right to a fair trial, as guaranteed by the Constitution, the Supreme
			<lb />
			Court has said in Moti Ram &amp; Ors. vs. State of M.P. , that a very
			<lb />
			19
			<lb />
			important consideration for grant of bail is to allow an accused the
			<lb />
			liberty to prepare his defence, so that this right guaranteed under
			<lb />
			Article 21 is real and not merely chimerical. Commenting on the
			<lb />
			consequences of pre-trial detention, in Moti Ram (supra) the Supreme
			<lb />
			Court has said:
			<lb />
			&quot;14. The consequences of pre-trial detention are grave. Defendants
			<lb />
			presumed innocent are subjected to the psychological and physical
			<lb />
			deprivations of jail life, usually under more onerous conditions than are
			<lb />
			imposed on convicted defendants. The jailed defendant loses his job if he
			<lb />
			has one and is prevented from contributing to the preparation of his
			<lb />
			defence. Equally important, the burden of his detention frequently falls
			<lb />
			heavily on the innocent members of his family.&quot;
			<lb />
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
			58. Again, in Babu Singh &amp; Ors. vs. State of U.P. the Supreme Court
			<lb />
			20
			<lb />
			observed :
			<lb />
			&quot;18. We must weigh the contrary factors to answer the test of
			<lb />
			reasonableness, subject to the need for securing the presence of the bail
			<lb />
			applicant. It makes sense to assume that a man on bail has a better chance
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			(1978) 4 SCC 47
			<lb />
			19
			<lb />
		</note>
		<note>
			(1978) 1 SCC 579
			<lb />
			20
			<lb />
		</note>
		<note place="footnote">
			BAIL APPL. No. 1559/2020
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page
			<lb />
			31 of 45
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			to prepare or present his case than one remanded in custody. And if public
			<lb />
			justice is to be promoted, mechanical detention should be demoted. .........
			<lb />
			The considerable public expense in keeping in custody where no danger of
			<lb />
			disappearance or disturbance can arise, is not a negligible consideration.
			<lb />
			Equally important is the deplorable condition, verging on the inhuman, of
			<lb />
			our sub-jails, that the unrewarding cruelty and expensive custody of
			<lb />
			avoidable incarceration makes refusal of bail unreasonable and a policy
			<lb />
			favouring release justly sensible.&quot;
			<lb />
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
			59. However, if at the stage of considering a bail plea even before charges
			<lb />
			are framed, a court is to form an opinion on the merits of the
			<lb />
			evidence, what then would be the purpose of granting bail to an
			<lb />
			accused to prepare his defence for a fair trial ? It must also be
			<lb />
			pointed-out here that the Supreme Court has clearly said in Ash
			<lb />
			Mohammad vs. Shiv Raj Singh &amp; Anr. that when deciding a bail
			<lb />
			21
			<lb />
			plea, the court ought only to be prima facie satisfied as regards the
			<lb />
			charge, meaning thereby that at the stage of considering bail, the court
			<lb />
			is to see if there is evidence in support of the allegations, and not
			<lb />
			proof of evidence. In Ash Mohammad (supra), the Supreme Court says
			<lb />
			this :
			<lb />
			&quot;8. In Ram Govind Upadhyay v. Sudarshan Singh , it has been opined
			<lb />
			22
			<lb />
			that the grant of bail though involves exercise of discretionary power of
			<lb />
			the Court, such exercise of discretion has to be made in a judicious
			<lb />
			manner and not as a matter of course. The heinous nature of the crime
			<lb />
			warrants more caution and there is greater chance of rejection of bail,
			<lb />
			though, however dependent on the factual matrix of the matter. In the said
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			(2012) 9 SCC 446
			<lb />
			21
			<lb />
			(2002) 3 SCC 598
			<lb />
			22
			<lb />
		</note>
		<note place="footnote">
			BAIL APPL. No. 1559/2020
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			32
			
			of
			
			45
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			case the learned Judges referred to the decision in Prahlad Singh Bhati v.
			<lb />
			NCT, Delhi and stated as follows: (Ram Govind case, SCC p. 602, para
			<lb />
			23
			<lb />
			4)
			<lb />
			&quot;(a) While granting bail the court has to keep in mind not only the
			<lb />
			nature of the accusations, but the severity of the punishment, if the
			<lb />
			accusation entails a conviction and the nature of evidence in support
			<lb />
			of the accusations.
			<lb />
			(b) Reasonable apprehensions of the witnesses being tampered with
			<lb />
			or the apprehension of there being a threat for the complainant
			<lb />
			should also weigh with the court in the matter of grant of bail.
			<lb />
			(c) While it is not expected to have the entire evidence establishing
			<lb />
			the guilt of the accused beyond reasonable doubt but there ought
			<lb />
			always to be a prima facie satisfaction of the court in support of
			<lb />
			the charge.
			<lb />
			(d) Frivolity in prosecution should always be considered and it is
			<lb />
			only the element of genuineness that shall have to be considered in
			<lb />
			the matter of grant of bail, and in the event of there being some
			<lb />
			doubt as to the genuineness of the prosecution, in the normal course
			<lb />
			of events, the accused is entitled to an order of bail.&quot;
			<lb />
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
			60. Furthermore, in CBI vs. V. Vijay Sai Reddy the Supreme Court has
			<lb />
			24
			<lb />
			held as under :
			<lb />
			&quot;34. While granting bail, the court has to keep in mind the nature of
			<lb />
			accusations, the nature of evidence in support thereof, the severity of the
			<lb />
			punishment which conviction will entail, the character of the accused,
			<lb />
			circumstances which are peculiar to the accused, reasonable possibility of
			<lb />
			securing the presence of the accused at the trial, reasonable apprehension
			<lb />
			of the witnesses being tampered with, the larger interests of the public/
			<lb />
			State and other similar considerations. It has also to be kept in mind that
			<lb />
			for the purpose of granting bail, the legislature has used the words
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			(2001) 4 SCC 280
			<lb />
			23
			<lb />
			(2013) 7 SCC 452
			<lb />
			24
			<lb />
		</note>
		<note place="footnote">
			BAIL APPL. No. 1559/2020
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page
			<lb />
			33 of 45
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			&quot;reasonable grounds for believing&quot; instead of &quot;the evidence&quot; which
			<lb />
			means the court dealing with the grant of bail can only satisfy itself as to
			<lb />
			whether there is a genuine case against the accused and that the
			<lb />
			prosecution will be able to produce prima facie evidence in support of the
			<lb />
			charge. It is not expected, at this stage, to have the evidence establishing
			<lb />
			the guilt of the accused beyond reasonable doubt.&quot;
			<lb />
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
			61. Having discussed the application of section 29 at the pre-charge stage
			<lb />
			above, this court must now examine as to what is the position of
			<lb />
			application of section 29 to a stage after charges are framed.
			<lb />
			62. On this point, reference may be made to the decision of the Supreme
			<lb />
			Court in State of Bihar vs. Rajballav Prasad , in which case while
			<lb />
			25
			<lb />
			dealing with a post-charge stage, the Supreme Court has said that
			<lb />
			when deciding the question of bail under the POCSO Act, the
			<lb />
			paramount consideration should be the reasonable apprehension as to
			<lb />
			whether the accused would tamper with evidence or interfere in trial
			<lb />
			or flee from justice but the Supreme Court goes on to say that section
			<lb />
			29 should also be considered, in the following words:
			<lb />
			&quot;Dr A.K. Sikri, J.-The respondent herein is facing trial in Mahila Police
			<lb />
			Station Case No. 15 of 2016, wherein he is charged for committing
			<lb />
			offences under Sections 376, 420/34, 366-A, 370, 370-A, 212, 120-B of the
			<lb />
			Penal Code, 1860, Sections 4, 6 and 8 of the Protection of Children from
			<lb />
			Sexual Offences Act, 2012 (&quot;the Pocso Act&quot;, for short) as well as Sections
			<lb />
			4, 5 and 6 of the Immoral Traffic (Prevention) Act, 1956. He is one of the
			<lb />
			co-accused in the said trial. ..... During investigation, the respondent was
			<lb />
			identified as the main accused having committed the rape on the said
			<lb />
			minor. ........ After conclusion of the investigation, charge-sheet in the case
			<lb />
			was filed on 20-4-2016 and the charges were framed on 6-8-2016.&quot;
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			(2017) 2 SCC 178
			<lb />
			25
			<lb />
		</note>
		<note place="footnote">
			BAIL APPL. No. 1559/2020
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page
			<lb />
			34  of
			45
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			* * * * *
			<lb />
			&quot;20. It has also come on record that the prosecutrix and her family
			<lb />
			members made representations claiming that the respondent is threatening
			<lb />
			the family members of the prosecutrix. So much so, having regard to
			<lb />
			several complaints of intimidation of the witnesses made on behalf of the
			<lb />
			prosecutrix and her family members, the State administration has deputed
			<lb />
			a force of 1 + 4 for the safety and security of the prosecutrix and her
			<lb />
			family.
			<lb />
			&quot;21. In spite of the aforesaid material on record, the High Court has made
			<lb />
			casual and cryptic remarks that there is no material showing that the
			<lb />
			accused had interfered with the trial by tampering evidence. On the other
			<lb />
			hand, it has discussed the merits of the case/evidence which was not called
			<lb />
			for at this stage. No doubt, in a particular case if it appears to the court
			<lb />
			that the case foisted against the accused is totally false, that may become a
			<lb />
			relevant factor while considering the bail application. However, it can
			<lb />
			(sic, cannot) be said at this stage that the present case falls in this
			<lb />
			category. That would be a matter of trial. Therefore, the paramount
			<lb />
			consideration should have been as is pointed out above, whether there are
			<lb />
			any chances of the accused person fleeing from justice or reasonable
			<lb />
			apprehension that the accused person would tamper with the evidence/
			<lb />
			trial if released on bail. These aspects are not dealt with by the High
			<lb />
			Court appropriately and with the seriousness they deserved. This
			<lb />
			constitutes a sufficient reason for interfering with the exercise of discretion
			<lb />
			by the High Court.
			<lb />
			&quot;22. The High Court also ignored another vital aspect, namely, while
			<lb />
			rejecting the bail application of the co-accused, the High Court had
			<lb />
			ordered expeditious, nay, day-to-day trial to ensure that the trial comes to
			<lb />
			an end most expeditiously. When order had already been passed to fast
			<lb />
			track the trial, and the application for bail by the co-accused Sandeep
			<lb />
			Suman alias Pushpanjay was also rejected, the High Court, while
			<lb />
			considering the bail application of the respondent, was supposed to take
			<lb />
			into consideration this material fact as well. Further, while making a
			<lb />
			general statement of law that the accused is innocent, till proved guilty,
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			BAIL APPL. No. 1559/2020
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page
			<lb />
			35 of 45
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			the provisions of Section 29 of the POCSO Act have not been taken into
			<lb />
			consideration, which reads follows:
			<lb />
			* * * * * &quot;
			<lb />
			&quot;23. Keeping in view all the aforesaid considerations in mind, we are of
			<lb />
			the opinion that it was not a fit case for grant of bail to the respondent at
			<lb />
			this stage and grave error is committed by the High Court in this
			<lb />
			behalf. .....&quot;
			<lb />
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
			63. It is pertinent to notice therefore, that in Rajballav Prasad (supra)
			<lb />
			since charges had already been framed, the Supreme Court took
			<lb />
			section 29 into account.
			<lb />
			Conclusions &amp; decision :
			<lb />
			64. As held by the Supreme Court in Hardeep Singh (supra), since &apos;trial&apos;
			<lb />
			commences when charges are framed against an accused and not
			<lb />
			before that, it is clear that only at the stage when charges are framed
			<lb />
			does the court apply its judicial mind to whether there is enough
			<lb />
			evidence on record to frame a precise allegation, which the accused
			<lb />
			must answer. Therefore, it is only once charges are framed that the
			<lb />
			accused knows exactly what he is alleged to be guilty of; and
			<lb />
			therefore, what guilt he is required to rebut.
			<lb />
			65. Since a negative cannot be proved, an accused cannot be asked to
			<lb />
			disprove his guilt even before the foundational allegations with
			<lb />
			supporting evidence that suggest guilt are placed by the prosecution
			<lb />
			before the court. To be sure, at the stage of framing charges, what is
			<lb />
			seen is if there is evidence (documentary, electronic, oral) on record,
			<lb />
			not proof of such evidence.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			BAIL APPL. No. 1559/2020
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page
			<lb />
			36 of 45
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			66. That section 29 has been engrafted in the POCSO Act does not mean
			<lb />
			that the presumption of innocence, which is a foundational tenet of
			<lb />
			criminal jurisprudence, is to be thrown to the winds. If section 29 is so
			<lb />
			interpreted as to apply it to the stage even before charges are framed,
			<lb />
			it would not pass constitutional muster since Article 21 of our
			<lb />
			Constitution requires that all substantive as well as procedural
			<lb />
			provisions must be reasonable, just and fair, as held inter alia in
			<lb />
			Maneka Gandhi (supra). Such interpretation of section 29 would also
			<lb />
			render the right of the accused to a fair trial nugatory and dead letter,
			<lb />
			which would again do violence to the constitutional guarantee
			<lb />
			contained in Article 21.
			<lb />
			67. Applying section 29 to bail proceedings at a stage before charges are
			<lb />
			framed, would in effect mean that the accused must prove that he has
			<lb />
			not committed the offence even before he is told the precise offence he
			<lb />
			is charged with, which would do violence to all legal rationality.
			<lb />
			68. In view of the above discussion and after considering the opinion of
			<lb />
			the Supreme Court and the views taken by the other High Courts, this
			<lb />
			court is persuaded to hold that the presumption of guilt engrafted in
			<lb />
			section 29 gets triggered and applies only once trial begins, that is
			<lb />
			after charges are framed against the accused but not before that. The
			<lb />
			significance of the opening words of section 29 &quot;where a person is
			<lb />
			prosecuted&quot; is that until charges are framed, the person is not being
			<lb />
			prosecuted but is being investigated or is in the process of being
			<lb />
			charged. Accordingly, if a bail plea is considered at any stage prior to
			<lb />
			framing of charges, section 29 has no application since upto that stage
			<lb />
			an accused is not being prosecuted.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			BAIL APPL. No. 1559/2020
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page
			<lb />
			37 of 45
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			69. Therefore, if a bail plea is being considered before charges have been
			<lb />
			framed, section 29 has no application ; and the grant or refusal of bail
			<lb />
			is to be decided on the usual and ordinary settled principles.
			<lb />
			70. Now coming to a scenario where a bail plea is being considered at a
			<lb />
			stage after charges have been framed, in keeping with the
			<lb />
			observations of the Supreme Court in Rajballav Prasad (supra), the
			<lb />
			presumption of guilt contained in section 29 would get triggered and
			<lb />
			will have to be &quot;taken into consideration&quot;.
			<lb />
			71. However, the dilemma would remain as to how the presumption of
			<lb />
			guilt contained in section 29 is to be applied even after charges have
			<lb />
			been framed, when the accused has not been given the opportunity to
			<lb />
			rebut such presumption. When section 29 engrafts the presumption of
			<lb />
			guilt against the accused, it also affords an opportunity to the accused
			<lb />
			to rebut the presumption by proving to the contrary. It cannot possibly
			<lb />
			be that the court should invoke half the provision of section 29 while
			<lb />
			ignoring the other half, much less to the detriment of the accused.
			<lb />
			But even after charges are framed, the accused does not get the
			<lb />
			opportunity to rebut the presumption or to prove the contrary by
			<lb />
			leading defence evidence, until prosecution evidence is concluded. It
			<lb />
			would be anathema to fundamental criminal jurisprudence to ask the
			<lb />
			accused to disclose his defence; or, worse still, to adduce evidence in
			<lb />
			his defence even before the prosecution has marshalled its evidence.
			<lb />
			Again therefore, even for a stage after charges have been framed,
			<lb />
			section 29 cannot be applied in absolute terms to a bail plea without
			<lb />
			doing violence to the &apos;due process&apos; and &apos;fair trial&apos; tenets read into
			<lb />
			Article 21 of our Constitution.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			BAIL APPL. No. 1559/2020
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page
			<lb />
			38 of 45
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			72. It is a settled constitutional principle that, if there are two possible
			<lb />
			interpretations or applications, a statutory provision must be
			<lb />
			interpreted or applied in a way that preserves its constitutional
			<lb />
			validity rather than one that renders it unconstitutional (cf. Kedar
			<lb />
			Nath Singh vs. State of Bihar ).
			<lb />
			26
			<lb />
			73. Another significant legal principle which we must not omit to
			<lb />
			consider, is that if a penal provision, whether substantive or
			<lb />
			procedural, is susceptible to two interpretations, it must be construed
			<lb />
			strictly, narrowly and in a manner that is favourable to the accused (cf.
			<lb />
			Bijaya Kumar Agarwala vs. State of Orissa ).
			<lb />
			27
			<lb />
			74. As always, when faced with such dilemma, the court must apply the
			<lb />
			golden principle of balancing rights. In the opinion of this court
			<lb />
			therefore, at the stage of considering a bail plea after charges have
			<lb />
			been framed, the impact of section 29 would only be to raise the
			<lb />
			threshold of satisfaction required before a court grants bail. What
			<lb />
			this means is that the court would consider the evidence placed by the
			<lb />
			prosecution along with the charge-sheet, provided it is admissible in
			<lb />
			law, more favorably for the prosecution and evaluate, though without
			<lb />
			requiring proof of evidence, whether the evidence so placed is
			<lb />
			credible or whether it ex facie appears that the evidence will not
			<lb />
			sustain the weight of guilt.
			<lb />
			75. If the court finds that the evidence adduced by the prosecution is
			<lb />
			admissible and ex facie credible, and proving it during trial is more a
			<lb />
			1962 Supp (2) SCR 769: para 26 ; Constitution Bench
			<lb />
			26
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			(1996) 5 SCC 1: paras 17, 18
			<lb />
			27
			<lb />
		</note>
		<note place="footnote">
			BAIL APPL. No. 1559/2020
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page
			<lb />
			39 of 45
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			matter of legal formality, it may decide not to grant bail. If, on the
			<lb />
			other hand, the court finds that the evidence before it, is either
			<lb />
			inadmissible or, is such that even if proved, it will not bring home
			<lb />
			guilt upon the accused, it would grant bail.
			<lb />
			76. In a given case, the accused may, of his own volition, be willing to
			<lb />
			disclose his defence even while arguing for bail, to prevail upon the
			<lb />
			court; in which case, the task of the court would become easier. If
			<lb />
			however, the accused decides not to disclose his evidence at that
			<lb />
			stage, he would suffer the consequences of the presumption of guilt
			<lb />
			engrafted in section 29.
			<lb />
			77. Though the heinousness of the offence alleged will beget the length of
			<lb />
			sentence after trial, in order to give due weightage to the intent and
			<lb />
			purpose of the Legislature in engrafting section 29 in this special
			<lb />
			statute to protect children from sexual offences, while deciding a bail
			<lb />
			plea at the post-charge stage, in addition to the nature and quality of
			<lb />
			the evidence before it, the court would also factor in certain real life
			<lb />
			considerations, illustrated below, which would tilt the balance
			<lb />
			against or in favour of the accused :
			<lb />
			a. the age of the minor victim : the younger the victim, the more
			<lb />
			heinous the offence alleged;
			<lb />
			b. the age of the accused : the older the accused, the more heinous
			<lb />
			the offence alleged;
			<lb />
			c. the comparative age of the victim and the accused : the more
			<lb />
			their age difference, the more the element of perversion in the
			<lb />
			offence alleged;
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			BAIL APPL. No. 1559/2020
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page
			<lb />
			40 of 45
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			d. the familial relationship, if any, between the victim and the
			<lb />
			accused : the closer such relationship, the more odious the
			<lb />
			offence alleged;
			<lb />
			e. whether the offence alleged involved threat, intimidation,
			<lb />
			violence and/or brutality;
			<lb />
			f. the conduct of the accused after the offence, as alleged;
			<lb />
			g. whether the offence was repeated against the victim; or whether
			<lb />
			the accused is a repeat offender under the POCSO Act or
			<lb />
			otherwise;
			<lb />
			h. whether the victim and the accused are so placed that the
			<lb />
			accused would have easy access to the victim, if enlarged on
			<lb />
			bail : the more the access, greater the reservation in granting
			<lb />
			bail;
			<lb />
			i. the comparative social standing of the victim and the accused :
			<lb />
			this would give insight into whether the accused is in a
			<lb />
			dominating position to subvert the trial;
			<lb />
			j. whether the offence alleged was perpetrated when the victim
			<lb />
			and the accused were at an age of innocence : an innocent,
			<lb />
			though unholy, physical alliance may be looked at with less
			<lb />
			severity;
			<lb />
			k. whether it appears there was tacit approval-in-fact, though not
			<lb />
			consent-in-law, for the offence alleged;
			<lb />
			l. whether the offence alleged was committed alone or along with
			<lb />
			other persons, acting in a group or otherwise;
			<lb />
			m. other similar real-life considerations.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			BAIL APPL. No. 1559/2020
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page
			<lb />
			41 of 45
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			The above factors are some cardinal considerations, though far
			<lb />
			from exhaustive, that would guide the court in assessing the
			<lb />
			egregiousness of the offence alleged ; and in deciding which way the
			<lb />
			balance would tilt. At the end of the day however, considering the
			<lb />
			myriad facets and nuances of real-life situations, it is impossible to
			<lb />
			cast in stone all considerations for grant or refusal of bail in light of
			<lb />
			section 29. The grant or denial of bail will remain, as always, in the
			<lb />
			subjective satisfaction of a court; except that in view of section 29,
			<lb />
			when a bail plea is being considered after charges have been framed,
			<lb />
			the above additional factors should be considered.
			<lb />
			78. It goes without saying that while considering a bail plea at any stage,
			<lb />
			whether before or after framing of charges, the court would of course
			<lb />
			apply all the other well settled principles and parameters for grant or
			<lb />
			denial of bail.
			<lb />
			79. It is important to state here that the aforesaid considerations are only
			<lb />
			to be applied while deciding a bail plea and may not have a bearing
			<lb />
			on the merits of the case.
			<lb />
			80. Since in the matter under consideration, charges have already been
			<lb />
			framed, section 29 of the POCSO Act will apply. Accordingly it is
			<lb />
			necessary to evaluate how the illustrative considerations indicated
			<lb />
			above apply in this case.
			<lb />
			81. In the facts of the present case, what weighs with the court is that:
			<lb />
			i. for one, the age difference between the complainant and
			<lb />
			the applicant is about 4-5 years. But more importantly,
			<lb />
			both were at an age when a reciprocal physical relationship
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			BAIL APPL. No. 1559/2020
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page
			<lb />
			42 of 45
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			between two not so young, though not fully mature,
			<lb />
			persons cannot be ruled-out;
			<lb />
			ii. next, there appears to be very little to support any
			<lb />
			allegation of serious violence or injury, that would betray
			<lb />
			brutality in the offence alleged ;
			<lb />
			iii. next, the complainant appears to have returned to the
			<lb />
			applicant time-and-again and to have lived with the
			<lb />
			applicant for periods of time at his house along with his
			<lb />
			mother, which again betrays approval-in-fact, if not
			<lb />
			consent-in-law, on her part for the acts alleged;
			<lb />
			iv. next, charges have already been framed and complainant&apos;s
			<lb />
			deposition is well underway. But due to the restricted
			<lb />
			functioning of courts by reason of the prevailing
			<lb />
			coronavirus pandemic, it is unlikely that trial will be
			<lb />
			completed anytime soon;
			<lb />
			v. next, there is no allegation that the offence alleged was
			<lb />
			committed along with any other persons acting in a group
			<lb />
			or otherwise ;
			<lb />
			vi. next, the complainant, though minor, was not of an age
			<lb />
			that she did not understand the act involved. In fact she
			<lb />
			speaks of a marriage of sorts having been conducted
			<lb />
			between the two in the presence of the applicant&apos;s mother;
			<lb />
			vii. next, the applicant is not a repeat offender nor does he
			<lb />
			have any prior or other criminal involvement; and
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			BAIL APPL. No. 1559/2020
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page
			<lb />
			43 	of 45
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			viii. lastly, there is no allegation of any threat having been
			<lb />
			extended by or on the applicant&apos;s behalf between the
			<lb />
			registration of the FIR on 14.10.2018 and the date of his
			<lb />
			arrest on 17.11.2018.
			<lb />
			82. Upon a conspectus of the foregoing facts and circumstances, applying
			<lb />
			the above principles and the opinion of this court as to the
			<lb />
			applicability of section 29 of the POCSO Act, this court is persuaded
			<lb />
			to admit the applicant to regular bail, on the following conditions :
			<lb />
			a. The applicant shall furnish a personal bond in the sum of Rs.
			<lb />
			30,000/-(Rupees Thirty Thousand) with 01 surety in the like
			<lb />
			amount from the applicant&apos;s mother, to the satisfaction of the
			<lb />
			trial court ;
			<lb />
			b. The applicant shall furnish to the Investigating Officer/S.H.O. a
			<lb />
			cell phone number on which the applicant may be contacted at
			<lb />
			any time and shall ensure that the number is kept active and
			<lb />
			switched-on at all times;
			<lb />
			c. If the applicant has a passport, he shall also surrender the same
			<lb />
			to the trial court ;
			<lb />
			d. The applicant shall not contact, nor visit, nor offer any
			<lb />
			inducement threat or promise to the first informant/
			<lb />
			complainant or to any of the prosecution witnesses. The
			<lb />
			applicant shall not tamper with evidence nor otherwise indulge
			<lb />
			in any act or omission that is unlawful or that would prejudice
			<lb />
			the proceedings in the pending trial.
			<lb />
			83. Nothing in this judgment shall be construed as an expression on the
			<lb />
			merits of the evidence in the pending trial.
			<lb />
			84. The bail application is disposed of in the above terms.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			BAIL APPL. No. 1559/2020
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page
			<lb />
			44 of 45
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			85. Other pending applications, if any, also stand disposed of.
			<lb />
			86. A copy of this judgment be sent to the concerned Jail Superintendent.
			<lb />
			ANUP JAIRAM BHAMBHANI, J.
			<lb />
			22 nd SEPTEMBER 2020
			<lb />
			j/Ne/uj
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			BAIL APPL. No. 1559/2020
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page
			<lb />
			45 of 45
		</page>
	</text>
</tei>
