<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			IN THE HIGH COURT OF DELHI AT NEW DELHI
			<lb />
			% Judgment Reserved on: September 06, 2012
			<lb />
			Judgment Pronounced on: September 12, 2012
			<lb />
			+ FAO(OS) 429/2012
			<lb />
			BHARAT HEAVY ELECTRICALS LTD. ..... Appellant
			<lb />
			Represented by: Mr.A.S.Chandhiok, Sr.Adv.,
			<lb />
			Mr.Sandeep Sethi, Sr.Adv. instructed by
			<lb />
			Mr.Kamaljeet Singh, Mr.Bhagat Singh, Mr.Vidit
			<lb />
			Gupta, Ms.Harleen Singh, Mr.Akshay Palavi,
			<lb />
			Mr.Prashant Mehta, Advs.
			<lb />
			versus
			<lb />
			MASS GLOBAL INVESTMENT CO &amp; ORS ..... Respondents
			<lb />
			Represented by: Mr.C.A.Sundaram, Sr.Adv.,
			<lb />
			Mr.Neeraj Kishan Kaul, Sr.Adv. instructed by
			<lb />
			Ms.Divya Kapur, Ms.Manjira Dasgupta, Adv. for
			<lb />
			respondent No.1.
			<lb />
			Mr.S.L.Gupta, Adv. for State Bank of India.
			<lb />
			AND
			<lb />
			FAO(OS) 430/2012
			<lb />
			BHARAT HEAVY ELECTRICALS LTD ..... Appellant
			<lb />
			Represented by: Mr.A.S.Chandhiok, Sr.Adv.,
			<lb />
			Mr.Sandeep Sethi, Sr.Adv. instructed by
			<lb />
			Mr.Kamaljeet Singh, Mr.Bhagat Singh, Mr.Vidit
			<lb />
			Gupta, Ms.Harleen Singh, Mr.Akshay Palavi,
			<lb />
			Mr.Prashant Mehta, Advs.
			<lb />
			versus
			<lb />
			MASS GLOBAL INVESTMENT CO &amp; ORS ..... Respondents
			<lb />
			Represented by: Mr.C.A.Sundaram, Sr.Adv.,
			<lb />
			Mr.Neeraj Kishan Kaul, Sr.Adv. instructed by
			<lb />
			Ms.Divya Kapur, Ms.Manjira Dasgupta, Adv. for
			<lb />
		</front>
		<note place="footnote">
			FAO(OS) 429/2012 &amp; 430/2012
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 1 of 59
			<lb />
		</page>
		<front>
			respondent No.1.
			<lb />
			Mr.S.L.Gupta, Adv. for State Bank of India.
			<lb />
			CORAM:
			<lb />
			HON&apos;BLE MR. JUSTICE PRADEEP NANDRAJOG
			<lb />
			HON&apos;BLE MR. JUSTICE MANMOHAN SINGH
			<lb />
			PRADEEP NANDRAJOG, J.
			<lb />
		</front>
		<body>
			1.
			<lb />
			The requirement of law, while deciding an appeal, is to lay the
			<lb />
			appellate track parallel to the track on which the learned Trial Judge has
			<lb />
			undertaken the journey, and if the destination reached is a place other than
			<lb />
			the one reached by the learned Trial Judge, to highlight the junction from
			<lb />
			where the direction in the track was made; for only then can a reader of the
			<lb />
			appellate opinion understand with clarity, with least time spent, on what
			<lb />
			account the two decisions are at variance.
			<lb />
			2.
			<lb />
			But, we regret our inability to adhere to the aforesaid principle
			<lb />
			of law on account of the reason, as conceded to by learned counsel for the
			<lb />
			parties during arguments in the appeal, the learned Single Judge has not
			<lb />
			noted many facts which were relied upon by the parties and has therefore not
			<lb />
			dealt with the submissions which were advanced, requiring us to have a
			<lb />
			virtual original hearing on the subject of : Whether the appellant was entitled
			<lb />
			to injunct respondent No.2 bank to pay any money to respondent No.1, the
			<lb />
			beneficiary under the two bank guarantees which were to secure repayment
			<lb />
			of the advance received by the appellant from respondent No.1 and one bank
			<lb />
			guarantee to secure due performance of the contract i.e. three bank
			<lb />
			guarantees issued by respondent No.2 in favour of respondent No.1 at the
			<lb />
			asking of the appellant.
			<lb />
			3.
			<lb />
			On March 04, 2007, contract No.4/2000 was executed between
			<lb />
			the appellant and respondent No.1, a company incorporated in Jordan,
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			FAO(OS) 429/2012 &amp; 430/2012
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 2 of 59
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			requiring the appellant to execute, on a turnkey basis, a Gas Turbine Power
			<lb />
			Plant: 4XFr9E at Kurdistan, Iraq.
			<lb />
			4.
			<lb />
			Being a turnkey contract, the appellant had to design the power
			<lb />
			project, supply the equipment, after testing, install the same and thereafter
			<lb />
			commission the plant and operate it for the period specified in the contract at
			<lb />
			the agreed price US$ 117 million. It is not in dispute that by a
			<lb />
			supplementary agreement dated August 04, 2008, scope of work being
			<lb />
			reduced, the price was reduced to US$ 100 million.
			<lb />
			5.
			<lb />
			As the nomenclature of the turnkey contract: &quot;4XFr9E&quot;
			<lb />
			suggests, 4 gas turbine units had to be erected.
			<lb />
			6.
			<lb />
			The contract envisaged a performance guarantee of 10% of the
			<lb />
			value of the contract to be issued to secure due performance of the
			<lb />
			obligations of the appellant under the contract, as also advance payments to
			<lb />
			be made by respondent No.1 to the appellant, return whereof had to be
			<lb />
			secured by means of bank guarantees, as and when advance payments were
			<lb />
			made.
			<lb />
			7.
			<lb />
			Accordingly, at the asking of the appellant, respondent No.2
			<lb />
			issued a bank guarantee to secure due performance of its obligations by the
			<lb />
			appellant under the contract in favour of respondent No.1 in sum of US$
			<lb />
			11.7 million, the relevant part whereof reads as under:-
			<lb />
			&quot;According to the said contract the principal will furnish
			<lb />
			a performance bond for US$ 11,700,000.00 (say US
			<lb />
			dollars eleven million seven hundred thousand only) in
			<lb />
			favour of Messrs Mass Global Investment Co., Jordan
			<lb />
			(The Beneficiary) as security in the event that the
			<lb />
			Principal failed to fulfil his contractual obligations under
			<lb />
			and in conformity with the terms of the Contract.
			<lb />
			At the request of Messrs Bharat Heavy Electricals
			<lb />
			Limited (BHEL), New Delhi, India we State Bank of
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			FAO(OS) 429/2012 &amp; 430/2012
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 3 of 59
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			India, CAG Branch, 11 th Floor, Jawahar Vyapar Bhavan,
			<lb />
			11 th Floor, 1 Tolstoy Marg, New Delhi -110001, India
			<lb />
			(Guarantor) hereby irrevocably undertake to pay to you
			<lb />
			on your first written demand any amount upto USD
			<lb />
			11,700,000.00 (Say US Dollars Eleven Million Seven
			<lb />
			Hundred Thousand only) upon receipt of your written
			<lb />
			request for payment accompanied with your signed
			<lb />
			statement stating:
			<lb />
			(a)
			<lb />
			That the Principal has failed to fulfil their
			<lb />
			obligation in accordance with the conditions of the
			<lb />
			contract, and
			<lb />
			(b)
			<lb />
			The amount which the Principal has failed to
			<lb />
			fulfil.
			<lb />
			(c)
			<lb />
			The Principal has failed to perform or fulfil any
			<lb />
			of the material acts or obligations set forth under the
			<lb />
			contract, despite 30 calendar days notice having elapsed
			<lb />
			and the Principal still failing to remedy failure/defects
			<lb />
			and consequently beneficiary demanding payment of an
			<lb />
			amount of _______________ under the bank guarantee
			<lb />
			no._______________ dated _____________.
			<lb />
			This guarantee shall become effective upon payment of
			<lb />
			US$ 9,000,000.00 (US dollars nine million) to the
			<lb />
			Principal to their account with us.&quot;
			<lb />
			8.
			<lb />
			In terms of the contract, receiving an advance payment in sum
			<lb />
			of US$ 11 million, at the asking of the appellant, respondent No.2 issued a
			<lb />
			bank guarantee dated August 06, 2007 in favour of respondent No.1, the
			<lb />
			relevant term(s) whereof reads as under:-
			<lb />
			&quot;According to the said contract you will make first
			<lb />
			advance payment of US$ 11,000,000.00 (say US dollars
			<lb />
			eleven million only) of which two million has been
			<lb />
			already paid to Messrs Bharat Heavy Electricals Limited
			<lb />
			(BHEL), New Delhi -110003, India in security for the
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			FAO(OS) 429/2012 &amp; 430/2012
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 4 of 59
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			adjustment of the advance payment a guarantee by a bank
			<lb />
			shall be furnished.
			<lb />
			At the request of Messrs Bharat Heavy Electricals
			<lb />
			Limited (BHEL), New Delhi, India we State Bank of
			<lb />
			India, CAG Branch, 11 th Floor, Jawahar Vyapar Bhavan,
			<lb />
			11 th Floor, 1 Tolstoy Marg, New Delhi -110001, India
			<lb />
			(The Guarantor) hereby irrevocably undertake to pay to
			<lb />
			you on your first written demand any amount upto
			<lb />
			USD11,000,000.00 (Say US Dollars Eleven Million
			<lb />
			only) upon receipt of your written request for payment
			<lb />
			accompanied with your signed statement stating:
			<lb />
			(a)
			<lb />
			That the Principal has failed to fulfil their
			<lb />
			obligation for adjustment of the advance payment in
			<lb />
			accordance with the conditions of the contract, and
			<lb />
			(b)
			<lb />
			The amount which the Principal has failed to
			<lb />
			fulfil.
			<lb />
			This guarantee shall become effective upon payment of
			<lb />
			US$ 9,000,000.00 (US dollars nine million) to the
			<lb />
			Principal to their account with us.&quot;
			<lb />
			9.
			<lb />
			Having received a further advance payment in sum of US$
			<lb />
			6,727,265.00, at the asking of the appellant, respondent No.2 issued another
			<lb />
			bank guarantee on December 10, 2007 in favour of respondent No.1, on
			<lb />
			identical terms as the earlier guarantee, except that the value of the guarantee
			<lb />
			was the sum received in advance i.e. US$ 6,727,265.00.
			<lb />
			10.
			<lb />
			With respect to the bank guarantees to secure repayment of the
			<lb />
			advance received by the appellant from respondent No.1, admittedly vide
			<lb />
			amendment made on December 29, 2009, while extending the two bank
			<lb />
			guarantees till March 30, 2010, the value of each guarantee was reduced to
			<lb />
			US$ 2 million.
			<lb />
			11.
			<lb />
			The appellant claims to have not only successfully executed the
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			FAO(OS) 429/2012 &amp; 430/2012
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 5 of 59
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			installation of the four gas turbine units but even commissioning thereof
			<lb />
			after completing testing of the four units on May 11, 2009, June 04, 2009,
			<lb />
			November 19, 2009 and February 26, 2010 and has a grievance that the
			<lb />
			respondent No.1 has not issued the requisite taking over certificate.
			<lb />
			12.
			<lb />
			Respondent No.1 invoked the two bank guarantees pertaining to
			<lb />
			repayment advance vide two identically worded letters dated March 21, 2010
			<lb />
			which read as under:-
			<lb />
			&quot;Dear Sirs,
			<lb />
			Reference
			<lb />
			is
			<lb />
			made
			<lb />
			to
			<lb />
			your
			<lb />
			Guarantee
			<lb />
			No.0999607FG0000699 Dated 6 th of Aug.2007 for
			<lb />
			USD11,000,000.00.
			<lb />
			We Mass Global Investment Co. P.O. Box 546,
			<lb />
			Amman 11953 -Jordan (the Beneficiary) hereby certify:
			<lb />
			1.
			<lb />
			That the Principal M/s Bharat Heavy
			<lb />
			Electricals Limited (BHEL), New Delhi -110 003,
			<lb />
			India has failed to fulfill their obligation for adjustment
			<lb />
			of the advance payment in accordance with the
			<lb />
			conditions of the contract and also that the Principal is in
			<lb />
			breach of his obligation(s) under the underlying
			<lb />
			contract(s); and
			<lb />
			2.
			<lb />
			the amount which the principal has failed to
			<lb />
			fulfil USD2,000,000.00 say USD TWO MILLION only.
			<lb />
			3.
			<lb />
			the respect in which the Principal is in breach is
			<lb />
			in respect of delay in shipping part of required materials
			<lb />
			and goods and not executing part of the services at site in
			<lb />
			accordance with the contract.&quot;
			<lb />
			13.
			<lb />
			It also issued a letter of even date i.e. March 21, 2010 invoking
			<lb />
			the performance guarantee which reads as under:-
			<lb />
			&quot;Dear Sirs,
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			FAO(OS) 429/2012 &amp; 430/2012
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 6 of 59
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			Reference
			<lb />
			is
			<lb />
			made
			<lb />
			to
			<lb />
			your
			<lb />
			Guarantee
			<lb />
			No.0999607FG0000700 Dated 6 th of Aug.2007 for
			<lb />
			USD11,700,000.00.
			<lb />
			We Mass Global Investment Co. P.O. Box 546,
			<lb />
			Amman 11953 -Jordan (the Beneficiary) hereby certify:
			<lb />
			1.
			<lb />
			That the Principal M/s Bharat Heavy
			<lb />
			Electricals Limited (BHEL), New Delhi -110 003,
			<lb />
			India has failed to fulfill their obligation in accordance
			<lb />
			with the conditions of the contract and also that the
			<lb />
			Principal is in breach of his obligation(s) under the
			<lb />
			underlying contract(s), and
			<lb />
			2.
			<lb />
			the amount which the principal has failed to
			<lb />
			fulfil USD11,700,000.00 say USD eleven million seven
			<lb />
			hundred thousand only.
			<lb />
			3.
			<lb />
			the Principal M/s Bharat Heavy Electricals
			<lb />
			Limited (BHEL), New Delhi -110 003, India has failed
			<lb />
			to perform or fulfil any of the material acts or obligations
			<lb />
			set forth under the contract, despite 30 calendar days
			<lb />
			notice having elapsed and the Principal still failing to
			<lb />
			remedy failure/defects and consequently beneficiary
			<lb />
			demanding payment of an amount of USD11,700,000.00
			<lb />
			say USD eleven million seven hundred thousand only
			<lb />
			under the bank guarantee No.0999607FG0000700 dated
			<lb />
			6 th of Aug.2007.
			<lb />
			4.
			<lb />
			the respect in which the Principal is in breach is
			<lb />
			in respect of delay in performing and executing the
			<lb />
			contract/project and also they did not finish the project
			<lb />
			until now.&quot;
			<lb />
			14.
			<lb />
			This led the appellant to file a suit for permanent and mandatory
			<lb />
			injunction to restrain defendant No.2 from making payment under the bank
			<lb />
			guarantees to respondent No.1.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			FAO(OS) 429/2012 &amp; 430/2012
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 7 of 59
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			15.
			<lb />
			Eschewing reference to the prolix pleadings in the plaint and the
			<lb />
			written statement containing the rival versions which led to the delay in
			<lb />
			executing the works and whether or not the owner of the work was justified
			<lb />
			in not taking over the works or whether it was the appellant which had to
			<lb />
			receive money from respondent No.1 for the works executed; pleading fraud
			<lb />
			in invoking the bank guarantees, in para 13 and 14 of the plaint it was
			<lb />
			pleaded as under:-
			<lb />
			&quot;13.
			<lb />
			That the Contract was to be performed in
			<lb />
			relation to 4 Units. Two Units, i.e. Unit 1 and Unit 2 of
			<lb />
			the Project have been commissioned and synchronized
			<lb />
			successfully on 11 May, 2009 and 4 June, 2009
			<lb />
			respectively.
			<lb />
			Unit 3 was commissioned and
			<lb />
			synchronized on 19 November 2009. Unit 4 was
			<lb />
			commissioned and synchronized on 26 February 2010.
			<lb />
			The fact of successful running of all four Units in their
			<lb />
			full capacity, was intimated by the Plaintiff to the
			<lb />
			Defendant No.1 on 10 March 2010.
			<lb />
			14. That as would be evident from the above, the Plaintiff
			<lb />
			herein has complied with its obligations under the
			<lb />
			Contract. However, as would be evident from the
			<lb />
			discussion below, the defendant No.1 herein has been in
			<lb />
			constant violation of its contractual obligations, and has
			<lb />
			also acted in an illegal, mala fide and fraudulent manner,
			<lb />
			causing grave prejudice to the Plaintiff herein.&quot;
			<lb />
			16.
			<lb />
			With respect to the two bank guarantees to secure advance
			<lb />
			payments received by the appellant from respondent No.1, in the context
			<lb />
			whether the guarantees were validly invoked in terms of the guarantees, in
			<lb />
			para 39 of the plaint it is pleaded as under:-
			<lb />
			&quot;39.
			<lb />
			That the terms of the APG1 and APG2
			<lb />
			mandates the Defendant No.1, while demanding money
			<lb />
			from the Defendant No.2, shall provide statements
			<lb />
			stating:
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			FAO(OS) 429/2012 &amp; 430/2012
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 8 of 59
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			&quot;(a) that the Principal has failed to fulfil their
			<lb />
			obligation for adjustment of the advance
			<lb />
			payment in accordance with the conditions of
			<lb />
			the contract, and
			<lb />
			(b) the amount which the Principal has failed to
			<lb />
			fulfill.&quot;
			<lb />
			A bare perusal of the letters written by the Defendant
			<lb />
			No.1 herein to the Defendant No.2, seeking to encash the
			<lb />
			APG1 and APG2, would clearly show that the Defendant
			<lb />
			No.1 herein has failed to meet the above-mentioned
			<lb />
			stipulations.
			<lb />
			Assuming without admitting that the
			<lb />
			Defendant No.1 is entitled to the amounts demanded by it
			<lb />
			under APG1 and APG2, the plaintiff humbly submits that
			<lb />
			the Defendant No.1 has completely failed to indicate let
			<lb />
			alone prove that any of the aforesaid conditions of APG1
			<lb />
			and APG2 have been fulfilled. The statements made by
			<lb />
			the Defendant No.1 are vague, baseless, incorrect and
			<lb />
			have been made in a fraudulent manner, merely with
			<lb />
			malafide attempt to encash the APG1 and APG2
			<lb />
			illegally, to defeat the rights and interest of the Plaintiff
			<lb />
			under the Contract, and to cause grave financial loss to
			<lb />
			the Plaintiff herein. The Plaintiff humbly submits that
			<lb />
			the above-mentioned illegal and malafide action on part
			<lb />
			of the Defendant No.1 herein is not only against the
			<lb />
			provisions of the Contract, but is also impermissible
			<lb />
			under the law, as well as equity.&quot;
			<lb />
			17.
			<lb />
			And with respect to the guarantee pertaining to performance, in
			<lb />
			paragraph 40 of the plaint it is pleaded as under:-
			<lb />
			&quot;40.
			<lb />
			That the terms of PBG clearly states that while
			<lb />
			demanding any amount under the guarantee the
			<lb />
			Defendant No.1 has to provide statements to the
			<lb />
			Defendant No.2 in following terms:
			<lb />
			&quot;(a) That the Principal has failed to fulfill their
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			FAO(OS) 429/2012 &amp; 430/2012
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 9 of 59
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			obligation in accordance with the conditions of
			<lb />
			the contract; and
			<lb />
			(b) the amount which the Principal has failed to
			<lb />
			fulfill.
			<lb />
			(c) the principal has failed to perform or fulfill any
			<lb />
			of the material acts or obligations set forth
			<lb />
			under the contract, despite 30 calendar days
			<lb />
			notice having elapsed and the principal still
			<lb />
			failing to remedy failure/defects and
			<lb />
			consequently beneficiary demanding payment
			<lb />
			of an amount of ____ under the bank guarantee
			<lb />
			No.____ dated _____.&quot;
			<lb />
			A bare perusal of the letters written by the Defendant
			<lb />
			No.1 herein to the Defendant No.2, seeking to encash the
			<lb />
			PBG, would clearly show that the Defendant No.1 herein
			<lb />
			has failed to meet the above-mentioned stipulations. It is
			<lb />
			most respectfully submitted that the statements made by
			<lb />
			the Defendant No.1, vide its letter dated 21 March 2010,
			<lb />
			addressed to the Defendant No.2, are incorrect and
			<lb />
			baseless. The Plaintiff states and submits that no such
			<lb />
			notice pursuant to any alleged failure/defect on Plaintiff&quot;s
			<lb />
			part, was received from Defendant No.1 prior to the
			<lb />
			instant illegal attempt of the Defendant No.1 to encash
			<lb />
			the PBG. This clearly shows that the malafide nature of
			<lb />
			the actions on part of the Defendant No.1 in its dealings
			<lb />
			with the Plaintiff and its complete disregard to the clear
			<lb />
			and unambiguous terms of the Contract and its
			<lb />
			contractual obligations. It is most respectfully submitted
			<lb />
			that the there was no delay in performing its obligations
			<lb />
			by the Plaintiff. On the contrary, it is submitted that the
			<lb />
			Plaintiff herein, as has already been detailed herein
			<lb />
			above, has at all times complied with its contractual
			<lb />
			obligations and it is the Defendant No.1 who has sought
			<lb />
			to wrongfully withhold the amounts payable to the
			<lb />
			Plaintiff and has now also sought to encash the Bank
			<lb />
			Guarantees in fraudulent manner, in complete disregard
			<lb />
			of the clear and unambiguous terms of the Contract and
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			FAO(OS) 429/2012 &amp; 430/2012
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 10 of 59
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			its contractual obligations and in clear violation of law.&quot;
			<lb />
			18.
			<lb />
			With respect to the plea of irretrievable injury if the guarantees
			<lb />
			were permitted to be encashed, in paragraph 46 of the plaint it is pleaded as
			<lb />
			under:-
			<lb />
			&quot;46.
			<lb />
			That it is most respectfully submitted that the
			<lb />
			Plaintiff is entitled to an ad interim ex-parte injunction
			<lb />
			restraining the Defendant No.2 from extending the
			<lb />
			APG1, PBG and APG2 in terms as sought by the
			<lb />
			Defendant No.1 or making any payment under the APG1,
			<lb />
			PBG and APG2 in the event of Defendant No.1 seeking
			<lb />
			to encash the said bank guarantees or any part thereof.
			<lb />
			The Plaintiff further submits that the Defendant No.1 has
			<lb />
			not suffered any loss or damage under the Contract, and
			<lb />
			if the reliefs prayed for in the present Suit are not been
			<lb />
			granted, it would cause grave and irreparable loss to the
			<lb />
			Plaintiff herein. If the Defendant No.1 takes away the
			<lb />
			amount under the Bank Guarantees, the Plaintiff will
			<lb />
			never be able to recover it as the Defendant No.1 is only
			<lb />
			based in Jordan and has no assets outside Jordan. The
			<lb />
			Plaintiff states that there is no established system in
			<lb />
			Jordan to enable the Plaintiff to recover the amount even
			<lb />
			if there is an award in favour of the Plaintiff. Hence
			<lb />
			there would be irretrievable injustice to the Plaintiff if the
			<lb />
			Defendant No.2 pays the amounts under the Bank
			<lb />
			Guarantees.&quot;
			<lb />
			19.
			<lb />
			The response of respondent No.1 to the averments made in para
			<lb />
			13 and 14, 39, 40 and 46 of the plaint, being an intermix of the justification
			<lb />
			for the stand taken by it while simultaneously traversing the averments made
			<lb />
			in the plaint, being unnecessarily prolix and lengthy; and if reproduced by us
			<lb />
			would span nearly 20 pages, require us to summarize the response by noting
			<lb />
			that while responding to averments in para 13 of the plaint, respondent No.1
			<lb />
			did not dispute the dates set out in the plaint when the four units were
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			FAO(OS) 429/2012 &amp; 430/2012
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 11 of 59
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			commissioned and synchronized, but highlighted that as per contract the
			<lb />
			corresponding dates were January 31, 2008, February 10, 2008, May 22,
			<lb />
			2008 and June 05, 2008. It was pleaded that though commissioned,
			<lb />
			respondent No.1 had not taken over the plants as several material elements
			<lb />
			were found missing and significantly were not running on liquid fuel and this
			<lb />
			was a material non-performance inasmuch as the plants were required to run
			<lb />
			on dual fuel system being liquid and gas. With reference to the averments
			<lb />
			made in para 14 of the plaint, apart from highlighting delay in performance
			<lb />
			of the contract, material failures in operation of the plant i.e. its inability to
			<lb />
			perform while running on a dual fuel system, failure to deliver the functional
			<lb />
			power etc. were highlighted and in addition various defects in the power
			<lb />
			plant and failure to deliver some key components were highlighted i.e. it was
			<lb />
			asserted that it was not a case where the guarantees were being invoked in
			<lb />
			the teeth of the appellant having commissioned the works in question. It was
			<lb />
			thus justified that respondent No.1 was entitled not to take over the plant.
			<lb />
			Responding to the averments made in paras 39 and 40 of the plaint, it was
			<lb />
			pleaded that respondent No.1 was justified in invoking all the three
			<lb />
			guarantees, and with respect to the performance guarantee various facts were
			<lb />
			pleaded with reference to e-mails exchanged between parties to highlight
			<lb />
			non-performance of the obligations by the appellant. Response to the
			<lb />
			averments made in para 46 of the plaint, need to be extracted. It is as under:-
			<lb />
			&quot;Contents of Para 46 are denied and it is submitted that
			<lb />
			the Answering Defendant is entitled to encash the said
			<lb />
			guarantees in view of Plaintiff&quot;s failure to fulfill
			<lb />
			materials obligations under the Contract and the delay
			<lb />
			caused by the Plaintiff in performance of the Contract.
			<lb />
			Furthermore the Guarantees are irrevocable guarantees
			<lb />
			which are payable on first written demand of the
			<lb />
			Answering Defendant specifying conditions, prescribed
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			FAO(OS) 429/2012 &amp; 430/2012
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 12 of 59
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			in the respective guarantees for invocation of the same.
			<lb />
			As the Defendant has invoked the guarantees in terms
			<lb />
			specified for the same, Defendant No.2 is bound to
			<lb />
			release the said payments and no injunction restraining
			<lb />
			defendant No.2 from releasing the said amount lies
			<lb />
			against Defendant No.2. It is settled law that bank
			<lb />
			guarantees have to be invoked in terms thereof and
			<lb />
			disputes pending between the parties cannot be
			<lb />
			considered in releasing the guaranteed amounts.
			<lb />
			It is denied that the Plaintiff has not suffered any loss or
			<lb />
			damage under the Contract. It is submitted that the loss
			<lb />
			suffered by the Answering Defendant in view of the
			<lb />
			delays and failures of the Plaintiff in performance of its
			<lb />
			obligations under the contract, far exceeds the guaranteed
			<lb />
			amounts. It is also pertinent to reiterate that in total, the
			<lb />
			Answering Defendant has paid the Plaintiff $96,979,850
			<lb />
			of the contract price of approximately @ 118,18,750.
			<lb />
			However due to failures by the Plaintiff to deliver
			<lb />
			equipment and services, the Plaintiff is liable to refund
			<lb />
			$6,500,747 of the Contract price already paid. The
			<lb />
			Answering Defendant is entitled to invoke the
			<lb />
			performance guarantee to recover at least a portion of the
			<lb />
			loss and damage caused to it due to the above stated
			<lb />
			failures of the Plaintiff and grave prejudice will be
			<lb />
			caused to the Answering Defendant if he is not able to
			<lb />
			recover the same.
			<lb />
			Further grave prejudice to
			<lb />
			international trade and commerce if bank guarantees are
			<lb />
			not honoured. On the other hand no prejudice will be
			<lb />
			caused to the Plaintiff as the Plaintiff has remedy in
			<lb />
			arbitration in London governed by ICC rules to recover
			<lb />
			any moneys that it can prove are owed to it whether on
			<lb />
			account of invocation of the guarantees or otherwise. A
			<lb />
			foreign arbitral award is enforceable in Jordan as it is a
			<lb />
			signatory of the New York Convention and there can
			<lb />
			therefore not be an apprehension that the monies will not
			<lb />
			be recovered.&quot;
			<lb />
			20.
			<lb />
			Realizing that it had overlooked the fact that the performance
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			FAO(OS) 429/2012 &amp; 430/2012
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 13 of 59
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			guarantee was limited to 10% of the contract value, and when issued the
			<lb />
			contract value was US$ 117 million, which was reduced to US$ 100 million
			<lb />
			as also the fact that during execution of the works, respondent No.1 had
			<lb />
			reduced the scope of supplies, thereby further reducing the price payable to it
			<lb />
			under the contract, a lesser amount was required to be secured towards due
			<lb />
			performance of the contract, the appellant moved an application to amend
			<lb />
			para 41 of the plaint and substitute the same by pleading afore-noted facts;
			<lb />
			and the obvious object to amend the pleading was to bring home the point
			<lb />
			that the performance guarantee could not be invoked for the value thereof.
			<lb />
			21.
			<lb />
			Issuing summons in the Suit to the respondents, as recorded in
			<lb />
			the order dated March 27, 2010, counsel for the respondent No.1 who
			<lb />
			appeared when the Suit was listed for admission before the learned Single
			<lb />
			Judge made a statement that said respondent shall maintain status quo vis-à-
			<lb />
			vis the bank guarantees. Thereafter pleadings were completed and matter
			<lb />
			lingered on. On May 06, 2010 I.A. No.5975/2010 was listed before the
			<lb />
			Court in which appellant had made a prayer, as noted above to amend the
			<lb />
			plaint.
			<lb />
			22.
			<lb />
			Parties thereafter attempted a negotiated settlement. The matter
			<lb />
			was adjourned from time to time.
			<lb />
			23.
			<lb />
			The parties were able to arrive at a settlement as a result of
			<lb />
			various meetings held between August 18, 2010 and August 21, 2010. The
			<lb />
			same was reflected in a minutes drawn up concerning the meetings held from
			<lb />
			August 18, 2010 to August 21, 2010. Vide Serial No.2 of the minutes it was
			<lb />
			recorded that in view of several unforeseen challenges faced, procurement
			<lb />
			actions were taken and supplies effected by respondent No.1 pertaining to
			<lb />
			some equipment, which as per the contract, had to be supplied by the
			<lb />
			appellant. Vide Serial No.3 it was recorded that the four units were
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			FAO(OS) 429/2012 &amp; 430/2012
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 14 of 59
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			commissioned and were running at base load as per grid demand with effect
			<lb />
			from May 11, 2009, June 04, 2009, November 19, 2009 and February 26,
			<lb />
			2010, i.e. the dates alleged by the appellant of having commissioned the four
			<lb />
			units. The value of the equipment procured and brought at the site by
			<lb />
			respondent No.1 was thereafter valued. With respect to the payments made
			<lb />
			by respondent No.1 to the appellant, vide Serial No.7 of the minutes it was
			<lb />
			recorded that parties have agreed that appellant had to pay US$ 13 million to
			<lb />
			the respondent No.1. Vide Serial No.10 it was minuted that the four
			<lb />
			unfinished systems listed at Serial No.10 would be completed by the
			<lb />
			appellant pertaining to the existing contract.
			<lb />
			24.
			<lb />
			How would appellant pay US$ 13 million to respondent No.1
			<lb />
			was recorded as per Serial No.8. And the mode of payment was agreed to be
			<lb />
			by way of an adjustment with respect to a new contract requiring appellant to
			<lb />
			execute, on turnkey basis, either 2XFr 6B GTG Open Cycle project at
			<lb />
			Sulemaniyah Cement Plant or one unit Frame-9E and in respect of which, it
			<lb />
			was agreed that a new contract pertaining to either one of the two works
			<lb />
			which would be executed by the appellant, would be executed by September
			<lb />
			27, 2010. Vide Serial No.9 of the minutes it was recorded:
			<lb />
			&quot;Till signing of the contract by 27 th September 2010,
			<lb />
			between MGI and BHEL for supply of 2XFr 6B GTG
			<lb />
			Units for Sulemaniyah Cement Plant or one Frame 9E
			<lb />
			Unit, the encashment of three numbers of Bank
			<lb />
			Guarantees by MGI and proceedings in Hon&quot;ble High
			<lb />
			Court of New Delhi would be kept under hold.&quot;
			<lb />
			25.
			<lb />
			To give a formal legal colour to what was agreed between the
			<lb />
			appellant and respondent No.1 and was briefly minuted in the minutes of the
			<lb />
			meetings held between August 18, 2010 and August 21, 2010, the appellant
			<lb />
			and the respondent No.1 executed a SETTLEMENT AGREEMENT on
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			FAO(OS) 429/2012 &amp; 430/2012
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 15 of 59
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			August 22, 2010; relevant portions of the recitals whereof read as under:-
			<lb />
			&quot;WHEREAS, during execution of the Turnkey Contract,
			<lb />
			certain disputes had arisen between the parties in respect
			<lb />
			of the execution of the Power Plant and parts thereof (all
			<lb />
			such disputes hereinafter referred to as the &quot;Disputed
			<lb />
			Matters&quot;)
			<lb />
			WHEREAS, pursuant to the said Disputed Matters MGI
			<lb />
			purported to invoke the three Bank Guarantees provided
			<lb />
			to MGI on behalf of BHEL under the terms of the
			<lb />
			Turnkey Contract, such Guarantees being (1) Advance
			<lb />
			Payment Bank Guarantee number 0999607FG0001132,
			<lb />
			in its current amount of USD 2,000,000.00 (Two Million
			<lb />
			United States Dollars) (2) Advance Payment Bank
			<lb />
			Guarantee number 0999607FG0000699 in its current
			<lb />
			amount of USD 2,000,000.00 (Two Million United States
			<lb />
			Dollars) and (3) Performance Bank Guarantee number
			<lb />
			0999607FG0000700 in an amount of USD 11,700,000.00
			<lb />
			(Eleven Million, Seven Hundred Thousands United
			<lb />
			States Dollars) (hereinafter collectively the &quot;Bank
			<lb />
			Guarantees&quot;)
			<lb />
			WHEREAS, BHEL vide a suit filed in the Delhi High
			<lb />
			Court (bearing number CS(OS) No.583 of 2010)
			<lb />
			obtained an interim injunction on the said invocation of
			<lb />
			the three Bank Guarantees against MGI and State Bank
			<lb />
			of India, however, the final judgment for the above has
			<lb />
			not yet been issued as on date;
			<lb />
			WHEREAS, Now, in pursuance of the meetings dated
			<lb />
			19 th to 21 st June 2010; 31 st July 2010 to 4 th Aug.2010;
			<lb />
			18 th to 21 st August 2010 at Amman and 18 th to 24 th July
			<lb />
			2010 at Sulymaniyh site between the Parties, the Parties
			<lb />
			have accordingly agreed to settle all disputes and
			<lb />
			differences on the terms and conditions more particularly
			<lb />
			described and stated hereinafter, (Minutes of the Amman
			<lb />
			meeting from 18 th to 21 st August 2010 signed by the
			<lb />
			parties are enclosed herewith as Schedule (1) of this
			<lb />
			Settlement Agreement, which shall be considered an
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			FAO(OS) 429/2012 &amp; 430/2012
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 16 of 59
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			integral part and parcel of this Settlement Agreement)&quot;
			<lb />
			AND WHEREAS, now, the Parties through their
			<lb />
			authorized representatives have mutually negotiated a
			<lb />
			settlement and have accordingly agreed to amicably
			<lb />
			resolve the Disputed Matters in good faith by entering
			<lb />
			into this Settlement Agreement, which shall, upon
			<lb />
			implementation of its terms and conditions as stated
			<lb />
			herein below, constitute a final and irrevocable
			<lb />
			settlement of all claims and demands of the Parties in
			<lb />
			respect thereof in connection with the Turnkey Contract.&quot;
			<lb />
			26.
			<lb />
			After recording the recitals, the parties set down in writing the
			<lb />
			terms of the settlement agreement, relevant clauses, being 1 to 9, whereof
			<lb />
			read as under:-
			<lb />
			&quot;1. THE SETTLEMENT
			<lb />
			The Parties agree that this Settlement Agreement and
			<lb />
			the terms set out herein shall be in full, unconditional,
			<lb />
			irrevocable, comprehensive and final settlement in
			<lb />
			connection with the Disputed Matters and all claims
			<lb />
			arising pursuant to the Turnkey Contract, from the date
			<lb />
			of the commencement of the Parties&quot; commercial
			<lb />
			relationship until the date of this Settlement Agreement.
			<lb />
			Upon execution of this Settlement Agreement in
			<lb />
			accordance with the terms and conditions stated below,
			<lb />
			each Party irrevocably and unconditionally relinquishes
			<lb />
			and waives all claims and demands, and further releases
			<lb />
			the other Party from all liabilities and amounts whether
			<lb />
			known or unknown in connection with the Turnkey
			<lb />
			Contract in perpetuity.
			<lb />
			2. TERMS OF SETTLEMENT
			<lb />
			In full, unconditional, irrevocable, comprehensive and
			<lb />
			final settlement of all claims and demands in respect of
			<lb />
			the Disputed Matters and the Turnkey Contract, the
			<lb />
			Parties agree as follows:-
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			FAO(OS) 429/2012 &amp; 430/2012
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 17 of 59
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			(a) Compensation to be paid by BHEL to MGI in an
			<lb />
			amount of USD 24,046,065.67 (Twenty Four Million and
			<lb />
			Forty Six Thousand and Sixty Five United States Dollars
			<lb />
			and 67/100) towards procurement by MGI of certain
			<lb />
			materials and providing services at site part of BHEL
			<lb />
			scope of works and pecuniary liabilities linked to
			<lb />
			scheduled completion;
			<lb />
			MINUS
			<lb />
			(b) An amount of USD 11,046,065.67 (Eleven Million
			<lb />
			and Forty Six Thousand and Sixty Five United States
			<lb />
			Dollars and 67/100) due to BHEL by MGI pursuant to
			<lb />
			the Turnkey Contract.
			<lb />
			The Parties hereby irrevocably agree on the calculation
			<lb />
			of the amounts and the amount itself herenabove and
			<lb />
			irrevocably agree to affect a setoff.
			<lb />
			Accordingly, BHEL hereby irrevocably acknowledges
			<lb />
			that it owes MGI, and hereby irrevocably undertakes to
			<lb />
			settle to MGI, an amount of USD 13 Million (Thirteen
			<lb />
			Million United States Dollars) (hereinafter the
			<lb />
			&quot;Settlement Amount&quot;).
			<lb />
			3. MANNER OF SETTLEMENT
			<lb />
			The Parties agree that the settlement described herein
			<lb />
			above shall be fulfilled as follows:
			<lb />
			(a) MGI hereby agrees to purchase, and BHEL hereby
			<lb />
			agrees to supply, the Turbines and Power Generation
			<lb />
			Equipments comprising of 2x Fr 6B GTG Units for MGI
			<lb />
			Sulymaniyh Cement Plant and as per the Technical
			<lb />
			Proposals -Annex (1) of Schedule (1)) or one unit frame
			<lb />
			9E. To that end, the Parties will negotiate in good faith
			<lb />
			and shall exert all reasonable efforts to negotiate and sign
			<lb />
			a supply agreement no later than 27 September 2010 or
			<lb />
			such extended period as may be mutually agreed
			<lb />
			(hereinafter the &quot;Supply Agreement&quot;)
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			FAO(OS) 429/2012 &amp; 430/2012
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 18 of 59
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			(b) It is agreed that the Settlement Amount (USD 13
			<lb />
			Million) shall constitute 52% of the contract value of the
			<lb />
			Supply Agreement. The Settlement Amount referred to
			<lb />
			herein above shall be considered as advance payment for
			<lb />
			the Turbines and Power Generation Equipments. The
			<lb />
			Supply Agreement will expressly stipulate the receipt by
			<lb />
			BHEL of the Settlement Amount as payment on account
			<lb />
			(down payment) against the total contract price of the
			<lb />
			Supply Agreement of USD 25 million (Twenty Five
			<lb />
			Million United States Dollars).
			<lb />
			(c) Upon signature of the Supply Agreement, BHEL will
			<lb />
			issue an advance payment bank guarantee in an amount
			<lb />
			equivalent to USD 13 Million (Thirteen Million United
			<lb />
			States Dollars), effective from the date of operation of
			<lb />
			letter of credit to be issued by MGI. The advance
			<lb />
			payment bank guarantee shall be issued through a bank
			<lb />
			of international repute (Citibank, Commerce Bank or any
			<lb />
			other similar bank mutually agreed) as per mutually
			<lb />
			agreed text. All banking charges towards issuance and
			<lb />
			confirmation of the advance payment bank guarantee will
			<lb />
			be BHEL&quot;s account.
			<lb />
			(d) Upon signature of the Supply Agreement and the
			<lb />
			provision of the advance payment bank guarantee
			<lb />
			referred to above under paragraph (c), MGI undertakes to
			<lb />
			discharge the Bank Guarantees in full by issuing the
			<lb />
			necessary instructions to State Bank of India and
			<lb />
			simultaneously making a joint application to the Delhi
			<lb />
			High Court for dissolution of all pending claims.
			<lb />
			(e) The remaining 43% of the Contract value (of the
			<lb />
			Supply Agreement) shall be payable to BHEL
			<lb />
			progressively against presentation of shipping documents
			<lb />
			on pro rata dispatches.
			<lb />
			(f) The remaining 5% of the Contract value (of the
			<lb />
			Supply Agreement) shall be payable to BHEL against
			<lb />
			issuance of Taking over Certificates by MGI. This
			<lb />
			clause will be further discussed during contract
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			FAO(OS) 429/2012 &amp; 430/2012
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 19 of 59
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			discussion.
			<lb />
			(g) Mode of payment for (e) and (f) above shall be
			<lb />
			through a confirmed and irrevocable Letter of Credit to
			<lb />
			be established by MGI in favour of BHEL within a
			<lb />
			maximum of Thirty Days from the date of signing the
			<lb />
			Supply Agreement. The above Letter of Credit shall be
			<lb />
			issued through a bank of International repute (Citibank,
			<lb />
			Commerce Bank or any other similar bank mutually
			<lb />
			agreed) as per mutually agreed text. All banking charges
			<lb />
			towards issuance and confirmation of L/C will be to
			<lb />
			MGI&quot;s account.
			<lb />
			(h) It is agreed that BHEL will issue a performance bank
			<lb />
			guarantee as per mutually agreed text for 10% of the
			<lb />
			contract price of the Supply Agreement within two weeks
			<lb />
			from the date of opening of L/C by MGI in favour of
			<lb />
			BHEL.
			<lb />
			4. RELEASE, WAIVER, DISCHARGE
			<lb />
			(a) Release by MGI Upon: (i) signing of the Supply
			<lb />
			Agreement, (ii) issuance of the advance payment bank
			<lb />
			guarantee referred to under clause 3 (c) above, and (iii)
			<lb />
			fulfillment by BHEL of its obligations stated herein
			<lb />
			including clause (5), MGI holds BHEL free of any
			<lb />
			responsibility and waives its rights against BHEL as
			<lb />
			regards the Disputed Matters and any obligations, claims,
			<lb />
			compensations, liabilities or any other, arising out of or
			<lb />
			in connection with the Turnkey Contract and the
			<lb />
			Disputed Matters and such release conferred herein shall
			<lb />
			be considered final and irrevocable.
			<lb />
			(b) Release by BHEL. Upon: (i) signing this Agreement,
			<lb />
			(ii) signing of the Supply Agreement, and (iii) fulfillment
			<lb />
			by MGI of its obligations set out under clause 3(d) BHEL
			<lb />
			holds MGI free of any responsibility and waives its rights
			<lb />
			against MGI as regards the Disputed Matters and any
			<lb />
			obligations, claims, compensations, liabilities or any
			<lb />
			other, arising out of or in connection with the Turnkey
			<lb />
			Contract and the Disputed Matters and such release
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			FAO(OS) 429/2012 &amp; 430/2012
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 20 of 59
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			conferred herein shall be considered final and
			<lb />
			irrevocable.
			<lb />
			(c) In relation to any claims/counter claims, upon
			<lb />
			fulfillment of all the terms and conditions of this
			<lb />
			Settlement Agreement, the Parties agree to fully and
			<lb />
			finally release, waive and forever discharge each other
			<lb />
			and any of its affiliated companies, directors, officers,
			<lb />
			counsels, agents or other representatives from:
			<lb />
			-All claims, demands, debts, accounts, expenses,
			<lb />
			costs, liens, actions and proceedings of any and
			<lb />
			every kind, nature and description and under
			<lb />
			any
			<lb />
			legal
			<lb />
			theory
			<lb />
			be
			<lb />
			it
			<lb />
			contract,
			<lb />
			misrepresentations, fraud etc., whether known
			<lb />
			or unknown, which the Parties has or might
			<lb />
			have or might assert in relation to the Disputed
			<lb />
			Matters and Turnkey Contract; and
			<lb />
			-Any legal liability arising, directly or indirectly,
			<lb />
			out of or in any way connected hereto, in
			<lb />
			relation to the Disputed Matters and Turnkey
			<lb />
			Contract.
			<lb />
			(d) Upon fulfillment of all terms and conditions of this
			<lb />
			Settlement Agreement, the Parties agree that they will not
			<lb />
			take any further action or any other measure of any
			<lb />
			nature, against each other or any of its affiliated
			<lb />
			companies, directors, officers, counsels, agents or other
			<lb />
			representatives, in relation to the Disputed Matters and
			<lb />
			Turnkey Contract.
			<lb />
			(e) The Parties hereby agree that the current injunction
			<lb />
			proceedings being deliberated by the High Court of New
			<lb />
			Delhi shall temporarily be put on hold until the signing of
			<lb />
			the Supply Agreement. To that end, the Parties agree to
			<lb />
			jointly request the High Court of New Delhi to adjourn
			<lb />
			the proceedings until the Parties move a joint application
			<lb />
			(if any) in CS(OS) No.583 of 2010 pending before the
			<lb />
			Delhi High Court to record the terms of this Settlement
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			FAO(OS) 429/2012 &amp; 430/2012
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 21 of 59
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			Agreement so that a compromise decree can be passed by
			<lb />
			the Delhi High Court in accordance with this Settlement
			<lb />
			Agreement. For the avoidance of doubt the joint
			<lb />
			application referred to above will be made only following
			<lb />
			signature of the Supply Agreement.
			<lb />
			5. COMPLETION OF WORKS
			<lb />
			BHEL undertakes to complete the unfinished systems,
			<lb />
			including: (1) Fire Fighting System by end of October
			<lb />
			2010, (2) Commissioning of the GTG&quot;s Units for 3&amp;4 on
			<lb />
			liquid fuel without undue delay, (3) DM Water System,
			<lb />
			and (4) CCTV.
			<lb />
			6. INCONSISTENCIES
			<lb />
			In the event of any discrepancies or conflicts between
			<lb />
			this Settlement Agreement and Schedule (1), the terms of
			<lb />
			this Settlement Agreement shall prevail.
			<lb />
			7. CONFIDENTIALITY AND VALIDITY
			<lb />
			In the event this Settlement Agreement is not executed
			<lb />
			for any reason whatsoever, none of the Parties will have
			<lb />
			the right to use or refer to this Settlement Agreement and
			<lb />
			Schedule (1) to arbitration or a court of law, or any other
			<lb />
			quasi judicial proceeding.
			<lb />
			Furthermore, if the Supply Agreement is not signed by
			<lb />
			27 September 2010 or such other extended date agreed in
			<lb />
			writing, this Settlement Agreement and Schedule (1)
			<lb />
			shall be considered null and void.
			<lb />
			8. COSTS
			<lb />
			The lawsuit court fees paid by BHEL in connection with
			<lb />
			the suit filed in the Delhi High Court shall not be claimed
			<lb />
			by BHEL.
			<lb />
			9. SEVERABILITY
			<lb />
			If for any reason whatsoever any provision of the
			<lb />
			Settlement Agreement is or becomes invalid, illegal or
			<lb />
			unenforceable or is declared by any court of competent
			<lb />
			jurisdiction or any other instrumentality to be invalid,
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			FAO(OS) 429/2012 &amp; 430/2012
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 22 of 59
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			illegal or unenforceable, the validity, legality or
			<lb />
			enforceability of the remaining provisions shall not be
			<lb />
			affected in any manner, and the Parties shall negotiate in
			<lb />
			good faith with a view to agreeing upon one or more
			<lb />
			provisions which may be substituted for such invalid,
			<lb />
			illegal or unenforceable provisions, as nearly as is
			<lb />
			practicable.&quot;
			<lb />
			27.
			<lb />
			Relevant would it be to note that annexed as Schedule-1 to the
			<lb />
			agreement afore-noted was a detailed document delineating the scope of
			<lb />
			work pertaining to 2XFr-6B Gas Turbine Unit as also the mode of payment
			<lb />
			pertaining thereto.
			<lb />
			28.
			<lb />
			As per the appellant, the settlement agreement dated August 22,
			<lb />
			2010 read with the minutes of the meeting dated August 18, 2010 -August
			<lb />
			21, 2010 is a complete accord between the parties and discharges the liability
			<lb />
			of the appellant under the original contract dated March 04, 2007 as
			<lb />
			modified on August 04, 2007. Thus, the appellant filed an application
			<lb />
			registered as IA No.2852/2011 praying that the suit should be disposed of in
			<lb />
			terms of the settlement and the bank guarantees be discharged.
			<lb />
			29.
			<lb />
			In the application, with reference to the Supply Agreement
			<lb />
			which was envisaged to be executed not later than September 27, 2010 (refer
			<lb />
			clause 3(a) of the Settlement Agreement dated August 22, 2010), it was
			<lb />
			pleaded in the application in para 7 as under:-
			<lb />
			&quot;7.
			<lb />
			It is further submitted that even though
			<lb />
			the formal Supply Agreement was not signed/executed
			<lb />
			by the parties, however pursuant to the process of
			<lb />
			finalizing the Supply Agreement, BHEL in accordance
			<lb />
			with the Settlement Agreement and in utter good faith
			<lb />
			had commenced performing its obligations as stipulated
			<lb />
			under the Settlement Agreement. BHEL till date has
			<lb />
			completed approx 35% -40% of the works in relation to
			<lb />
			engineering, procurement, manufacture and assembly of
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			FAO(OS) 429/2012 &amp; 430/2012
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 23 of 59
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			the two turbines. The said works performed by BHEL in
			<lb />
			relation to the Turbines amount to INR 37 crores i.e.
			<lb />
			USD 8.4 million (at the prevailing currency exchange
			<lb />
			rates). The works were carried out by BHEL in good
			<lb />
			faith and with due knowledge of MGI. The same was
			<lb />
			informed to MGI orally during various discussions
			<lb />
			BHEL had with the representatives of MGI and was
			<lb />
			further brought to the notice of MGI vide the letter sent
			<lb />
			by BHEL on 11 February 2011 along with the
			<lb />
			photographs of the ongoing works in respect of the
			<lb />
			2XFr6B Turbines.&quot;
			<lb />
			30.
			<lb />
			In the reply filed by respondent No.1 to the aforesaid
			<lb />
			application it was pleaded that the execution of the Supply Agreement was a
			<lb />
			condition precedent for a binding obligation to arise and highlighted that 20
			<lb />
			issues pertaining to the supply had yet to be agreed upon: (i) site conditions,
			<lb />
			(ii) computation of liquidated damages, (iii) performance parameters of the
			<lb />
			turbines, (iv) liquidated damages for failure to attain guaranteed
			<lb />
			performance, (v) liquidated damages for delay/late delivery, (vi) delivery
			<lb />
			terms, (vii) delivery period, (viii) number of lots, (ix) performance bank
			<lb />
			guarantee, (x) warranty/defect liability, (xi) shipping dates, (xii) indemnity,
			<lb />
			(xiii) supervision of erection and commissioning, (xiv) inspection, (xv)
			<lb />
			approval of sub-vendors, (xvi) payment terms, (xvii) default and termination
			<lb />
			and consequences thereof, (xviii) rectification and cure, (xix) dispute
			<lb />
			resolution, and (xx) terms pertaining to staff, accommodation, travel, custom
			<lb />
			clearance etc. It was thus pleaded that no settlement agreement which would
			<lb />
			discharge appellant&quot;s liabilities under the contract in respect whereof the
			<lb />
			bank guarantees were issued was arrived at between the parties. It was
			<lb />
			prayed that the application be dismissed.
			<lb />
			31.
			<lb />
			Vide impugned order dated August 31, 2012 the learned Single
			<lb />
			Judge has dismissed IA No.2852/2011 and has also vacated the injunction
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			FAO(OS) 429/2012 &amp; 430/2012
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 24 of 59
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			granted in favour of the appellant, i.e. has dismissed I.A.No.4049/2010. As
			<lb />
			recorded by us in para 1 and 2 of the present decision while commencing our
			<lb />
			journey, the learned Single Judge has not noted many facts on which parties
			<lb />
			had placed reliance and thus we may very briefly note that after referring to
			<lb />
			the pleadings of the parties, in para 19 of the impugned decision, the learned
			<lb />
			Single Judge has noted that though in the plaint grant of injunction was
			<lb />
			prayed on the plea of fraud and alternatively on the plea of irretrievable
			<lb />
			injury to the plaintiff, but the same was not canvassed during course of
			<lb />
			submission. But, opining that the bank guarantees are unconditional demand
			<lb />
			guarantees, in paragraphs 24 onward till the learned Single Judge decided IA
			<lb />
			No.4049/2010, with the discussion concluding in paragraph 40 of the
			<lb />
			impugned order, the entire discussion pertains to whether a case of fraud or
			<lb />
			irretrievable injury was made out with reference to the case law on the
			<lb />
			subject.
			<lb />
			32.
			<lb />
			There is obviously a disconnect in what the learned Single
			<lb />
			Judge has recorded in paragraph 19 and what follows thereafter. If the
			<lb />
			appellant had not argued the application with reference to the plea of fraud in
			<lb />
			invoking the guarantee as also the plea of irretrievable injustice, where was
			<lb />
			the occasion for the learned Single Judge to labour on the said issues?
			<lb />
			Further, even the issue: Whether the guarantees were invoked in terms
			<lb />
			thereof arising out of the pleadings in paragraphs 39 and 40 of the plaint and
			<lb />
			the response thereto have just not been discussed by the learned Single
			<lb />
			Judge. Even with respect to the discussion on the subject of fraud and
			<lb />
			irretrievable injury, we find no discussion in the context of the pleadings in
			<lb />
			paragraph 13, 14 and 46 of the plaint and the response thereto in the
			<lb />
			corresponding paragraphs of the written statement.
			<lb />
			33.
			<lb />
			With respect to the view taken that the Settlement Agreement
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			FAO(OS) 429/2012 &amp; 430/2012
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 25 of 59
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			dated August 22, 2010 is not a complete accord, the learned Single Judge has
			<lb />
			opined (refer para 55 of the impugned decision) that execution of the Supply
			<lb />
			Agreement was an integral part of the Settlement Agreement and since the
			<lb />
			Supply Agreement was not executed, it could not be said that the parties had
			<lb />
			entered into an agreement which could be treated as a compromise between
			<lb />
			the parties requiring the suit to be disposed of in terms of the compromise.
			<lb />
			34.
			<lb />
			Learned counsel for the parties, Shri Amarjit Singh Chandhiok,
			<lb />
			Additional Solicitor General and Shri Sandeep Sethi, Senior Advocate who
			<lb />
			appeared for the appellant and Shri C.A.Sundaram, Senior Advocate and
			<lb />
			Shri Neeraj Kishan Kaul, Senior Advocate who appeared for respondent
			<lb />
			No.1 did not dispute the legal proposition: that of the many modes by which
			<lb />
			a contract can be discharged, one mode is the same process by which it was
			<lb />
			created i.e. by a mutual agreement. Learned senior counsel did not dispute
			<lb />
			that parties to an original contract may enter into a new contract in
			<lb />
			substitution of the previous contract. Learned senior counsel were not at
			<lb />
			variance that the legal incidents of the substituted contract stand pithily
			<lb />
			summarized on the subject of: &quot;Discharge By Agreement&quot;, i.e. accord and
			<lb />
			satisfaction, in the Treatise: CHITTY ON CONTRACTS (13 th Edition-2008)
			<lb />
			in paras 22-014 and 22-015 in the following terms:-
			<lb />
			&quot;22-014 Form of accord. At common law, accord and
			<lb />
			satisfaction was no answer to a claim on a specialty, but
			<lb />
			the rule was otherwise in equity and the latter now
			<lb />
			prevails. The accord need not be in writing even if the
			<lb />
			contract which it is sought to discharge, or for the breach
			<lb />
			of which a claim is made, is required by law to be made
			<lb />
			or evidenced in writing. An oral accord will suffice,
			<lb />
			unless the accord itself constitutes a contract or
			<lb />
			transaction which is required to be made or evidenced in
			<lb />
			writing.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			FAO(OS) 429/2012 &amp; 430/2012
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 26 of 59
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			22-015 Executory satisfaction. At one time, a number
			<lb />
			of cases appeared to establish the rule that satisfaction
			<lb />
			was of no effect unless it was executed. While the
			<lb />
			satisfaction remained executory, that is to say, so long as
			<lb />
			the agreement to give satisfaction remained unperformed,
			<lb />
			the original claim was not discharged, nor would any
			<lb />
			action lie for breach of the accord. Even a tender of
			<lb />
			performance of the satisfaction agreed upon was
			<lb />
			adjudged insufficient. Only executed satisfaction would
			<lb />
			suffice. This rule, however, was never completely
			<lb />
			accepted and it is now established that satisfaction may
			<lb />
			be executory. The question is one of the construction of
			<lb />
			the accord: whether it was intended that the promise itself
			<lb />
			or the performance of the promise should discharge the
			<lb />
			original claim:
			<lb />
			&quot;The rational distinction seems to be, that if the
			<lb />
			promise be received in satisfaction, it is a good
			<lb />
			satisfaction; but if the performance, not the promise,
			<lb />
			is intended to operate in satisfaction, there will be no
			<lb />
			satisfaction without performance.&quot;
			<lb />
			In the modern law, therefore, a claimant may still
			<lb />
			insist upon the performance of some act by the other
			<lb />
			party in satisfaction of his claim. In that case, there is
			<lb />
			no satisfaction until performance, and the other party
			<lb />
			remains liable on the original claim until the
			<lb />
			satisfaction is executed. More often, however, the
			<lb />
			claimant will agree to accept the other party&quot;s promise
			<lb />
			of performance in satisfaction of his claim. The
			<lb />
			original claim is then discharged from the date of the
			<lb />
			agreement and cannot be revived. The claimant&quot;s sole
			<lb />
			remedy, in the event that the other party fails to
			<lb />
			perform, is by action for breach of the substituted
			<lb />
			agreement, and he has no right of resort to the original
			<lb />
			claim. If he wishes to preserve his right to proceed
			<lb />
			with the original claim should the other party fail to
			<lb />
			perform, an express term should be incorporated in
			<lb />
			the agreement to that effect.&quot;
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			FAO(OS) 429/2012 &amp; 430/2012
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 27 of 59
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			35.
			<lb />
			Thus, with reference to the substituted contract, it needs to be
			<lb />
			discerned whether under the accord it is the promise which is received in
			<lb />
			satisfaction of the dispute or whether it is the performance and not the
			<lb />
			promise which is intended to operate in satisfaction of the accord.
			<lb />
			36.
			<lb />
			The legal position and how the issue has to be approached, finds
			<lb />
			a reflection in the decision of the Privy Council reported as 1914 AC 618
			<lb />
			Payana Reena Saminathan v. Panna Lanapalaniappa, and the decision of
			<lb />
			the House of Lords reported as 1918 AC 1 Morris v. Baron &amp; Co., which
			<lb />
			were cited with approval in the majority opinion of the Supreme Court in the
			<lb />
			decision reported as AIR 1959 SC 1362 UOI v. Kishorilal Gupta &amp; Bros.
			<lb />
			The legal position being: Where the respective rights under a contract are
			<lb />
			abandoned in consideration of the acceptance of promises under a new
			<lb />
			agreement, new rights are born and the new agreement becomes a new
			<lb />
			departure and the rights of the parties are fully represented by it. The
			<lb />
			approach to the issue has to be to find either express words in the substituted
			<lb />
			contract to said effect i.e. parties abandoning their rights in the previous
			<lb />
			agreement and new rights being born under the new agreement or to find
			<lb />
			whether the first contract is got rid of by a second contract which is capable
			<lb />
			of being performed, i.e. the reciprocal obligations being set out with clarity,
			<lb />
			and consequences of breach provided. In other words, if under the new
			<lb />
			alleged contract, it is found that it lacks essential features of it being capable
			<lb />
			of being performed, it would not be a case where parties have abandoned
			<lb />
			their rights under the original contract. Since, fortunately for us, learned
			<lb />
			senior counsel for the parties were not at variance on the legal position, our
			<lb />
			task has become simple i.e. to peruse the Settlement Agreement and
			<lb />
			determine whether the parties have agreed therein to get rid of the first
			<lb />
			contract and create new obligations i.e. the promise being received in
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			FAO(OS) 429/2012 &amp; 430/2012
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 28 of 59
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			satisfaction of the discharge under the original claim or whether it was the
			<lb />
			performance (and not the promise) which was intended to operate in
			<lb />
			satisfaction; and this exercise to be performed keeping in view the decisions
			<lb />
			of the Privy Council and the House of Lords which were approved in the
			<lb />
			majority decision by the Supreme Court in Kishorilal Gupta&quot;s case (supra).
			<lb />
			37.
			<lb />
			With reference to the recitals of the Settlement Agreement dated
			<lb />
			August 22, 2010, which have been reproduced by us in paragraph 25 of our
			<lb />
			opinion, the first recital throws light that disputes had risen between the
			<lb />
			parties with reference to the execution of the turnkey contract and the second
			<lb />
			and the third recitals records that pursuant to the dispute, respondent No.1
			<lb />
			had invoked the two advance payment bank guarantees and the performance
			<lb />
			bank guarantee, and in respect whereof the appellant had obtained an interim
			<lb />
			injunction. The fourth recital records that parties have agreed to settle all
			<lb />
			disputes and differences on the terms and conditions herein after recorded
			<lb />
			i.e. the operative covenants of the contract. The recital expressly makes it
			<lb />
			clear that the minutes of the meetings from 18 th to 21 st August 2010 shall be
			<lb />
			considered as an integral part of the Settlement Agreement. The last recital,
			<lb />
			has a key to unravel the deadlock. It expressly records that after mutual
			<lb />
			negotiations a settlement was arrived at and the purport of this Settlement
			<lb />
			Agreement was to not only reduce the terms of the settlement in writing but
			<lb />
			to discharge the parties from their obligations under the original contract
			<lb />
			upon implementation of its terms and conditions as stated herein below.
			<lb />
			Prima facie, the recital makes it very clear that it is not the promise but the
			<lb />
			satisfaction of the promise which would have discharged the parties from
			<lb />
			their obligations under the original contract.
			<lb />
			38.
			<lb />
			However, there is much more to note and say on the subject for
			<lb />
			the reason it is settled law that intention of the parties has to be gathered
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			FAO(OS) 429/2012 &amp; 430/2012
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 29 of 59
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			after reading, as a whole, the contractual documents. We highlight that the
			<lb />
			same very recital which prima facie leans in favour of the view that it was
			<lb />
			not the promise but the performance of the promise which was intended to
			<lb />
			be the satisfaction to discharge the obligations under the original contract,
			<lb />
			records that the Settlement Agreement constitutes a final and irrevocable
			<lb />
			settlement of all claims and demands of the parties in respect of the turnkey
			<lb />
			contract, a language which is prima facie suggestive of the contrary i.e. that
			<lb />
			the parties have agreed to venture a new journey.
			<lb />
			39.
			<lb />
			But what are the operative clauses of the contract? It is
			<lb />
			probably somewhere hidden within them, that the true intention of the parties
			<lb />
			has to be found. Indeed it is.
			<lb />
			40.
			<lb />
			We have reproduced the relevant clauses, being 1 to 9 of the
			<lb />
			agreement in para 26 above of our opinion; and we revisit them one by one.
			<lb />
			Clause 1 records that the parties are fully, unconditionally, irrevocably and
			<lb />
			comprehensively bound to the Settlement Agreement in connection with the
			<lb />
			disputed matters and their claims arising pursuant to the turnkey contract.
			<lb />
			But, in the same very clause, i.e. the second part, records that it is the
			<lb />
			execution of the Settlement Agreement in accordance with the terms and
			<lb />
			conditions thereof that the parties would irrevocably and unconditionally
			<lb />
			relinquish and waive their claims and demands under the turnkey contract.
			<lb />
			41.
			<lb />
			In clause 1, the parties have not expressed themselves with
			<lb />
			clarity and on the one hand have recorded that the Settlement Agreement
			<lb />
			binds them unconditionally, comprehensively and irrevocably and in the
			<lb />
			same breath have proceeded to record that the claims and demands under the
			<lb />
			turnkey contract shall be discharged upon execution of the Settlement
			<lb />
			Agreement. The problem is with the use of the word &apos;execution&apos; in the
			<lb />
			second part of the clause. Did the parties understand &apos;execution&apos; to mean the
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			FAO(OS) 429/2012 &amp; 430/2012
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 30 of 59
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			signing of the Settlement Agreement, for to execute an agreement would
			<lb />
			mean parties appending their signatures thereto, or the parties used the word
			<lb />
			&apos;execution&apos; as a synonym for the word &apos;performance&apos;; to be understood to
			<lb />
			mean that upon performance of the terms and conditions of the Settlement
			<lb />
			Agreement the parties would relinquish and waive their claims and demands
			<lb />
			under the turnkey contract?
			<lb />
			42.
			<lb />
			Clause 1 also has scope for a debate and till now, if it was
			<lb />
			boxing round, and we were match referees, we would say it is &quot;One : One&quot;.
			<lb />
			43.
			<lb />
			Does clause 2 tilt the balance? It records that the appellant has
			<lb />
			to compensate respondent No.1 in sum of US$ 24,046,065.67 towards
			<lb />
			procurement by respondent No.1 of materials and services provided at site
			<lb />
			for scope of work which had to be executed by the appellant. It records that
			<lb />
			for the work done a balance amount of US$ 11,046,065.67 is payable by
			<lb />
			respondent No.1 to the appellant; and thereafter the clause records that by
			<lb />
			affecting set-off, the appellant acknowledges a liability to pay US$ 13
			<lb />
			million to the respondent.
			<lb />
			44.
			<lb />
			The clause helps us no bit to understand on the subject we are
			<lb />
			discussing. It simply records an accord that with respect to the turnkey
			<lb />
			contract, after squaring off the respective claims i.e. affecting set-off,
			<lb />
			appellant acknowledges a liability to pay US$ 13 million to the respondent
			<lb />
			No.1. But whether the promise is the satisfaction to discharge the parties
			<lb />
			from their obligations under the turnkey contract or it is the performance
			<lb />
			thereof, the subject with which we are grappling, the clause throws no light.
			<lb />
			Thus, till clause 2 it can be said that the parties are: &quot;One : One&quot;. Let us see
			<lb />
			whether clause 3 helps us. Its caption: &quot;MANNER OF SETTLEMENT&quot;, is
			<lb />
			expected to resolve the issue. Sub-para (a) of clause 3 records that the
			<lb />
			promise under the accord to pay US$ 13 million to respondent No.1 would
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			FAO(OS) 429/2012 &amp; 430/2012
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 31 of 59
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			be satisfied by the appellant by supplying either Turbines and Power
			<lb />
			Generation Equipments comprising 2XFr6B GTG Units as per technical
			<lb />
			proposals annexed as Annexure-1 to the Settlement Agreement or one unit
			<lb />
			frame 9E, and for which contract the parties shall further negotiate and sign,
			<lb />
			not later than September 27, 2010, a Supply Agreement. Sub-para (b) of
			<lb />
			clause 3 records that US$ 13 million payable under the turnkey contract by
			<lb />
			the appellant to respondent No.1 shall be adjusted as payment under the
			<lb />
			Supply Agreement, whether it would relate to the 2XFr6B GTG Units or 9E
			<lb />
			Unit frame, and this would constitute 52% of the contract value, meaning
			<lb />
			thereby that the contract value for the proposed new contract would be US$
			<lb />
			25 million. Prima facie, the game now leans in favour of respondent No.1
			<lb />
			inasmuch as law requires that to break from the past contract, with reference
			<lb />
			to an accord, the new contract has to be an executable contract and this
			<lb />
			would mean the terms of the further journey and the new destination have to
			<lb />
			be clearly defined. In other words, the execution of a Supply Agreement
			<lb />
			was essential, to put it in yet different words, it was the execution of the
			<lb />
			Supply Agreement which would have severed the parties from their
			<lb />
			respective obligations to each other under the turnkey contract. But Sub-
			<lb />
			para (c) of clause 3 of the Settlement Agreement records that when the
			<lb />
			Supply Agreement was signed only then the settled amount i.e. US$ 13
			<lb />
			million would be treated as an advance payment under the Supply
			<lb />
			Agreement and simultaneously would oblige the appellant to issue an
			<lb />
			advance payment bank guarantee in the amount equivalent to US$ 13
			<lb />
			million. Simultaneously, to secure payment of further sum of US$ 12
			<lb />
			million by respondent No.1 to the appellant, it would open a Letter of Credit.
			<lb />
			The balance now shift in favour of respondent No.1 Sub-para (d) of clause 3
			<lb />
			further shifts the balance in favour of respondent No.1 and against the
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			FAO(OS) 429/2012 &amp; 430/2012
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 32 of 59
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			appellant, inasmuch as the clause clearly envisages that when the Supply
			<lb />
			Agreement is signed i.e. executed and the condition of advance payment
			<lb />
			bank guarantee referred to in para (c) of the clause is complied with,
			<lb />
			respondent No.1, shall discharge the bank guarantees pertaining to the
			<lb />
			turnkey contract and simultaneously, the parties shall make a joint
			<lb />
			application to the Delhi High Court for resolution of the pending claims.
			<lb />
			Sub-paras (e) and (f) of the clause record the stages at which the remainder
			<lb />
			48% of the contract value under the Supply Agreement would be paid. Sub-
			<lb />
			para (h) requires appellant to issue a performance guarantee for 10% of the
			<lb />
			contract price under the Supply Agreement.
			<lb />
			45.
			<lb />
			Clause 4, under the caption &quot;RELEASE, WAIVER,
			<lb />
			DISCHARGE&quot;, records that upon signing of the Supply Agreement and
			<lb />
			issuance of the bank guarantee referred to in sub-para (c) of clause 3, alone
			<lb />
			would respondent No.1 waive its rights against the appellant as regards the
			<lb />
			disputed matters under the turnkey contract.
			<lb />
			46.
			<lb />
			Clause 4 needs to be spoken of a little more. Since a contract is
			<lb />
			the result of mutually agreed terms being accepted by the parties, its
			<lb />
			novation by way of an accord has obviously to be the result of mutually
			<lb />
			agreed terms. Whether it is the promise under a new agreement which is
			<lb />
			intended to discharge the parties i.e. satisfy the claims under a previous
			<lb />
			agreement or it is the satisfaction of the promise which was intended to
			<lb />
			discharge the parties i.e. satisfy the claims under the previous agreements, is
			<lb />
			the position which needs to be determined with reference to the language of
			<lb />
			the accord. But what we find in the instant case is that the parties have
			<lb />
			clearly intended to charter the journey through a different route. Clause 4 of
			<lb />
			the accord clearly evidences that the mutually agreed terms of the accord are
			<lb />
			that it is the signing of the Supply Agreement and issuance of the advance
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			FAO(OS) 429/2012 &amp; 430/2012
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 33 of 59
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			payment bank guarantees referred to in sub-para (c) of clause 3 which was
			<lb />
			intended by the parties to be the satisfaction of the accord to discharge the
			<lb />
			appellant and respondent No.1 from their respective obligations under the
			<lb />
			turnkey contract. The parties have clearly contemplated that unless, not only
			<lb />
			the Supply Agreement is executed but is put into the journey of
			<lb />
			&quot;performance&quot;, the relationship, the rights and liabilities under the turnkey
			<lb />
			contract would not stand discharged.
			<lb />
			47.
			<lb />
			It had to be so. The accord is that with respect to the turnkey
			<lb />
			contract, after effecting set-off, the appellant owed US$ 13 million to
			<lb />
			respondent No.1, which amount became the advance payment in the hands
			<lb />
			of the appellant pertaining to the new contract i.e. the Supply Agreement to
			<lb />
			supply either equipment pertaining to the 2XFr6B GTG Units or the Unit
			<lb />
			Frame 9E. Respondent No.1 had to be secured repayment of the said
			<lb />
			advance under a bank guarantee. Further, it had to be secured, by way of a
			<lb />
			performance guarantee, for the due performance of the obligations under the
			<lb />
			new contract. The situation was akin to a baton being passed at a relay race.
			<lb />
			Unless the previous runner, on the track, within the limited distance
			<lb />
			recognized by the rules of the race, passes on the baton to the next runner,
			<lb />
			alone she can fade away from the race, with the next runner completing the
			<lb />
			next lap. Without the baton in hand, the next runner cannot run the lap.
			<lb />
			With this analogy, one can understand that the intention of the parties was
			<lb />
			that unless the accord i.e. the settlement amount i.e. US$ 13 million was not
			<lb />
			secured by another bank guarantee and due performance of the new contract
			<lb />
			was not secured by a performance guarantee, the parties would remain tied
			<lb />
			with the umbilical cord to the turnkey contract. This is the reason why, as
			<lb />
			per sub-paras (d) and (e) of clause 4, the parties clearly recorded that till the
			<lb />
			Supply Agreement was executed and it took off with respect to respondent
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			FAO(OS) 429/2012 &amp; 430/2012
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 34 of 59
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			No.1 being secured through a security advance guarantee and a performance
			<lb />
			guarantee, neither party would be discharged from the obligations under the
			<lb />
			turnkey contract. And what more clear language could the parties use, other
			<lb />
			than in sub-para (e) of clause 4 when they recorded that the current
			<lb />
			injunction proceedings shall temporarily be put on hold till the parties signed
			<lb />
			the Supply Agreement.
			<lb />
			48.
			<lb />
			Clause 5 of the Settlement Agreement is interesting. It shows
			<lb />
			that even if the Supply Agreement was executed and the guarantees
			<lb />
			envisaged under sub-para (c) of clause 3 were issued, not everything
			<lb />
			pertaining to the turnkey contract would have stood discharged. Four items
			<lb />
			of work which were unfinished pertaining to the turnkey contract were
			<lb />
			required to be completed by the appellant. Thus it can be said that clause 5
			<lb />
			of the Settlement Agreement is a residue clause, saving the performance of
			<lb />
			some obligations under the turnkey contract. However, we hasten to add that
			<lb />
			the clause in question is of no help to resolve the issue at hand which we are
			<lb />
			discussing; but would simultaneously highlight that clause 3 and clause 4
			<lb />
			have sufficient indicators, signposts and signage to point the direction in
			<lb />
			which the parties intended to move. The victory is not on points but on a
			<lb />
			clean knock out.
			<lb />
			49.
			<lb />
			Clause 6, 7 and 8 of the Settlement Agreement have no bearing
			<lb />
			on the issue at hand; and thus we reach clause 9, which requires that in the
			<lb />
			event of any provision of the Settlement Agreement becoming invalid,
			<lb />
			illegal or unenforceable or is declared so by any Court of competent
			<lb />
			jurisdiction, the legality or enforceability of the remaining provisions shall
			<lb />
			not be affected in any manner and the parties shall negotiate in good faith
			<lb />
			with a view to agree upon one or more provisions which may be substituted
			<lb />
			for the provision declared invalid, illegal or unenforceable, as nearly as is
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			FAO(OS) 429/2012 &amp; 430/2012
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 35 of 59
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			practicable.
			<lb />
			50.
			<lb />
			Prima facie clause 9 reflects the intention of the parties to save
			<lb />
			such part of the Settlement Agreement which can be save upon a part thereof
			<lb />
			being declared illegal, invalid or unenforceable.
			<lb />
			51.
			<lb />
			We propose to discuss further clause 9 after we note the rival
			<lb />
			submissions of the learned Senior Advocates who appeared for the parties
			<lb />
			because the issue of severability would be inter linked to not only their
			<lb />
			submissions but even to the overall structure of the agreement.
			<lb />
			52.
			<lb />
			Mr. Amarjeet Singh Chandhiok, learned Additional Solicitor
			<lb />
			General, had rightly urged that the Settlement Agreement, though factually
			<lb />
			one entity, has two distinct severable parts, i.e. it is an agreement which is
			<lb />
			factually one but conceptually two. The first part of the Settlement
			<lb />
			Agreement, which is distinct from the second part thereof, is that the parties
			<lb />
			have recorded a complete accord pertaining to the Disputed Matters relating
			<lb />
			to the turnkey contract. They have listed the terms of the settlement in the
			<lb />
			two sub-paras of clause 2 of the Settlement Agreement. Briefly recorded,
			<lb />
			parties have settled that pertaining to the turnkey contract, the appellant
			<lb />
			would pay to respondent No.1, by way of compensation, a sum of US$ 24,
			<lb />
			046,065.67 and that for the work done by the appellant and accepted by
			<lb />
			respondent No.1 US$ 11,046,065.67 are payable. Setting off the two sums,
			<lb />
			the parties have recorded that appellant would pay to respondent No.1 sum
			<lb />
			of US$ 13 million. Pertaining to the turnkey contract, the parties have
			<lb />
			further agreed, as recorded in clause 5 of the Settlement Agreement, that
			<lb />
			pertaining to the turnkey contract, the appellant would complete the
			<lb />
			unfinished systems listed in clause 5 of the Settlement Agreement. In other
			<lb />
			words, the parties have agreed that the turnkey contract shall be closed upon
			<lb />
			the appellant completing the unfinished systems mentioned in clause 5 of the
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			FAO(OS) 429/2012 &amp; 430/2012
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 36 of 59
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			Settlement Agreement and paying US$ 13 million to respondent No.1. The
			<lb />
			Settlement Agreement, after crystallizing as aforesaid, and being a complete
			<lb />
			accord, requiring satisfaction of the promise by the appellant to pay US$ 13
			<lb />
			million to respondent No.1, proceeds to record the manner in which the
			<lb />
			satisfaction of the promise would be made. And here enters the distinct
			<lb />
			subsequent agreement, a new agreement, embodying the terms of the
			<lb />
			satisfaction of the promise under the accord and clearly envisages that under
			<lb />
			a Supply Agreement (to be executed by the parties not later than September
			<lb />
			27, 2010), on the terms contained therein, the appellant would supply either
			<lb />
			Turbines and Power Generation Equipment comprising of 2XFr 6B GTG
			<lb />
			units or one unit frame 9E. Pertaining to the 2XFr 6B GTG units, as per
			<lb />
			Annexure-1 to the Settlement Agreement, the description and the
			<lb />
			specifications of the supplies to be made have been clearly spelled out as
			<lb />
			also the terms of payment. The price has been agreed to, i.e. US$ 25 million.
			<lb />
			It has been recorded that the amount crystallized under the accord pertaining
			<lb />
			to the turnkey contract, i.e. US$ 13 million, payable by appellant to
			<lb />
			respondent No.1, would be treated as an advance payment under the Supply
			<lb />
			Agreement and the balance sum of US$ 12 million would be paid: 43%
			<lb />
			progressively against presentation of shipping documents on pro-rate
			<lb />
			dispatches and 5% against issuance of taking over certificate. The
			<lb />
			Settlement Agreement further records that the mode of payment by
			<lb />
			respondent No.1 to the appellant would be through confirmed and
			<lb />
			irrevocable Letter of Credit. However, the Settlement Agreement i.e. the
			<lb />
			Annexure-1 thereto, clearly requires the parties to negotiate further and agree
			<lb />
			the date wherefrom supplies would be effected as also other commercial
			<lb />
			terms and conditions. If the alternative pertained to 2XFr 6B GTG Units, the
			<lb />
			parties were obliged to discuss further the proposal for installation and
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			FAO(OS) 429/2012 &amp; 430/2012
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 37 of 59
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			commissioning of the Units, and these are to be found in clauses 3(iii)(c), (g)
			<lb />
			and clause 5 of an appendix to the schedule. Clause 6 of the said appendix
			<lb />
			requires appellant to submit an offer to the respondent No.1 regarding 2XFr
			<lb />
			6B GTG Units with an option to buy Frame 9 instead of Frame 6.
			<lb />
			53.
			<lb />
			As regards the alternative contemplated by the Settlement
			<lb />
			Agreement, with respect to either supplying 2XFr 6B GTG Units or one unit
			<lb />
			frame 9E, it is not in dispute that the parties agreed that the Supply Contract
			<lb />
			would be with respect to the former, i.e. 2XFr 6B GTG Unit.
			<lb />
			54.
			<lb />
			What happened due to which the parties could not execute the
			<lb />
			Supply Agreement by September 27, 2010, is not clear from the pleadings of
			<lb />
			the parties, but apparently the dialogue continued to settle such terms which
			<lb />
			were required to be settled for the contract to be formally drawn up; and
			<lb />
			needless to state the said unsettled terms were the ones which the parties had
			<lb />
			in mind when they recorded in the Settlement Agreement that they would
			<lb />
			negotiate further and agree to the dates wherefrom supplies would be
			<lb />
			effected as also other commercial terms and conditions. These negotiations
			<lb />
			took the parties till early January 2011, evidenced by a letter written by
			<lb />
			respondent No.1 to the appellant on January 03, 2011, requiring the appellant
			<lb />
			to reach Amman so that the matter pertaining to the 2XFr 6B GTG Units
			<lb />
			could be finalized and the Supply Agreement drawn and executed. In the
			<lb />
			said letter, respondent No.1 informed the appellant to ensure that somebody
			<lb />
			should reach Amman latest by January 15, 2011, so that negotiations could
			<lb />
			be held over the next two days and contract finalized by January 17, 2011.
			<lb />
			On January 14, 2011, the appellant requested the meeting to be postponed,
			<lb />
			and on January 20, 2011, the respondent No.1 terminated the Settlement
			<lb />
			Discussions informing that there was an unjust delay, attributable to the
			<lb />
			appellant, in executing the Supply Contract, date of execution of which was
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			FAO(OS) 429/2012 &amp; 430/2012
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 38 of 59
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			fixed as September 27, 2010 under the Settlement Agreement. It was also
			<lb />
			informed that the appellant was in breach of clause 5 of the Settlement
			<lb />
			Agreement which obliged the appellant to complete the listed incomplete
			<lb />
			works pertaining to the turnkey project.
			<lb />
			55.
			<lb />
			It was rightly urged, and with which submissions we agree, by
			<lb />
			Sh.Amarjeet Singh Chandhiok, learned Additional Solicitor General, that the
			<lb />
			Settlement Agreement has two distinct parts and that the severability clause
			<lb />
			No.9 does not render the Settlement Agreement to be void or non-est, if a
			<lb />
			part of it was illegal, invalid or unenforceable. We also agree with the
			<lb />
			submissions made by the learned Additional Solicitor General that this
			<lb />
			would include a breach of a part of the Settlement Agreement, requiring the
			<lb />
			remainder to be enforced. But this takes the appellant nowhere.
			<lb />
			56.
			<lb />
			Every Settlement Agreement, which is by way of an accord
			<lb />
			pertaining to a dispute under an existing contract, is bound to have two
			<lb />
			limbs. The first limb is to record the term of the settlement, which would
			<lb />
			mean the promise by one party to the other. The second limb would be the
			<lb />
			manner in which the promise would be satisfied. Thus, the submissions
			<lb />
			urged by the learned Additional Solicitor General would take us nowhere to
			<lb />
			resolve and untie the knot, with which we are grappling, i.e. whether the
			<lb />
			parties agreed under the accord that the promise be received in satisfaction of
			<lb />
			the accord or it was the performance of the promise which would operate in
			<lb />
			satisfaction of the accord. And on the facts of the instant case, as we have
			<lb />
			already opined in paragraph 52 above, there is a problem with the
			<lb />
			identification of the promise itself. Whether the promise under the accord is
			<lb />
			accepted in satisfaction of the accord or whether the performance of the
			<lb />
			promise is the satisfaction of the accord, is thus not even arising for
			<lb />
			consideration, inasmuch as the promise which was intended to be the sine
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			FAO(OS) 429/2012 &amp; 430/2012
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 39 of 59
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			qua non of the accord has not been fully crystallized. What we find on facts
			<lb />
			is that as per the accord, the settlement amount i.e. US$ 13 million, has been
			<lb />
			recorded as payable by the appellant to respondent No.1 and completion of
			<lb />
			the listed incomplete works as per clause 5 of the Settlement Agreement, and
			<lb />
			this was the promise under the accord. But the parties did not leave the
			<lb />
			matter at that. Contemplating what would be the promise, the parties were
			<lb />
			conscious of the fact that apart from the Settlement agreed amount, the mode
			<lb />
			of payment thereof would also be within the ambit of the promise: akin to a
			<lb />
			situation where &quot;A&quot; promises to pay &quot;B&quot; a sum of 500/-at 12 Noon on
			<lb />
			January 01, 2012. The promise would be not only to pay 500/-but the time
			<lb />
			as well. Further, if the promise was to pay 500/-at 12 Noon at Volga
			<lb />
			Restaurant in Connaught Place Volga Restaurant, i.e. the place would also be
			<lb />
			the part of the promise. The promise would embrace the amount, the time
			<lb />
			and the place.
			<lb />
			57.
			<lb />
			We highlight once again that as per the law noted by us in
			<lb />
			paragraph 36 above, where the parties under a contract abandon their rights
			<lb />
			in consideration of the acceptance of a promise under a new agreement
			<lb />
			whereunder new rights are born and the new agreement becomes a new
			<lb />
			departure, unless the promise is clearly defined there cannot be in law: A
			<lb />
			new defined contract.
			<lb />
			58.
			<lb />
			To overcome the problem, learned Additional Solicitor General
			<lb />
			urged that law recognizes the distinction between a condition precedent and
			<lb />
			a condition antecedent. The former would be a sine qua non for a contract to
			<lb />
			come into existence and the latter would be a part of the contract. Learned
			<lb />
			Additional Solicitor General urged that the Settlement Agreement had
			<lb />
			included as Schedule-1, the minutes of the meetings drawn up pertaining to
			<lb />
			the meeting held between August 18, 2010 and August 21, 2010 as also an
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			FAO(OS) 429/2012 &amp; 430/2012
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 40 of 59
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			Annexure-1, in which, i.e. both documents the contractual terms and
			<lb />
			conditions pertaining to the supply of the equipment relating to 2XFr 6B
			<lb />
			GTG Units were listed, and thus urged the learned Additional Solicitor
			<lb />
			General, that the Settlement Agreement distinctly embodies the Supply
			<lb />
			Agreement, execution whereof was a mere formality, i.e. the execution of the
			<lb />
			Supply Agreement was a condition antecedent of the agreement between the
			<lb />
			parties and not a condition precedent for a contract to come into existence.
			<lb />
			In other words the submission was that the promise under the accord relating
			<lb />
			to the terms of the discharge of the promise was a complete promise, and not
			<lb />
			as urged by learned Senior Advocates appearing for respondent No.1.
			<lb />
			59.
			<lb />
			The minutes of the meetings held between August 18, 2010 and
			<lb />
			August 21, 2010, which are an integral part of the Settlement Agreement,
			<lb />
			vide clause 3(iii)(g) and clause 4 stipulate as under:
			<lb />
			&quot;3(iii)(g)
			<lb />
			All other commercial terms and conditions shall
			<lb />
			be mutually agreed between MGI and BHEL as per
			<lb />
			following schedule:
			<lb />
			 Draft contract to be submitted by BHEL to MGI by 1 st
			<lb />
			September 2010.
			<lb />
			 MGI to furnish their comments on the draft contract
			<lb />
			by 9 th September 2010.
			<lb />
			 Mutually agreed contract to be finalized and signed
			<lb />
			between MGI and BHEL during a meeting on 27 th
			<lb />
			September 2010
			<lb />
			For the purposes of the above, both parties shall agree to
			<lb />
			adhere to the dates mentioned herein. However, in case of
			<lb />
			minor changes/deviations, the parties shall mutually agree
			<lb />
			upon the revised dates.
			<lb />
			4.
			<lb />
			The time schedule mentioned in the offer dated 11 th
			<lb />
			August, 2010 was not acceptable to MGI and both parties
			<lb />
			will mutually agree upon a revised time schedule during the
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			FAO(OS) 429/2012 &amp; 430/2012
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 41 of 59
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			Purchase Contract discussions.&quot;
			<lb />
			60.
			<lb />
			It is apparent that the parties had to agree some commercial
			<lb />
			terms and conditions as also the time schedule to execute the contract
			<lb />
			pertaining to 2XFr 6B GTG Units. It is true that the technical details
			<lb />
			pertaining to the supply items have been put down in detail, but pertaining to
			<lb />
			a supply and installation contract to be a concluded and a binding contract
			<lb />
			coming into being, not only the price of the goods and the description
			<lb />
			thereof, but even the time and mode of the delivery; installation and
			<lb />
			execution thereof and other commercial terms, for example, excise, sales tax,
			<lb />
			custom duties, transportation charges etc. etc. would require to be finalized
			<lb />
			before an identifiable promise comes into existence. Sans all these, the
			<lb />
			discussions pertaining to the promise would be inchoate. In the instant case,
			<lb />
			the parties clearly understood that they had broadly agreed to some of the
			<lb />
			essential features of the promise pertaining to the Supply Agreement, and
			<lb />
			had additionally clearly understood that a few of them remained to be firmed
			<lb />
			up and this is the reason why the Settlement Agreement clearly records that
			<lb />
			unless the Supply Agreement is drawn up, the parties would not be released
			<lb />
			of their obligations under the turnkey contract.
			<lb />
			61.
			<lb />
			On facts, we may summarize that the Settlement Agreement is
			<lb />
			an accord requiring appellant to pay US$ 13 million to the respondent No.1
			<lb />
			and additionally complete the unfinished works detailed in clause 5 of the
			<lb />
			Settlement Agreement. The promise under the accord i.e. to pay US$ 13
			<lb />
			million is by way of executing another contract valued at US$ 25 million,
			<lb />
			requiring the amount under the accord i.e. US$ 13 million to be treated as
			<lb />
			advance payments under the said contract. The accord does not treat the
			<lb />
			promise as satisfaction of the claims under the original contract nor does the
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			FAO(OS) 429/2012 &amp; 430/2012
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 42 of 59
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			accord contemplate the performance of the promise to be the satisfaction of
			<lb />
			the claim under the original contract, but contemplates a third kind of a
			<lb />
			situation i.e. unless all the parameters of the promise were finalized and new
			<lb />
			rights and liabilities were created, the past rights and liabilities were not to
			<lb />
			be extinguished. With respect to the bank guarantees issued under the
			<lb />
			turnkey contract, the Settlement Agreement i.e. the accord clearly
			<lb />
			contemplates the validity thereof to be existing and the right and liability
			<lb />
			thereunder to be existing till the Supply Agreement was executed and the
			<lb />
			two guarantees i.e. Advance Payment Guarantee and Performance Guarantee
			<lb />
			pertaining to the Supply Agreement executed. To put it in other words, as
			<lb />
			regards the bank guarantees which were issued pertaining to the turnkey
			<lb />
			contract, parties clearly agreed that these guarantees would enure till
			<lb />
			discharged, and the discharge to be simultaneous with the execution of fresh
			<lb />
			Advance Payment Guarantee and Performance Guarantee pertaining to the
			<lb />
			Supply Agreement.
			<lb />
			62.
			<lb />
			Realizing that the appellant had to overcome the aforesaid
			<lb />
			intention of the parties, Shri Amarjit Singh Chandhiok, learned Additional
			<lb />
			Solicitor General had urged that it is one thing to say that I have settled and
			<lb />
			it is altogether another thing to say that I will tell somebody else that I have
			<lb />
			settled. To make good the argument, learned Additional Solicitor General
			<lb />
			referred to sub-para (d) of para 3 of the Settlement Agreement, which reads:
			<lb />
			Upon signature of the Supply Agreement and the provision of the advance
			<lb />
			payment bank guarantee referred to above under paragraph (c), MGI
			<lb />
			undertakes to discharge the Bank Guarantees in full by issuing the necessary
			<lb />
			instructions to State Bank of India and simultaneously making a joint
			<lb />
			application to the Delhi High Court for dissolution of all pending claims.
			<lb />
			63.
			<lb />
			The argument was that the execution of the Supply Agreement
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			FAO(OS) 429/2012 &amp; 430/2012
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 43 of 59
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			being a condition antecedent to the accord, and in law a Supply Agreement
			<lb />
			having come into existence, the bank guarantees stood discharged as far as
			<lb />
			the respondent No.1 was concerned and this has been covenanted by the
			<lb />
			parties in sub-para (d) of clause 3 of the Settlement Agreement. Dovetailing
			<lb />
			clause 9 of the agreement under the caption: SEVERABILITY, learned
			<lb />
			Additional Solicitor General urged that if for any reason the Supply
			<lb />
			Agreement fell, or there was a dispute in relation thereto, the remainder
			<lb />
			under the Settlement Agreement had to be severed and the same would
			<lb />
			survive. In other words, what was urged was that whatever be the position
			<lb />
			pertaining to the Supply Agreement, the accord in relation to the bank
			<lb />
			guarantees being discharged had to be given effect to.
			<lb />
			64.
			<lb />
			We have already opined against the stand taken by the appellant
			<lb />
			with respect to the execution of the Supply Agreement being a formality or a
			<lb />
			condition antecedent. We have already held that not all what would have
			<lb />
			constituted the promise under the Supply Agreement was negotiated by the
			<lb />
			parties when the Settlement Agreement was executed. Many aspects of the
			<lb />
			promise pertaining to the Supply Agreement were settled and finalized, but
			<lb />
			parties clearly understood that many aspects of the promise pertaining to the
			<lb />
			Supply Agreement had yet to be finalized and thus they fixed the date
			<lb />
			September 27, 2010 to do the needful, and thereafter, in writing, reduce the
			<lb />
			terms of the Supply Agreement for future reference. We have already held
			<lb />
			that the parties clearly agreed that till the bank guarantees contemplated
			<lb />
			under the Supply Agreement were executed, the bank guarantees under the
			<lb />
			turnkey contract would not be discharged. This intention is to be specifically
			<lb />
			found in sub-para (d) of clause 3 of the Settlement Agreement where the
			<lb />
			parties have recorded that respondent No.1 undertakes to discharge (and we
			<lb />
			emphasize the use of the word &apos;undertakes&apos;) the bank guarantees under the
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			FAO(OS) 429/2012 &amp; 430/2012
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 44 of 59
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			turnkey contract when appellant will get issued through a bank of
			<lb />
			international repute the bank guarantee referred to in paragraph (c) of the
			<lb />
			clause; and suffice would it be to state that as per said paragraph the bank
			<lb />
			guarantee to be got issued through a bank of international repute was the
			<lb />
			advance payment bank guarantee in sum of US$ 13 million.
			<lb />
			65.
			<lb />
			It made commercial sense for respondent No.1 to so insist.
			<lb />
			Under the Settlement Agreement i.e. the accord, which was a severable
			<lb />
			accord, requiring: if the latter part failed the former to survive; the appellant
			<lb />
			agreed liability to pay US$ 13 million to respondent No.1 and needless to
			<lb />
			state this liability would have the composite element of non-performance of
			<lb />
			the obligations by the appellant thereby entitling respondent No.1 to invoke
			<lb />
			the performance guarantee as also excess payments made by respondent
			<lb />
			No.1 to the appellant after effecting set-off and thus rendering the advance
			<lb />
			payment guarantees liable to be invoked. The parties clearly understood,
			<lb />
			may be at the insistence of respondent No.1, that it would not permit any
			<lb />
			chink in its armour by releasing the bank guarantees under the turnkey
			<lb />
			contract without obtaining back to back guarantees under the Supply
			<lb />
			Agreement and these guarantees under the Supply Agreement were to be in
			<lb />
			sum of US$ 13 million to secure advance payment under the second contract
			<lb />
			i.e. the guarantee in sum of US$ 13 million and another bank guarantee in
			<lb />
			sum of US$ 2.5 million to secure due performance of the Supply Agreement,
			<lb />
			for the reason the performance guarantee had to be 10% of the value of the
			<lb />
			supply contract which was agreed to be US$ 25 million.
			<lb />
			66.
			<lb />
			We thus agree with the conclusion arrived at by the learned
			<lb />
			Single Judge, but not on the reasoning of the learned Single Judge, and on
			<lb />
			the strength of the reasoning herein above noted that no compromise was
			<lb />
			effected between the parties of the kind which satisfied the dispute which
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			FAO(OS) 429/2012 &amp; 430/2012
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 45 of 59
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			was the subject matter of the instant suit, requiring the suit to be disposed of
			<lb />
			in terms of the compromise. The dispute settled by the parties was to close
			<lb />
			the turnkey contract by setting off the amounts found due and payable to the
			<lb />
			appellant with respect to the amounts paid by the respondent No.1 to it and
			<lb />
			such amounts to which respondent No.1 would be entitled to on adjustment
			<lb />
			for works not carried out by the appellant, and the net position being the
			<lb />
			appellant was liable to pay US$ 13 million to respondent No.1. The matter
			<lb />
			would have rested if the accord simply stopped there, requiring appellant to
			<lb />
			pay, in cash, US$ 13 million the respondent No.1, and in said circumstance
			<lb />
			the parties would have certainly decided that the suit could be disposed of as
			<lb />
			compromised by appellant either simultaneously paying US$ 13 million to
			<lb />
			respondent No.1 or that under the bank guarantees which were invoked by
			<lb />
			respondent No.1, only said sum could be released. But, this did not happen
			<lb />
			and thus it cannot be said that with reference to the dispute pertaining to the
			<lb />
			bank guarantees a compromise took place which embraced the subject matter
			<lb />
			of the suit. We highlight once again that as per sub-para (e) of clause 4 of
			<lb />
			the Settlement Agreement pertaining to RELEASE, WAIVER AND
			<lb />
			DISCHARGE the parties have clearly recorded that the current injunction
			<lb />
			proceedings being deliberated by the High Court of Delhi shall not be
			<lb />
			withdrawn till signing of the Supply Agreement and only by way of a joint
			<lb />
			application to record the terms of the settlement so that a compromise decree
			<lb />
			could be passed.
			<lb />
			67.
			<lb />
			This takes us to the next part of the discussion pertaining to the
			<lb />
			invocation of the three bank guarantees in question, which question would
			<lb />
			have a sub-issue to be answered with reference to the Settlement Agreement
			<lb />
			having two distinct parts and a Severability clause therein. Whether or not,
			<lb />
			in the instant proceedings, it would arise for determination by the Court as to
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			FAO(OS) 429/2012 &amp; 430/2012
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 46 of 59
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			who was responsible for the Supply Agreement not being executed inasmuch
			<lb />
			as, the learned Additional Solicitor General urged that if respondent No.1
			<lb />
			was responsible for non-execution of the Supply Agreement, and the take off
			<lb />
			clause thereof not taking off, breach would be attributable to respondent
			<lb />
			No.1 and since there was a complete accord pertaining to the turnkey
			<lb />
			contract, the appellant would stand relieved of the obligations to have
			<lb />
			furnished the bank guarantees, meaning thereby the bank guarantees would
			<lb />
			have to be treated as discharged.
			<lb />
			68.
			<lb />
			We are of the opinion that the said issue would not arise for
			<lb />
			consideration in the instant suit and irrespective of the fact whether
			<lb />
			respondent No.1 acted as a horrible party and was wholly responsible for the
			<lb />
			Supply Agreement not being executed, the same would have no bearing on
			<lb />
			the continued rights under the bank guarantees which were invoked, for the
			<lb />
			reason this dispute would be a distinct dispute, required to be severed under
			<lb />
			the severability clause of the Settlement Agreement and to be adjudicated
			<lb />
			upon independently. We are thus not dealing with the issue that there is
			<lb />
			some evidence to support the stand of the appellant that pertaining to the
			<lb />
			supply contract it had started fabricating the equipment which was to the
			<lb />
			knowledge of respondent No.1 and thus said respondent would be estopped
			<lb />
			from acting in a manner which would breach the supply contract. Even if
			<lb />
			this be so, the appellant would have an independent cause of action to sue for
			<lb />
			breach thereof.
			<lb />
			69.
			<lb />
			From the pleadings in the plaint we find that invocation of the
			<lb />
			three bank guarantees has been challenged on the plea of fraud in the factual
			<lb />
			setting pleaded in paragraphs 13 and 14 of the plaint which we have
			<lb />
			reproduced in paragraph 15 of our opinion; on the plea that the bank
			<lb />
			guarantees have not been invoked validly as per the pleadings in paragraph
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			FAO(OS) 429/2012 &amp; 430/2012
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 47 of 59
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			No.39 and 40 of the plaint which we have reproduced in paragraph 16 and
			<lb />
			17 of our opinion and lastly on the plea of irretrievable injury as per pleading
			<lb />
			in paragraph 46 of the plaint, noted in para 19 above.
			<lb />
			70.
			<lb />
			On the subject of there being a fraud in invoking the bank
			<lb />
			guarantees, learned Additional Solicitor General who appeared for the
			<lb />
			appellant, stated that the fraud was that notwithstanding the appellant having
			<lb />
			completed the turnkey contract, the performance guarantee as also the two
			<lb />
			guarantees pertaining to advance payments were invoked. It was highlighted
			<lb />
			that in the pleadings, the respondent No.1 had admitted said fact while
			<lb />
			responding to the averments made in para 13 of the plaint. Learned
			<lb />
			Additional Solicitor General urged that there was an apparent malice in not
			<lb />
			issuing the &quot;Taking Over&quot; certificate; and hence the fraud.
			<lb />
			71.
			<lb />
			We have noted in para 15 of our opinion the pleadings in para
			<lb />
			13 and 14 of the plaint and have highlighted, in para 19 of our opinion, that
			<lb />
			since the response was prolix and lengthy, and if reproduced would span
			<lb />
			nearly 20 pages, we would be summarizing the response; and while
			<lb />
			summarizing the response have noted that as against the four contractual
			<lb />
			dates: January 31, 2008, February 10, 2008, May 22, 2008 and June 05,
			<lb />
			2008, the works were completed on the dates mentioned in para 13 of the
			<lb />
			written statement i.e. May 11, 2009, June 04, 2009, November 19, 2009 and
			<lb />
			February 26, 2010 i.e. with an extreme delay. The respondent No.1 has also
			<lb />
			highlighted that though commissioned, several elements were found missing
			<lb />
			and the biggest problem was a material non-performance, inasmuch as the
			<lb />
			plants were required to run on dual fuel system i.e. liquid and gas. The
			<lb />
			systems were capable of running only on liquid fuel. The written statement
			<lb />
			also highlights various works not executed by the appellant which were then
			<lb />
			executed by respondent No.1 to complete the works (and in respect of which
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			FAO(OS) 429/2012 &amp; 430/2012
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 48 of 59
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			we find considerable evidence even in the Settlement Agreement of August
			<lb />
			22, 2010). Besides, the written statement highlights the incomplete works,
			<lb />
			which were listed in paragraph 5 of the Settlement Agreement.
			<lb />
			72.
			<lb />
			The contract clearly envisaged the respondent No.1 to issue a
			<lb />
			Taking Over certificate after the works were satisfactorily completed. In the
			<lb />
			instant case, not only the pleadings in the written statement but even the
			<lb />
			documents filed by both parties would reveal that prima-facie the works
			<lb />
			were not completed as per contract. Four units were set up, but not as per a
			<lb />
			turnkey contract. The units were not running on a dual fuel system. They
			<lb />
			could not be operated on liquid fuel. If this be so, respondent No.1 could
			<lb />
			have rejected the entire works and proceeded to invoke the bank guarantees
			<lb />
			and additionally sue for a refund of all amounts paid to the appellant as also
			<lb />
			damages. We need not reiterate our discussion with respect to the
			<lb />
			Settlement Agreement which records unsatisfactory executed works; monies
			<lb />
			payable to the respondent No.1 from the appellant and vice-versa; net
			<lb />
			amount being payable to respondent No.1.
			<lb />
			73.
			<lb />
			The plea of fraud, prima-facie, fails on the facts and thus we
			<lb />
			need not note the case law cited on either side on the issue: Whether the plea
			<lb />
			of fraud in invoking the bank guarantee would be with reference to a fraud in
			<lb />
			the issuance of a bank guarantee or a fraud in enforcing the guarantee. But
			<lb />
			we cannot refrain from observing that under what circumstances certain
			<lb />
			decisions hold that a plea of fraud must relate to the issuance of the bank
			<lb />
			guarantee, is not clear to us for the reason one of the first reported decisions
			<lb />
			on a plea of fraud made prima-facie good, acting as an exception to the rule
			<lb />
			of absolute independence of a bank guarantee, is the opinion of Shientag J.
			<lb />
			reported as 31 NYS 2d 631 Sztejn v. J.Henry Schroder Banking Corp. The
			<lb />
			year was 1941. Injunctions under letters of credit were not issued by
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			FAO(OS) 429/2012 &amp; 430/2012
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 49 of 59
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			Courts. Mr.Sztejn had placed an order for quality bristles from India and
			<lb />
			payment was secured by means of a letter of credit. Somehow Mr.Sztejn
			<lb />
			discovered that the shipment made was crates of worthless rubbish. He went
			<lb />
			to the bank with a request not to pay under the letter of credit and received a
			<lb />
			response from the bank that being an independent undertaking of the bank it
			<lb />
			had to pay when documents were presented with bill of exchange to
			<lb />
			negotiate the letter of credit. Mr.Sztejn went to Court alleging fraud in
			<lb />
			invoking the letter of credit and made prima-facie good his allegation, that as
			<lb />
			against the contracted goods i.e. quality bristles, worthless material was
			<lb />
			shipped. Noting a fraud, the Court issued an injunction. The exception
			<lb />
			carved out by Shientag J. was accepted by the Courts in England in the
			<lb />
			decisions reported as 1958 (2) QBD 127 Hamzen Milas &amp; Sons v. British
			<lb />
			Imex Industries Ltd., 1977 (2) All.E.R. 862 R.D.Harbottle Mercantile Ltd. &amp;
			<lb />
			Anr. v. National West Minister Bank Ltd., 1978 (1) All.E.R. 976 Edward
			<lb />
			Oven Engineering Ltd. v Barklay&apos;s Bank International Ltd., and 1982 (2)
			<lb />
			All.E.R. 720 UCM (Investment) v. Royal Bank of India, in which decision
			<lb />
			the opinion of Shientag, J. was hailed as a landmark case by Lord Diplock, J.
			<lb />
			74.
			<lb />
			In our opinion, the first judgment with respect to a plea of fraud
			<lb />
			acting as an exception in a letter of credit, and which would apply even to
			<lb />
			bank guarantees, and which opinion set the trend even in Common Law
			<lb />
			Jurisdiction, pertained to a plea of fraud in invoking the guarantee and not at
			<lb />
			the time when the guarantee was issued; and thus we hardly see any scope
			<lb />
			for a debate on the subject that the plea of fraud recognized by Courts as an
			<lb />
			exception would be limited to when the guarantee was issued.
			<lb />
			75.
			<lb />
			However, on the facts of the instant case we find no fraud made
			<lb />
			prima-facie good, when the bank guarantee was invoked.
			<lb />
			76.
			<lb />
			On the subject of irretrievable injustice/injury, the said defence
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			FAO(OS) 429/2012 &amp; 430/2012
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 50 of 59
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			against the bank guarantee being invoked, has been predicated by the
			<lb />
			appellant with respect to the averments made in paragraph 46 of the plaint;
			<lb />
			contents whereof have been noted by us in paragraph 18 of our opinion. The
			<lb />
			plea is rested on the pleading that if respondent No.1 receives the amount
			<lb />
			under the bank guarantees the appellant will never be able to recover it since
			<lb />
			respondent No.1 is based in Jordan and has no assets outside Jordan and
			<lb />
			there is no established system in Jordan to enable the appellant to recover the
			<lb />
			amount if it has an award in its favour. The response to said paragraph has
			<lb />
			been noted by us in paragraph 19 of our opinion and suffice would it be to
			<lb />
			highlight that the admitted position is, as pleaded in the written statement,
			<lb />
			that Jordan is a signatory to the New York Convention. The contract
			<lb />
			between the parties has a remedy by way of arbitration in London; governed
			<lb />
			by ICC Rules. Thus, on facts, it cannot be said that the appellant has made
			<lb />
			out a prima facie case of irretrievable injury. In fact, what the appellant
			<lb />
			really intended to plead was a case of special equity, for the reason an
			<lb />
			irretrievable injury is always contemplated of a kind which was noted in the
			<lb />
			celebrated decision reported as 566 Fed. Supp. 1210 Itek Corpn. v. First
			<lb />
			National Bank of Boston which was noted with approval by the Supreme
			<lb />
			Court in the decision reported as 1988 (1) SCC 174 U.P. Co-operative
			<lb />
			Federation Ltd. v. Singh Consultants &amp; Engineers. Special equities is also
			<lb />
			an exception recognized against the rule of absolute invocation of bank
			<lb />
			guarantees in terms of the bank guarantees. Courts have used the two
			<lb />
			expressions &quot;Special Equity&quot; and &quot;Irretrievable Injustice&quot;, as interchangeable
			<lb />
			expressions. One instance of a Special Equity is to be found in the opinion
			<lb />
			of Lord Dening M.R. reported as 1966 (2) Lloyd&quot;s List Law Reports 495
			<lb />
			Elian &amp; Rabbath (Trading as Elian &amp; J Rabbath) v. Massas &amp; Ors. In that
			<lb />
			case the first defendants&apos; Greek motor vessel &apos;Flora M&apos; was chartered by
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			FAO(OS) 429/2012 &amp; 430/2012
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 51 of 59
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			Lebanese charterers for carriage of plaintiffs&apos; cargo (consigned to Hungary)
			<lb />
			from Bairut to Rijeka. Discharge was delayed at Rijeka and Ship owners
			<lb />
			exercised lien on cargo in respect of demurrage. Third defendant bank put up
			<lb />
			guarantee in London in favour of second defendant (first defendants&apos; London
			<lb />
			agents) to secure release of cargo. There was a claim by Yugoslavians to
			<lb />
			distrain on goods, involving ship in further delay and master of Flora M, on
			<lb />
			lifting original lien, immediately exercised another lien in respect of extra
			<lb />
			delay (which was raised when Hungarian buyers put up 2000). Two years
			<lb />
			later, shipowners claimed arbitration with charterers to assess demurrage for
			<lb />
			which first lien was exercised and claimed to enforce guarantee. Plaintiff
			<lb />
			claimed declaration that guarantee was not valid and injunction to restrain
			<lb />
			shipowners or their agents from enforcing guarantee. First and second
			<lb />
			defendants appealed against granting of injunction by Blain, J. It was held by
			<lb />
			the Court of Appeal that it was a special case in which the Court should
			<lb />
			grant an injunction to prevent what might by irretrievable injustice. Lord
			<lb />
			Denning, M.R., observed that although the shippers were not parties to the
			<lb />
			bank guarantee, nevertheless they had a most important interest in it. If the
			<lb />
			Midland Bank Ltd., paid under this guarantee, they would claim against the
			<lb />
			Lebanese bank who in turn would claim against the shippers. The shippers
			<lb />
			would certainly be debited with the account. On being so debited, they
			<lb />
			would have to sue the shipowners for breach of their promise express or
			<lb />
			implied, to release the goods. Lord Denning, M.R., further posed the
			<lb />
			question were the shippers to be forced to take that course? Or can they
			<lb />
			shortcircuit the dispute by suing the shipowners at once for an injunction?
			<lb />
			He further observed at page 497 of the Report that this was a special case in
			<lb />
			which injunction should be granted. Lord Denning, M.R. went on to observe
			<lb />
			that there was a prima facie ground for saying that on telex messages which
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			FAO(OS) 429/2012 &amp; 430/2012
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 52 of 59
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			passed (and indeed, on the first three lines of the guarantee) the ship owners
			<lb />
			promised that, if the bank guarantee was given, they would release the
			<lb />
			goods. He further observed that the only lien they had in mind at that time
			<lb />
			was the lien for demurrage. But would anyone suppose that the goods would
			<lb />
			be held for another lien? It can well be argued that the guarantee was given
			<lb />
			on the understanding that the lien was raised and no further lien imposed and
			<lb />
			that when the shipowners, in breach of that understanding imposed a further
			<lb />
			lien, they were disabled from acting on the guarantee.
			<lb />
			77.
			<lb />
			We may only highlight that the expression &apos;That it was a
			<lb />
			special case&apos; in which the Courts should grant an injunction to prevent what
			<lb />
			might be irretrievable injustice had caught the eye of the Supreme Court in
			<lb />
			U.P.Co-operative Federation case (supra) (refer para 16), and needless to
			<lb />
			state with approval.
			<lb />
			78.
			<lb />
			But, as we have already noted herein above, the pleadings in the
			<lb />
			plaint, on the subject of either irretrievable injury or a special
			<lb />
			circumstance/special equity are found to be prima-facie wanting in making
			<lb />
			out a prima-facie case for grant of an injunction.
			<lb />
			79.
			<lb />
			And this takes us to the last plea: Whether the guarantees were
			<lb />
			invoked in terms thereof, and for which the rival pleadings would be as per
			<lb />
			para 39 and 40 of the plaint, reproduced by us in para 16 and 17 of our
			<lb />
			opinion, and the summarized response thereto in the corresponding
			<lb />
			paragraphs of the written statement as per what we have noted in paragraph
			<lb />
			19 of our opinion.
			<lb />
			80.
			<lb />
			From the pleadings of the appellant, pertaining to the
			<lb />
			performance guarantee, it is apparent that the fulcrum rests on the words: in
			<lb />
			the event that the Principal failed to fulfill his contractual obligations under
			<lb />
			and in conformity with the terms of the contract; and the argument is that the
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			FAO(OS) 429/2012 &amp; 430/2012
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 53 of 59
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			terms of the contract not being fulfilled, as per the contract, is an integral
			<lb />
			part of the bank guarantee. Thus, notwithstanding that a bank guarantee is
			<lb />
			an independent contract, in the instant case, pertaining to the performance
			<lb />
			guarantee, the parties have made the contract a part of the bank guarantee.
			<lb />
			Extending the argument, reliance is placed upon sub para &quot;a&quot; of the bank
			<lb />
			guarantee in question, where the words used are: That the Principal has
			<lb />
			failed to fulfill their obligation in accordance with the conditions of the
			<lb />
			contract. Sh.Amarjeet Singh Chandhiok, learned Additional Solicitor
			<lb />
			General urged that the letter invoking the bank guarantee in question,
			<lb />
			contents whereof have been noted by us in paragraph 13 above, is not in
			<lb />
			conformity with the performance guarantee inasmuch as it merely reiterates
			<lb />
			parrot like words of the bank guarantee. The words in the letter invoking the
			<lb />
			bank guarantee to the effect that the principal has failed to fulfill their
			<lb />
			obligation in accordance with the contract are unintelligible and are
			<lb />
			meaningless words unless and until a reference was made to some particular
			<lb />
			obligation which the principal had failed to perform in the judgment of the
			<lb />
			respondent was the submission made. Pertaining to the two bank guarantees
			<lb />
			to secure advance payments, learned Additional Solicitor General
			<lb />
			highlighted sup-para &quot;a&quot; of the two guarantees where the words used were:
			<lb />
			That the Principal has failed to fulfill their obligation for adjustment of the
			<lb />
			advance payment in accordance with the conditions of the contract.
			<lb />
			Subsequently reduced to US$ 2 million, the guarantee being the same,
			<lb />
			learned Additional Solicitor General urged that for the submissions made
			<lb />
			pertaining to the performance guarantee, the invocation of the two bank
			<lb />
			guarantees with respect to advance payment being secured were not in
			<lb />
			accordance with the terms of the guarantee. Reliance was placed upon the
			<lb />
			decision of the Supreme Court reported as 1999 (8) SCC 436 Hindustan
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			FAO(OS) 429/2012 &amp; 430/2012
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 54 of 59
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			Construction Co.Ltd. v. State of Bihar &amp; Ors., where the words in the bank
			<lb />
			guarantee pertaining to secure the advance mobilization loan: &apos;In the event
			<lb />
			that the obligations expressed in the said clause of the above-mentioned
			<lb />
			contract have not been fulfilled by the contractor giving the right of claim to
			<lb />
			the employer for recovery of the whole or part of the advance mobilization
			<lb />
			loan from the contractor under the contract&apos; were interpreted by the
			<lb />
			Supreme Court as clearly referring to the original contract and the guarantee
			<lb />
			becaming liable to be invoked only in circumstances referred to in clause 9
			<lb />
			of the contract and in that context opined, in para 14 of the opinion.
			<lb />
			81.
			<lb />
			The decision afore-noted has been explained by the Supreme
			<lb />
			Court in a later decision reported as AIR 2007 SC 2361 State Bank of India
			<lb />
			&amp; Anr. v. Mula Sahakari Sakhar Karkhana Ltd., in paragraphs 30 to 32, by
			<lb />
			highlighting that the rectial in the bank guarantee which was being
			<lb />
			considered by the Supreme Court in Hindustan Construction Co. Ltd.&apos;s case
			<lb />
			(supra) had indicated clearly, by referring to clause 9 of the contract, that the
			<lb />
			parties were embodying the contract in the bank guarantee, and thereafter the
			<lb />
			use of the words: &apos;in the event that the obligations expressed in the said
			<lb />
			clause of the above-mentioned contract&quot; made it clear that by referring
			<lb />
			specifically to clause 9 in the recital and thereafter reflecting the same in the
			<lb />
			operative part of the bank guarantee, the bank had qualified its liability to
			<lb />
			pay the amount. In other words, the defaults had to be specifically listed or
			<lb />
			in other words the guarantee was conditional.
			<lb />
			82.
			<lb />
			The three bank guarantees at hand simply make a reference to
			<lb />
			they being issued pursuant to the contract between the parties and we may
			<lb />
			note that virtually all bank guarantees which we have come across refer, in
			<lb />
			the rectial, to the guarantee being executed pursuant to a condition under the
			<lb />
			main contract obliging the contractor to furnish a bank guarantee(s). A
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			FAO(OS) 429/2012 &amp; 430/2012
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 55 of 59
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			recital in a bank guarantee to the effect, of it being issued pursuant to a term
			<lb />
			in the contract, requiring the bank guarantee to be furnished would not mean
			<lb />
			that the terms of the contract get embodied in the terms of the bank
			<lb />
			guarantee, unless a condition of a contract is made an integral part of the
			<lb />
			operative part of a bank guarantee as was to be found in the decision in
			<lb />
			Hindustan Construction Co.&quot;s case (supra). Otherwise, the issue has to be
			<lb />
			approached: On the premise that a bank guarantee is an independent contract
			<lb />
			unrelated to the main contract.
			<lb />
			83.
			<lb />
			The operative parts of the guarantees in question do not embody
			<lb />
			any term of the contract as a condition for the invocation thereof. The
			<lb />
			guarantees clearly use the expressions: &apos;hereby irrevocably undertake to pay
			<lb />
			to you on your first written demand.&apos;
			<lb />
			84.
			<lb />
			With respect to the submissions urged that parrot like
			<lb />
			reproduction of the language of the bank guarantees is insufficient, suffice
			<lb />
			would it be for us to state that the advance payment guarantees simply
			<lb />
			require the beneficiary, while raising the demand in writing, to incorporate in
			<lb />
			the demand three statements: (i) the principal has failed to fulfill their
			<lb />
			obligation in accordance with the conditions of the contract, (ii) the amount
			<lb />
			which the principal has failed to fulfill; and (iiii) the principal has failed to
			<lb />
			perform or fulfill any material act or obligation under the contract despite 30
			<lb />
			days&quot; calendar notice. The performance guarantee simply requires it to be
			<lb />
			stated that the principal has failed to fulfill its obligation for adjustment of
			<lb />
			the advance payment in accordance with the conditions of the contract and
			<lb />
			secondly the amount which the principal has failed to fulfill.
			<lb />
			85.
			<lb />
			A bank guarantee has to be strictly construed. If the parties
			<lb />
			chose to incorporate as above, they have to be bound to what they chose. To
			<lb />
			accept the argument advanced by the learned Additional Solicitor General
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			FAO(OS) 429/2012 &amp; 430/2012
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 56 of 59
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			would mean that letters invoking bank guarantees have to be a virtual plaint.
			<lb />
			86.
			<lb />
			Having negated the three grounds on which the invocation of
			<lb />
			the bank guarantees was challenged, as per the pleadings, we proceed to note
			<lb />
			some additional submissions made by learned Senior Counsel for the
			<lb />
			appellant, which strictly speaking do not arise out of the pleadings in the
			<lb />
			suit.
			<lb />
			87.
			<lb />
			The first additional submission urged was that when issued, the
			<lb />
			performance guarantee envisaged a contract value of US$ 117 million which
			<lb />
			admittedly got reduced to US$ 100 million. Thus, it was urged that the
			<lb />
			performance guarantee could not be invoked beyond a value 10% of the
			<lb />
			original contract price.
			<lb />
			88.
			<lb />
			It may be true that when the bank guarantee was issued at 10%
			<lb />
			of the value of the contract i.e. to secure due performance and default valued
			<lb />
			at US$ 11.7 million and later on the contract price was reduced, but it was
			<lb />
			for the appellant to have got the bank guarantee modified suitably. As
			<lb />
			regards the bank and the beneficiary, the guarantee amount remained the
			<lb />
			same.
			<lb />
			89.
			<lb />
			It was urged that since there are traces of acquiescence on the
			<lb />
			part of respondent No.1 in the appellant proceeding to fabricate the
			<lb />
			equipment covered by the Supply Agreement (which as we have noted above
			<lb />
			was never executed), prima-facie it would be an invocation of the bank
			<lb />
			guarantees which lacked good faith or it being enforced with an oblique
			<lb />
			purpose.
			<lb />
			90.
			<lb />
			In the decision reported as (2002) 1 SLR 1 Samwoh Asphalt
			<lb />
			Premix Ptc. Ltd. v. Sum Cheong Piling Pte Ltd. the Court of Appeal in
			<lb />
			Singapore held that where a bank guarantee was invoked as a &apos;bargaining
			<lb />
			chip&apos; or as a &apos;deterrent&apos; or in an &apos;abusive manner&apos; it would amount to calling
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			FAO(OS) 429/2012 &amp; 430/2012
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 57 of 59
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			a guarantee for an oblique purpose, justifying the issuance of an injunction.
			<lb />
			This decision was relied before the Supreme Court on the argument of &apos;lack
			<lb />
			of good faith&apos; and/or &apos;enforcing with an oblique purpose&apos; in the decision
			<lb />
			reported as 2006 (2) SCC 728 BSES Ltd. v. Fenner India Ltd. Refusing to go
			<lb />
			for the bite, the Supreme Court held:-
			<lb />
			&quot;We are afraid that in the face of the law succinctly laid down
			<lb />
			in U.P.Coop. Federation and reiterated in numerous
			<lb />
			judgments of this Court referred to earlier, we are unable to
			<lb />
			accept the wide proposition of law laid down in the foreign
			<lb />
			judgments cited by Mr.Sorabjee. Whatever may be the law, as
			<lb />
			to the encashment of bank guarantees in other jurisdictions,
			<lb />
			when the law in India is clear, settled and without any
			<lb />
			deviation whatsoever, there is no occasion to rely upon
			<lb />
			foreign case-law.&quot;
			<lb />
			91.
			<lb />
			This closes the legal debate, which reaches its destination
			<lb />
			against the appellant.
			<lb />
			92.
			<lb />
			But we have a word to be spoken of. What if, all the aforesaid
			<lb />
			facts were told to a layman with a request to take a decision as a reasonable
			<lb />
			man, using the tools of reason and logic. The fact would be that under the
			<lb />
			turnkey contract the appellant managed to set up gas turbine units which
			<lb />
			could operate only on one fuel system and not dual fuel system. Even the
			<lb />
			executed works were not fully complete when the plant was put into
			<lb />
			operation. The appellant delayed the setting up of the four turbine units. It
			<lb />
			did not supply all the equipment which was to be supplied thereby
			<lb />
			compelling respondent No.1 to procure and install at its own level the
			<lb />
			equipment in question. The parties negotiated and mutually agreed that a net
			<lb />
			sum of US$ 13 million is due from the appellant to respondent No.1. They
			<lb />
			settled to close the contract requiring appellant to pay respondent No.1 a sum
			<lb />
			of US$ 13 million and additionally (refer clause 5 of the Settlement
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			FAO(OS) 429/2012 &amp; 430/2012
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 58 of 59
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			Agreement) that the appellant would complete the unfinished works. The
			<lb />
			common man would obviously say that the appellant has become liable to
			<lb />
			pay respondent No.1 US$ 13 million and such amount as would be payable
			<lb />
			for the unfinished works listed in clause 5 of the Settlement Agreement. On
			<lb />
			being further informed that the bank guarantees under the turnkey contract
			<lb />
			are still alive and were clearly envisaged to be substituted by bank
			<lb />
			guarantees in sum of US$ 13 million (to secure repayment of US$ 13 million
			<lb />
			treated as advance payment in the hands of the appellant for the Supply
			<lb />
			Agreement) and also issue a performance guarantee in sum of US$ 2.5
			<lb />
			million for the Supply Agreement contract, and that the said guarantees were
			<lb />
			not issued for the reason the Supply Agreement was never executed, and
			<lb />
			required to factor in the same in the decision making process and then reach
			<lb />
			the conclusion, the common man is bound to say, or at least in all reasonable
			<lb />
			probability would say: that prima-facie the appellant must pay respondent
			<lb />
			US$ 13 million and such sum as would be required to complete the balance
			<lb />
			works.
			<lb />
			93.
			<lb />
			We accordingly dismiss the two appeals but without there being
			<lb />
			any order as to costs.
			<lb />
			(PRADEEP NANDRAJOG)
			<lb />
			JUDGE
			<lb />
			(MANMOHAN SINGH)
			<lb />
			JUDGE
			<lb />
			SEPTEMBER 12, 2012
			<lb />
			dk
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			FAO(OS) 429/2012 &amp; 430/2012
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 59 of 59
			<lb />
		</page>
	</text>
</tei>
