<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			*
			<lb />
			IN THE HIGH COURT OF DELHI AT NEW DELHI
			<lb />
			%
			<lb />
			Date of Decision: 6.7.2012
			<lb />
			+
			<lb />
			W.P.(C) No.5725/2008
			<lb />
			Ms.Flora Gupta
			<lb />
			…
			<lb />
			Petitioner
			<lb />
			versus
			<lb />
			Jawahar Lal Nehru University &amp; Ors.
			<lb />
			…
			<lb />
			Respondents
			<lb />
			Advocates who appeared in this case:
			<lb />
			For the Petitioner
			<lb />
			: Mr. Vishwendra Verma &amp; Ms.Subhavna
			<lb />
			For Respondents
			<lb />
			: Mr. Vikram Nandrajog, Mr. Gagan Minocha
			<lb />
			and Mr. Sushil Jaiswal
			<lb />
			CORAM:
			<lb />
			HON&apos;BLE MR. JUSTICE ANIL KUMAR
			<lb />
		</front>
		<body>
			ANIL KUMAR, J.
			<lb />
			1.
			<lb />
			The petitioner, who wanted to pursue her doctorate degree from
			<lb />
			the session of 2007-08, had appeared for the Ph.D entrance
			<lb />
			examination for the said period. She has sought quashing of alleged
			<lb />
			Inquiry Committee report dated 7 th March, 2008 and has also sought
			<lb />
			quashing of office Order No. 08/CP/2008 based on said enquiry report
			<lb />
			whereby Vice Chancellor of Respondent no.1 in exercise of power vested
			<lb />
			in him under Statute 32 of the University has ordered that the entire
			<lb />
			JNU campus is declared out of bounds for petitioner for five years and
			<lb />
			debarring her from taking admission in any program of study of the
			<lb />
			Respondent no.1 for next five academic years and any other actions of
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P(C) 5725/2008
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 1 of 71
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			the respondents based on the said report The petitioner has also sought
			<lb />
			directions to the respondents to give her admission in the Ph.D
			<lb />
			programme after providing her the fresh character certificate for the
			<lb />
			term of 2003-05, during which the petitioner had completed her Master
			<lb />
			of Science in Biotechnology.
			<lb />
			2.
			<lb />
			Brief facts to comprehend the controversies are that the petitioner
			<lb />
			was a student of M.Sc. Biotechnology in the academic session 2003-05.
			<lb />
			She had passed her course of M.Sc. in Biotechnology in the year 2005
			<lb />
			from the School of Biotechnology (SBT) of Jawahar Lal Nehru
			<lb />
			University, New Delhi, respondent No.1.
			<lb />
			3.
			<lb />
			After completing her M.Sc. in Biotechnology, the petitioner
			<lb />
			wanted to pursue her doctorate during the session of 2007-08. The
			<lb />
			petitioner, therefore, appeared for the Ph.D. entrance examination. The
			<lb />
			petitioner contended that it was disclosed to her that she had been
			<lb />
			successfully in the Ph.D. entrance examination.
			<lb />
			4.
			<lb />
			The plea of the petitioner is that on 25 th July, 2007 prior to
			<lb />
			formal declaration of the results, she was called by Ms.Aparna Dixit,
			<lb />
			Dean, School of Biotechnology, respondent no.2 to her office. On
			<lb />
			reaching the office of Ms.Aparna Dixit, she found that two other
			<lb />
			professors, namely, Mr.R.Bhatnagar and Mr.Uttam Pati were also
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P(C) 5725/2008
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 2 of 71
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			present there. The petitioner alleged that it was disclosed to her by the
			<lb />
			respondent no.2 that she had got the first rank among the candidates
			<lb />
			and had therefore, topped the merit list.
			<lb />
			5.
			<lb />
			However, the petitioner contended that to her utter surprise,
			<lb />
			despite securing a very high position in the examination, she was
			<lb />
			pressurized, not to get herself registered. The petitioner further
			<lb />
			disclosed that she was threatened by Ms.Aparna Dixit, respondent no.2
			<lb />
			to write a letter addressed to her, incorporating a confession that she
			<lb />
			had used unfair means during the Ph.D. entrance examination and
			<lb />
			therefore, she would not want to pursue the Ph.D programme. The
			<lb />
			petitioner also alleged that she had been threatened that her career
			<lb />
			would be destroyed and that an inquiry would be set up and that
			<lb />
			consequently she would be blacklisted from pursuing any career
			<lb />
			throughout India.
			<lb />
			6.
			<lb />
			The contention of the petitioner is that at that time she did not
			<lb />
			succumb to the pressures of Ms.Aparna Dixit, respondent no.2.
			<lb />
			However, thereafter, respondent no.2 became more abusive and
			<lb />
			shouted at her and even pushed her on the chair, because of which the
			<lb />
			petitioner even hurt her arm and became scared. The petitioner was
			<lb />
			thereafter, confined to the room of respondent No.2 and she was further
			<lb />
			threatened that if she did not write the confession that the examination
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P(C) 5725/2008
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 3 of 71
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			paper was leaked out to her, her image would be maligned by falsely
			<lb />
			publicizing that the petitioner was having illicit sexual relations with
			<lb />
			Professor Uttam Pati. The petitioner further alleged that when she still
			<lb />
			refused to comply with respondent no.2&quot;s demands, she was locked into
			<lb />
			the room and was not even given water or even allowed to go for nature
			<lb />
			calls. The petitioner had also noticed that there were other persons
			<lb />
			present near the door of the room in order to help respondent no.2 due
			<lb />
			to which reason the petitioner got scared and thereafter, she wrote
			<lb />
			whatsoever was dictated to her by Ms.Aparna Dixit under coercion and
			<lb />
			pressure.
			<lb />
			7.
			<lb />
			Thereafter, whatsoever was dictated by Ms.Aparna Dixit, was
			<lb />
			written by the petitioner. Even after that respondent no.2 was not
			<lb />
			satisfied with the same and therefore, asked the petitioner re-write it.
			<lb />
			Respondent No.2, Ms.Aparna Dixit, thereafter directed Professor
			<lb />
			R.Bhatnagar to dictate certain statements and coerced the petitioner to
			<lb />
			write the same. Still not being satisfied with whatsoever was dictated by
			<lb />
			respondent No.2, Ms.Aparna Dixit and Professor Bhatnagar, they again
			<lb />
			wanted the petitioner to modify her alleged confession. The petitioner
			<lb />
			however, declined to do so, due to which reason she was even slapped
			<lb />
			by respondent no.2. Under these circumstances, left with no other
			<lb />
			choice the petitioner again wrote whatsoever was dictated to her. On
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P(C) 5725/2008
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 4 of 71
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			account of this behavior and treatment meted to her as detailed, she
			<lb />
			started weeping and pleaded with Ms.Aparna Dixit to let her go.
			<lb />
			8.
			<lb />
			The petitioner alleged that ignoring her pleas, Ms.Aparna Dixit
			<lb />
			and Professor Bhatnagar, dictated yet another, fourth letter as she
			<lb />
			wasn&quot;t still satisfied by the third letter. Respondent No.2, Ms.Aparna
			<lb />
			Dixit also stated at the time as under:
			<lb />
			&quot;YEH BAHUT DHEETH LADKI HAI SHAYAD ISKE PARIWAR
			<lb />
			VALE BHI AISE HAI. MUJHE TO LAGTA HAI KISI CHOTI
			<lb />
			JATI KI HAI TABHI TO PRESSURE MEI NAHI AA RAHI HAI.
			<lb />
			KAMINI YOU BITCH WRITE DOWN YOUR CONFESSION
			<lb />
			(Petitioner is very obstinate person like her other family
			<lb />
			member. I feel that she belongs to a lower castes and that&quot;s
			<lb />
			why she cannot be pressurized. Bitch, write down your
			<lb />
			confession)&quot;
			<lb />
			9.
			<lb />
			The alleged confessions/letters obtained from the petitioner in the
			<lb />
			above noted circumstances are as under:-
			<lb />
			FIRST
			<lb />
			&quot;To,
			<lb />
			The Dean
			<lb />
			School of Biotechnology
			<lb />
			Jawaharlal Nehru University
			<lb />
			New Delhi-110067.
			<lb />
			Dear Sir,
			<lb />
			With regret I admit to having gained access to the
			<lb />
			entrance examination paper for the Ph.d entrance
			<lb />
			examination, 2007. And I request you not to take any
			<lb />
			action against me I assure you that I will not join if I will be
			<lb />
			selected.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P(C) 5725/2008
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 5 of 71
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			Yours sincerely,
			<lb />
			Flora Gupta
			<lb />
			Date: 25.7.07
			<lb />
			Time: 6.50 pm
			<lb />
			SECOND
			<lb />
			To,
			<lb />
			The Dean
			<lb />
			School of Biotechnology
			<lb />
			Jawaharlal Nehru University
			<lb />
			JNU
			<lb />
			N.D-110067.
			<lb />
			Dear Madam,
			<lb />
			I got the Ph.D entrance examination on paper from
			<lb />
			the Sir room and I confess that I did that mistake.
			<lb />
			Yours sincerely,
			<lb />
			Flora Gupta
			<lb />
			Sd/-
			<lb />
			Date: 25.7.07
			<lb />
			THIRD
			<lb />
			To,
			<lb />
			The Dean
			<lb />
			School of Biotechnology
			<lb />
			Jawaharlal Nehru University
			<lb />
			JNU
			<lb />
			N.D-110067.
			<lb />
			Dear Madam,
			<lb />
			I got the question papers from the Sir&quot;s room &amp;
			<lb />
			practice for 1 hour &amp; just wrote down the answers. And I
			<lb />
			confess that I did that mistake &amp; feel sorry for that.
			<lb />
			Yours sincerely,
			<lb />
			Flora Gupta
			<lb />
			Sd/-
			<lb />
			Date: 25.7.07
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P(C) 5725/2008
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 6 of 71
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			FOURTH
			<lb />
			To,
			<lb />
			The Dean
			<lb />
			School of Biotechnology
			<lb />
			Jawaharlal Nehru University
			<lb />
			JNU
			<lb />
			N.D-110067.
			<lb />
			Dear Sir,
			<lb />
			I asked the sir that Ph.d entrance examination
			<lb />
			question paper, &amp; he told me that it was in the table draw
			<lb />
			and I take it from there.
			<lb />
			I confess that I did that mistake, and feel very sorry.
			<lb />
			Please don&quot;t take any action against me.
			<lb />
			Yours sincerely,
			<lb />
			Flora Gupta
			<lb />
			Date: 25.7.07&quot;
			<lb />
			10. The petitioner alleged that Ms.Aparna Dixit had told her that she
			<lb />
			would burn the earlier three drafts and would keep only the last letter
			<lb />
			written by her and thereafter, she started to tear down the earlier drafts
			<lb />
			of the alleged confession letters and threw them into the trash.
			<lb />
			Thereafter, the petitioner was allowed to leave the room around 9.00
			<lb />
			pm.
			<lb />
			11. According to the petitioner, on 25 th July, 2007 as it had been very
			<lb />
			late, she could not make any complaint with the Police, however, on
			<lb />
			26 th July, 2007 the very next day she went to the Police Station to file
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P(C) 5725/2008
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 7 of 71
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			the complaint. The result of the Ph.D entrance examination was also
			<lb />
			declared on 26 th July, 2007.
			<lb />
			12. On 26 th July, 2007, the petitioner also went to the office of Ms.
			<lb />
			Aparna Dixit, respondent no.2 to give to her a letter retracting the
			<lb />
			alleged confessions which were obtained from her under duress and
			<lb />
			coercion, however, respondent No.2 tore her retraction letter and stated
			<lb />
			angrily as under:-
			<lb />
			&quot;TUM APNI JID SE BAAJ NAHI AAEE AUR PHIR AA GAI AB
			<lb />
			DEKHTI HU KI TUMHAE ENQUIRY COMMISSION SE KAUN
			<lb />
			BACHATA HAI. AB MEI TUMARA SARA CAREER AUR
			<lb />
			ZINDAGI TABAH KAR DUNGI&quot;
			<lb />
			13. The petitioner, thereafter, narrated the incident to her parents,
			<lb />
			pursuant to which her father wrote a letter dated 29 th July, 2007 to Mr.
			<lb />
			Kumar Adhikari, Rector-II, JNU. Another letter was written on 30 th
			<lb />
			July, 2007 in respect of the whole episode, however, the petitioner was
			<lb />
			not allowed to register herself for the Ph.D. programme although she
			<lb />
			had topped the entrance examination.
			<lb />
			14. The petitioner had also applied for the character certificate for the
			<lb />
			period of 2003-05 by letter dated 11 th October, 2007 to Ms.Aparna
			<lb />
			Dixit, during which period she had completed her M.Sc. in
			<lb />
			Biotechnology. As the character certificate was not given to the
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P(C) 5725/2008
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 8 of 71
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			petitioner, another request was made on 17 th October, 2007. However,
			<lb />
			without disclosing any reason the character certificate for 2003-05 was
			<lb />
			not issued to the petitioner, because of which reason the petitioner,
			<lb />
			thereafter, again made another request on 11 th January, 2008. As
			<lb />
			Ms.Aparna Dixit was persistently declining to give the character
			<lb />
			certificate to the petitioner, a request was even sent to the Vice
			<lb />
			Chancellor of respondent No.1 on 13 th February, 2008 and thereafter,
			<lb />
			another request was made on 15 th March, 2008. On failing to get a
			<lb />
			character certificate without any cause or reason, the petitioner
			<lb />
			ultimately sent a legal notice dated 7 th April, 2008. The communication
			<lb />
			requesting the character certificate and also the legal notice demanding
			<lb />
			the character certificate was not replied to by the respondents. The
			<lb />
			petitioner contended that thereafter, she got a character certificate
			<lb />
			dated 9 th April, 2008 incorporating that an Inquiry Committee has been
			<lb />
			set up against the petitioner and that the report of the Inquiry
			<lb />
			committee is awaited.
			<lb />
			15. The petitioner further disclosed that she had been informed on
			<lb />
			11 th January, 2008 about the single member inquiry committee
			<lb />
			comprising of Professor Rameshwar Singh, respondent No.3 being
			<lb />
			constituted by the Vice Chancellor of respondent No.1 against the
			<lb />
			selection of the petitioner in the Ph.D Programme. The letter dated 11 th
			<lb />
			January, 2008 intimating the petitioner about the appointment of a one
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P(C) 5725/2008
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 9 of 71
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			member inquiry committee and directing her to appear before the said
			<lb />
			committee so that the member of the committee could talk to her and
			<lb />
			record her statement is as under:-
			<lb />
			&quot;PROFESSOR RAMESHWAR SINGH ENQUIRY COMMITTEE
			<lb />
			11 TH January, 2008
			<lb />
			The undersigned has been appointed by the Vice-
			<lb />
			Chancellor, JNU as One-member Enquiry Committee to
			<lb />
			look into the matter (issue) of selection of two candidates in
			<lb />
			Pre-Ph.D. programme of the School of Biotechnology in
			<lb />
			which the candidates allegedly appeared to have had prior
			<lb />
			access to the question papers of entrance examination. The
			<lb />
			enquiry is to ascertain the correct facts relating to the said
			<lb />
			matter in the contest of deliberations done by faculty and
			<lb />
			statements/representations made by candidates.
			<lb />
			The undersigned would like to talk to the concerned
			<lb />
			persons and record their statements to ascertain the facts
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			matter.
			<lb />
			Since
			<lb />
			your
			<lb />
			name
			<lb />
			appears
			<lb />
			in
			<lb />
			statements/proceedings on record concerning this matter, I
			<lb />
			need to have a talk with you and record your statement.
			<lb />
			I request you to please come to Room No.026,
			<lb />
			Administrative Block, JNU at 3.30 p.m. on 17 th January,
			<lb />
			2008.
			<lb />
			(RAMESHWAR SINGH)
			<lb />
			Enquiry Officer&quot;
			<lb />
			16. The petitioner averred that she was not given any
			<lb />
			statements/documents or any material relied on by respondent No.2 on
			<lb />
			the basis of which, the single member inquiry committee was
			<lb />
			appointed. She contended that nothing was disclosed to her on the
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P(C) 5725/2008
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 10 of 71
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			basis of one member committee was constituted, however, she filed
			<lb />
			some relevant documents substantiating her innocence on 17 th
			<lb />
			January, 2008.
			<lb />
			17. On 7 th February, 2008, the petitioner even sought information
			<lb />
			about the findings of the one man inquiry committee under the
			<lb />
			provisions of the Right to Information Act. Consequent to her request
			<lb />
			dated 7 th February, 2008, the petitioner received a reply by
			<lb />
			communication dated 7 th March, 2008 intimating her that any
			<lb />
			information which is not in existence or is not held by the public
			<lb />
			authority cannot be supplied for the reason that it is not available and
			<lb />
			therefore, the information sought by her cannot be supplied as
			<lb />
			respondent No.1 does not have any information about the inquiry report
			<lb />
			from the inquiry officer, Professor Rameshwar Singh, respondent No.3.
			<lb />
			18. The petitioner had also sought a copy of the order constituting
			<lb />
			the single member inquiry committee by her letter dated 14 th February,
			<lb />
			2008. Subsequently she was intimated by letter dated 3 rd April, 2008
			<lb />
			indicating that the information sought by her has been received and
			<lb />
			duly enclosed with the said letter.
			<lb />
			19. Aggrieved by the non-supply of the information regarding the
			<lb />
			enquiry report sought by the petitioner, she filed an appeal, which was
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P(C) 5725/2008
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 11 of 71
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			however, disposed of by order dated 6 th May, 2008. The order
			<lb />
			categorically stated that the concerned department had intimated that
			<lb />
			the information sought by the petitioner is not available with them
			<lb />
			which fact had already been disclosed to the petitioner by letter dated
			<lb />
			7 th March, 2008. The order further stipulated that though later on, the
			<lb />
			information was received from the concerned department, however, as
			<lb />
			the final action on the inquiry committee report had not yet been taken,
			<lb />
			therefore, the information is not ripe for disclosure and so it is to be
			<lb />
			exempted under Section 8(1)(h) of the Right to Information Act, 2005.
			<lb />
			Relevant extract of the order dated 6 th May, 2008 is as under:-
			<lb />
			&quot;It was explained to the Appellant that information sought
			<lb />
			by her regarding a copy of the Inquiry Report was
			<lb />
			ascertained from the concerned Deptts in the University.
			<lb />
			However, since the concerned Deptts. have intimated that
			<lb />
			no such information is available with them, about which
			<lb />
			the Appellant has been duly informed vide letter dated
			<lb />
			7.3.2008. However, the appellant requested that perhaps
			<lb />
			the Inquiry Officer, Professor Rameshwar Singh, may be
			<lb />
			contacted by the dealing office to ascertain the status of the
			<lb />
			Inquiry Report. She further requests that the O/O the Vice-
			<lb />
			Chancellor/Rectors/Coordinator may also be contacted
			<lb />
			once again if they have received the Inquiry Committee
			<lb />
			Report. It was agreed that after this the Appellant may be
			<lb />
			informed about the outcome of the efforts, as aforesaid.
			<lb />
			Subsequently, before this Order could be issued, the
			<lb />
			concerned Deptts. informed that although the Inquiry
			<lb />
			Report has been received, but final action on the inquiry
			<lb />
			Committee Report is not yet taken, i.e. Inquiry Report is
			<lb />
			still under the consideration of the University. Therefore, in
			<lb />
			my view, the information since not ripe for disclosure at
			<lb />
			this premature-stage, the same is exempt under Section
			<lb />
			8(1)(h), which is reproduced below:
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P(C) 5725/2008
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 12 of 71
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			Section 8: Exemption from disclosure of information
			<lb />
			(1)
			<lb />
			Notwithstanding anything contained in this Act, there
			<lb />
			shall be no obligation to give citizen:-
			<lb />
			(h)
			<lb />
			Information which would impede the process of
			<lb />
			investigation or apprehension or prosecution of
			<lb />
			offenders.&quot;
			<lb />
			20. The grievance of the petitioner is that though the single member
			<lb />
			commission had already given its report dated 7 th March, 2008,
			<lb />
			however, the same was not given to her despite repeated pleas.
			<lb />
			Consequently, the petitioner was left with no option but to file a
			<lb />
			criminal complaint against Ms.Aparna Dixit, which the petitioner
			<lb />
			contends is pending before the court of Sh. Sameer Vajpayee,
			<lb />
			Metropolitan Magistrate. In the complaint filed before the metropolitan
			<lb />
			magistrate, a copy of the report dated 7 th March, 2008 was also filed on
			<lb />
			3 rd July, 2008.
			<lb />
			21. Impugning the inquiry report dated 7 th March, 2008, the
			<lb />
			petitioner has contended that the inquiry officer had relied on certain
			<lb />
			documents detailed in the report, the copy of which were not supplied
			<lb />
			to her. The documents referred to and relied on by the one member
			<lb />
			inquiry committee are as under:-
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P(C) 5725/2008
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 13 of 71
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			&quot;ENQUIRY REPORT
			<lb />
			With the Office Order appointing me as Enquiry
			<lb />
			Officer, I was provided the following &quot;documents (photostat
			<lb />
			copies)&quot;.
			<lb />
			1.
			<lb />
			A letter, dated July 30, 2007, from the Dean Prof.
			<lb />
			Aparna Dixit, addressed to the JNU Vice Chancellor, which
			<lb />
			contained detailed information about as to how the
			<lb />
			concerned matter was dealt with by the Faculty Committee
			<lb />
			etc. The letter also made a request to set up an inquiry to
			<lb />
			look into the matter.
			<lb />
			2.
			<lb />
			Minutes of the Faculty Meeting held on July 25,
			<lb />
			2007. In their deliberations, the faculty discussed the
			<lb />
			matter of very high marks scored by the two candidates in
			<lb />
			JNU Entrance Examination of 2007, and had decided: not
			<lb />
			to withhold the declaration of entrance examination results
			<lb />
			and that the matter should be investigated.
			<lb />
			3.
			<lb />
			Four different statements of Ms.Gargi Roy, which she
			<lb />
			wrote on 25 th July, 2007 during 6.40 pm to 7.45 p.m. In
			<lb />
			these, she revealed how she gained access to the entrance
			<lb />
			examination question paper. The statements were
			<lb />
			addressed to the Dean, School of Biotechnology.
			<lb />
			4.
			<lb />
			Four different statements of Ms.Flora Gupta, which
			<lb />
			she wrote on 25 th July, 2007 at 6.50 p.m. onwards. In these
			<lb />
			statements, she revealed how she got access to the
			<lb />
			examination paper etc. The statements were addressed to
			<lb />
			the Dean, School of Biotechnology.
			<lb />
			5.
			<lb />
			Letter dated 25.07.2007 addressed by Ms.Flora
			<lb />
			Gupta to Prof. Uttam K.Pati. In this letter, she talks of
			<lb />
			pressure etc. put on her to write confessional statements,
			<lb />
			and further stated that none of the statements were true.
			<lb />
			6.
			<lb />
			Minutes of the Faculty Meeting held on July 27,
			<lb />
			2007. In their deliberations, the faculty seem to have
			<lb />
			discussed the concerned matter in great details, and have
			<lb />
			talked to the two candidates.
			<lb />
			7.
			<lb />
			A letter from Ms.Gargi Roy (dated 27.07.07)
			<lb />
			addressed to the Dean, School of Biotechnology in which
			<lb />
			she stated that &quot;the statements&quot; were dictated, and she was
			<lb />
			retracting them etc.&quot;
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P(C) 5725/2008
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 14 of 71
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			22. The petitioner also referred to the categorical observation made in
			<lb />
			the enquiry commission report indicating that Professor Uttam Pati had
			<lb />
			stated that the petitioner had not written the statement on her own and
			<lb />
			that the text written in the confessional statement was entirely the
			<lb />
			product of the Professor Bhatnagar and Ms.Aparna Dixit, respondent
			<lb />
			No.2. The relevant observations made in the inquiry report dated 7 th
			<lb />
			March, 2008 are as under:-
			<lb />
			&quot;To look into the matter, I felt it necessary to talk to the
			<lb />
			Faculty members of the School of Biotechnology, as they at
			<lb />
			one stage or the other had dealt with the matter. It was in
			<lb />
			the presence of three faculty members, i.e., Prof. Aparna
			<lb />
			Dixit, Prof. Uttam Pati and Prof.Rakesh Bhatnagar, that the
			<lb />
			two (Flora Gupta and Gargi) wrote their &quot;confessional&quot;
			<lb />
			statements. Thereafter, a full fledged Faculty Meeting took
			<lb />
			place and deliberated over the matter.
			<lb />
			I, therefore, talked to the Faculty of the School of
			<lb />
			Biotechnology and recorded their statements. I also talked
			<lb />
			to the two candidates: Ms.Flora Gupta and Ms.Gargi Roy
			<lb />
			and took their statements on record.
			<lb />
			In their testimony (deposition) before me, the two:
			<lb />
			Flora Gupta and Gargi Roy admitted that they wrote their
			<lb />
			statements when Professors Dixit, Uttam Pati and Rakesh
			<lb />
			Bhatnagar were present, and these statements are on
			<lb />
			record. Four statements were written by each one of them
			<lb />
			in a span of about an hour. A close perusal of these
			<lb />
			statements would show that the first statements of the two
			<lb />
			were &quot;Identical&quot; to each other (only there is a minor
			<lb />
			difference in the last few words of Flora Gupta&quot;s statement).
			<lb />
			They admitted that they had gained &quot;access&quot; to the
			<lb />
			entrance examination paper, requested not to take any
			<lb />
			action against them, and assured that they would not join if
			<lb />
			selected. Gargi Roy wrote at 6.40 p.m. and Flora Gupta at
			<lb />
			6.50 p.m. It, therefore, appears that the latter &quot;copied&quot; from
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P(C) 5725/2008
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 15 of 71
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			the text of the former&quot;s statement.
			<lb />
			It seems that when they (i.e. the two girls) were
			<lb />
			grilled/probed further as to how they obtained access to the
			<lb />
			question paper, they wrote their second statements which
			<lb />
			were &quot;not identical&quot;: Gargi wrote &quot;regret and confess and
			<lb />
			Flora wrote that &quot;I got the Ph.D. entrance examination
			<lb />
			paper from the Sir room-I confess that I did that mistake.
			<lb />
			On further probing, they responded by giving other
			<lb />
			two statements which were not identical to each other&quot;s.
			<lb />
			However, both of them revealed one common thing, that is,
			<lb />
			&quot;they got the question papers from their guides&quot; &quot;Sir&quot;s room,
			<lb />
			and Flora, in addition, wrote that &quot;she wrote answers and
			<lb />
			practiced for one hour&quot;. On still further probing, they again
			<lb />
			wrote statements (one each) which were not identical to
			<lb />
			each other&quot;s. But these statements have a common point
			<lb />
			that they (the two) asked &quot;guide&quot; &quot;Sir&quot; about examination-
			<lb />
			examination paper and they were helped by him in getting
			<lb />
			the access&quot; etc.
			<lb />
			In all, each one of the two wrote four written
			<lb />
			statements and handed them to the Dean Prof. Aparna
			<lb />
			Dixit in the presence of Prof. Rakesh Bhatnagar and Prof.
			<lb />
			Uttam Pati.
			<lb />
			Prof. Uttam Pati, in his testimony before me, claimed
			<lb />
			that he did not open his mouth during this meeting in
			<lb />
			which the two girls were questioned, and all the questioning
			<lb />
			was done by Prof. Dixit and Prof. Bhatnagar only.
			<lb />
			Prof.Uttam Pati further claimed that the text of the
			<lb />
			statements the girls wrote was dictated by Prof. Bhatnagar
			<lb />
			and Prof. Dixit implying that the two girls on their own did
			<lb />
			not write the statements, and the text written in the said
			<lb />
			statements &quot;is entirely the product of Prof. Bhatnagar&quot;s and
			<lb />
			Prof. Dixit&quot;s mind.&quot;
			<lb />
			The two candidates after having given their
			<lb />
			statements on 25 th July, 2007 came up with letters which
			<lb />
			they claim to be their &quot;retraction&quot; letters in which they have
			<lb />
			&quot;retracted&quot; from their earlier statements. Flora Gupta
			<lb />
			addressed her retraction letter (dated 25.07.07) to Prof.Pati
			<lb />
			and a copy of was endorsed to the President Student&quot;s
			<lb />
			Union. In this letter she says none of the statements given
			<lb />
			by her were &quot;true&quot;, and the statements were taken under
			<lb />
			threat etc. Flora Gupta then addressed a &quot;retraction&quot; letter
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P(C) 5725/2008
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 16 of 71
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			to Rector-II on July 30, 2007 in which she alleged that her
			<lb />
			confession letters were dictations given by the Dean. Flora
			<lb />
			Gupta&quot;s father has also sent a letter to JNU VC claiming
			<lb />
			essentially that his daughter was harassed and
			<lb />
			inappropriately treated etc.&quot;
			<lb />
			23. The inquiry committee report dated 7 th March, 2008 also
			<lb />
			discussed about the recorded statements of Professor S.K.Kar, Dr.Rajiv
			<lb />
			Bhat, Dr.S.Maitra, Dr.D.Choudhury and Dr.K.J.Mukherjee as well as
			<lb />
			the retraction letter produced by Professor Uttam Pati given by the
			<lb />
			petitioner dated 25 th July, 2007 which was produced in the meeting on
			<lb />
			27 th July, 2007.
			<lb />
			24. The single member committee however rejected the retraction
			<lb />
			letter given by the petitioner on the ground that it was dropped into the
			<lb />
			mail box of Professor Uttam Pati and that said the retraction letter was
			<lb />
			clearly an afterthoughts and thus it does not deserve any credence. The
			<lb />
			relevant portion of the reasoning given in the inquiry committee report
			<lb />
			is as under:-
			<lb />
			&quot;It is also instructive to note that the &quot;retraction&quot;
			<lb />
			statement written by Flora Gupta was addressed to Prof.
			<lb />
			Pati and was dropped into his mail box, and Prof. Pati
			<lb />
			brings it to the notice of the Faculty Committee only when
			<lb />
			the matter had already been discussed and deliberated for
			<lb />
			quite sometime. This also cannot be ignored that Professor
			<lb />
			Pati did not bring to the attention of the Faculty Committee
			<lb />
			that &quot;the statements which are being attributed to the two
			<lb />
			girls&quot; are dictions by the two Professors because the Faculty
			<lb />
			Committee was deciding to ask for an enquiry or as such
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P(C) 5725/2008
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 17 of 71
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			was dealing with the matter largely and substantially on
			<lb />
			the basis of their confessional statements. Furthermore, it
			<lb />
			is also of great interest that in those statements Prof. Pati
			<lb />
			had been referred to as &quot;Sir (and he admits &quot;Sir&quot; refers to
			<lb />
			him)-even then before the Faculty Committee he does not
			<lb />
			disclose &quot;that the statements are the result of dictations&quot;.
			<lb />
			In response to the interrogation by Prof. Dixit and Prof.
			<lb />
			Bhatnagar aimed at finding out whether the two candidates
			<lb />
			(Ms. Flora Gupta and Ms.Gargi Roy adopted some unfair
			<lb />
			means n the examination or have had access to the
			<lb />
			question papers prior to the examination, Flora Gupta and
			<lb />
			Gargi Roy wrote their separate statements in which they
			<lb />
			said they had access to the question paper (prior to the
			<lb />
			entrance exam), and briefly also outlined how they got the
			<lb />
			access. Their statements reveal they sought help from their
			<lb />
			teacher (Prof. Pati) for preparing for the entrance
			<lb />
			examination of JNU. The teacher responded by making it
			<lb />
			convenient for them to go through the copy of the
			<lb />
			concerned question paper. This could be possible because
			<lb />
			Prof. Pati had set (compiled) the question paper. So the
			<lb />
			&quot;access&quot; came to them (the two candidates), they did not
			<lb />
			indulge in some unfair activity to obtain it.
			<lb />
			In view of this my conclusion is that these theories of
			<lb />
			&quot;retraction&quot; &quot;dictations&quot; are simply after thoughts and
			<lb />
			command no credence/credibility, and the statements
			<lb />
			which the two candidates Flora Gupta and Gargi wrote
			<lb />
			were not the product of dictions but of whatever they could
			<lb />
			truthfully write at that point of time, and certainly reveal a
			<lb />
			substantial part of the truth of the matter i.e. they did not
			<lb />
			have an access to the paper and that &quot;access&quot; was provided
			<lb />
			to them in Prof. Pati&quot;s room. Prof. Pati&quot;s assertion, as I have
			<lb />
			discussed above would command no credence. He in his
			<lb />
			written deposition before me talks of that nobody else knew
			<lb />
			the question paper. But he wholly ignores, that the point
			<lb />
			here is not that nobody else knew the question paper after
			<lb />
			he has compiled it, the crux of the matter was whether he
			<lb />
			made it known to the two candidates. His implied silence
			<lb />
			on this despite the reference to &quot;Sir&quot;s Room&quot; etc in the
			<lb />
			25.07.07 statements (of the two candidates) is indeed
			<lb />
			intriguing, and his taking shelter behind the wholly
			<lb />
			untenable &quot;theory of dictions&quot; demolishes his innocence in
			<lb />
			the matter, thus it is not possible to exonerate him because
			<lb />
			of his plea that &quot;statements&quot; were dictated.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P(C) 5725/2008
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 18 of 71
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			Therefore, I conclude that it is beyond any reasonable
			<lb />
			doubt that the two candidates did have access to the
			<lb />
			question paper prior to the entrance examination and the
			<lb />
			bits of how they came to have that access are also clear in
			<lb />
			the discussion above in this report.&quot;
			<lb />
			25. The petitioner was, thereafter given a show cause notice dated
			<lb />
			15 th July, 2008 stipulating as to why disciplinary action should not be
			<lb />
			taken against her. The petitioner replied to the show cause notice by
			<lb />
			reply dated 18 th July, 2008 contending, inter-alia, that she cannot
			<lb />
			comprehend as to on what grounds the single member inquiry
			<lb />
			committee had arrived at the conclusion that she had access to the
			<lb />
			examination paper and that she is also unable to answer the allegation
			<lb />
			against her as inquiry committee report dated 7 th March, 2008 was not
			<lb />
			given to her. The petitioner, therefore, sought to be provided with the
			<lb />
			complete inquiry report including all the relevant documents.
			<lb />
			26. The respondents refuted the pleas and contentions raised by the
			<lb />
			petitioner and filed the counter affidavit dated 1 st November, 2008
			<lb />
			contending, inter-alia that no cause of action had arisen in favor of the
			<lb />
			petitioner to file the present writ petition. According to the respondents
			<lb />
			the petitioner is guilty of gross misconduct as she had obtained illegal
			<lb />
			access to the Ph.D. entrance examination paper of the School of
			<lb />
			Biotechnology, JNU and had thereafter appeared for the same. Since
			<lb />
			the petitioner had answered the said examination (Theory/written part)
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P(C) 5725/2008
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 19 of 71
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			after having prior access to the question paper, had obtained
			<lb />
			exceptionally high marks i.e. 58 ½ out of 70 in the written examination.
			<lb />
			As a result of the manipulation done by the petitioner it was contended
			<lb />
			that her examination result was vitiated.
			<lb />
			27.
			<lb />
			According to the respondents, the faculty of the School of
			<lb />
			Biotechnology, JNU considered the matter and forwarded it to the Vice
			<lb />
			Chancellor of JNU who appointed a one man inquiry committee
			<lb />
			comprising of Prof. Rameshwar Singh, Respondent no.3 who enquired
			<lb />
			into the matter and submitted his report on 7 th March, 2007 giving the
			<lb />
			finding that the petitioner had prior access to the question paper. The
			<lb />
			said report had been accepted by the Vice Chancellor of JNU pursuant
			<lb />
			to which the order dated 5 th August, 2008 was passed whereby the Vice
			<lb />
			Chancellor exercised the power vested in him under Statue 32 of the
			<lb />
			Statutes of the University under The Jawahar Lal Nehru University Act,
			<lb />
			1966 whereby he ordered that the entire JNU Campus would be out of
			<lb />
			bounds for the petitioner for five years with immediate effect and that
			<lb />
			she would also be debarred from taking admission in any program of
			<lb />
			study of the JNU for the next five academic years. It was also ordered
			<lb />
			that anyone who would give shelter to the petitioner in any of the
			<lb />
			premises of the University would invite strict disciplinary action against
			<lb />
			him/her.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P(C) 5725/2008
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 20 of 71
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			28. The respondents denied that the petitioner was a brilliant student
			<lb />
			who topped the Ph.D. entrance examination of School of Biotechnology,
			<lb />
			JNU. It was also categorically denied that she was forced to write the
			<lb />
			confession by respondent No.2 and was prevented for enrolling for the
			<lb />
			Ph.D. program so as to make the seat available for another student.
			<lb />
			29. The respondents averred that the allegations made in the writ
			<lb />
			petition are baseless and have been made with the malafide intention of
			<lb />
			somehow deflecting the attention from the manipulation/illegality done
			<lb />
			by the petitioner. Regarding the petitioner, the respondents further
			<lb />
			asserted that after doing her M.Sc. in the year 2005 from the School of
			<lb />
			Biotechnology, JNU, she did not join any course. In her M.Sc. course,
			<lb />
			the petitioner was placed at the ranking of 12 in the batch of 14
			<lb />
			students and that she had secured a cumulative grade point average
			<lb />
			(CGPA) of 5.18 out of 9 and thus, barely qualified for writing the Ph.D.
			<lb />
			entrance test. The respondents also disclosed that the petitioner had
			<lb />
			failed to clear the Ph.D. entrance exam of JNU in the year 2005 and
			<lb />
			2006.
			<lb />
			30. According to the respondents, after qualifying the M.Sc. in
			<lb />
			Biotechnology in the year 2005, the petitioner had been working as a
			<lb />
			Junior Research Fellow (JRF) with Prof. Uttam Pati, who was the Dean
			<lb />
			of the School of Biotechnology before Ms.Aparan Dixit, who took over as
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P(C) 5725/2008
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 21 of 71
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			Dean on 25 th April, 2007. The respondents further disclosed that the
			<lb />
			theory question paper of the Ph.D. entrance exam for the year 2007 was
			<lb />
			compiled by and typed out under the supervision of Prof. Uttam Pati.
			<lb />
			According to the respondents, the petitioner and another candidate, Ms
			<lb />
			Gargi Roy, who was also working as a Junior Research Fellow, had
			<lb />
			managed to secure access to the question papers of the Ph.D. entrance
			<lb />
			exam and both of them had obtained very high marks which aroused
			<lb />
			the suspicion of the faculty members of the School of Biotechnology.
			<lb />
			According to the respondents, the petitioner had confessed on her own
			<lb />
			that she adopted illegal and unlawful means and wrote the same in her
			<lb />
			confession dated 25 th July, 2007. The respondents also averred that the
			<lb />
			petitioner had never complained to the police at the said point of time
			<lb />
			that she had allegedly been forced to write the confession, nor had she
			<lb />
			made any complaint to the higher police authority against the non-
			<lb />
			recording of her complaint at the concerned police station as alleged by
			<lb />
			her.
			<lb />
			31. Regarding the character certificate, the respondents have
			<lb />
			contended that the character certificate was sought with the intention
			<lb />
			of diverting the attention from her own wrong doings and that it was
			<lb />
			pertinent to note that the petitioner did not seek the character
			<lb />
			certificate from her project supervisor Prof. Uttam Pati and instead
			<lb />
			insisted the same from Ms.Aparna Dixit, Dean of the School of
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P(C) 5725/2008
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 22 of 71
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			Biotechnology, who regardless had issued the character certificate
			<lb />
			dated 9 th April, 2008 after obtaining the approval from the Rector-II,
			<lb />
			JNU. Since the inquiry report dated 7 th March, 2008 had been
			<lb />
			submitted by respondent No.3 affirming the fact that the petitioner had
			<lb />
			prior access to the question paper, therefore, it was endorsed on the
			<lb />
			character certificate as well.
			<lb />
			32. The respondents, however, admitted that the petitioner had filed
			<lb />
			a criminal complaint dated 26 th May, 2008 against Ms.Aparna Dixit
			<lb />
			before the ACMM, Patiala House Court in which the police was directed
			<lb />
			to investigate the allegations and submit a status report. The police had
			<lb />
			thereafter, filed a status report stipulating that the allegations made by
			<lb />
			the petitioner were not true.
			<lb />
			33. According to the respondents, subsequently a show cause notice
			<lb />
			dated 15 th July, 2008 was issued against the petitioner stipulating as to
			<lb />
			why disciplinary action should not be taken against her. The
			<lb />
			respondents also contended that the petitioner has not come with clean
			<lb />
			hand on the issue as she has not denied that she did not have prior
			<lb />
			access to the question paper. According to the respondents, she has set
			<lb />
			up a baseless and false story with a view to escape the consequences of
			<lb />
			her own deeds. The respondents also disclosed that the criminal
			<lb />
			complaint dated 26 th May, 2008 was filed by the petitioner under
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P(C) 5725/2008
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 23 of 71
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			Sections 348/323/506/469/327/330/342 of Indian Penal Code against
			<lb />
			Ms.Aparna Dixit, whereas the incident complained of had taken place
			<lb />
			on 25 th July, 2007. Thus for almost 10 months she had not made any
			<lb />
			complaints to the police in relation to the alleged incident of Ms.Aparna
			<lb />
			Dixit having obtained the confession from the petitioner under duress
			<lb />
			and coercion. The respondents asserted that the plea of the petitioner
			<lb />
			that the police did not register her complaint is negated by the fact that
			<lb />
			she did not make any complaint to the higher police authorities
			<lb />
			regarding the non-recording her complaint in the said police station.
			<lb />
			The respondents also placed reliance on the status report dated 2 nd
			<lb />
			July, 2008 filed by the police before the Metropolitan Magistrate stating
			<lb />
			that upon inquiry none of the allegations made by the petitioner could
			<lb />
			be substantiated.
			<lb />
			34. Regarding the appointment of the petitioner as a Junior Research
			<lb />
			Fellow (JRF), it was averred that she was appointed for the period 31 st
			<lb />
			July, 2005 till 31 st October, 2005 on the specific request of Prof. Uttam
			<lb />
			Pati. Her appointment as JRF was thereafter extended in the project
			<lb />
			titled as &quot;Co-relation of P53….Cells&quot; from 31 st October, 2005 till 30 th
			<lb />
			October, 2006. The appointment was further extended till 31 st March,
			<lb />
			2007 and thereafter again extended from April to June, 2007.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P(C) 5725/2008
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 24 of 71
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			35. The petitioner was also given appointment in the project titled as,
			<lb />
			&quot;Suppression of Oral-Cancer specific p53 mutants by SIRANA&quot; from 1 st
			<lb />
			July, 2007 to 30 th September, 2007 and extended to 30 th September,
			<lb />
			2008. It was also disclosed that till the date of filing the counter
			<lb />
			affidavit on 1 st November, 2008 the petitioner has continued to work
			<lb />
			with Prof. Uttam Pati in the said project.
			<lb />
			36. Regarding the question paper in which the petitioner is alleged to
			<lb />
			have scored very high marks on account of allegedly having prior access
			<lb />
			to said the question paper, it was disclosed that the written
			<lb />
			examination has both basic and applied questions from different
			<lb />
			disciples of sciences i.e. physics, mathematics, biology, chemistry and
			<lb />
			modern biological sciences and that the answer sheets of the written
			<lb />
			examination are evaluated by computer. However, the candidates never
			<lb />
			score such high marks as were obtained by the petitioner and Ms. Gargi
			<lb />
			Roy in the written examination. It was further alleged that the
			<lb />
			candidates majoring in physical sciences (mathematics, physics &amp;
			<lb />
			chemistry) are able to answer the applied questions related to these
			<lb />
			fields whereas the candidates majoring in Biological sciences
			<lb />
			(biochemistry, Biotechnology &amp; Biology) are able to answer applied
			<lb />
			questions from these subjects/areas. The respondents also relied on the
			<lb />
			comparison of the petitioner&quot;s marks in the examination for the year
			<lb />
			2005-2006, 2006-2007 &amp; 2007-2008 in her attempts at the Ph. D.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P(C) 5725/2008
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 25 of 71
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			Entrance exams. The comparison of the marks as given by the
			<lb />
			respondents is as under:-
			<lb />
			Ph.D
			<lb />
			entrance
			<lb />
			examination for
			<lb />
			admission in the
			<lb />
			Ph.D
			<lb />
			programme of
			<lb />
			Examination for
			<lb />
			admission in the
			<lb />
			Acad.Year 2005-
			<lb />
			2006 (held in
			<lb />
			May 2006)
			<lb />
			Examination for
			<lb />
			admission in the
			<lb />
			Acad.Year 2006-
			<lb />
			2007 (held in
			<lb />
			May 2006)
			<lb />
			Examination for
			<lb />
			admission in the
			<lb />
			Acad.Year 2007-
			<lb />
			2008 (held in
			<lb />
			May 2007)
			<lb />
			Flora Gupta
			<lb />
			Flora Gupta
			<lb />
			Flora Gupta
			<lb />
			School of Life
			<lb />
			Sciences
			<lb />
			11.00
			<lb />
			11.00
			<lb />
			18.50
			<lb />
			School
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			Biotechnology
			<lb />
			03.00
			<lb />
			20.50
			<lb />
			58.50
			<lb />
			Special Centre
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			Molecular
			<lb />
			Medicine
			<lb />
			25.50
			<lb />
			14.50
			<lb />
			15.50
			<lb />
			37. The respondents also asserted that in the viva voce, the petitioner
			<lb />
			had failed to answer the questions from the basic sciences on the
			<lb />
			pretext that she had studied the same three years ago. Thereafter, the
			<lb />
			petitioner was posed the questions relating to her project where she has
			<lb />
			been working since 2005 with Prof. Uttam Pati and the answers given
			<lb />
			by the petitioner were endorsed to be correct by Prof. Uttam Pati.
			<lb />
			According to the respondents, in the meeting of the faculty which was
			<lb />
			attended by 7 faculty members, it was decided to probe into the matter
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P(C) 5725/2008
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 26 of 71
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			and to withhold the result of the Ph.D. entrance examination. The
			<lb />
			petitioner was then called on 25 th July, 2007 and was questioned by
			<lb />
			Ms.Aparna Dixit, Prof. Uttam Pati and Prof. R.Bhatnagar after which
			<lb />
			the petitioner confessed to have adopted illegal means. According to the
			<lb />
			respondents, the confessions were given by the petitioner in the
			<lb />
			presence of three members, Ms.Aparna Dixit, Prof. Uttam Pati and Prof.
			<lb />
			R.Bhatnagar in a fair and transparent manner without any threat or
			<lb />
			coercion to the petitioner. The allegation of the petitioner being abused
			<lb />
			and physically injured by Ms.Aparna Dixit was specifically denied. It
			<lb />
			was also denied that the alleged confessions were written by the
			<lb />
			petitioner at the instance and on account of the coercion by respondent
			<lb />
			No.2 so that she could secure one seat of the Ph.D. program for another
			<lb />
			student. The allegation that the petitioner had written the retraction
			<lb />
			letter to the respondent No.2 was not admitted and according to the
			<lb />
			respondents, she did not report her alleged version to any other
			<lb />
			authority in JNU as well.
			<lb />
			38. The respondents further disclosed that the matter was considered
			<lb />
			in the subsequent meeting held on 27 th July, 2007 which was attended
			<lb />
			by 8 faculty members and it was unanimously decided to refer the
			<lb />
			matter to the administration to carry out the investigation. The minutes
			<lb />
			of the meeting dated 27 th July, 2007 were forwarded to the Vice
			<lb />
			Chancellor of JNU by letter dated 30 th July, 2007 and on the orders of
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P(C) 5725/2008
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 27 of 71
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			the Vice Chancellor, respondent No.3, Prof. Rameshwar Singh was
			<lb />
			appointed as the one man inquiry committee to enquire into the matter.
			<lb />
			39. The respondents also disclosed that a show cause notice dated
			<lb />
			24 th July, 2008 was issued to Prof. Uttam Pati and the Executive
			<lb />
			Council of JNU in its meeting held on 3 rd September, 2008 has decided
			<lb />
			to authorized the Vice Chancellor, JNU to constitute a full Inquiry
			<lb />
			Committee to investigate the matter as regards Prof. Uttam Pati and his
			<lb />
			involvement in the present matter.
			<lb />
			40. Regarding the inquiry conducted by Prof. Rameshwar Singh and
			<lb />
			the plea taken by the petitioner that she was not allowed to cross-
			<lb />
			examination the witness nor the witnesses were recorded in her
			<lb />
			presence, it was asserted that no witnesses as such were examined
			<lb />
			in the inquiry. According to the respondents, this was neither a Govt.
			<lb />
			departmental inquiry, nor was it subjected to any rigid rules as to
			<lb />
			cross-examine etc. and that the inquiry in any case meets the
			<lb />
			requirements of the principles of natural justice and thus, is valid and
			<lb />
			proper. The grounds as taken in para O-Q of the counter affidavit dated
			<lb />
			1 st November, 2008 are as under:-
			<lb />
			&quot;That the contents of grounds O to Q are wrong and are
			<lb />
			denied. It is denied that the petitioner did not have
			<lb />
			sufficient time to file her defense. There was no occasion
			<lb />
			for cross examination as no witnesses as such were
			<lb />
			examined in the inquiry. The inquiry in question is not a
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P(C) 5725/2008
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 28 of 71
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			government departmental inquiry nor is subject to rigid
			<lb />
			rules as to cross examination etc. The inquiry meets the
			<lb />
			requirements of the principles of natural justice and is valid
			<lb />
			and proper. It is denied that the inquiry report is based on
			<lb />
			frivolous ground.&quot;
			<lb />
			41. Respondents also contended that the case of the petitioner is not
			<lb />
			that of no notice/no hearing but may be a case of inadequate hearing
			<lb />
			and relied on (1996) 3 SCC 364, State Bank of Patiala &amp; Ors. v.
			<lb />
			S.K.Sharma and 19 (2001) DLT 735, Mansoor Azam v. Jamia Milia
			<lb />
			Islamia &amp; Ors. It is contended that the case of the petitioner is not of no
			<lb />
			notice or no hearing as the petitioner was given notice of the inquiry
			<lb />
			proceedings and she has been given an opportunity to state her case
			<lb />
			before the inquiry officer and before passing the order of debarment for
			<lb />
			five years, she was given a show cause notice and the documents as
			<lb />
			demanded by her were given to her. The petitioner too had submitted
			<lb />
			her reply, therefore, no prejudice has been caused to the petitioner by
			<lb />
			the procedure followed and the inquiry held was fair and the order of
			<lb />
			debarment and punishment is therefore, not vitiated. The respondents
			<lb />
			also contended that circumstantial evidence against the petitioner and
			<lb />
			her subsequent conduct point to her guilt and that she herself was
			<lb />
			unable to give any cogent explanation when she was called on 25 th July,
			<lb />
			2007, which is why she had written the confession willfully and without
			<lb />
			any coercion or pressure. Regarding the alleged retraction, it was stated
			<lb />
			that it was an act of afterthought. The respondents also emphasized
			<lb />
			that the petitioner never stake any claim to secure admission to the
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P(C) 5725/2008
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 29 of 71
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			Ph.D. course which fact in itself inculpates the petitioner. The
			<lb />
			respondents refuted the plea of the petitioner regarding the inquiry not
			<lb />
			being conducted under the ordinance of JNU on the ground that she
			<lb />
			was not a student of JNU. As it is contended that &quot;student&quot; under the
			<lb />
			ordinance contemplates a student on the active roll of the University. It
			<lb />
			was further contended that in the circumstances, inquiry could not be
			<lb />
			held under the ordinance of JNU, since the petitioner had merely
			<lb />
			appeared in the entrance examination to secure admission in the
			<lb />
			course. Thus, no formal rules of inquiry were applicable and what was
			<lb />
			required was a fair hearing to the petitioner which has been complied
			<lb />
			with. The respondents justified the action against the petitioner under
			<lb />
			Statue 32 of the JNU and contended that it was a valid, legal and
			<lb />
			justified action as it was taken by the Vice Chancellor of JNU and not
			<lb />
			by any junior official. The respondents also relied on (1993) Supp. 3
			<lb />
			SCC, 82, Controller of Examination &amp; Ors. v. G.S.Sunder &amp; Ors. and
			<lb />
			(2009) 1 SCC, Director (Studies), Dr.Ambedkar Institute of Hotel
			<lb />
			Management, Nutrition and Catering Technology, Chandigarh &amp; Ors. v.
			<lb />
			Vaibhav Singh Chauhan to contend that since the matter of the
			<lb />
			petitioner relates to the enforcement of discipline, the Court should be
			<lb />
			slow in interfering. Reliance was also placed on 70 (1997) DLT 509,
			<lb />
			Narendra Singh v. University of Delhi &amp; Ors., wherein according to the
			<lb />
			respondents, the action against the student of Delhi University was
			<lb />
			upheld even though it was without a formal inquiry. The respondents
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P(C) 5725/2008
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 30 of 71
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			contended that the provisions of the Delhi University are pari-materia to
			<lb />
			Statue 32 of the Statue of JNU. The respondents asserted that the
			<lb />
			petitioner has not challenged the Statue 32 of JNU and that the action
			<lb />
			taken against the petitioner is therefore, entitled to be upheld.
			<lb />
			42. Relying on (1996) 9 SCC, 322, State of Punjab &amp; Ors. v.
			<lb />
			Dr.Harbhajan Singh Grisy, the respondents further contended that if
			<lb />
			there is any flaw in the procedure adopted by the respondents then the
			<lb />
			matter should be remanded back for rehearing/proceeding from the
			<lb />
			point when the flaw had occurred.
			<lb />
			43. The petitioner refuted the allegations made by the respondents
			<lb />
			against her in their counter affidavit and filed a rejoinder affidavit dated
			<lb />
			4 th December, 2008. The petitioner challenged the appointment of
			<lb />
			respondent No.3 as the one man committee relying on the letter dated
			<lb />
			9 th March, 2002 of the University Grants Commission stipulating that
			<lb />
			no retired teacher after the age of 62 years could be appointed on any
			<lb />
			Statutory or even non-statutory position in the University/Colleges.
			<lb />
			Letter dated 9 th March, 2012 of the University Grant Commission is as
			<lb />
			under:-
			<lb />
			&quot;March, 2002
			<lb />
			Dear Sir/Madam,
			<lb />
			It has been brought to the notice of UGC that some of
			<lb />
			the Universities are appointing retired teachers to the
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P(C) 5725/2008
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 31 of 71
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			statutory and non-statutory bodies of the University. The
			<lb />
			matter has been examined by the UGC and it is decided
			<lb />
			that no retired teachers after the age of 62 years be
			<lb />
			appointed on any statutory or even non-statutory position
			<lb />
			in Universities/Colleges.
			<lb />
			This is for your information and necessary action.&quot;
			<lb />
			44. The petitioner refuted the claim of the respondents that she had
			<lb />
			failed to answer the questions regarding the basic science by
			<lb />
			contending that she had been awarded 25 marks out of 30 in the viva
			<lb />
			voce which marks were confirmed to her pursuant to the petitioner
			<lb />
			seeking the information in the application dated 8 th November, 2011
			<lb />
			under the Right to Information Act, 2005. She further disclosed that the
			<lb />
			said Viva Voce had been taken by 5 professors of the JNU, in a face to
			<lb />
			face discussion and thus there was no possibility of cheating at the
			<lb />
			time.
			<lb />
			45. The petitioner has relied on Harpal Singh Sangwal v. University of
			<lb />
			Delhi &amp; Ors., 2008 VIII AD (Delhi) 494; Sibaram Panda &amp; Ors. v.
			<lb />
			Collector, Cuttack &amp; Ors., AIR 1982 Orissa 117; Sunil Kant v. The
			<lb />
			Kurukshetra University &amp; Ors., AIR 1977, Punjab &amp; Harayana 37;
			<lb />
			Neha Jain v. University of Delhi &amp; Anr., AIR 2002 Delhi 403; K.Santha
			<lb />
			Kumari &amp; Anr. v. Sri Krishnadave Raya University &amp; Anr., AIR 1997,
			<lb />
			Andhra Pradesh 72; D.T.C. v. Shyam Lal, AIR 2004 SC 4271; Amit
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P(C) 5725/2008
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 32 of 71
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			Kumar Bashista v. Jamia Millia Islamia University &amp; Ors., 2003 VII AD
			<lb />
			(Delhi) 377; Nagarjuna Construction Co. Ltd. v. Govt. of Andhra
			<lb />
			Pradesh &amp; Ors., 2009 II AD (S.C.) 139, Roop Singh Negi v. Punjab
			<lb />
			National Bank &amp; Ors., 2009 II AD(S.C.) 177 and Gopal Sah v. State of
			<lb />
			Bihar, 2008 Suppl. I AD (S.C.) 1.
			<lb />
			46. This court has heard the learned counsel for the parties and have
			<lb />
			also perused various documents filed along with the writ petition and
			<lb />
			with the counter affidavit. Though specific allegations have been made
			<lb />
			against respondent no. 2, however, no affidavit of respondent no. 2 has
			<lb />
			been filed by the respondents. The parties have referred to various
			<lb />
			precedents and in the facts and circumstances it will be appropriate to
			<lb />
			first consider the precedents relied on by the parties.
			<lb />
			47. In Harpal Singh Sangwal (supra), the candidate had appeared in
			<lb />
			the entrance examination for the post of graduate course in Hindi
			<lb />
			Journalism. When the result was declared and the names of the
			<lb />
			successful candidates were revealed, it was realized by the petitioner
			<lb />
			that his name had been initially displayed, but subsequently the said
			<lb />
			list was substituted with another list which did not include his name.
			<lb />
			Thereafter, the candidate received a notification that on account of his
			<lb />
			misbehavior and acts of indiscipline as a student of M.A. in Russian
			<lb />
			Studies, University of Delhi and in exercise of the power vested under
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P(C) 5725/2008
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 33 of 71
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			the Ordinance XV-B and in order to maintain the discipline, it was
			<lb />
			decided not to admit him in any course in the University of Delhi for a
			<lb />
			period of next five years. The candidate had challenged the action of
			<lb />
			the University in not admitting him to any course by filing a writ
			<lb />
			petition before the Delhi High Court. During the pendency of the
			<lb />
			petition, the University had issued a notification that the competent
			<lb />
			authority had decided to grant post decisional hearing to the candidate
			<lb />
			and had accordingly constituted a committee to look into the complaint
			<lb />
			against the candidate. The complaints against the petitioner were given
			<lb />
			by the committee and the candidate also filed his replies. A report
			<lb />
			prepared by the committee was also given to the candidate, which was
			<lb />
			also replied to by the candidate and thereafter, the Vice Chancellor after
			<lb />
			considering the report of the Inquiry Committee, concluded that the
			<lb />
			response of the candidate was unsatisfactory and unacceptable and
			<lb />
			that thus there was no ground to review the decision not to admit the
			<lb />
			petitioner in any course in the University of Delhi for the next five years.
			<lb />
			The candidate had also challenged the subsequent order passed by the
			<lb />
			Vice Chancellor on the ground that in a matter like his, a post
			<lb />
			decisional hearing could not be an adequate substitute and that the
			<lb />
			decision taken to debar him from admissions to any course in the
			<lb />
			University was in complete violation of the principles of natural justice.
			<lb />
			On behalf of the University, the plea was taken that during the
			<lb />
			admission to the course of Hindi Journalism, the petitioner had
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P(C) 5725/2008
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 34 of 71
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			appeared in the entrance examination and that at the time he had
			<lb />
			already completed hid M.A. Russian Language and hence he was not a
			<lb />
			student of the University. However the single bench of this Court had
			<lb />
			repelled the plea that since the petitioner was not a student, a proper
			<lb />
			inquiry was not to be constituted on the ground that whether the
			<lb />
			candidate was a student or not, the principle of natural justice had to
			<lb />
			be adhered to and thus in the facts and circumstances, it was held that
			<lb />
			the principles of natural justice had been violated. Referring to
			<lb />
			Ordinance XV-B of the Delhi University, the Court held that though it
			<lb />
			does not provide the procedure to conduct the inquiry, however, the
			<lb />
			inquiry had to be conducted in compliance with the basic principles of
			<lb />
			natural justice and consequently, the post decisional hearing after the
			<lb />
			impugned notification and all the proceedings subsequent thereto were
			<lb />
			quashed. The University was also directed to consider the entrance test
			<lb />
			result of the candidate for the entrance examination for the current
			<lb />
			academic year and to proceed to hold his interview for the admission to
			<lb />
			the Hindi Journalism Post Graduate Course for the ensuing year.
			<lb />
			Considering the facts and circumstances whereby the candidate was
			<lb />
			subjected to absolutely arbitrary and illegal acts on the part of the
			<lb />
			respondents leading to the deprivation of the candidate&quot;s right to study
			<lb />
			in the University for one year, the Court had also awarded a cost of Rs.
			<lb />
			30,000/-.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P(C) 5725/2008
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 35 of 71
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			48. In Sibaram Panda (supra), the transfer certificates were issued
			<lb />
			against the students of the Orissa School of Engineering, Cuttack
			<lb />
			compulsorily transferring them on account of their alleged misconduct
			<lb />
			and indiscipline. Since some criminal cases were filed, the principal of
			<lb />
			the college had treated the mere allegations as sufficient proof and
			<lb />
			justification for the punitive action of issuing the compulsory transfer
			<lb />
			certificates, which was done for the best interest of the institutions and
			<lb />
			to control the law and order situation for the purpose of maintenance of
			<lb />
			the discipline of the institution. Reliance was also placed on the
			<lb />
			allegation made by the members of the staff and other students
			<lb />
			regarding the highhanded action and misconduct of those candidates
			<lb />
			who had been issued the compulsory transfer certificates. It was also
			<lb />
			alleged that as the atmosphere of the institution was surcharged with
			<lb />
			rowdiness, it was considered that issue of show cause would frustrate
			<lb />
			the very purpose for which the action was proposed. The students who
			<lb />
			had been issued compulsory transfer certificate had challenged the
			<lb />
			action of the institution and the question for consideration before the
			<lb />
			Court was whether the delinquents/students had been deprived of a
			<lb />
			reasonable opportunity to show cause and if the rules of natural justice
			<lb />
			have been violated. The Division Bench of the Orissa High Court had
			<lb />
			held that the action of the institution in issuing the compulsory transfer
			<lb />
			certificate was hit by the violation of principles of natural justice and
			<lb />
			that such an action was not sustainable in law and thus was set aside.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P(C) 5725/2008
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 36 of 71
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			49. The Division Bench of the Punjab High Court in Sunil Kant
			<lb />
			(supra), relied on by the petitioner, had set aside the notification by the
			<lb />
			University disqualifying a candidate from passing the examination on
			<lb />
			the ground that the candidate was not supplied the material which was
			<lb />
			intended to be used against him. The candidate in this case had
			<lb />
			appeared in the pre-medical examination held in April/May, 1975.
			<lb />
			When the candidate was doing his paper, the Superintendent of the
			<lb />
			Examination had called him and told him that some printing papers
			<lb />
			had been recovered by the members of the Flying Squad. The statement
			<lb />
			of the candidate was recorded by the Superintendent, who had stated
			<lb />
			that the papers were lying near his seat on the floor and that he was
			<lb />
			busy doing his paper and had not taken any help from them. Those
			<lb />
			papers lying on the floor were recovered by the Superintendent of
			<lb />
			Examination, but nothing was recovered from the petitioner&quot;s
			<lb />
			possession and he did not know as to who had thrown the papers as
			<lb />
			well. In the facts and circumstances it was held by the Court that the
			<lb />
			proceedings initiated by the Unfair Means Committee were vitiated
			<lb />
			against the candidate, as he was not supplied with the material on
			<lb />
			which the Unfair Means Committee had relied, nor was he given a copy
			<lb />
			of the report of the Superintendent, or the statement of the members of
			<lb />
			the Flying Squad or the printing material allegedly recovered from the
			<lb />
			candidate. The Court had therefore, held that the notification
			<lb />
			disqualifying the said candidate from passing the examination was in
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P(C) 5725/2008
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 37 of 71
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			violation of the principles of natural justice and thus had set aside the
			<lb />
			same.
			<lb />
			50. In Neha Jain (supra), relied on by the petitioner, a student had
			<lb />
			made notes on the date sheet instead of the answer sheet and it was
			<lb />
			found that the said notes were found to be relevant to only one question
			<lb />
			in the question paper. The University of Delhi had imposed the
			<lb />
			punishment of cancellation of the entire examination and had debarred
			<lb />
			the candidate from appearing for any examination for 12 months. The
			<lb />
			Court had held that the punishment imposed was disproportionate to
			<lb />
			the alleged offence and that though the decision of the University that
			<lb />
			the note on the date sheet was not permissible could not be
			<lb />
			substituted, however, in the facts and circumstances, it was held that
			<lb />
			punishment of cancellation of only the paper in question was adequate
			<lb />
			and sufficient and consequently, the decision of the University to debar
			<lb />
			the student for 12 months and cancelling her entire examination was
			<lb />
			set aside.
			<lb />
			51. In K.Santha Kumari &amp; Anr. (supra), on the basis of probability
			<lb />
			and circumstantial evidence, it was alleged by the Educational
			<lb />
			Authority that the student had indulged in mass coping
			<lb />
			and
			<lb />
			consequently the punishment of cancellation of examination and
			<lb />
			debarring the candidate for taking next two examination was imposed.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P(C) 5725/2008
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 38 of 71
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			The Court had held that a decision given in disregard to the principles
			<lb />
			of natural justice is void and that a body with the power to decide,
			<lb />
			cannot lawfully proceed to make a decision until it has afforded the
			<lb />
			person affected an appropriate opportunity to state his case. The Court
			<lb />
			had also held that though it is not within the purview of the Court to
			<lb />
			substitute a decision taken by an administrative or quasi-judicial
			<lb />
			authority simply because the decision sought to be substituted is a
			<lb />
			better one. However, unless it is shown that the conclusion arrived at
			<lb />
			by the authority suffers from want of evidence, breach of principles of
			<lb />
			natural justice, unreasonableness, illegality, irrationality or perversity,
			<lb />
			bad faith, they are not susceptible for interference under Article 226 of
			<lb />
			the Constitution of India. In the circumstances, it was held that though
			<lb />
			the charges of malpractice against the candidate about mass copying
			<lb />
			was established, however, the punishment was modified to the
			<lb />
			cancellation of the paper in which mass copying was alleged and the
			<lb />
			candidates were allowed to appear in the ensuing examination, which
			<lb />
			was to be conducted by the University.
			<lb />
			52. In Amit Kumar Bashista (supra), in which the candidate was
			<lb />
			denied admission on account of his alleged involvement in the serious
			<lb />
			misconduct of manufacturing a fraudulent degree, the Court had
			<lb />
			noticed that the candidate was only named in the FIR however, there
			<lb />
			was nothing in the FIR to connect the candidate to the said offence and
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P(C) 5725/2008
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 39 of 71
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			thus in such circumstances refusing the admission to the candidate
			<lb />
			was held to be clearly arbitrary a mala fide exercise of discretion which
			<lb />
			was not sustainable in law. In the circumstances, the University was
			<lb />
			directed to admit the candidate in the current year.
			<lb />
			53. Relying on Nagarjuna Construction Co.Ltd. (supra), it has been
			<lb />
			contended by the learned counsel for the petitioner that rules of natural
			<lb />
			justice are not codified canons. The first and foremost principle is what
			<lb />
			is commonly known as audi alteram partem rule which contemplates
			<lb />
			that no one should be condemned unheard. Thus, notice is the first
			<lb />
			limb of this principle which should be precise and unambiguous. Time
			<lb />
			given to respond to the notice should be adequate so as to enable the
			<lb />
			person concerned to make his effective representation. In the absence of
			<lb />
			any notice of the kind and in case such reasonable opportunity is
			<lb />
			denied, the order passed thereafter becomes wholly vitiated. The
			<lb />
			Supreme Court in Para 33 to 41 of the judgment had held as under:-
			<lb />
			&quot;33. Natural justice is another name for commonsense
			<lb />
			justice. Rules of natural justice are not codified canons. But
			<lb />
			they are principles ingrained into the conscience of man.
			<lb />
			Natural justice is the administration of justice in a
			<lb />
			commonsense liberal way. Justice is based substantially on
			<lb />
			natural ideals and human values. The administration of
			<lb />
			justice is to be freed from the narrow and restricted
			<lb />
			considerations which are usually associated with a
			<lb />
			formulated law involving linguistic technicalities and
			<lb />
			grammatical niceties. It is the substance of justice which
			<lb />
			has to determine its form.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P(C) 5725/2008
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 40 of 71
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			34. The expressions &quot;natural justice&quot; and &quot;legal justice&quot; do
			<lb />
			not present a water-tight classification. It is the substance
			<lb />
			of justice which is to be secured by both, and whenever
			<lb />
			legal justice fails to achieve this solemn purpose, natural
			<lb />
			justice is called in aid of legal justice. Natural justice
			<lb />
			relieves legal justice from unnecessary technicality,
			<lb />
			grammatical pedantry or logical prevarication. It supplies
			<lb />
			the omissions of a formulated law. As Lord Buckmaster
			<lb />
			said, no form or procedure should ever be permitted to
			<lb />
			exclude the presentation of a litigants&apos; defense.
			<lb />
			35. The adherence to principles of natural justice as
			<lb />
			recognized by all civilized States is of supreme importance
			<lb />
			when a quasi-judicial body embarks on determining
			<lb />
			disputes between the parties, or any administrative action
			<lb />
			involving civil consequences is in issue. These principles
			<lb />
			are well settled. The first and foremost principle is what is
			<lb />
			commonly known as audi alteram partem rule. It says that
			<lb />
			no one should be condemned unheard. Notice is the first
			<lb />
			limb of this principle. It must be precise and
			<lb />
			unambiguous.
			<lb />
			It
			<lb />
			should
			<lb />
			appraise
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			party
			<lb />
			determinatively the case he has to meet. Time given for
			<lb />
			the purpose should be adequate so as to enable him to
			<lb />
			make his representation. In the absence of a notice of
			<lb />
			the kind and such reasonable opportunity, the order
			<lb />
			passed becomes wholly vitiated. Thus, it is but essential
			<lb />
			that a party should be put on notice of the case before any
			<lb />
			adverse order is passed against him. This is one of the most
			<lb />
			important principles of natural justice. It is after all an
			<lb />
			approved rule of fair play. The concept has gained
			<lb />
			significance and shades with time. When the historic
			<lb />
			document was made at Runnymede in 1215, the first
			<lb />
			statutory recognition of this principle found its way into the
			<lb />
			&quot;Magna Carta&quot;. The classic exposition of Sir Edward Coke of
			<lb />
			natural justice requires to &quot;vocate interrogate and
			<lb />
			adjudicate&quot;. In the celebrated case of Cooper v. Wandsworth
			<lb />
			Board of Works 1963 (143) ER 414, the principle was thus
			<lb />
			stated:
			<lb />
			&quot;Even God did not pass a sentence upon Adam,
			<lb />
			before he was called upon to make his defense.
			<lb />
			&quot;Adam&quot; says God, &quot;where art thou has thou not eaten
			<lb />
			of the tree whereof I commanded thee that though
			<lb />
			should not eat.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P(C) 5725/2008
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 41 of 71
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			Since then the principle has been chiselled, honed
			<lb />
			and refined, enriching its content. Judicial treatment
			<lb />
			has added light and luminosity to the concept, like
			<lb />
			polishing of a diamond.
			<lb />
			36. Principles of natural justice are those rules which have
			<lb />
			been laid down by the Courts as being the minimum
			<lb />
			protection of the rights of the individual against the
			<lb />
			arbitrary procedure that may be adopted by a judicial,
			<lb />
			quasi-judicial and administrative authority while making
			<lb />
			an order affecting those rights. These rules are intended to
			<lb />
			prevent such authority from doing injustice.
			<lb />
			37. What is meant by the term `principles of natural justice&apos;
			<lb />
			is not easy to determine. Lord Summer (then Hamilton,
			<lb />
			L.J.) in Ray v. Local Government Board (1914) 1 KB 160 at
			<lb />
			p.199 : 83 LJKB 86) described the phrase as sadly lacking
			<lb />
			in precision. In General Council of Medical Education &amp;
			<lb />
			Registration of U.K. v. Sanckman 1943 AC 627 : (1948) 2
			<lb />
			All ER 337, Lord Wright observed that it was not desirable
			<lb />
			to attempt `to force it into any procusteam bed&apos; and
			<lb />
			mentioned that one essential requirement was that the
			<lb />
			Tribunal should be impartial and have no personal interest
			<lb />
			in the controversy, and further that it should give `a full
			<lb />
			and fair opportunity&apos; to every party of being heard.
			<lb />
			38. Lord Wright referred to the leading cases on the subject.
			<lb />
			The most important of them is the Board of Education v.
			<lb />
			Rice 1911 AC 179 : 80 LJKB 796, where Lord Loreburn,
			<lb />
			L.C. observed as follows:
			<lb />
			Comparatively recent statutes have extended, if they
			<lb />
			have originated, the practice of imposing upon
			<lb />
			departments or offices of State the duty of deciding or
			<lb />
			determining questions of various kinds. It will, I
			<lb />
			suppose usually be of an administrative kind, but
			<lb />
			sometimes, it will involve matter of law as well as
			<lb />
			matter of fact, or even depend upon matter of law
			<lb />
			alone. In such cases, the Board of Education will
			<lb />
			have to ascertain the law and also to ascertain the
			<lb />
			facts. I need not and that in doing either they must
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P(C) 5725/2008
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 42 of 71
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			act in good faith and fairly listen to both sides for
			<lb />
			that is a duty lying upon everyone who decides
			<lb />
			anything. But I do not think they are bound to treat
			<lb />
			such a question as though it were a trial....The Board
			<lb />
			is in the nature of the arbitral tribunal, and a Court
			<lb />
			of law has no jurisdiction to hear appeals from the
			<lb />
			determination either upon law or upon fact. But if the
			<lb />
			Court is satisfied either that the Board have not acted
			<lb />
			judicially in the way I have described, or have not
			<lb />
			determined the question which they are required by
			<lb />
			the Act to determine, then there is a remedy by
			<lb />
			mandamus and certiorari.
			<lb />
			Lord Wright also emphasized from the same decision
			<lb />
			the observation of the Lord Chancellor that the Board
			<lb />
			can obtain information in any way they think best,
			<lb />
			always giving a fair opportunity to those who are
			<lb />
			parties to the controversy for correcting or
			<lb />
			contradicting any relevant statement prejudicial to
			<lb />
			their view&quot;. To the same effect are the observations of
			<lb />
			Earl of Selbourne, LO in Spackman v. Plumstead
			<lb />
			District Board of Works 1985 (10) AC 229 : 54 LJMC
			<lb />
			81, where the learned and noble Lord Chancellor
			<lb />
			observed as follows:
			<lb />
			No doubt, in the absence of special provisions as to
			<lb />
			how the person who is to decide is to proceed, law
			<lb />
			will imply no more than that the substantial
			<lb />
			requirements of justice shall not be violated. He is
			<lb />
			not a judge in the proper sense of the word; but he
			<lb />
			must give the parties an opportunity of being heard
			<lb />
			before him and stating their case and their view. He
			<lb />
			must give notice when he will proceed with the
			<lb />
			matter and he must act honestly and impartially and
			<lb />
			not under the dictation of some other person or
			<lb />
			persons to whom the authority is not given by law.
			<lb />
			There must be no malversation of any kind. There
			<lb />
			would be no decision within the meaning of the
			<lb />
			statute if there were anything of that sort done
			<lb />
			contrary to the essence of justice.
			<lb />
			Lord Selbourne also added that the essence of justice
			<lb />
			consisted in requiring that all parties should have an
			<lb />
			opportunity of submitting to the person by whose
			<lb />
			decision they are to be bound, such considerations as
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P(C) 5725/2008
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 43 of 71
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			in their judgment ought to be brought before him. All
			<lb />
			these cases lay down the very important rule of
			<lb />
			natural justice contained in the oft-quoted phrase
			<lb />
			`justice should not only be done, but should be seen
			<lb />
			to be done&apos;.
			<lb />
			39. Concept of natural justice has undergone a great deal of
			<lb />
			change in recent years. Rules of natural justice are not
			<lb />
			rules embodied always expressly in a statute or in rules
			<lb />
			framed thereunder. They may be implied from the nature of
			<lb />
			the duty to be performed under a statute. What particular
			<lb />
			rule of natural justice should be implied and what its
			<lb />
			context should be in a given case must depend to a great
			<lb />
			extent on the fact and circumstances of that case, the
			<lb />
			frame-work of the statute under which the enquiry is held.
			<lb />
			The old distinction between a judicial act and an
			<lb />
			administrative act has withered away. Even an
			<lb />
			administrative order which involves civil consequences
			<lb />
			must be consistent with the rules of natural justice.
			<lb />
			Expression `civil consequences&apos; encompasses infraction of
			<lb />
			not merely property or personal rights but of civil liberties,
			<lb />
			material deprivations, and non-pecuniary damages. In its
			<lb />
			wide umbrella comes everything that affects a citizen in his
			<lb />
			civil life.
			<lb />
			40. Natural justice has been variously defined by different
			<lb />
			Judges. A few instances will suffice. In Drew v. Drew and
			<lb />
			Lebura 1855(2) Macg. 1.8, Lord Cranworth defined it as
			<lb />
			`universal justice&apos;. In James Dunber Smith v. Her Majesty
			<lb />
			the Queen 1877-78(3) App.Case 614, 623 JC Sir Robort P.
			<lb />
			Collier, speaking for the judicial committee of Privy council,
			<lb />
			used the phrase `the requirements of substantial justice&apos;,
			<lb />
			while in Arthur John Specman v. Plumstead District Board
			<lb />
			of Works 1884-85(10) App. Case 229, 240, Earl of
			<lb />
			Selbourne, S.C. preferred the phrase `the substantial
			<lb />
			requirement of justice&apos;. In Vionet v. Barrett 1885(55) LJRD
			<lb />
			39, 41, Lord Esher, MR defined natural justice as `the
			<lb />
			natural sense of what is right and wrong&apos;. While, however,
			<lb />
			deciding Hookings v. Smethwick Local Board of Health
			<lb />
			1890 (24) QBD 712, Lord Fasher, M.R. instead of using the
			<lb />
			definition given earlier by him in Vionet&apos;s case (supra) chose
			<lb />
			to define natural justice as `fundamental justice&apos;. In Ridge
			<lb />
			v. Baldwin 1963(1) WB 569, 578, Harman LJ, in the Court
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P(C) 5725/2008
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 44 of 71
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			of Appeal countered natural justice with `fair-play in action&apos;
			<lb />
			a phrase favoured by Bhagawati, J. in Maneka Gandhi v.
			<lb />
			Union of India 1978 (2) SCR 621. In re R.N. (An Infaot)
			<lb />
			1967(2) B617, 530, Lord Parker, CJ, preferred to describe
			<lb />
			natural justice as `a duty to act fairly&apos;. In fairmount
			<lb />
			Investments Ltd. v. Secretary to State for Environment
			<lb />
			1976 WLR 1255 Lord Russell of Willowan somewhat
			<lb />
			picturesquely described natural justice as `a fair crack of
			<lb />
			the whip&apos; while Geoffrey Lane, LJ. In Regina v. Secretary of
			<lb />
			State for Home Affairs Ex Parte Hosenball 1977 (1) WLR
			<lb />
			766 preferred the homely phrase `common fairness&apos;.
			<lb />
			41. How then have the principles of natural justice been
			<lb />
			interpreted in the Courts and within what limits are they to
			<lb />
			be confined? Over the years by a process of judicial
			<lb />
			interpretation two rules have been evolved as representing
			<lb />
			the principles of natural justice in judicial process,
			<lb />
			including therein quasi-judicial and administrative process.
			<lb />
			They constitute the basic elements of a fair hearing, having
			<lb />
			their roots in the innate sense of man for fair-play and
			<lb />
			justice which is not the preserve of any particular race or
			<lb />
			country but is shared in common by all men. The first rule
			<lb />
			is `nemo judex in causa sua&apos; or `nemo debet esse judex in
			<lb />
			propria causa sua&apos; as stated in (1605) 12 Co.Rep.114 that
			<lb />
			is, `no man shall be a judge in his own cause&apos;. Coke used
			<lb />
			the form `aliquis non debet esse judex in propria causa
			<lb />
			quia non potest esse judex at pars&apos; (Co. Litt. 1418), that is,
			<lb />
			`no man ought to be a judge in his own case, because he
			<lb />
			cannot act as Judge and at the same time be a party&apos;. The
			<lb />
			form `nemo potest esse simul actor et judex&apos;, that is, `no
			<lb />
			one can be at once suitor and judge&apos; is also at times used.
			<lb />
			The second rule is `audi alteram partem&apos;, that is, `hear the
			<lb />
			other side&apos;. At times and particularly in continental
			<lb />
			countries, the form `audietur at altera pars&apos; is used,
			<lb />
			meaning very much the same thing. A corollary has been
			<lb />
			deduced from the above two rules and particularly the audi
			<lb />
			alteram partem rule, namely `qui aliquid statuerit parte
			<lb />
			inaudita alteram actquam licet dixerit, haud acquum
			<lb />
			facerit&apos; that is, `he who shall decide anything without the
			<lb />
			other side having been heard, although he may have said
			<lb />
			what is right, will not have been what is right&apos; (See
			<lb />
			Bosewell&apos;s case (1605) 6 Co.Rep. 48-b, 52-a) or in other
			<lb />
			words, as it is now expressed, `justice should not only be
			<lb />
			done but should manifestly be seen to be done&apos;. Whenever
			<lb />
			an order is struck down as invalid being in violation of
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P(C) 5725/2008
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 45 of 71
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			principles of natural justice, there is no final decision of the
			<lb />
			case and fresh proceedings are left upon. All that is done is
			<lb />
			to vacate the order assailed by virtue of its inherent defect,
			<lb />
			but the proceedings are not terminated.&quot;
			<lb />
			54. In Roop Singh Negi (supra), the Supreme Court had held that
			<lb />
			suspicion, as is well know, however, high it may be, can under no
			<lb />
			circumstances be held to be a substitute for legal proof. It was further
			<lb />
			held that though the provisions of Evidence Act may not be applicable
			<lb />
			on departmental proceeding but the principles of natural justice are. In
			<lb />
			this matter, the inquiry officer had relied upon the alleged confession
			<lb />
			made by the delinquent. The Court had observed that that there was no
			<lb />
			reason as to why the order of discharge passed by the Criminal court
			<lb />
			on the basis of the same evidence should not have been taken into
			<lb />
			consideration and it was held that the material brought on record
			<lb />
			pointing out the guilt of the delinquent are required to be proved. In the
			<lb />
			circumstances, it was held that the decision must be arrived at on some
			<lb />
			evidence which is legally admissible and since the report of the inquiry
			<lb />
			officer was found based on ipse dixit and also surmises and
			<lb />
			conjectures, therefore, such action was not to be sustained.
			<lb />
			55. About the alleged confession of the petitioner, the counsel for the
			<lb />
			petitioner relied on Gopal Sah (supra), to contend that extra judicial
			<lb />
			confession is, in the face of it, a week piece of evidence and the courts
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P(C) 5725/2008
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 46 of 71
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			are reluctant in the absence of a chain of cogent circumstances to rely
			<lb />
			on this evidence for the purpose of recording conviction.
			<lb />
			56. Per contra the learned counsel for the respondents relied on State
			<lb />
			Bank of Patiala &amp; Ors v. S.K.Sharma, (1996) 3 SCC 364; Mansoor Azam
			<lb />
			v. Jamia Milia Islamia &amp; Ors, 90(2001) DLT 735; Controller of
			<lb />
			Examinations and Ors v. G.S.Sunder &amp; Anr, 1993 Supp (3) SCC 82 and
			<lb />
			Director (Studies), Dr.Ambedkar Institute of Hotel Management,
			<lb />
			Nutrition &amp; Catering Technology, Chandigarh and Ors v. Vaibhav Singh
			<lb />
			Chauhan, (2009) 1 SCC 59; Narender Singh v. University of Delhi &amp;
			<lb />
			Ors, 70 (1997) DLT 509 and State of Punjab &amp; Ors v. Dr.Harbhajan
			<lb />
			Singh Greasy, (1996) 9 SCC 322. According to the learned counsel for
			<lb />
			the respondents it was held in State Bank of Patiala (Supra) that the
			<lb />
			interests of justice equally demands that the guilty should be punished
			<lb />
			and that technicalities and irregularities which do not occasion failure
			<lb />
			of justice are not allowed to defeat the ends of justice. It is contended
			<lb />
			that the principles of natural justice cannot be perverted to achieve the
			<lb />
			very opposite end. The Supreme Court had summarized the principles
			<lb />
			in this context as follows:-
			<lb />
			&quot;(1) An order passed imposing a punishment on an
			<lb />
			employee consequent upon a disciplinary/departmental
			<lb />
			enquiry in violation of the rules/regulations/statutory
			<lb />
			provisions governing such enquiries should not be set aside
			<lb />
			automatically. The Court or the Tribunal should enquire
			<lb />
			whether (a) the provision violated is of a substantive
			<lb />
			nature of (b) whether it is procedural in character.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P(C) 5725/2008
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 47 of 71
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			(2) A substantive provision has normally to be complied
			<lb />
			with as explained hereinbefore and the theory of
			<lb />
			substantial compliance or the test of prejudice would not be
			<lb />
			applicable in such a case.
			<lb />
			(3) In the case of violation of a procedural provision, the
			<lb />
			position is this: Procedural provisions are generally meant
			<lb />
			for affording a reasonable and adequate opportunity to the
			<lb />
			delinquent officer/employee. They are, generally speaking,
			<lb />
			conceived in his interest. Violation of any and every
			<lb />
			procedural provision cannot be said to automatically vitiate
			<lb />
			the enquiry held or order passed.-Except cases falling
			<lb />
			under &apos;no notice&apos;, &apos;no opportunity&apos; and &apos;no hearing&apos;
			<lb />
			categories, the complaint of violation of procedural
			<lb />
			provision should be examined from the point of view of
			<lb />
			prejudice, viz., whether such violation has prejudiced the
			<lb />
			delinquent officer/employee in defending himself properly
			<lb />
			and effectively. If it is found that he has been so prejudiced,
			<lb />
			appropriate orders have to be made to repair and remedy
			<lb />
			the prejudice including setting aside the enquiry and/or the
			<lb />
			order of punishment. If no prejudice in established to have
			<lb />
			resulted there from, it is obvious, no interference is called
			<lb />
			for. In this connection, it may be remembered that there
			<lb />
			may be certain procedural provisions which are of a
			<lb />
			fundamental character, whose violation is by itself proof of
			<lb />
			prejudice. The Court may not insist on proof of prejudice in
			<lb />
			such eases. As explained in the body of the judgment, take
			<lb />
			a case where there is a provision expressly providing that
			<lb />
			after the evidence of the employer/government is over, the
			<lb />
			employee shall be given an opportunity to lead defense in
			<lb />
			his evidence and in a given case, the enquiry officer does
			<lb />
			not give that opportunity inspite of the delinquent
			<lb />
			officer/employee asking for it. The prejudice is sell-evident.
			<lb />
			No proof of prejudice as such need be called for in such a
			<lb />
			case. To report, the test is one of prejudice, i.e., whether the
			<lb />
			person has received a fair hearing considering all things.
			<lb />
			Now, this very aspect can also be looked at from the point
			<lb />
			of view of directory and mandatory provisions, if one is so
			<lb />
			inclined. The principle slated under (4) herein below is only
			<lb />
			another way of looking at the same aspect as is dealt with
			<lb />
			herein and not a different or distinct principle.
			<lb />
			(4)(a) In the case of a procedural provision which is not of a
			<lb />
			mandatory character, the complaint of violation has to be
			<lb />
			examined from the standpoint of substantial compliance.
			<lb />
			Be that as it may, the order passed in violation of such a
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P(C) 5725/2008
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 48 of 71
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			provision can be set aside only where such violation has
			<lb />
			occasioned prejudice to the delinquent employee.
			<lb />
			(b) In the case of violation of a procedural provision, which
			<lb />
			is of a mandatory character, it has to be ascertained
			<lb />
			whether the provision is conceived in the interest of the
			<lb />
			person proceeded against or in public interest. If it is found
			<lb />
			to be the former, then it must be seen whether the
			<lb />
			delinquent officer has waived the said requirement, either
			<lb />
			expressly or by his conduct. If he is found to have waived it,
			<lb />
			then the order of punishment cannot be set aside on the
			<lb />
			ground of said violation. If, on the other hand, it is found
			<lb />
			that the delinquent officer/employee has not it or that the
			<lb />
			provision could not be waived by him, then the Court or
			<lb />
			Tribunal should make appropriate directions (include the
			<lb />
			setting aside of the order of punishment) keeping in mind
			<lb />
			the approach adopted by the Constitution Bench in B.
			<lb />
			Karunakaran. The ultimate test is always the same, viz.,
			<lb />
			test of prejudice or the test of fair hearing, as it may be
			<lb />
			called.
			<lb />
			(5) Where the enquiry is not governed by any
			<lb />
			rules/regulations/statutory provisions and the only
			<lb />
			obligation is to observe the principles of natural justice or,
			<lb />
			for that matter, wherever such principles are held to be
			<lb />
			implied by the very nature and impact of the order/action-
			<lb />
			the Court or the Tribunal should make a distinction
			<lb />
			between a total violation of natural justice (rule of audi
			<lb />
			alteram pattern) and violation of a facet of the said rule, as
			<lb />
			explained in the body of the judgment. In other words, a
			<lb />
			distinction must be made between &quot;no opportunity&quot; and no
			<lb />
			adequate opportunity, i.e., between &quot;no notice/no hearing&quot;
			<lb />
			and &quot;no fair hearing&quot;, (a) In the case of former, the order
			<lb />
			passed would undoubtedly be invalid (one may call it &quot;void&quot;
			<lb />
			or a nullity if one chooses to). In such cases, normally,
			<lb />
			liberty will be reserved for the Authority to take proceedings
			<lb />
			afresh according to law, i.e., in accordance with the said
			<lb />
			rule (audi alterant paitem). (b) But in the latter case, the
			<lb />
			effect of violation (of a facet of the rule audi alterant partem)
			<lb />
			has to be examined from the standpoint of prejudice; in
			<lb />
			other words, what the Court or Tribunal has to see is
			<lb />
			whether in the totality of the circumstances, the delinquent
			<lb />
			officer/employee did or did not have a fair hearing and the
			<lb />
			orders to be made shall depend upon the answer to the said
			<lb />
			query. (It is made clear that this principle (No. 5) does not
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P(C) 5725/2008
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 49 of 71
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			apply in the case of rule against bias, the test in which
			<lb />
			behalf are laid down elsewhere.
			<lb />
			(6) While applying the rule of audi alteram partem (the
			<lb />
			primary
			<lb />
			principle
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			natural
			<lb />
			justice)
			<lb />
			the
			<lb />
			Court/Tribunal/Authority must always bear in mind the
			<lb />
			ultimate and over-riding objective underlying the said rule,
			<lb />
			viz., to ensure a fair hearing and to ensure that there is
			<lb />
			no failure of justice. It is this objective which should guide
			<lb />
			them in applying the rule to varying situations that arises
			<lb />
			before them.
			<lb />
			(7) There may be situations where the interests of state or
			<lb />
			public interest may call for a curtailing of the rule of audi
			<lb />
			alteram partem. In such situations, the Court may have to
			<lb />
			balance public/State interest with the requirement of
			<lb />
			natural justice and arrive at an appropriate decision.&quot;
			<lb />
			57. In the above noted case relied on by the respondents though the
			<lb />
			copies of the statements of two witnesses were not given to him,
			<lb />
			however, the delinquent was permitted to take notes there from three
			<lb />
			days prior to their examination and even one of the witnesses was not
			<lb />
			examined. The delinquent had not raised any objection during the
			<lb />
			enquiry that non furnishing of the copies of the statement had disabled
			<lb />
			him and in these circumstances it was held that no prejudice had been
			<lb />
			caused to him. In these circumstances on account of not furnishing the
			<lb />
			copies of the statement of two witnesses, it was held that the principles
			<lb />
			of natural justice were not violated and the delinquent had a fair
			<lb />
			hearing and the disciplinary proceedings were not set aside. In Mansoor
			<lb />
			Azam (Supra) it was held by a Single Judge relying on Controller of
			<lb />
			Examinations &amp; Ors v. G.S.Sunder &amp; Anr, (1993) Supp.3 SCC 82 that
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P(C) 5725/2008
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 50 of 71
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			in matters of enforcement of discipline, the Courts must be very slow in
			<lb />
			interference, as the authorities who are in-charge of education know
			<lb />
			best how to deal with situation and fine principles of law cannot be
			<lb />
			interpolated in their functioning. In the said case relied on by the
			<lb />
			respondents, the petitioner Mansoor Alam was debarred from taking
			<lb />
			admission in the university on account of his misconduct along with
			<lb />
			two others. The Court had found the punishment imposed upon him
			<lb />
			disproportionate to his misconduct and the matter was referred back to
			<lb />
			the University for re-consideration of the case of the petitioner for award
			<lb />
			of lesser punishment which was also awarded to other two students.
			<lb />
			58. In G.S.Sunder (Supra) relied on by the respondents the principal
			<lb />
			of the college had brought malpractices conducted by students in the
			<lb />
			examination to the notice of the University. The malpractice had
			<lb />
			affected innocent and intelligent students, as G.S.Sunder had
			<lb />
			interchanged his roll number with that of another student K.R.Gandhi,
			<lb />
			as Gandhi used to be a better student. Consequently G.S.Sunder was
			<lb />
			passing all the examinations with good marks in those subjects where
			<lb />
			the roll number was interchanged whereas Gandhi failed in those
			<lb />
			subjects where the roll number were interchanged. However,
			<lb />
			K.R.Gandhi had scored good marks in all subjects in supplementary
			<lb />
			examination in which he had failed in the main examination.
			<lb />
			G.S.Sunder had first denied the knowledge about interchanging the roll
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P(C) 5725/2008
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 51 of 71
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			number, however, at the second sitting of enquiry he had given a
			<lb />
			statement admitting the commission of malpractice. A sub-committee
			<lb />
			was appointed and the Chairman of the Syndicate Sub Committee
			<lb />
			submitted the report and recommended the punishment. In these
			<lb />
			circumstances it was held by the Supreme Court that it was a case of
			<lb />
			systematic fraud conducted by G.S.Sunder and it could not be a sheer
			<lb />
			coincidence that in all the semesters Sh.G.S.Sunder had been scoring
			<lb />
			good marks and other student K.R.Gandhi had failed and in these
			<lb />
			circumstances there was nothing unbelievable in G.S.Sunder admitting
			<lb />
			his mistake and giving a statement to this effect. The case of the
			<lb />
			petitioner, however, is apparently distinguishable. Besides the
			<lb />
			continuous violations of the principles of natural justice and not
			<lb />
			conducting any enquiry, as what has been alleged is that a fact finding
			<lb />
			committee was appointed which did not examine any of the witnesses or
			<lb />
			recorded the statements in the presence of the petitioner nor gave the
			<lb />
			copies of the same to the petitioner but referred to alleged confession
			<lb />
			letters. In the first confession letter it is allegedly stated by the
			<lb />
			petitioner not to take any action against her and she would not join if
			<lb />
			she will be selected whereas the fact is that on 25 th July, 2007 it had
			<lb />
			already been disclosed to her that she has scored very high marks and
			<lb />
			she has been selected. In the circumstances she won&quot;t have written on
			<lb />
			her own such a letter. A few minutes after writing the said confession
			<lb />
			she allegedly wrote second confession where she simply admitted her
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P(C) 5725/2008
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 52 of 71
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			alleged mistake that she took the examination paper from the room of
			<lb />
			Professor Uma Pati and in the third alleged confession she says that she
			<lb />
			wrote down the answers. In the fourth alleged confession she implicated
			<lb />
			her professor that he had told her that the entrance examination paper
			<lb />
			were in the drawer and she could take it from there. The petitioner had
			<lb />
			made categorical allegation against Ms. Aparna Dixit and other two
			<lb />
			persons regarding the pressure and coercion and the circumstances
			<lb />
			which they created under which the petitioner was left with no option
			<lb />
			but to write whatsoever was dictated to her which facts have not been
			<lb />
			refuted by Professor Aparna Dixit, respondent No.2 by filing her
			<lb />
			affidavit. In these circumstances, the alleged confessions of the
			<lb />
			petitioner cannot be accepted and cannot be the basis for inculpating
			<lb />
			her in any manner. In these circumstances the respondents cannot rely
			<lb />
			on the ratio of G.S.Sunder (Supra) in the facts and circumstances
			<lb />
			which is quite distinguishable.
			<lb />
			59. In Vaibhav Singh Chauhan (Supra) the candidate had a slip of
			<lb />
			paper in his possession which pertained to examination in question,
			<lb />
			which was recovered from him when the examination was going on. The
			<lb />
			material on the slip of paper pertained to the examination and in these
			<lb />
			circumstances it was held that it was immaterial whether the candidate
			<lb />
			had used the piece of paper for writing the examination or not and had
			<lb />
			set aside the decision of the High Court. Apparently the case relied on
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P(C) 5725/2008
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 53 of 71
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			by the respondents is distinguishable. In Narender Singh (Supra) the
			<lb />
			allegation against the candidate was of ragging and consequently he
			<lb />
			was not allowed admission to the third year. In the circumstances the
			<lb />
			decision not to admit the petitioner to the third year although he was
			<lb />
			not expelled was upheld and it was observed that it was necessary in
			<lb />
			the interest of justice among students. It was further held that a
			<lb />
			student has no right for admission in such a situation, even assuming
			<lb />
			that terminology used in the order of the principal does not clearly and
			<lb />
			fully express the intention to keep the candidate out of the college
			<lb />
			permanently. The High Court had further held that though one may
			<lb />
			have sympathy for a young person whose educational career is being
			<lb />
			lost, however, such sympathy cannot be allowed to influence the Court
			<lb />
			to impose on a college, a student whose presence in the campus is
			<lb />
			perceived by college authorities as a potential threat to the discipline
			<lb />
			and peaceful functioning of the college. In Dr.Harbhajan Singh Greasy
			<lb />
			(Supra) relied on by the respondents the finding of the enquiry officer
			<lb />
			were based on alleged admission of guilt which was not supported by
			<lb />
			any statement of the delinquent in writing. In these circumstances
			<lb />
			though the enquiry report was set aside, however, fresh enquiry was not
			<lb />
			directed by the Supreme Court as the delinquent had retired in the
			<lb />
			meantime. The Court had permitted pensionary benefits to the
			<lb />
			delinquent, however, had declined back wages.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P(C) 5725/2008
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 54 of 71
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			60. Perusal of the enquiry record produced by the respondents
			<lb />
			reveals that the Vice Chancellor of respondent No.2 had appointed one
			<lb />
			man Enquiry Committee to look into the matter of selection of two
			<lb />
			candidates in pre Ph.D Program. The scope of the enquiry was to
			<lb />
			ascertain the correct facts relating to said matter in the context of
			<lb />
			deliberation done by the faculty and the statements/submissions
			<lb />
			allegedly made by the candidate. In this background the respondent
			<lb />
			No.3 had issued a communication to Professor Rakesh Bhatnagar,
			<lb />
			Dr.K.J.Mukherjee, Dr.H.Chaudhary, Professor S.K.Kar, Dr.Rajiv Bhat
			<lb />
			and Dr.S.Maitra to come to him on 18 th January, 2008 for talking to
			<lb />
			them.
			<lb />
			61. Respondent No.3 thereafter, on 18 th January, 2008 recorded the
			<lb />
			statements of Dr.K.J.Mukherjee, Professor D.Choudhary, Professor
			<lb />
			S.K.Kar, Professor Rakesh Bhatnagar and Professor Uttam Pati. The
			<lb />
			statements of Dr. Shubrhangshu Maitra and Dr.Bhatt was recorded on
			<lb />
			23 rd January, 2008. On both the dates the petitioner was not present
			<lb />
			nor the statements were recorded in her presence nor the copies of the
			<lb />
			statements recorded by the one man committee were given to the
			<lb />
			petitioner nor the petitioner was given any opportunity to cross examine
			<lb />
			these persons on the statements of which it has been inferred that the
			<lb />
			petitioner used unfair means by getting the question paper of the
			<lb />
			entrance examination in advance.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P(C) 5725/2008
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 55 of 71
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			62. The statements of Aparna Dixit was also recorded on 18 th
			<lb />
			January, 2008, however, her recorded statement also bears the date of
			<lb />
			17 th January, 2008. At that time also the petitioner was not present nor
			<lb />
			the copy of the said statement was given to her. Similarly the statement
			<lb />
			of Professor Uttam Pati was recorded on 18 th January, 2008 in absence
			<lb />
			of petitioner. Another statement of Professor Uttam Pati is also on the
			<lb />
			file which was recorded on 17 th January, 2008. Though copy of the
			<lb />
			notice directing the other witnesses to come for `talk&apos; on 18.1.2008 is on
			<lb />
			record but there is no copy of any notice to said two witnesses to come
			<lb />
			and `talk&quot; to one man committee/respondent no.3. When and how they
			<lb />
			were called and when their statements were recorded cannot be
			<lb />
			ascertained from the record of alleged enquiry.
			<lb />
			63. The statement of Gargi Roy, another candidate who is also alleged
			<lb />
			to have used unfair means was also recorded on 17 th December, 2007
			<lb />
			who deposed that she was forced to write that she used unfair means to
			<lb />
			qualify the entrance examination. She categorically deposed that when
			<lb />
			she was leaving her office Professor Rakesh Bhatnagar follower her in
			<lb />
			the corridor and he had said &quot;I did not like the statements you have
			<lb />
			written just now. Just write what I am telling you. Your boss has
			<lb />
			already fired you, but don&quot;t worry if you write as I want I will get you a
			<lb />
			job definitely, otherwise you and your future will be in great trouble.&quot;
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P(C) 5725/2008
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 56 of 71
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			64. According to Gargi Roy, another candidate, she was brought to
			<lb />
			Professor Bhatnagar&quot;s office again where she was made to write
			<lb />
			statements against Dr.Uttam Pati as she was working under his
			<lb />
			guidance in a project. Gargi Roy also deposed that she had submitted
			<lb />
			her retraction letter to the Rector-II. She categorically deposed that on
			<lb />
			27 th July, 2008 also she was abused by respondent No.2 Professor
			<lb />
			Aparna Dixit. She also produced her retraction letter dated 30 th July,
			<lb />
			2007 addressed to Rector-II.
			<lb />
			65. The enquiry record also has another statement of Gargi Roy
			<lb />
			recorded on 17 th January, 2008 and the letter of Sh.Subhash C.Gupta
			<lb />
			father of Flora Gupta dated 29 th July, 2007 addressed to Professor
			<lb />
			Kumar Adhikari, Rector-II along with a letter dated 30 th July, 2007 by
			<lb />
			petitioner to Rector-II retracting her alleged confessions.
			<lb />
			66. Whether the character certificate was to be issued or not was not
			<lb />
			the scope of enquiry, however, the letters addressed by the petitioner to
			<lb />
			the Dean, School of Biotechnology and other letters to Professor Kumar
			<lb />
			Adhikari; Professor Rajendra Prasad asking for character certificate are
			<lb />
			also on the record of the enquiry. There is no explanation as to why the
			<lb />
			certificate demanded by the petitioner was not issued to her till 9 th
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P(C) 5725/2008
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 57 of 71
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			April, 2008 and thereafter, it was issued with the stipulation that an
			<lb />
			enquiry committee has been constituted against her.
			<lb />
			67. The minutes of faculty meeting held on 27 th July, 2007 on the
			<lb />
			basis of which, it appears decision was taken to have the matter
			<lb />
			enquired are as under:-
			<lb />
			&quot;The Dean reported to the faculty that the two girls, Miss
			<lb />
			Gargi Roy and Miss Flora Gupta were called to talk after
			<lb />
			the meeting of July 25, 2007 was over. Prof.Rakesh
			<lb />
			Bhatnagar and Prof.Pati were present during the meeting
			<lb />
			with the girls.
			<lb />
			The Dean read out all the statements given by the
			<lb />
			two girls. After the statements were read, Prof.Pati told that
			<lb />
			he has received a letter in his mail box two hours ago and
			<lb />
			brought it from his office. The letter was from Miss Flora
			<lb />
			Gupta addressed to Prof.Uttam Pati with a copy marked to
			<lb />
			the President Students Union (copy of the letter enclosed).
			<lb />
			The faculty unanimously resolved that the entire
			<lb />
			matter be referred to the administration to carry out
			<lb />
			investigation into this matter.
			<lb />
			The faculty also resolved that the two girls be called
			<lb />
			and informed that an enquiry into the matter will be taking
			<lb />
			place, where in Miss Roy broke down and stated that she
			<lb />
			would prefer that no enquiry be held otherwise her career
			<lb />
			might be ruined.&quot;
			<lb />
			68. Surprisingly though a number of persons were present on 27 th
			<lb />
			July, 2007 but the minutes are signed by respondent No.2 only. The
			<lb />
			record of the enquiry also has the minutes of faculty meeting held on
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P(C) 5725/2008
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 58 of 71
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			25 th July, 2007 which is also signed only by respondent No.2 which is
			<lb />
			as under:-
			<lb />
			&quot;The faculty discussed about very high marks scored by the
			<lb />
			two girls of the school. However, the faculty resolved that
			<lb />
			the declaration of the results should not be withheld
			<lb />
			because it holds up the admission process.
			<lb />
			The faculty resolved that the matter should be
			<lb />
			investigated and authorized the Dean to take adequate
			<lb />
			steps.&quot;
			<lb />
			69. If it was resolved not to withhold the result, then why the result of
			<lb />
			the petitioner was not disclosed has not been explained. There is no
			<lb />
			decision on the file by anyone that pending the decision to conduct an
			<lb />
			enquiry, the petitioner be not admitted to the course. If that be so then
			<lb />
			why she was not admitted has not been satisfactorily explained by the
			<lb />
			counsel for the respondents.
			<lb />
			70. The plea of the petitioner is that she had given the retraction
			<lb />
			letter on the next day to respondent no.2, however she refused to accept
			<lb />
			it. This allegation has not been categorically denied by the said
			<lb />
			respondent by filing an affidavit. There are other allegations against the
			<lb />
			said respondent as to how she forced petitioner to write alleged four
			<lb />
			confession letters. Though these allegations have been denied by the
			<lb />
			Registrar, Mr. Avais Ahmed but they have not been denied by
			<lb />
			respondent no. 2. The counter affidavit filed on behalf of University
			<lb />
			which is supported by the affidavit of the registrar does not even
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P(C) 5725/2008
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 59 of 71
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			disclose that respondent no. 2 had disclosed the facts on the allegation
			<lb />
			made against her to the said registrar. In the circumstances the
			<lb />
			inevitable inference is that the allegations made by the petitioner
			<lb />
			against respondent no. 2 have remained un-rebutted. If the respondent
			<lb />
			no. 2 had refused to accept the retraction letter given by the petitioner,
			<lb />
			then sending the retraction letter by the petitioner to the students
			<lb />
			union and another to Prof. Uttam Pati who had produced the same on
			<lb />
			27 th July, 2007, two days after the alleged confessions were taken,
			<lb />
			cannot be construed to be implausible or an afterthought.
			<lb />
			71. By letter dated 30 th July, 2007 addressed to Professor
			<lb />
			D.B.Bhattacharya, Vice Chancellor of respondent No.1, respondent No.2
			<lb />
			had sought a full fledged enquiry in the matter. A one man Enquiry
			<lb />
			Committee was ordered and the one man Enquiry Committee on the
			<lb />
			basis of alleged statements recorded on 18 th January, 2008, 17 th
			<lb />
			January, 2008 and 23 rd January, 2008 gave the report holding that the
			<lb />
			petitioner had access to the question paper prior to the entrance
			<lb />
			examination.
			<lb />
			72. The enquiry committee did not give any notice to the petitioner as
			<lb />
			to what is the basis of the allegation made against her. No documents
			<lb />
			or material was supply to her on the basis of which it was prima facie
			<lb />
			inferred that she had access to examination paper before the
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P(C) 5725/2008
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 60 of 71
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			examination. The one-man committee has followed its own procedure
			<lb />
			which is not based on any statue or ordinance of respondent no. 1. He
			<lb />
			issued notice to some of the witnesses to have talk with them. The
			<lb />
			alleged talk was reduced into writing and has been treated as the
			<lb />
			statements on the basis of which the one-man enquiry committee
			<lb />
			inferred that the allegation against the petitioner was made out. The
			<lb />
			copies of alleged `talk&quot; between the one-man committee and witnesses
			<lb />
			were not given to the petitioner. Petitioner was also not allowed to `talk&quot;
			<lb />
			to such witnesses whose statements became the basis of alleged fact-
			<lb />
			finding committee. Consequently, the petitioner had no opportunity to
			<lb />
			ask questions from such witnesses in order to impeach whatsoever had
			<lb />
			been stated by them. After recording the statement of such persons as
			<lb />
			detailed hereinabove, the one-man committee did not ask petitioner to
			<lb />
			give her version or to adduce evidence in support of her defense. The
			<lb />
			petitioner has made a specific allegation that respondent no. 2 did all
			<lb />
			this to accommodate his favorite persons which allegation has not been
			<lb />
			denied by respondent no. 2 by filing her affidavit. The whole procedure
			<lb />
			adopted by one-man committee is whimsical and without any basis and
			<lb />
			is not sustainable under law or based on any statue or ordinance of the
			<lb />
			University.
			<lb />
			73. The respondents have also taken conflicting and contradictory
			<lb />
			stands. The respondents have contended in response to the plea that
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P(C) 5725/2008
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 61 of 71
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			the petitioner was not allowed to cross examine the witnesses alleging
			<lb />
			that &quot;as such no witnesses were examined in the enquiry&quot;. If that be so
			<lb />
			then on what basis the enquiry committee could give its report holding
			<lb />
			that the allegations against the petitioner were made out. Regarding
			<lb />
			violation of principles of natural Justice it is alleged that it was not a
			<lb />
			departmental enquiry nor it was subjected to any rigid rules. Even if it
			<lb />
			was not subjected to any rigid rules, the minimum that was required
			<lb />
			was to make the petitioner know about the allegation against her and
			<lb />
			the basis of said allegations and during the enquiry to allow her to
			<lb />
			know as to what deposition or evidence was adduced against her.
			<lb />
			Despite no rigid rules, if something is as stated against any person, he
			<lb />
			has a right to ask that person such questions which will impeach his
			<lb />
			deposition. There is no presumption in law that whatsoever will be
			<lb />
			stated before one-man enquiry committee by any professor or official of
			<lb />
			the University would be nothing but truth and has to be accepted as
			<lb />
			such. The learned counsel for the respondents has not given a single
			<lb />
			satisfactory explanation as to how the one-man enquiry met the
			<lb />
			requirements of principles of natural Justice. The only answer is that it
			<lb />
			was a fact-finding committee. If it was a fact-finding committee in which
			<lb />
			neither the delinquent had to be explained as to what was against her
			<lb />
			and what was the basis of that and what deposition or evidence was
			<lb />
			adduced against and the findings of the one-man committee were only
			<lb />
			prima facie, then a regular enquiry ought to have been conducted
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P(C) 5725/2008
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 62 of 71
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			afterwards. The fact-finding enquiry conducted by one-man committee
			<lb />
			has not met the requirements of principles of natural Justice on any
			<lb />
			count.
			<lb />
			74. The enquiry committee has also held that the petitioner admitted
			<lb />
			that she had written the statements before the respondent no. 2 and
			<lb />
			other persons. This is not disputed that the statements were written by
			<lb />
			her. What is disputed is whether she had given the alleged confession
			<lb />
			on her own or she was coerced or pressurized to write the alleged
			<lb />
			confessions within a span of one hour. The enquiry committee has
			<lb />
			noticed the statement of Prof. Uttam Pati who stated that the
			<lb />
			statements were dictated by Prof. Bhatnagar and Prof. Dixit, respondent
			<lb />
			no.2 and the petitioner and another student did not write the
			<lb />
			statements on their own. There is apparently no finding that the four
			<lb />
			different statements were given by the petitioner on her own free will
			<lb />
			75. The grounds on which administrative action is subject to control
			<lb />
			by judicial review are, &quot;illegality&quot;; &quot;irrationality&quot; and &quot;procedural
			<lb />
			impropriety&quot;. The Court will be entitled to interfere in such matters if
			<lb />
			the decision is tainted by any vulnerability like illegality, irrationality
			<lb />
			and procedural impropriety. To be &quot;irrational&quot; it has to be held that on
			<lb />
			material, it is a decision &quot;so outrageous&quot; as to be in total defiance of
			<lb />
			logic or moral standards. If the power is exercised on the basis of facts
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P(C) 5725/2008
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 63 of 71
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			which do not exist having which are patently erroneous, such exercise
			<lb />
			of power shall be vitiated. Exercise of power will be set aside if there is
			<lb />
			manifest error in the exercise of such power or the exercise of power is
			<lb />
			manifestly arbitrary. To arrive at a decision on &quot;reasonableness&quot; the
			<lb />
			court has to find out if the respondents have left out a relevant factor or
			<lb />
			taken into account irrelevant factors.
			<lb />
			76. The respondent no. 3&quot;s report dated 7.3.2008 is in total defiance
			<lb />
			of logic and any rationality and has manifest errors. The said
			<lb />
			respondent has left out relevant factors and has taking into account
			<lb />
			irrelevant factors. The case of the respondents is also not that the
			<lb />
			petitioner had stolen the question papers or had access to them by any
			<lb />
			other illegal means without the knowledge of paper setter Prof. Uttam
			<lb />
			Pati. In the circumstances the deposition of the said witness was very
			<lb />
			material. The said witness did not say that he gave access to the
			<lb />
			petitioner to the question paper. It was not even put to him that he had
			<lb />
			allowed the petitioner to see the question papers and note down the
			<lb />
			questions and solve the answers. Surprisingly though it is stated that
			<lb />
			the decision was taken to take action against the said Professor,
			<lb />
			however, it has not been divulged or disclosed that any enquiry was
			<lb />
			conducted against the said Professor or not. The whole approach of the
			<lb />
			respondents is completely outrageous and in defiance, logic. The
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P(C) 5725/2008
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 64 of 71
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			culpability of the petitioner could be established only on the basis of
			<lb />
			culpability of the said Professor.
			<lb />
			77. After the conclusion of the alleged fact-finding enquiry in which
			<lb />
			no established procedure was followed and the one-man committee
			<lb />
			talked to certain witnesses, wrote down their statements thereafter and
			<lb />
			concluded that the allegations against the petitioner were made out by
			<lb />
			giving a report dated 7 th March, 2008, the copy of the said report was
			<lb />
			not given to the petitioner on one pretext or another for a considerable
			<lb />
			period. A show cause notice dated 15 th July, 2007 was given asking
			<lb />
			petitioner to show cause as to why disciplinary action be not initiated
			<lb />
			against them without giving the copy of the enquiry report. Another
			<lb />
			show cause notice of the same date was thereafter given after the
			<lb />
			receipt of reply dated 18 th July, 2008 categorically stipulating that the
			<lb />
			petitioner does not know on what grounds the enquiry committee has
			<lb />
			arrived at the conclusion as stated in the show cause notice because
			<lb />
			even the copy of the enquiry report had not been given to her.
			<lb />
			Thereafter, on another copy of show cause notice dated 15.7.2008, an
			<lb />
			endorsement dated 21 st July, 2008 at 5.00 P.M was made by the Chief
			<lb />
			Proctor contending that the copy of the enquiry report is enclosed with
			<lb />
			the notice and the petitioner was asked to give reply by 23 rd July, 2008,
			<lb />
			i.e within 24 hours. Apparently sufficient time was not given to the
			<lb />
			petitioner to reply to show cause notice. The respondents are unable to
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P(C) 5725/2008
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 65 of 71
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			give any cogent reason as to why the copy of the enquiry report was not
			<lb />
			given to the petitioner earlier. Perusal of the report dated 7 th March,
			<lb />
			2008 reveals that it is not self explanatory and merely on the basis of
			<lb />
			the report, the rationale for the inferences drawn by the one-man
			<lb />
			enquiry committee be comprehended. The petitioner had
			<lb />
			therefore demanded the copies of the statements and the documents on
			<lb />
			the basis of which the report was given by communication dated 23 rd
			<lb />
			July, 2008. No reasons had been disclosed as to why the copies of the
			<lb />
			documents and the statement of witnesses were not required to be given
			<lb />
			to the petitioner. Every step taken by the respondents in awarding the
			<lb />
			punishment to the petitioner in the facts and circumstances is in
			<lb />
			violation of the principles of natural Justice.
			<lb />
			78. The respondent no.1 has an ordinance which stipulates the
			<lb />
			procedure for dealing with the cases of use of unfair means. The
			<lb />
			relevant ordinance of the respondents is as under:-
			<lb />
			25.
			<lb />
			*ORDINANCE RELATING TO THE USE OF UNFAIR
			<lb />
			MEANS BY STUDENTS IN EVALUATION
			<lb />
			1.
			<lb />
			Definitions:
			<lb />
			For the purposes of this Ordinance:
			<lb />
			(a)
			<lb />
			Evaluation means and includes all learning processes
			<lb />
			followed by evaluation such as quizzes, term papers,
			<lb />
			assigned readings, laboratory tests, seminars mid-semester
			<lb />
			examinations and end-semester examinations and research
			<lb />
			papers including dissertations and theses.
			<lb />
			(b)
			<lb />
			Student means a student on active rolls of the University.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P(C) 5725/2008
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 66 of 71
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			(c)
			<lb />
			Semester implies Monsoon or Winter semester of an
			<lb />
			Academic year.
			<lb />
			(d)
			<lb />
			The use of unfair means implies any dishonest or unfair
			<lb />
			means or indulging in disorderly conduct including
			<lb />
			plagiarism during the course of study in a programme at
			<lb />
			the University.
			<lb />
			(e)
			<lb />
			Committee means the Standing Committee of the Academic
			<lb />
			Council for looking into the cases of use of unfair means by
			<lb />
			the students.
			<lb />
			2. Constitution of the Standing Committee:
			<lb />
			(a)
			<lb />
			On the recommendations of the Vice-Chancellor, the
			<lb />
			Academic Council shall constitute a Standing Committee
			<lb />
			consisting of the following:
			<lb />
			(i)
			<lb />
			Two Deans; and
			<lb />
			(ii)
			<lb />
			The Dean of the School from where the case of use of unfair
			<lb />
			means by student(s) reported (to be co-opted);
			<lb />
			Provided that if the reported case of the student(s) happens
			<lb />
			to be from the School whose Dean is already represented in
			<lb />
			the Committee, then the Vice-Chancellor shall nominate
			<lb />
			another Dean to be a member of the Committee.
			<lb />
			(b)
			<lb />
			An Officer of the University nominated by the Vice-
			<lb />
			Chancellor will function as non-member Secretary of the
			<lb />
			Committee.
			<lb />
			3.
			<lb />
			A student of the University who is reported to have
			<lb />
			indulged in use of unfair means in any aspect of evaluation
			<lb />
			inclusive of quizzes, term papers, assigned readings,
			<lb />
			laboratory tests, seminars, mid-semester or end-semester
			<lb />
			examinations and or have indulged in plagiarism while
			<lb />
			writing
			<lb />
			research
			<lb />
			publications/articles
			<lb />
			including
			<lb />
			dissertations and theses would made himself/herself liable
			<lb />
			for disciplinary action as may be determined by the
			<lb />
			committee of the Academic Council dealing with cases of
			<lb />
			use of unfair means.
			<lb />
			4.(a) Any faculty member finding a student of the University
			<lb />
			indulging in the use of unfair means will report in writing to
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P(C) 5725/2008
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 67 of 71
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			the Chairperson of the Centre with copies to the Dean of
			<lb />
			the School concerned and the Co-ordinator (Evaluation) for
			<lb />
			placing before the Committee dealing with cases of use of
			<lb />
			unfair means for its appropriate consideration and
			<lb />
			directions.
			<lb />
			(b)
			<lb />
			The concerned Centre/School shall forward their views to
			<lb />
			the Committee within 15 days of the receipt of the said
			<lb />
			communication from the faculty member. In case no views
			<lb />
			are received from the concerned Centre/School, the
			<lb />
			Committee will proceed suo moto.
			<lb />
			5.
			<lb />
			The Committee will provide a student alleged to have been
			<lb />
			involved in the use of unfair means, fair and reasonable
			<lb />
			opportunity to prove his/her innocence before pronouncing
			<lb />
			him/her as guilty.
			<lb />
			6.
			<lb />
			The Committee shall be entitled to exercise all or any of the
			<lb />
			powers relating to discipline and disciplinary action in
			<lb />
			relation to any student as contained in the Statute 32 of
			<lb />
			the Statutes of the University as may be delegated to it by
			<lb />
			the Vice-Chancellor.
			<lb />
			7.
			<lb />
			A student awarded punishment by the Committee dealing
			<lb />
			with the cases of use of unfair means shall be entitled to
			<lb />
			make an appeal to the Vice-Chancellor within 30 days of
			<lb />
			the award of punishment.
			<lb />
			8.
			<lb />
			In all matters relating to discipline and disciplinary action
			<lb />
			against students for use of unfair means, the decision of
			<lb />
			the Vice-Chancellor shall be final and no further appeal
			<lb />
			shall be against it.
			<lb />
			79. According to the learned counsel for the respondents, the said
			<lb />
			ordinance and the procedures set therein is not applicable in the case of
			<lb />
			the petitioner as she was not a student of respondent no.1. According to
			<lb />
			him a student under the said ordinance is one who is on the active roll
			<lb />
			of the University. The respondents however, cannot deny that in the
			<lb />
			entrance examination a student who is on the active role of the
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P(C) 5725/2008
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 68 of 71
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			University or other candidates who are not on the active role of the
			<lb />
			university could appear. In case of use of unfair means in the entrance
			<lb />
			examination, the respondents could not use two types of procedures in
			<lb />
			the facts and circumstances. Even if, strictly speaking the ordinance 25
			<lb />
			regarding use of unfair means was not applicable to a candidate who
			<lb />
			was not on active roll, the same procedure ought to have been followed
			<lb />
			by the respondents.
			<lb />
			80. University Grants commission activities are regulated under Act
			<lb />
			33 of 1972. The power and functions of the Commission were detailed
			<lb />
			by the Act 59 of 1984 (w.e.f. 1.10.1984). Section 12 A (1) (g) defines
			<lb />
			`student&quot; which is as under:
			<lb />
			&quot;(g) &quot;Student&quot; includes a person seeking admission as a student:&quot;
			<lb />
			In the circumstances in dealing with the case of the petitioner for
			<lb />
			alleged use of unfair means, the respondents ought to have followed the
			<lb />
			same procedure as stipulated in ordinance 25 even if a strictly speaking
			<lb />
			it was not applicable to the petitioner. Therefore for the foregoing
			<lb />
			reasons and in the totality of the facts and circumstances, the Office
			<lb />
			order No.08/CP/2008 dated 5 th August, 2008 and the enquiry report
			<lb />
			dated 7 th March, 2008 cannot be sustained in the facts and in law and
			<lb />
			they are set aside.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P(C) 5725/2008
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 69 of 71
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			81. On setting aside the order of punishment and the enquiry report,
			<lb />
			the next question is whether the matter should be remanded to the
			<lb />
			respondent for fresh enquiry in accordance with the procedure
			<lb />
			analogous to the procedural detailed in ordinance 25 or to direct the
			<lb />
			respondents to allow the petitioner to join Ph.D course now as she has
			<lb />
			already lost five years. Even if the lapse of the petitioner is established
			<lb />
			after a proper enquiry, the punishment for debarment for more than five
			<lb />
			years could not be granted. The petitioner has already undergone the
			<lb />
			punishment for a lapse which has not been established against her.
			<lb />
			82. Even if the matter is remanded and fresh enquiry is conducted
			<lb />
			and if the petitioner is found guilty, she cannot be imposed more severe
			<lb />
			punishment than what had been awarded to him. The High
			<lb />
			Court/Tribunal, while exercising the power of judicial review, should
			<lb />
			not normally substitute its own conclusion on penalty and impose some
			<lb />
			other penalty. However, if the punishment imposed by the disciplinary
			<lb />
			authority or by the appellate authority shocks the conscience of the
			<lb />
			High Court/Tribunal, it would appropriately mould the relief, either
			<lb />
			directing the disciplinary/applicant authority to reconsider the penalty
			<lb />
			imposed, or to shorten the litigation, it may itself, in exceptional and
			<lb />
			rare cases, impose appropriate punishment with cogent reasons in
			<lb />
			support thereof. In the circumstances, remanding the matter to the
			<lb />
			respondents would result in imposing more stringent punishment on
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P(C) 5725/2008
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 70 of 71
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			the petitioner than what has been awarded to her without
			<lb />
			establishment of her culpability.
			<lb />
			83. Therefore, in the peculiar facts and circumstances, the matter is
			<lb />
			not remanded for fresh enquiry and the order of punishment being
			<lb />
			office order no. 08/CP/2008 and consequence thereof are set aside. The
			<lb />
			writ petition is therefore, allowed. The respondents are directed to admit
			<lb />
			the petitioner to Ph.D course in the ensuing session forthwith.
			<lb />
			Considering the facts and circumstances the petitioner is also awarded
			<lb />
			the costs of Rs.30,000/. Cost be paid within four weeks. With these
			<lb />
			directions the writ petition is allowed. All the pending applications also
			<lb />
			stand disposed of.
			<lb />
			ANIL KUMAR, J.
			<lb />
			July 6, 2012
			<lb />
			k/vk
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P(C) 5725/2008
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 71 of 71
			<lb />
		</page>
	</text>
</tei>
