<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			* IN THE HIGH COURT OF DELHI AT NEW DELHI
			<lb />
			+ W.P.(C) 4041-42/2006
			<lb />
			Reserved on: 21.03.2017
			<lb />
			Date of decision: 10.04.2017
			<lb />
			IN THE MATTER OF:
			<lb />
			M/S KOLMET ENTERPRISES ..... Petitioner
			<lb />
			Through: Mr. S.K. Maniktala, Advocate with
			<lb />
			Mr. Vinod Kumar, Advocate.
			<lb />
			versus
			<lb />
			NEW DELHI MUNICIPAL COUNCIL ..... Respondent
			<lb />
			Through: Mr. Jitendra Kumar Tripathi, proxy
			<lb />
			counsel for Ms. Sakshi Popli, Advocate.
			<lb />
			CORAM
			<lb />
			HONBLE MS.JUSTICE HIMA KOHLI
			<lb />
			HIMA KOHLI, J.
			<lb />
		</front>
		<body>
			1.
			<lb />
			The petitioner is aggrieved by the order dated 15.2.2016, passed by
			<lb />
			the Lieutenant Governor, Govt. of NCT of Delhi allowing the second
			<lb />
			appeal filed by the respondent/NDMC under Section 256 of the New Delhi
			<lb />
			Municipal Council Act, 1994 (in short &apos;the NDMC Act&apos;) against an order
			<lb />
			dated 16.8.2015 passed by the Appellate Tribunal, MCD/NDMC
			<lb />
			(hereinafter referred to as the ATMCD) whereunder, the demolition order
			<lb />
			dated 7.6.2005 passed by the Chief Architect, NDMC in respect of the
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P.(C) 4041-42/2006
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 1 of 17
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			alleged unauthorized construction existing at the backside of Host
			<lb />
			Restaurant, F-8, Connaught Place, New Delhi, was set aside.
			<lb />
			2.
			<lb />
			The facts leading to filing of the present petition, as gleaned from the
			<lb />
			petition, are that on 30.5.1978, the petitioner had taken on lease, the subject
			<lb />
			premises for running a restaurant under the name and style of &apos;Host
			<lb />
			Restaurant&apos;. At that time, in addition to two permanent kitchens in the
			<lb />
			subject premises, there existed a temporary kitchen behind the building,
			<lb />
			which was not a part of the tenanted premises. On 11.2.1983, the Medical
			<lb />
			Officer of Health and Licencing Authority, NDMC inspected the kitchen of
			<lb />
			the subject premises and served a notice dated 8.3.1983 on the petitioner
			<lb />
			pointing out several defects and the unhygienic condition prevailing in the
			<lb />
			kitchen. In para 1 of the said notice, a mention was made of a temporary
			<lb />
			kitchen in addition to the licensed kitchen where food articles were being
			<lb />
			cooked under unhygienic conditions and it was noted inter alia that the
			<lb />
			temporary kitchen was not completely fly-proof and flies were noticed
			<lb />
			inside. Directions were issued to the petitioner to shutdown the temporary
			<lb />
			kitchen or seek approval for operating the same under the relevant bye-
			<lb />
			laws.
			<lb />
			3.
			<lb />
			The petitioner had replied to the aforesaid notice, vide letter dated
			<lb />
			10.6.1983, and stated inter alia that they had removed all the defects that
			<lb />
			had been pointed out and a request was made to the authorities to undertake
			<lb />
			fresh inspection of the premises. The matter rested there till the year 1997
			<lb />
			when the Chief Architect, NDMC served on the petitioner, a notice to show
			<lb />
			cause dated 8.8.1997 which stated that unauthorized construction had been
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P.(C) 4041-42/2006
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 2 of 17
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			raised in the subject premises without obtaining the requisite approval
			<lb />
			under the Building Bye Laws, and the same was liable to be sealed under
			<lb />
			Section 250 of the NDMC Act. The petitioner was required to give a reply
			<lb />
			within five days as to why the proposed action should not be taken by the
			<lb />
			respondent/NDMC. The following were details of the unauthorized
			<lb />
			constructions mentioned in the notice to show cause dated 8.8.1997:-
			<lb />
			&quot;Covered area m.a. 22&apos;x20&apos; and 15&apos;x10&apos; with the help of ACC
			<lb />
			sheets at open area back side of Host Restaurant, F-B,
			<lb />
			Connaught Place, New Delhi.&quot;
			<lb />
			At the bottom of the notice to show cause, was a hand drawn site plan to
			<lb />
			indicate the location of the temporarily covered area.
			<lb />
			4.
			<lb />
			Vide reply dated 19.8.1997, the petitioner responded to the aforesaid
			<lb />
			notice to show cause, denying that there existed any unauthorized
			<lb />
			construction and asserted that the temporary structure in question is very
			<lb />
			old. To demonstrate that even as per the respondent/NDMC, a temporary
			<lb />
			kitchen was in existence for several years, reference was made to the earlier
			<lb />
			notice dated 8.3.1983 issued by the Medical Officer, Health NDMC. The
			<lb />
			petitioner stressed that they had remained in possession of the subject
			<lb />
			premises since the year 1978 and submitted three certificates issued by
			<lb />
			neighbours, who claimed to have attended the opening ceremony of the
			<lb />
			restaurant, and stated that the temporary structure in question was existing
			<lb />
			at the back of Host Restaurant from the date the said restaurant had been
			<lb />
			inaugurated on 4.2.1979. After receiving the aforesaid reply, the
			<lb />
			respondent/NDMC remained silent for almost eight years, till the matter
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P.(C) 4041-42/2006
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 3 of 17
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			was reopened on 7.6.2005, when the respondent/NDMC proceeded to issue
			<lb />
			an order under Section 247 of the NDMC Act holding that the temporary
			<lb />
			structure in question was unauthorized and liable to be demolished and the
			<lb />
			reply submitted by the petitioner was not found to be satisfactory. As a
			<lb />
			result, the petitioner was called upon to demolish the said structure within
			<lb />
			one week.
			<lb />
			5.
			<lb />
			Aggrieved by the aforesaid decision, the petitioner preferred an
			<lb />
			appeal under Section 256 of the NDMC Act before the Appellate Tribunal,
			<lb />
			MCD/NDMC. Vide order dated 16.8.2005, the Appellate Tribunal allowed
			<lb />
			the said appeal and held that the date of the alleged unauthorized
			<lb />
			construction had not been disclosed by the respondent/NDMC either in the
			<lb />
			notice to show cause or in the impugned order dated 7.6.2005 and the onus
			<lb />
			of proving the said fact lies with the respondent/NDMC, which they had
			<lb />
			failed to discharge. The Appellate Authority alluded to the extant statute,
			<lb />
			namely, the Punjab Municipal Act, 1911 and referred in particular to
			<lb />
			Section 195 thereof which prescribes the penalty for disobedience. The said
			<lb />
			provision is reproduced herein below for ready reference :
			<lb />
			&quot;195. Penalty for disobedience: -Should a building be begun,
			<lb />
			erected or re-erected.
			<lb />
			(a) without sanction as required by section189 (1); or
			<lb />
			(b) without notice as required by section 189 (2); or
			<lb />
			(c) when sanction has been refused;
			<lb />
			the [committee] may by notice delivered to the owner within six
			<lb />
			months from the completion of the building, require the
			<lb />
			building to be altered or demolished as it may deem necessary
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P.(C) 4041-42/2006
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 4 of 17
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			within the period specified in such notice; and should it be
			<lb />
			begun or erected.
			<lb />
			(d) in contravention of the terms of any sanction granted; or
			<lb />
			(e) when the sanction has lapsed; or
			<lb />
			(f) in contravention of any bye-law made under section190; or in
			<lb />
			the case of a building of which the erection has been deemed to
			<lb />
			be sanctioned under section 193(4), if it contravenes any scheme
			<lb />
			sanctioned under section 192;
			<lb />
			the [committee] may by notice to be delivered to the owner
			<lb />
			within six months from the completion of the building require the
			<lb />
			building to be altered in such a manner as it may deem
			<lb />
			necessary, within the period specified in such notice:
			<lb />
			Provided that the committee may, instead of requiring the
			<lb />
			alteration or demolition of any such building, accept by way of
			<lb />
			compensation such sum as it may deem reasonable:
			<lb />
			Provided also that the committee shall require a building to
			<lb />
			be demolished or altered so far as is necessary to avoid
			<lb />
			contravention of a building scheme drawn up under section 192:
			<lb />
			Provided further that if any notice is issued by the Executive
			<lb />
			Officer under this section on the ground that a building has
			<lb />
			been begun or has been erected in contravention of the terms of
			<lb />
			any sanction granted or in contravention of any bye-law made
			<lb />
			under section 190 the person to whom the notice is issued may,
			<lb />
			within fifteen days from the date of service of such notice,
			<lb />
			appeal to the committee, and subject to the provisions of
			<lb />
			sections 225, 232 and 236, the decision of the committee shall
			<lb />
			be final.&quot; (emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
			6.
			<lb />
			Holding that under Section 195 of the Punjab Municipal Act, 1911,
			<lb />
			the respondent/NDMC was under an obligation to demolish a building
			<lb />
			upon a notice being delivered to the owner, within a period of six months
			<lb />
			from the completion of the unauthorized construction, and observing that it
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P.(C) 4041-42/2006
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 5 of 17
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			had failed to do so in the present case by specifically mentioning in the
			<lb />
			notice to show cause, the date on which the alleged unauthorized
			<lb />
			construction had come into existence, the petitioners&apos; appeal was allowed
			<lb />
			and the impugned demolition order dated 07.6.2005 was set aside with a
			<lb />
			rider that the respondent/NDMC will be at liberty to initiate proceedings
			<lb />
			against the unauthorized construction if it has documentary evidence to
			<lb />
			substantiate the above date.
			<lb />
			7.
			<lb />
			The decision of the Appellate Authority was assailed by the
			<lb />
			respondent/NDMC in a second appeal filed before the Lieutenant
			<lb />
			Governor, Govt. of NCT of Delhi, which was allowed vide order dated
			<lb />
			15.2.2006. Aggrieved by the said decision, the petitioner has filed the
			<lb />
			present petition.
			<lb />
			8.
			<lb />
			Mr. Maniktala, learned counsel for the petitioner submitted that the
			<lb />
			impugned judgment is erroneous inasmuch as it failed to notice that the
			<lb />
			temporary kitchen in question was being run at the back side of the subject
			<lb />
			premises from the year 1979 onwards, which is apparent from a perusal of
			<lb />
			the notice dated 8.3.1983 issued by the Medical Officer, Health NDMC
			<lb />
			and the said document is a conclusive proof of the existence of the
			<lb />
			temporary structure. He adverted to the provisions of Section 195 of the
			<lb />
			Punjab Municipal Act, 1911 and argued that the temporary construction is
			<lb />
			covered by the Punjab Municipal Act, 1911 and not by the NDMC Act and
			<lb />
			once Section 195 of the Punjab Municipal Act, 1911 contemplates that no
			<lb />
			action can be taken after six months of the existence of the structure, any
			<lb />
			attempt on the part of the respondent/NDMC to take action under the
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P.(C) 4041-42/2006
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 6 of 17
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			NDMC Act, after a lapse of 18 years reckoned from the date when the
			<lb />
			construction had come into existence and 7 years after the date of issuance
			<lb />
			of the notice to show cause dated 8.8.1997, is patently illegal and arbitrary.
			<lb />
			To fortify his submissions, learned counsel had cited the following
			<lb />
			decisions :
			<lb />
			1. MCD vs. Surjit Kaur, 1973 AIR (Del.) 198,
			<lb />
			2. Masonic Club vs. MCD &amp; Ors., 91 (2001) DLT 149,
			<lb />
			3. Jor Bagh Association (Regd.) vs. UOI, 2004 AIR(Del.) 389, and
			<lb />
			4. H.K. Choudhary vs. NDMC, 2008 (155) DLT 267.
			<lb />
			9.
			<lb />
			It may be noted here that arguments were addressed in the present
			<lb />
			case by learned counsel for the petitioner on 21.3.2017. After about forty
			<lb />
			minutes into the arguments, learned proxy counsel for the
			<lb />
			respondent/NDMC had turned up and sought to explain his absence on the
			<lb />
			ground that he was held up before another Bench. When he was called
			<lb />
			upon to address arguments in reply, he had expressed his inability to do so.
			<lb />
			While reserving judgment, in the interest of justice, learned counsel for the
			<lb />
			respondent/NDMC was granted two working days to submit written
			<lb />
			submissions with a copy to the other side. On 24.3.2017, Ms. Popli, learned
			<lb />
			counsel for the respondent/NDMC had mentioned the present matter in the
			<lb />
			presence of the other side and requested for further time of one week to file
			<lb />
			the written submissions. While declining to extend the time by one week,
			<lb />
			she was granted time upto 27.3.2017 to submit the written submissions.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P.(C) 4041-42/2006
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 7 of 17
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			However, written submissions were not filed on behalf of NDMC till the
			<lb />
			court closed for one week, on 02.4.2017.
			<lb />
			10. Records reveal that respondent/NDMC did not file a counter
			<lb />
			affidavit in reply to the present petition. However, the petitioner did
			<lb />
			annex with the petition, a copy of the second appeal preferred by the
			<lb />
			respondent/NDMC before the Lieutenant Governor, GNCTD for assailing
			<lb />
			the order dated 16.8.2005 passed by the ATMCD/NDMC. This court has
			<lb />
			therefore culled out the pleas taken by the respondent/NDMC in the second
			<lb />
			appeal to assail the order dated 16.8.2005 passed by the ATMCD. In the
			<lb />
			appeal, it has been stated by NDMC that the impugned notice to show
			<lb />
			cause dated 8.8.1997 furnishes all the relevant details of the temporary
			<lb />
			construction existing at the subject premises and due opportunity was given
			<lb />
			to the petitioner to submit a reply. Only after examining the petitioner&apos;s
			<lb />
			reply was the order dated 7.6.2005 passed by the Chief Architect, NDMC
			<lb />
			directing demolition of the unauthorized construction.
			<lb />
			11. As for the notice dated 8.3.1983 issued by the Medical Officer of
			<lb />
			Health and Licencing Authority, NDMC, the respondent/NDMC took a
			<lb />
			stand that the said notice was issued in connection with a temporary
			<lb />
			kitchen situated at the back of Host Restaurant and it referred to the
			<lb />
			unhygienic conditions prevailing therein for preparation of food, etc., but
			<lb />
			nowhere in the said notice was there any description of the unauthorized
			<lb />
			construction for it to be treated as identical to the construction that finds
			<lb />
			mention in the notice to show cause dated 8.8.1997 and the demolition
			<lb />
			order dated 7.6.2005. Reference has also made by the NDMC to the reply
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P.(C) 4041-42/2006
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 8 of 17
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			of the petitioner dated 10.6.1983 in response to the notice dated 8.3.1983,
			<lb />
			to urge that they had cleverly avoided stating anything with regard to the
			<lb />
			temporary kitchen whereas they are now trying to rely on the same set of
			<lb />
			documents to demonstrate that the unauthorized construction is very old
			<lb />
			only to take advantage of the protection available under the Punjab
			<lb />
			Municipal Act, 1911.
			<lb />
			12. The Respondent/NDMC had also questioned the genuineness of
			<lb />
			three certificates issued by Shri Gulab Bhawani, M/s Kailash Carpet Co.
			<lb />
			and M/s Pandit Brothers (neighbours) and relied on by the petitioner to
			<lb />
			show that the temporary kitchen had existed at the back of the premises
			<lb />
			since the year 1979. Respondent/NDMC contended that the said certificates
			<lb />
			are of no value and could not be relied upon till the persons issuing them
			<lb />
			were summoned and examined.
			<lb />
			13. The respondent/NDMC has also taken a plea in their second appeal
			<lb />
			that the ATMCD had erred in fixing the responsibility of proving the age of
			<lb />
			the unauthorized construction on the NDMC and had wrongly concluded
			<lb />
			that the show cause notice/demolition order did not contain the complete
			<lb />
			and the relevant facts. It was urged by NDMC that even the notings in the
			<lb />
			department file dated 1.8.1997 and 29.8.1997 and relied on by the
			<lb />
			petitioner, would not be of any assistance as no conclusions could be drawn
			<lb />
			therefrom.
			<lb />
			14. The only question that engages this court is whether the construction,
			<lb />
			subject matter of the demolition of the order dated 07.6.2005, preceded by
			<lb />
			a notice to show cause dated 08.8.1997, is protected under the Punjab
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P.(C) 4041-42/2006
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 9 of 17
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			Municipal Act and if so, could it have been demolished by the
			<lb />
			respondent/NDMC. The contention of the learned counsel for the petitioner
			<lb />
			is that the construction in question is very old and was raised prior to
			<lb />
			coming into force of the NDMC Act, in the year 1994. As per the
			<lb />
			petitioner, at that time, Punjab Municipal Act was in force and the said
			<lb />
			construction is saved under the provision of Section 195 for the reason that
			<lb />
			the respondent/NDMC did not issue a notice of demolition within six
			<lb />
			months from the date of raising the said construction.
			<lb />
			15. On the other hand, the consistent stand of the respondent/NDMC
			<lb />
			before the ATMCD and in the second appeal has been that the construction
			<lb />
			in question does not enjoy the protection of the Punjab Municipal Act and
			<lb />
			the NDMC is well empowered to take demolition action under Section 247
			<lb />
			of the NDMC Act.
			<lb />
			16. On examining the documents filed by the petitioner and referred to
			<lb />
			herein above, it is quite apparent that a temporary kitchen was in existence
			<lb />
			behind the subject premises in the year 1983, as the same was pointed out
			<lb />
			by the Medical Officer Health Department, NDMC in the notice dated
			<lb />
			08.3.1983. Though details of the nature of the construction existing at that
			<lb />
			point in time were not specified in the captioned notice, the same did
			<lb />
			acknowledge the existence of a temporary kitchen behind the building, in
			<lb />
			addition to the licensed kitchen. That being the position, it cannot be urged
			<lb />
			by the respondent/NDMC that the entire construction subject matter of the
			<lb />
			notice to show cause dated 08.8.1997, had come into existence after
			<lb />
			enactment of the NDMC Act, 1994. This being the factual background, it is
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P.(C) 4041-42/2006
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 10 of 17
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			considered necessary to examine as to whether it was necessary for the
			<lb />
			petitioner to give a notice of completion of construction activities for
			<lb />
			seeking protection of the construction raised prior to the year 1994, for
			<lb />
			claiming the protection available under Section 195 of the Punjab
			<lb />
			Municipal Act.
			<lb />
			17. Section 195 postulates that if the building has begun, been erected or
			<lb />
			re-erected without necessary sanctions; or on refusal of sanction, the
			<lb />
			Committee shall deliver a notice to the owner within six months from the
			<lb />
			date of completion of the building, and
			<lb />
			require the owner to
			<lb />
			alter/demolish, the same within a period specified in such a notice. Further,
			<lb />
			the said provision contemplates that should a building be begun or erected
			<lb />
			in contravention to the terms of any sanction granted, or after the sanction
			<lb />
			has lapsed, or in contravention of any of the bye-law/scheme of sanction,
			<lb />
			then the Committee may deliver a notice to the owner within six months
			<lb />
			from the completion of the building, requiring the building to be altered, as
			<lb />
			may be necessary within a period specified in such a notice.
			<lb />
			18. The scheme of Section 195 and the effect of the said provision came
			<lb />
			up for discussion in the case of Surjit Kaur (supra). In the said case, the
			<lb />
			respondent had erected a building in the year 1957 without obtaining any
			<lb />
			sanction from the Municipal Authorities. The Municipal Corporation of
			<lb />
			Delhi served a notice of demolition of the said premises. Aggrieved by the
			<lb />
			said demolition order, the respondent therein instituted a suit for permanent
			<lb />
			injunction which was dismissed by the learned trial court. The respondent
			<lb />
			then filed an appeal wherein the judgment of the trial court was overturned.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P.(C) 4041-42/2006
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 11 of 17
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			Aggrieved by the said decision, MCD filed a second appeal before the High
			<lb />
			Court, wherein the legal question framed was as to whether the MCD was
			<lb />
			entitled in law to issue a notice of demolition. It was noticed in the said
			<lb />
			decision that the Punjab Municipal Act, 1911 was applicable to the areas in
			<lb />
			question till the Delhi Municipal Act came into force on 09.4.1958. The
			<lb />
			appellant/Corporation therein had invoked Section 343 of DMC Act and
			<lb />
			had contended that the notice of demolition could be issued at any time
			<lb />
			after completion of the building without any limitation of time. After
			<lb />
			examining the rights and obligations cast on the Municipal Corporation,
			<lb />
			flowing from the Punjab Municipal Act, which was succeeded by the Delhi
			<lb />
			Municipal Corporation Act, it was held that MCD would be bound by the
			<lb />
			liability of its predecessor Municipalities, in the light of Section 516 of
			<lb />
			DMC Act.
			<lb />
			19. In the captioned case, after carefully examining the provision of
			<lb />
			Section 195 of the Punjab Municipal Act, the Court had interpreted the
			<lb />
			same in the following manner:-
			<lb />
			&quot;4.
			<lb />
			…….Admittedly, the building in question was erected
			<lb />
			without the requisite sanction and, therefore, if the Punjab Act
			<lb />
			had continued to apply, the Municipality would have been
			<lb />
			entitled to require the respondent to demolish the said building.
			<lb />
			The first appellate Court has not given any finding as to the exact
			<lb />
			date or time when the building was constructed by the respondent
			<lb />
			other than saying that it was constructed in 1957. Taking the last
			<lb />
			day of the year 1957 to be the day when the building was
			<lb />
			constructed, the Municipality, if it had continued, could have
			<lb />
			served the notice of demolition under the aforesaid section by or
			<lb />
			before June 30, 1958.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P.(C) 4041-42/2006
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 12 of 17
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			XXXXX
			<lb />
			6.
			<lb />
			It is no doubt true that a liability was incurred by the
			<lb />
			respondent under section 195 of the Punjab Act to demolish the
			<lb />
			building upon a notice being delivered to her but this liability
			<lb />
			would have been incurred only if a notice had been delivered to
			<lb />
			her within six months from the completion of the building and
			<lb />
			that is the extent of the liability incurred by her. The liability
			<lb />
			was conditional upon a notice being delivered to her within six
			<lb />
			months from the completion of the building and it cannot be
			<lb />
			said to be a liability incurred without any limit of time. The
			<lb />
			Corporation cannot take advantage of the fact that in
			<lb />
			section 343 of the Corporation Act, there is no limit of time for
			<lb />
			the service of a notice of demolition because the Corporation can
			<lb />
			enforce only such liabilities which have been incurred under the
			<lb />
			Punjab Act and to determine the extent and nature of the liability,
			<lb />
			the provisions of the Punjab Act will have to be looked into
			<lb />
			notwithstanding its repeal. The provisions contained in
			<lb />
			sections 336, 343 and 344 of the Corporation Act are, by their
			<lb />
			language, of prospective operation and the appellant
			<lb />
			Corporation cannot rely upon these provisions to issue a notice
			<lb />
			of demolition after the expiry of six months from the
			<lb />
			completion of the building as was done in the present case in
			<lb />
			the year 1960.
			<lb />
			(7) It may be that a period of six months had not expired between
			<lb />
			the completion of the building and the coming into force of the
			<lb />
			Corporation Act. If the Corporation wanted to exercise the
			<lb />
			power of demolition by reason of clause (b) of sub-section (2) of
			<lb />
			section 516 of the Corporation Act, they ought to have acted
			<lb />
			within six months from the completion of the building and
			<lb />
			having failed to do so, they had no right to take action after the
			<lb />
			expiry of six months. Upon the expiry of six months from the
			<lb />
			completion of the building, no liability remained upon the
			<lb />
			respondent to have the building demolished as the liability
			<lb />
			ceased to remain a liability upon the expiry of this period.&quot;
			<lb />
			(emphasis added)
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P.(C) 4041-42/2006
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 13 of 17
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			The decision in the case of Surjit Kaur (supra), was followed as a precedent
			<lb />
			in the cases of Jor Bagh Association (supra) and H.K. Choudhary (supra).
			<lb />
			20. Coming to the facts of the case at hand, there is no quarrel with the
			<lb />
			proposition that the respondent/NDMC would have been well entitled to
			<lb />
			require the petitioner to demolish the construction undertaken by it without
			<lb />
			the requisite sanction, but the same could have been done only if a notice of
			<lb />
			demolition was served on the petitioner within six months from the date of
			<lb />
			completion of the said construction. Thus, unlike Section 247 of the
			<lb />
			NDMC Act, 1994 where there is no timeline fixed for the
			<lb />
			respondent/NDMC for service of a notice of demolition, a specific timeline
			<lb />
			was prescribed in Section 195. The NDMC Act, 1994 was enacted on
			<lb />
			14.7.1994 and the provisions contained in Chapter XIV thereof that relates
			<lb />
			to &quot;Building Regulations&quot;, provide for prohibition of building without
			<lb />
			sanction, erection of building, application for additions to, or repairs of
			<lb />
			buildings, sanction or refusal of erection of building, order of demolition
			<lb />
			and stoppage of erection of any buildings etc. are all prospective in nature.
			<lb />
			None of the said provisions can be invoked by the respondent/NDMC to
			<lb />
			issue a notice of demolition after expiry of six months from the date of
			<lb />
			completion of the erection without sanction, when the notice itself does not
			<lb />
			mention the date on which erection of the un-authorized construction was
			<lb />
			undertaken.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P.(C) 4041-42/2006
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 14 of 17
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			21. It may be noted here that Section 416 of the NDMC Act, 1994 that
			<lb />
			provides for repeal and savings is in pari materia with Section 516 of the
			<lb />
			Delhi Municipal Corporation Act, discussed in the case of Surjit Kaur
			<lb />
			(supra). Section 416 postulates that from the date of establishment of the
			<lb />
			Council, the Punjab Municipal Act, 1911 as applicable to New Delhi, shall
			<lb />
			cease to have effect within New Delhi. Section 416 (2)(b) provides that
			<lb />
			notwithstanding the provisions of sub-section (1), all debts, obligations and
			<lb />
			liabilities incurred, all contracts entered into and all matters and things
			<lb />
			engaged to be done by, with or for the New Delhi Municipal Committee
			<lb />
			before the establishment of the Council, shall be deemed to have been
			<lb />
			incurred, entered into or engaged to be done by, with or for the Council
			<lb />
			under this Act. In other words, if the respondent/NDMC wanted to exercise
			<lb />
			the powers of demolition by invoking the provision of Section 416 (2) (b)
			<lb />
			of the NDMC Act, 1994, then it ought to have taken action within a period
			<lb />
			of six months from the date of completion of the building, as contemplated
			<lb />
			in Section 195 of the Punjab Municipal Act, which it has failed to take in
			<lb />
			the present case.
			<lb />
			22. Given the fact that the notice issued by the Health Department of the
			<lb />
			respondent/NDMC in the year 1983 when the Punjab Municipal Act was in
			<lb />
			force, refers to a temporary kitchen behind the main building, it cannot be
			<lb />
			argued that a notice could be issued by the NDMC after enactment of the
			<lb />
			NDMC Act, 1994, thereby calling upon the owner to demolish the very
			<lb />
			same unauthorized construction. On expiry of a period of six months from
			<lb />
			the date of completion of the construction in question, the petitioner stands
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P.(C) 4041-42/2006
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 15 of 17
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			exonerated from the liability to undertake any demolition activity, as
			<lb />
			contemplated in Section 195 of Punjab Municipal Act.
			<lb />
			23. As a result, this Court is inclined to concur with view expressed by
			<lb />
			the ATMCD that upon expiry of six months from the date of completion of
			<lb />
			the building, no liability remains for the petitioner to have the building
			<lb />
			demolished as such a liability ceased to remain a liability after expiry of six
			<lb />
			months. Further, in the case of Masonic Club (supra) it was clearly held
			<lb />
			that a notice to show cause must contain the relevant description of the
			<lb />
			unauthorized construction including the date of construction, the area of
			<lb />
			unauthorized construction, its measurement etc. and in the absence of the
			<lb />
			material particulars, the notice to show cause has no value in the eyes of
			<lb />
			law. On a perusal of the notice to show cause in the present case, it is
			<lb />
			manifest that the respondent/NDMC failed to give the material particulars
			<lb />
			with regard to the date/year of the construction and has only given the
			<lb />
			measurement of the construction.
			<lb />
			24. Moreover, the notice to show cause was issued in the year 1997
			<lb />
			whereas, the demolition order came to be passed on 07.6.2005. There is no
			<lb />
			explanation worth the name offered by the respondent/NDMC for keeping
			<lb />
			the said notice to show cause pending for eight long years. Even if three
			<lb />
			certificates submitted by the petitioner are discarded on the ground that
			<lb />
			they are self serving and of doubtful veracity, the notice dated 08.3.1983,
			<lb />
			issued by none other than the Health Department, NDMC, cannot be
			<lb />
			overlooked when it comes to assessing the date of completion of or the
			<lb />
			vintage of the temporary structure in question.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P.(C) 4041-42/2006
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 16 of 17
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			25. As a result, the impugned order dated 15.2.2006 passed by the
			<lb />
			second Appellate Authority cannot be sustained and is set aside and the
			<lb />
			order dated 16.8.2005 passed by the Appellate Tribunal, MCD is restored.
			<lb />
			Axiomatically, the impugned demolition order dated 07.6.2005, passed by
			<lb />
			the respondent/NDMC is unsustainable and is quashed and set aside. At the
			<lb />
			same time, liberty is granted to the respondent/NDMC to initiate
			<lb />
			proceedings for demolition of the subject unauthorized construction, if it is
			<lb />
			in possession of documentary evidence to demonstrate that the said
			<lb />
			construction was erected after the NDMC Act, 1994 came to be legislated.
			<lb />
			26. In view of the peculiar facts and circumstances of the case, the
			<lb />
			parties are left to bear their own expenses.
			<lb />
			(HIMA KOHLI)
			<lb />
			JUDGE
			<lb />
			APRIL 10, 2017
			<lb />
			sk/ap
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			W.P.(C) 4041-42/2006
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 17 of 17
			<lb />
		</page>
	</text>
</tei>
