<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<note place="headnote">
			W.P.No.21815 of 2021
			<lb />
			and W.M.P.Nos.23004 &amp; 23005 of 2021
			<lb />
		</note>
		<front>
			IN THE HIGH COURT OF JUDICATURE AT MADRAS
			<lb />
			DATED: 20.10.2021
			<lb />
			CORAM
			<lb />
			THE HON&apos;BLE Mr.JUSTICE M.SUNDAR
			<lb />
			W.P.No.21815 of 2021
			<lb />
			and
			<lb />
			W.M.P.Nos.23004 &amp; 23005 of 2021
			<lb />
			Franciscan Sisters of Saint Aloysius Gonzaga,
			<lb />
			Rep by its President,
			<lb />
			Door No.6, St.Agnes Street,
			<lb />
			Puducherry-605001.
			<lb />
			... Petitioner
			<lb />
			-Vs.-
			<lb />
			1. Union of India,
			<lb />
			represented by the Secretary,
			<lb />
			Ministry of Finance,
			<lb />
			North Block,
			<lb />
			New Delhi-110 001.
			<lb />
			2. Central Board of Direct Taxes,
			<lb />
			represented by the Secretary,
			<lb />
			Ministry of Finance,
			<lb />
			North Block, New Delhi-110 001.
			<lb />
			3. Principal Chief Commissioner of Income Tax (Chennai),
			<lb />
			121, M.G.Road,
			<lb />
			Nungambakkam, Chennai-600 034.
			<lb />
			4. The Commissioner of Income Tax (TDS),
			<lb />
			7 th Floor, New Block,
			<lb />
			Aayakar Bhawan,
			<lb />
			121, M.G.Road, Chennai-600 034.
			<lb />
		</front>
		<page>
			1/14
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			W.P.No.21815 of 2021
			<lb />
			and W.M.P.Nos.23004 &amp; 23005 of 2021
			<lb />
		</note>
		<front>
			5. Director of Treasuries and Accounts,
			<lb />
			Office of the Treasuries and Accounts,
			<lb />
			Panagal Building,
			<lb />
			No.1 Jeenis Road,
			<lb />
			Saidapet, Chennai-600 015.
			<lb />
			6. The Commissioner of School Education,
			<lb />
			DPI Campus, Directorate of School Education,
			<lb />
			College Road, Chennai-600 006.
			<lb />
			7. The Director of Elementary Education,
			<lb />
			DPI Campus, College Road,
			<lb />
			Chennai-600 006.
			<lb />
			8. The Director of Teacher Education Research and Training,
			<lb />
			DPI Campus, College Road,
			<lb />
			Chennai-600 006.
			<lb />
			... Respondents
			<lb />
			Writ Petition filed under Article 226 of the Constitution of India
			<lb />
			praying to issue a Writ of Certiorarified Mandamus, calling for the
			<lb />
			records pertaining to the impugned order dated 07.10.2015 in
			<lb />
			C.No.Misc.PRO/2015-16, on the file of the 3 rd respondent and the
			<lb />
			consequential Circular dated 26.10.2015 in R.C.No.23545/2014/E1 on
			<lb />
			the file of the 5 th respondent and quash the same in respect of the catholic
			<lb />
			nuns among the teaching and the non-teaching staff working in the
			<lb />
			educational institutions of the petitioner educational agency, as
			<lb />
			mentioned in the Annexure to the petition, and directing the respondents
			<lb />
			to comply with the Circular of 2 nd respondent Central Board of Direct
			<lb />
			Taxes dated 05.12.1977 in F.No.200/88/75-IT(AI).
			<lb />
		</front>
		<page>
			2/14
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			W.P.No.21815 of 2021
			<lb />
			and W.M.P.Nos.23004 &amp; 23005 of 2021
			<lb />
		</note>
		<front>
			For Petitioner
			<lb />
			:
			<lb />
			Mr.Father Xavier,
			<lb />
			Senior Advocate
			<lb />
			of M/s.Father Xavier Associates
			<lb />
			instructed by Ms.A.Arul Mary
			<lb />
			For Respondents :
			<lb />
			Ms.Hema Muralikrishnan
			<lb />
			Senior standing counsel for R1 to R3
			<lb />
			Mr.Karthik Ranganathan
			<lb />
			Senior standing counsel for R4
			<lb />
			Mr.NRR.Arun Natarajan
			<lb />
			Government Advocate for R5 to R8
			<lb />
			******
			<lb />
			O R D E R
			<lb />
		</front>
		<body>
			Mr.Father Xavier, learned senior Advocate instructed by counsel
			<lb />
			on record for writ petitioner is before this Virtual Court.
			<lb />
			2. Short point (shorn of elaboration) that falls for consideration in
			<lb />
			this matter is whether salary payable to nuns, would attract &apos;Tax
			<lb />
			Deduction at Source&apos; [&apos;TDS&apos;] qua &apos;The Income-tax Act, 1961 (43 of
			<lb />
			1961)&apos; [hereinafter &apos;IT Act&apos; for the sake of brevity] i.e., in other words
			<lb />
			whether TDS deduction qua salary payable to nuns is imperative.
			<lb />
			3. Department took the stand that income which are adumbrated in
			<lb />
			Section 10 of the IT Act alone can be exempt. To be noted, this was
			<lb />
			followed by a circular in this regard.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			3/14
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			W.P.No.21815 of 2021
			<lb />
			and W.M.P.Nos.23004 &amp; 23005 of 2021
			<lb />
		</note>
		<body>
			4. The above matter came up for consideration before a Hon&apos;ble
			<lb />
			Single Judge of this Court in a batch of matters being W.P.Nos.37565 to
			<lb />
			37567 of 2015 and Hon&apos;ble Single Judge in and by a elaborate order
			<lb />
			dated 22.12.2016 held in favour of the Assessee. To be noted, Hon&apos;ble
			<lb />
			Single Judge inter alia held that as long as institution certifies names of
			<lb />
			staff members who are members of religious body, they would be
			<lb />
			exempt. This matter was carried in appeal by way of an intra Court
			<lb />
			appeal and a Hon&apos;ble Division Bench, in and by common order dated
			<lb />
			20.03.2019 in Writ Appeal No.391 to 402 of 2019 (reported in 2019 4
			<lb />
			MLJ 129), reversed the order of Hon&apos;ble Single Judge and held in favour
			<lb />
			of Revenue. The Assessees carried the matter to Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court
			<lb />
			and this Court is informed that in the batch of petitions, the lead matter is
			<lb />
			SLP(C) No.10456 of 2019. This batch of petitions are pending in
			<lb />
			Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court and the order made by Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court
			<lb />
			on 02.07.2019 reads as follows:
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			4/14
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			W.P.No.21815 of 2021
			<lb />
			and W.M.P.Nos.23004 &amp; 23005 of 2021
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			5/14
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			W.P.No.21815 of 2021
			<lb />
			and W.M.P.Nos.23004 &amp; 23005 of 2021
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			6/14
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			W.P.No.21815 of 2021
			<lb />
			and W.M.P.Nos.23004 &amp; 23005 of 2021
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			7/14
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			W.P.No.21815 of 2021
			<lb />
			and W.M.P.Nos.23004 &amp; 23005 of 2021
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			8/14
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			W.P.No.21815 of 2021
			<lb />
			and W.M.P.Nos.23004 &amp; 23005 of 2021
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			9/14
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			W.P.No.21815 of 2021
			<lb />
			and W.M.P.Nos.23004 &amp; 23005 of 2021
			<lb />
		</note>
		<body>
			5. When things stand as above i.e., in the aforesaid obtaining
			<lb />
			factual backdrop, impugned communication dated 07.10.2015 bearing
			<lb />
			reference C.No.Misc.PRO/2015-16 followed by Circular dated
			<lb />
			26.10.2015 bearing reference R.C.No.23545/2014/E1 has been assailed
			<lb />
			in captioned matter as petitioner (4 staff to be precise) could not join the
			<lb />
			earlier aforementioned trajectory qua legal proceedings and that has
			<lb />
			necessitated the filing of captioned writ petition is learned senior
			<lb />
			counsel&apos;s say.
			<lb />
			6. Ms.Hema Muralikrishnan, learned senior standing counsel
			<lb />
			accepts notice on behalf of the respondents 1 to 3, Mr.Karthik
			<lb />
			Ranganathan, learned senior standing counsel for Income Tax
			<lb />
			Department accepts notice on behalf of fourth respondent and
			<lb />
			Mr.NRR.Arun Natarajan, learned Government Advocate, (represented by
			<lb />
			Ms.Amirta Dinakaran, learned State counsel) accepts notice on behalf of
			<lb />
			respondents 5 to 8.
			<lb />
			7. From the narrative thus far, it becomes clear that the Hon&apos;ble
			<lb />
			Supreme Court is in seizin of the question as to whether salaries payable
			<lb />
			to nuns would attract TDS qua IT Act. It is also clear that Hon&apos;ble
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			10/14
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			W.P.No.21815 of 2021
			<lb />
			and W.M.P.Nos.23004 &amp; 23005 of 2021
			<lb />
		</note>
		<body>
			Supreme Court has made an interim order of status quo with regard to
			<lb />
			payment of tax. Tobe noted, this Court is informed (without any
			<lb />
			disputation or disagreement) that the aforementioned interim order made
			<lb />
			by Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court is now operating and Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court
			<lb />
			is in seizin of the main issue.
			<lb />
			8. In the light of the narrow compass with the consent of all the
			<lb />
			aforementioned learned senior counsel and State counsel, the captioned
			<lb />
			main writ petition was taken up. There is no disputation or disagreement
			<lb />
			before this Court that aforementioned SLP i.e., lead SLP and all the
			<lb />
			connected SLPs are pending in the Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court and Hon&apos;ble
			<lb />
			Supreme Court is in the seizen of these matters. Likewise, there is no
			<lb />
			disputation or disagreement that aforementioned interim order made by
			<lb />
			Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court on 02.07.2019 is still operating. This takes us to
			<lb />
			a scenario wherein the parties i.e., assessee as well as Revenue/State
			<lb />
			should await outcome or await verdict of Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court on this
			<lb />
			issue. There is no disputation or disagreement that the parties have to
			<lb />
			await outcome i.e., verdict of Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			11/14
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			W.P.No.21815 of 2021
			<lb />
			and W.M.P.Nos.23004 &amp; 23005 of 2021
			<lb />
		</note>
		<body>
			9. Therefore, captioned writ petition is disposed of holding that the
			<lb />
			impugned communication dated 07.10.2015 bearing reference
			<lb />
			No.Rc.No.23545/2014/E1 and circular dated 26.10.2015 issued by fifth
			<lb />
			respondent will be kept in abeyance and there will be an interim order on
			<lb />
			the same lines as made by Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court i.e., order of status
			<lb />
			quo with regard to payment of tax as of today.
			<lb />
			10. Though obvious, whether the impugned communication and
			<lb />
			circular get resuscitated or concluded by being set aside will depend on
			<lb />
			the verdict that Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court returns.
			<lb />
			11. Though obvious, it is made clear that this Court has not
			<lb />
			expressed any opinion or view on the merits of the matter and the
			<lb />
			captioned writ petition is disposed of solely on the basis that Hon&apos;ble
			<lb />
			Supreme Court is in seizin of the matter, interim order made by Hon&apos;ble
			<lb />
			Supreme Court is operating and the parties should await the verdict of
			<lb />
			Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court. There are four staff members who could not
			<lb />
			join the proceedings which are now pending in the Hon&apos;ble Supreme
			<lb />
			Court that has led to the present scenario as already alluded to supra in
			<lb />
			this order.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			12/14
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			W.P.No.21815 of 2021
			<lb />
			and W.M.P.Nos.23004 &amp; 23005 of 2021
			<lb />
		</note>
		<body>
			12. Captioned writ petition disposed of in the aforesaid manner
			<lb />
			with the aforesaid directives. Though obvious, it is made clear that this
			<lb />
			arrangement (status quo with regard to payment of tax) and
			<lb />
			notice/circular being kept in abeyance will operate till the disposal of
			<lb />
			matter by Hon&apos;ble Supreme Court. Consequently, connected
			<lb />
			WMP.Nos.23004 &amp; 23005 of 2021 are also disposed of as closed. There
			<lb />
			shall be no order as to costs.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			21.10.2021
			<lb />
			(1/2)
			<lb />
			Speaking/Non-speaking order
			<lb />
			Index: Yes/No
			<lb />
			kmi/nsa
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			13/14
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			W.P.No.21815 of 2021
			<lb />
			and W.M.P.Nos.23004 &amp; 23005 of 2021
			<lb />
		</note>
		<front>
			M.SUNDAR.J.,
			<lb />
			kmi/nsa
			<lb />
			To
			<lb />
			1. The Secretary,
			<lb />
			Union of India,
			<lb />
			Ministry of Finance,
			<lb />
			North Block, New Delhi-110 001.
			<lb />
			2. The Secretary,
			<lb />
			Central Board of Direct Taxes,
			<lb />
			Ministry of Finance,
			<lb />
			North Block, New Delhi-110 001.
			<lb />
			3. Principal Chief Commissioner of Income Tax (Chennai),
			<lb />
			121, M.G.Road,
			<lb />
			Nungambakkam, Chennai-600 034.
			<lb />
			4. The Commissioner of Income Tax (TDS),
			<lb />
			7 th Floor, New Block,
			<lb />
			W.P.No.21815 of 2021 &amp;
			<lb />
			Aayakar Bhawan,
			<lb />
			W.M.P.Nos.23004 &amp; 23005 of 2021
			<lb />
			121, M.G.Road, Chennai-600 034.
			<lb />
			5. Director of Treasuries and Accounts,
			<lb />
			Office of the Treasuries and Accounts,
			<lb />
			Panagal Building,
			<lb />
			No.1 Jeenis Road,
			<lb />
			Saidapet, Chennai-600 015.
			<lb />
			6. The Commissioner of School Education,
			<lb />
			DPI Campus, Directorate of School Education,
			<lb />
			College Road, Chennai-600 006.
			<lb />
			7. The Director of Elementary Education,
			<lb />
			DPI Campus, College Road,
			<lb />
			Chennai-600 006.
			<lb />
			8. The Director of Teacher Education Research and Training,
			<lb />
			DPI Campus, College Road,
			<lb />
			Chennai-600 006.
			<lb />
		</front>
		<note place="footnote">
			20.10.2021
			<lb />
			(1/2)
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			14/14
			<lb />
		</page>
	</text>
</tei>
