<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			IN THE HIGH COURT OF DELHI AT NEW DELHI
			<lb />
			Date of decision: 21st MARCH, 2022
			<lb />
			IN THE MATTER OF:
			<lb />
			+ BAIL APPLN. 1724/2021
			<lb />
			ANIL KUMAR @ NILLU ..... Petitioner
			<lb />
			Through: Mr. Rajinder Singh and Mr. Piyush
			<lb />
			Gupta, Ms. Himanshi Batheja,
			<lb />
			Advocates.
			<lb />
			versus
			<lb />
			STATE ..... Respondent
			<lb />
			Through: Mr. Amit Chadha, APP for the State
			<lb />
			with SI Thakur Singh, PS Special Cell
			<lb />
			CORAM:
			<lb />
			HONBLE MR. JUSTICE SUBRAMONIUM PRASAD
			<lb />
			SUBRAMONIUM PRASAD, J.
			<lb />
		</front>
		<body>
			1.
			<lb />
			This petition has been filed under Section 439 Cr.P.C. seeking interim
			<lb />
			bail in FIR No. 14/2014 dated 26.03.2014 registered at P.S. Special Cell
			<lb />
			under Sections 468/471/201 of the Indian Penal Code, 1860 (hereinafter,
			<lb />
			&quot;IPC&quot;) and Sections 20/29 of the Narcotic Drugs and Psychotropic
			<lb />
			Substances Act, 1985 (hereinafter, &quot;NDPS Act&quot;).
			<lb />
			2.
			<lb />
			The facts, in brief, leading up to the filing of the instant petition are as
			<lb />
			follows:
			<lb />
			a) It is stated that information was received in February 2014 that
			<lb />
			one Danveer @ Dannu was involved in an illegal interstate
			<lb />
			supply of drugs to foreigners in various states in India for the
			<lb />
			purpose of rave parties. Accordingly, a team to conduct a raid
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			Digitally Signed By:HARIOM
			<lb />
			SINGH KIRMOLIYA
			<lb />
			Signing Date:22.03.2022
			<lb />
			10:32:39
			<lb />
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
		</note>
		<note place="footnote">
			BAIL APPLN. 1724/2021
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 1 of 13
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			into the same was deployed and secret information was received
			<lb />
			that Danveer @ Dannu would come to Karol Bagh in an Alto
			<lb />
			car to deliver at 11 A.M. a consignment of charas/hashish to a
			<lb />
			Russian associate at Gurudwara Road, behind Jassa Ram
			<lb />
			Hospital, Karol Bagh.
			<lb />
			b) On the basis of the aforementioned information, a police team
			<lb />
			arrived at 8 A.M. at Karol Bagh Metro Station, Pusa Road,
			<lb />
			Delhi. Around 11:15 A.M., one white Alto car arrived, with two
			<lb />
			occupants in the front seats, and after five minutes, a foreigner
			<lb />
			emerged from the Intercity Hotel and walked towards the car. It
			<lb />
			is stated that during the exchange that took place between the
			<lb />
			foreigner and the two occupants of the car, a small yellow/black
			<lb />
			colour canvas bag was handed over to the foreigner.
			<lb />
			c) Around 11:30 A.M., as per instructions, the police team
			<lb />
			surrounded the car and asked the persons about their identity.
			<lb />
			The foreigner revealed his identity as Georgii Dedov, the driver
			<lb />
			of the car was Anil Kumar @ Nillu (the Petitioner herein), and
			<lb />
			the other occupant of the car was Anil Kumar @ Lucky.
			<lb />
			d) A cursory interrogation of the canvas bag which had been
			<lb />
			recovered revealed that the same contained ten small polythene
			<lb />
			pouches containing a black/brown coloured clay type
			<lb />
			material/substance in small pieces, wrapped with transparent
			<lb />
			cling foils and giving off a pungent smell resembling that of
			<lb />
			cannabis. The apprehended persons revealed the same to be
			<lb />
			charas/hashish, and the total weight of the substances was found
			<lb />
			to be 2.210 kgs.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			Digitally Signed By:HARIOM
			<lb />
			SINGH KIRMOLIYA
			<lb />
			Signing Date:22.03.2022
			<lb />
			10:32:39
			<lb />
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
		</note>
		<note place="footnote">
			BAIL APPLN. 1724/2021
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 2 of 13
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			e) The Petitioner was arrested on 27.03.2014. The first bail
			<lb />
			application moved by the Petitioner before the Ld. Trial Court
			<lb />
			was dismissed on 06.05.2016 and the second bail application
			<lb />
			was dismissed by the Ld. Trial Court on 02.02.2017. The first
			<lb />
			bail application was dismissed as withdrawn by this Court on
			<lb />
			21.08.2017, with the third bail application being dismissed by
			<lb />
			the Ld. Trial Court on 06.07.2021.
			<lb />
			f) The Petitioner has now approached this Court by way of the
			<lb />
			instant petition for interim bail.
			<lb />
			g) It is pertinent to note at this juncture that vide Order dated
			<lb />
			19.01.2022, this Court, considering the facts and circumstances
			<lb />
			of the instant case, exercised its powers under Section 482
			<lb />
			Cr.P.C. to covert the instant interim bail application into one for
			<lb />
			regular bail.
			<lb />
			3.
			<lb />
			Mr. Rajinder Singh, learned Counsel for the Petitioner, submits that
			<lb />
			the Petitioner has been falsely implicated and his job was only to drive the
			<lb />
			occupants of his vehicle from one place to another. He states that the
			<lb />
			Petitioner is the sole bread earner in his family and that his being in judicial
			<lb />
			custody for 7 years and 10 months has exacerbated the poor financial
			<lb />
			condition of his family, especially with the COVID-19 pandemic taking
			<lb />
			place.
			<lb />
			4.
			<lb />
			The learned Counsel for the Petitioner places reliance upon Supreme
			<lb />
			Court Legal Aid Committee (Representing Undertrial Prisoners) v. Union of
			<lb />
			India, (1994) 6 SCC 731, to submit that the Supreme Court had rendered
			<lb />
			directions for the release of those undertrial prisoners who had been in jail
			<lb />
			for over five years for offences that entailed a punishment of minimum
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			Digitally Signed By:HARIOM
			<lb />
			SINGH KIRMOLIYA
			<lb />
			Signing Date:22.03.2022
			<lb />
			10:32:39
			<lb />
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
		</note>
		<note place="footnote">
			BAIL APPLN. 1724/2021
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 3 of 13
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			imprisonment of ten years and a minimum fine of rupees one lakh. Citing
			<lb />
			this judgement, Mr. Singh submits that the Petitioner herein has been in
			<lb />
			custody for almost eight years now and is, therefore, entitled to release.
			<lb />
			5.
			<lb />
			Mr. Singh further submits that the Calcutta High Court had dealt with
			<lb />
			a similar issue In Re; Sanawar Ali, (MANU/WB/0750/2020) decided on
			<lb />
			27.11.2020 wherein it had considered as to whether the restrictions imposed
			<lb />
			by Section 37 of the NDPS Act were overridden by the operation of the
			<lb />
			Supreme Court Legal Aid Services Committee v. Union of India (supra) in
			<lb />
			the matter of grant of bail to undertrials in NDPS cases. It was held therein
			<lb />
			that inordinate delay in trial infracted the fundamental rights of the Petitioner
			<lb />
			therein and the directives under the aforementioned judgement would apply
			<lb />
			in full force.
			<lb />
			6.
			<lb />
			Mr. Amit Chadha, the learned APP for the State, vehemently opposes
			<lb />
			the bail application filed by the Petitioner and states that co-accused Danveer
			<lb />
			Singh @ Dannu had been granted interim bail on the pretext of his wife&apos;s
			<lb />
			surgery and had ended up absconding. He states that there is strong
			<lb />
			apprehension that the Petitioner herein is also likely to abscond if granted
			<lb />
			bail and pressure prosecution witnesses, and that the instant case involves
			<lb />
			recovery of substances of a commercial quantity. He submits that the case is
			<lb />
			currently pending trial before the Special Court, NDPS Act, Patiala House
			<lb />
			Courts, New Delhi.
			<lb />
			7.
			<lb />
			The learned APP further submits that the Supreme Court decision in
			<lb />
			Supreme Court Legal Aid Committee (Representing Undertrial Prisoners) v.
			<lb />
			Union of India (supra) was only a one-time measure and that there is no
			<lb />
			mandate that in all cases, an undertial who has been in custody for more than
			<lb />
			five years for a punishment that entails minimum imprisonment of ten years
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			Digitally Signed By:HARIOM
			<lb />
			SINGH KIRMOLIYA
			<lb />
			Signing Date:22.03.2022
			<lb />
			10:32:39
			<lb />
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
		</note>
		<note place="footnote">
			BAIL APPLN. 1724/2021
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 4 of 13
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			must be automatically granted bail. He refers to a judgement of this Bench
			<lb />
			dated 21.12.2021 in Atul Agarwal v. Directorate of Revenue Intelligence,
			<lb />
			(BAIL APPLN. 2477/2021) and states that the aforementioned Supreme
			<lb />
			Court judgement has been incorrectly interpreted and that the matter must be
			<lb />
			referred to a larger Bench for final adjudication of the issue that arises.
			<lb />
			8.
			<lb />
			Heard Mr. Rajinder Singh, learned Counsel for the Petitioner, Mr.
			<lb />
			Amit Chadha, learned APP for the State, and perused the material on record.
			<lb />
			9.
			<lb />
			At the outset, it would be pertinent to refer to Supreme Court Legal
			<lb />
			Aid Committee (Representing Undertrial Prisoners) v. Union of India
			<lb />
			(supra). The petition therein had been instituted with the aim to ensure that
			<lb />
			undertrial prisoners who had been languishing in jail for an extended period
			<lb />
			of time were granted bail despite the stringency of the provisions for bail
			<lb />
			under the NDPS Act. The underlying reason for the same was to uphold the
			<lb />
			right to personal liberty and the right to speedy trial of an undertrial under
			<lb />
			Article 21 of the Constitution of India.
			<lb />
			10. Accordingly, in the aforementioned judgement, the Supreme Court
			<lb />
			passed certain directions, subject to general conditions, wherein it
			<lb />
			categorically noted that where an undertrial accused has been charged with
			<lb />
			offence(s) under the NDPS Act which is punishable with minimum
			<lb />
			imprisonment of ten years and a minimum fine of rupees one lakh, then such
			<lb />
			an undertrial is to be released if he has been in jail for not less than five
			<lb />
			years. The entirety of the directions have been reproduced as under:
			<lb />
			&quot;(i) Where the undertrial is accused of an offence(s)
			<lb />
			under the Act prescribing a punishment of
			<lb />
			imprisonment of five years or less and fine, such an
			<lb />
			undertrial shall be released on bail if he has been in
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			Digitally Signed By:HARIOM
			<lb />
			SINGH KIRMOLIYA
			<lb />
			Signing Date:22.03.2022
			<lb />
			10:32:39
			<lb />
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
		</note>
		<note place="footnote">
			BAIL APPLN. 1724/2021
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 5 of 13
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			jail for a period which is not less than half the
			<lb />
			punishment provided for the offence with which he is
			<lb />
			charged and where he is charged with more than one
			<lb />
			offence, the offence providing the highest punishment.
			<lb />
			If the offence with which he is charged prescribes the
			<lb />
			maximum fine, the bail amount shall be 50% of the
			<lb />
			said amount with two sureties for like amount. If the
			<lb />
			maximum fine is not prescribed bail shall be to the
			<lb />
			satisfaction of the concerned Special Judge with two
			<lb />
			sureties for like amount.
			<lb />
			(ii) Where the undertrial accused is charged with an
			<lb />
			offence(s) under the Act providing for punishment
			<lb />
			exceeding five years and fine, such an undertrial shall
			<lb />
			be released on bail on the term set out in (i) above
			<lb />
			provided that his bail amount shall in no case be less
			<lb />
			than Rs. 50,000 with two sureties for like amount.
			<lb />
			(iii) Where the undertrial accused is charged with an
			<lb />
			offence(s) under the Act punishable with minimum
			<lb />
			imprisonment of ten years and a minimum fine of
			<lb />
			Rupees one lakh, such an undertrial shall be released
			<lb />
			on bail if he has been in jail for not less than five
			<lb />
			years provided he furnishes bail in the sum of Rupees
			<lb />
			one lakh with two sureties for like amount.&quot;
			<lb />
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
			11. It is the contention of the learned Counsel for the Petitioner that as the
			<lb />
			Petitioner herein has been accused of offences punishable under Sections
			<lb />
			20/29 of the NDPS Act and has been in custody for almost eight years till
			<lb />
			date, he is squarely covered by the aforementioned judgement and is entitled
			<lb />
			to be released. This has been opposed by the learned APP who relies upon
			<lb />
			paragraph 16 of the judgement to state that the directions were intended to
			<lb />
			operate as a one-time measure for the case therein and were not intended to
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			Digitally Signed By:HARIOM
			<lb />
			SINGH KIRMOLIYA
			<lb />
			Signing Date:22.03.2022
			<lb />
			10:32:39
			<lb />
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
		</note>
		<note place="footnote">
			APPLN. 1724/2021
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 6 of 13
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			apply to all subsequent cases of a like nature. For ease of comprehension, the
			<lb />
			said paragraph is as under:
			<lb />
			&quot;16. We may state that the above are intended to
			<lb />
			operate as one-time directions for cases in which the
			<lb />
			accused persons are in jail and their trials are delayed.
			<lb />
			They are not intended to interfere with the Special
			<lb />
			Court&apos;s power to grant bail under Section 37 of the
			<lb />
			Act. The Special Court will be free to exercise that
			<lb />
			power keeping in view the complaint of inordinate
			<lb />
			delay in the disposal of the pending cases. The Special
			<lb />
			Court will, notwithstanding the directions, be free to
			<lb />
			cancel bail if the accused is found to be misusing it and
			<lb />
			grounds for cancellation of bail exist. Lastly, we grant
			<lb />
			liberty to apply in case of any difficulty in the
			<lb />
			implementation of this order.&quot;
			<lb />
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
			12. A bare perusal of paragraph 16 indicates to this Court that the
			<lb />
			directions were not meant to be employed as one-time directions in the said
			<lb />
			case, but were meant to apply as a one-time measure in all cases in which the
			<lb />
			accused persons were in jail and their trials had been delayed. The intention
			<lb />
			of paragraph 16 was to convey that despite the absence or presence of delay
			<lb />
			in trial in a case, the Special Court was still free to exercise its power to
			<lb />
			grant bail under Section 37 of the NDPS Act. Furthermore, if the Special
			<lb />
			Court also retained the power to cancel bail if the accused was found to be
			<lb />
			misusing the same. The directions were certainly not, as the learned APP has
			<lb />
			submitted, meant to only apply in the case therein, but were directions that
			<lb />
			were to be followed by Courts in all cases pertaining to NDPS wherein the
			<lb />
			accused had been subjected to prolonged delay in their trials.
			<lb />
			13. It is unconscionable to state that the rights guaranteed under Article 21
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			Digitally Signed By:HARIOM
			<lb />
			SINGH KIRMOLIYA
			<lb />
			Signing Date:22.03.2022
			<lb />
			10:32:39
			<lb />
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
		</note>
		<note place="footnote">
			BAIL APPLN. 1724/2021
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 7 of 13
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			can be subjected to such arbitrary categorisation and would not apply across
			<lb />
			the board to all undertrials in NDPS cases who are at the receiving end of
			<lb />
			inordinate delay in trial. In Re: Sanawar Ali (supra), the Calcutta High Court
			<lb />
			had comprehensively considered the issue as to whether the directives in
			<lb />
			Supreme Court Legal Aid Committee (Representing Undertrial Prisoners)
			<lb />
			(supra) were only intended to operate as a &quot;one-time measure&quot; and had
			<lb />
			observed that the directives had been subsequently extended to other states
			<lb />
			vide Order dated 17.04.1995 in (1995) 4 SCC 695. The relevant portion of
			<lb />
			the Calcutta High Court judgement is as follows:
			<lb />
			&quot;10. It is argued that such directions were intended to
			<lb />
			operate as an &apos;one time measure&apos; in the State of
			<lb />
			Maharashtra. We, however, note that the directives
			<lb />
			were subsequently extended to the State of West Bengal
			<lb />
			and other States vide order dated 17th April, 1995
			<lb />
			reported in 1995 (4) SCC 695. We are of the view that
			<lb />
			the aforesaid directives of the Apex Court in the matter
			<lb />
			of grant of bail due to inordinate delay are required to
			<lb />
			be taken into consideration and similar relief is to be
			<lb />
			extended to all undertrials who stand on the same
			<lb />
			footing. Liberty is an inalienable right of every
			<lb />
			individual guaranteed by our Constitution and cannot
			<lb />
			be whittled down by arbitrary categorisation.
			<lb />
			&apos;Procedure established by law&apos; under Article 21 cannot
			<lb />
			be viewed in isolation from the principles of &apos;equal
			<lb />
			justice&apos; or &apos;equality before law&apos; enshrined under Article
			<lb />
			14. To achieve such universal equality it is imperative
			<lb />
			that the directives laid down by the Court in the said
			<lb />
			report be extended to all undertrials who are similarly
			<lb />
			circumstanced and are suffering protracted detention
			<lb />
			throughout the length and breadth of the country.
			<lb />
			Selective approach to personal liberty is an anathema
			<lb />
			to our constitutional scheme. Hence, it is the duty of
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			Digitally Signed By:HARIOM
			<lb />
			SINGH KIRMOLIYA
			<lb />
			Signing Date:22.03.2022
			<lb />
			10:32:39
			<lb />
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
		</note>
		<note place="footnote">
			APPLN. 1724/2021
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 8 of 13
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			every Court including the High Courts when faced with
			<lb />
			the question of &quot;bail or jail&quot; to bear in mind the
			<lb />
			beholden principles of parity and equal access to
			<lb />
			justice. Courts need to rise above petty technicalities
			<lb />
			to preserve and restore liberty to all similarly
			<lb />
			circumstanced persons. Failure to do so, would create
			<lb />
			privileged oases of liberty accessible to few and denial
			<lb />
			or freedom to most.&quot;
			<lb />
			14. In view of the above, this Court believes that achievement of universal
			<lb />
			equality before the law requires the tenets of personal liberty to be applicable
			<lb />
			to all similarly circumstanced individuals and must not be restricted unless
			<lb />
			according to procedure established by law. This Court does not find any
			<lb />
			weight in the submission of the learned APP that the aforementioned
			<lb />
			judgment of the Supreme Court does not apply to the instant case and that
			<lb />
			the judgement of this Court in Atul Agarwal v. Directorate of Revenue
			<lb />
			Intelligence (supra) must be referred to a larger Bench due to the incorrect
			<lb />
			application of the Supreme Court&apos;s judgement. Furthermore, in Atul
			<lb />
			Agarwal v. Directorate of Revenue Intelligence (supra), this Court had not
			<lb />
			solely granted bail on the footing of the inordinate delay in trial, but had also
			<lb />
			considered the twin requirements stipulated under Section 37 of the NDPS
			<lb />
			Act. Therefore, this Court is of the opinion that the Petitioner herein is
			<lb />
			squarely covered by judgement of the Supreme Court and is entitled to
			<lb />
			release on account of inordinate delay in trial and prolonged judicial
			<lb />
			custody.
			<lb />
			15. This Court also finds it necessary to state that the right to speedy trial
			<lb />
			is an intrinsic part of Article 21 of the Constitution of India. The Supreme
			<lb />
			Court has time and again delineated its importance as a constitutional right
			<lb />
			in various judgements, starting from Hussainara Khatoon and Ors. v. Home
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			Digitally Signed By:HARIOM
			<lb />
			SINGH KIRMOLIYA
			<lb />
			Signing Date:22.03.2022
			<lb />
			10:32:39
			<lb />
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
		</note>
		<note place="footnote">
			BAIL APPLN. 1724/2021
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 9 of 13
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			Secretary, State of Bihar, (1980) 1 SCC 81, to A.R. Antulay and Ors. v. R.S.
			<lb />
			Nayak and Anr., (1992) 1 SCC 225. In the latter judgement, the Supreme
			<lb />
			Court had laid down guidelines with regard to the right to speedy trial of an
			<lb />
			accused and had observed as follows:
			<lb />
			&quot;81. Article 21 declares that no person shall be
			<lb />
			deprived of his life or liberty except in accordance
			<lb />
			with procedure prescribed by law. The main
			<lb />
			procedural law in this country is the Code of
			<lb />
			Criminal Procedure, 1973. Several other enactments
			<lb />
			too contain many a procedural provision. After
			<lb />
			Maneka Gandhi [Maneka Gandhi v. Union of India,
			<lb />
			(1978) 1 SCC 248 : AIR 1978 SC 597] , it can hardly
			<lb />
			be disputed that the &apos;law&apos; [which has to be understood
			<lb />
			in the sense the expression has been defined in clause
			<lb />
			(3)(a) of Article 13 of the Constitution] in Article 21
			<lb />
			has to answer the test of reasonableness and fairness
			<lb />
			inherent in Articles 19 and 14. In other words, such
			<lb />
			law should provide a procedure which is fair,
			<lb />
			reasonable and just. Then alone, would it be in
			<lb />
			consonance with the command of Article 21. Indeed,
			<lb />
			wherever necessary, such fairness must be read into
			<lb />
			such law. Now, can it be said that a law which does
			<lb />
			not provide for a reasonably prompt investigation,
			<lb />
			trial and conclusion of a criminal case is fair, just
			<lb />
			and reasonable? It is both in the interest of the
			<lb />
			accused as well as the society that a criminal case is
			<lb />
			concluded soon. If the accused is guilty, he ought to
			<lb />
			be declared so. Social interest lies in punishing the
			<lb />
			guilty and exoneration of the innocent but this
			<lb />
			determination (of guilt or innocence) must be arrived
			<lb />
			at with reasonable despatch -reasonable in all the
			<lb />
			circumstances of the case. Since it is the accused who
			<lb />
			is charged with the offence and is also the person
			<lb />
			whose life and/or liberty is at peril, it is but fair to say
			<lb />
			that he has a right to be tried speedily.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			Digitally Signed By:HARIOM
			<lb />
			SINGH KIRMOLIYA
			<lb />
			Signing Date:22.03.2022
			<lb />
			10:32:39
			<lb />
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
		</note>
		<note place="footnote">
			APPLN. 1724/2021
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 10 of 13
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			Correspondingly, it is the obligation of the State to
			<lb />
			respect and ensure this right. It needs no emphasis to
			<lb />
			say, the very fact of being accused of a crime is cause
			<lb />
			for concern. It affects the reputation and the standing
			<lb />
			of the person among his colleagues and in the society.
			<lb />
			It is a cause for worry and expense. It is more so, if
			<lb />
			he is arrested. If it is a serious offence, the man may
			<lb />
			stand to lose his life, liberty, career and all that he
			<lb />
			cherishes.&quot;
			<lb />
			(emphasis supplied)
			<lb />
			16. Therefore, fair, just and reasonable procedure is implicit in Article 21
			<lb />
			and it creates a right in the accused to be tried speedily. This Court has
			<lb />
			consistently observed that while Courts must remain cognizant of the
			<lb />
			deleterious impact of drugs on society, it is also important to keep in mind
			<lb />
			that deprivation of personal liberty without the assurance of speedy trial
			<lb />
			contravenes the principles enshrined in our Constitution. In the instant case,
			<lb />
			the Petitioner has been incarcerated for almost eight years now, i.e. since
			<lb />
			27.03.2014, for an offence that is punishable with a minimum imprisonment
			<lb />
			of ten years. This is an egregious violation of an accused&apos;s right to personal
			<lb />
			liberty and right to speedy trial as, in the off-chance that the Petitioner is
			<lb />
			acquitted, it would entail an irretrievable loss of eight years of his life that
			<lb />
			cannot be compensated. Whether or not the Petitioner played an active role
			<lb />
			in the commission of the offence of drug trafficking and supply is a matter of
			<lb />
			trial and cannot justify the prolonged incarceration of the Petitioner.
			<lb />
			17. In light of the above, applying the law that has been laid down by the
			<lb />
			Supreme Court in Supreme Court Legal Aid Committee (Representing
			<lb />
			Undertrial Prisoners) v. Union of India (supra) and flowing from Section 37
			<lb />
			of the NDPS Act which governs the powers pertaining to grant of bail, this
			<lb />
			Court is of the opinion that the instant case is fit for grant of bail. This Court
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			Digitally Signed By:HARIOM
			<lb />
			SINGH KIRMOLIYA
			<lb />
			Signing Date:22.03.2022
			<lb />
			10:32:39
			<lb />
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
		</note>
		<note place="footnote">
			BAIL APPLN. 1724/2021
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 11 of 13
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			is, therefore, inclined to grant bail to the Petitioner herein, subject to the
			<lb />
			following conditions:
			<lb />
			a)
			<lb />
			The Petitioner shall furnish a personal bond in the sum of
			<lb />
			Rs.1,00,000/-with two sureties of the like amount, one of them
			<lb />
			should be the relative of the Petitioner, to the satisfaction of the
			<lb />
			Trial Court;
			<lb />
			b)
			<lb />
			The Petitioner is directed to deposit his passport with the Trial
			<lb />
			Court.
			<lb />
			c)
			<lb />
			The Petitioner is directed to reside in Delhi till further orders
			<lb />
			and the address shall be verified by the learned Trial Court at
			<lb />
			the time of acceptance of bail bonds.
			<lb />
			d)
			<lb />
			The Petitioner shall report to the concerned Police Station twice
			<lb />
			in a week, that is, on every Wednesday and Friday at 10:30 AM,
			<lb />
			and the Police is directed to release him by 11:00 AM after
			<lb />
			recording his presence and completion of all the necessary
			<lb />
			formalities;
			<lb />
			e)
			<lb />
			The Petitioner shall not leave NCT of Delhi without the prior
			<lb />
			permission of the trial Court;
			<lb />
			f)
			<lb />
			The Petitioner is directed to give all his mobile numbers to the
			<lb />
			Investigating Officer and keep them operational at all times;
			<lb />
			g)
			<lb />
			The petitioner shall not, directly or indirectly, tamper with
			<lb />
			evidence or try to influence the witnesses in any manner;
			<lb />
			h)
			<lb />
			In case it is established that the petitioner has indulged in
			<lb />
			similar kind of offences or tried to tamper with the evidence, the
			<lb />
			bail granted to the petitioner shall stand cancelled forthwith.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			Digitally Signed By:HARIOM
			<lb />
			SINGH KIRMOLIYA
			<lb />
			Signing Date:22.03.2022
			<lb />
			10:32:39
			<lb />
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
		</note>
		<note place="footnote">
			BAIL APPLN. 1724/2021
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 12 of 13
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			18.
			<lb />
			Be it noted that the observations made in this order are only for grant
			<lb />
			of bail and not on the merits of the case.
			<lb />
			19.
			<lb />
			The application stands disposed of along with all the pending
			<lb />
			application(s), if any.
			<lb />
			20. Let a copy of this order be communicated to the concerned Jail
			<lb />
			Superintendent.
			<lb />
			SUBRAMONIUM PRASAD, J.
			<lb />
			MARCH 21, 2022
			<lb />
			Rahul
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			Digitally Signed By:HARIOM
			<lb />
			SINGH KIRMOLIYA
			<lb />
			Signing Date:22.03.2022
			<lb />
			10:32:39
			<lb />
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
		</note>
		<note place="footnote">
			BAIL APPLN. 1724/2021
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 13 of 13
			<lb />
		</page>
	</text>
</tei>
