<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			IN THE HIGH COURT OF DELHI AT NEW DELHI
			<lb />
			%
			<lb />
			Judgment delivered on: 08.12.2021
			<lb />
			+
			<lb />
			O.M.P. (COMM) 139/2021
			<lb />
			M/S TATA PROJECTS LTD.
			<lb />
			..... Petitioner
			<lb />
			Versus
			<lb />
			M/S NTPC LIMITED
			<lb />
			..... Respondent
			<lb />
			Advocates who appeared in this case:
			<lb />
			For the Petitioner
			<lb />
			: Mr Sameer Parekh, Ms Smita Bhargava and
			<lb />
			Mr Tanuj Agarwal, Advocates.
			<lb />
			For the Respondent
			<lb />
			: Mr Chetan Sharma, ASGI with Mr Adarsh
			<lb />
			Tripathi, Mr Vikram S Baid, and Mr Ajitesh
			<lb />
			Garg, Advocates.
			<lb />
			AND
			<lb />
			+ O.M.P. (COMM) 171/2021 and IA Nos. 6288/2021 &amp; 6289/2021
			<lb />
			NTPC LTD .
			<lb />
			..... Petitioner
			<lb />
			Versus
			<lb />
			M/S TATA PROJECTS LTD.
			<lb />
			..... Respondent
			<lb />
			Advocates who appeared in this case:
			<lb />
			For the Petitioner
			<lb />
			: Mr Chetan Sharma, ASGI with Mr Adarsh
			<lb />
			Tripathi, Mr Vikram S Baid, and Mr Ajitesh
			<lb />
			Garg, Advocates.
			<lb />
			For the Respondent
			<lb />
			: Mr Sameer Parekh, Ms Smita Bhargava
			<lb />
			and Mr Tanuj Agarwal, Advocates.
			<lb />
			CORAM
			<lb />
			HON&apos;BLE MR JUSTICE VIBHU BAKHRU
			<lb />
		</front>
		<note palce="footnote">
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
			Digitally Signed
			<lb />
			By:DUSHYANT
			<lb />
			RAWAL
			<lb />
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
		</note>
		<note place="footnote">
			OMP(COMM) Nos.139/2021 &amp; 171/2021
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 1 of 33
			<lb />
		</page>
		<front>
			JUDGMENT
			<lb />
			VIBHU BAKHRU, J
			<lb />
		</front>
		<body>
			1.
			<lb />
			The parties have filed these petitions under Section 34 of the
			<lb />
			Arbitration and Conciliation Act, 1996 (hereinafter the &apos;A&amp;C Act&apos;)
			<lb />
			impugning an Arbitral Award dated 01.12.2020 (hereinafter the
			<lb />
			&apos;impugned award&apos;) passed by the Arbitral Tribunal constituted of
			<lb />
			three members, Justice (Retd.) Badar Durrez Ahmed, Justice (Retd.)
			<lb />
			Mukul Mudgal and Justice (Retd.) Dr. Mukundakam Sharma as the
			<lb />
			Presiding Arbitrator (hereinafter &apos;the Arbitral Tribunal&apos;).
			<lb />
			2.
			<lb />
			The impugned award has been rendered in the context of disputes
			<lb />
			that have arisen between the parties in relation with the agreements
			<lb />
			dated 12.09.2014 for execution of certain works relating to the Lara
			<lb />
			Super Power Thermal Project.
			<lb />
			Factual Context
			<lb />
			3.
			<lb />
			On 05.06.2014, NTPC issued an Invitation for Bids (IFB) for the
			<lb />
			works regarding &quot;Coal Handling Plant Package for Lara Super Power
			<lb />
			Thermal Project, Stage 1 (2 x 800 MW)&quot; (hereinafter &apos;the Project&apos;), on
			<lb />
			the terms and conditions stipulated therein.
			<lb />
			4.
			<lb />
			Pursuant to the said IFB, Tata Projects Ltd. (hereinafter &apos;TPL&apos;)
			<lb />
			participated in the two stage bidding process. It submitted its bids for
			<lb />
			executing the Project works: Techno Commercial Bid dated 27.06.2014
			<lb />
			(Stage I) and Price Bid dated 13.08.2014 (Stage II). TPL also submitted
			<lb />
			a discount letter dated 14.08.2014. TPL&apos;s bid was accepted and
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note palce="footnote">
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
			Digitally Signed
			<lb />
			By:DUSHYANT
			<lb />
			RAWAL
			<lb />
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
		</note>
		<note place="footnote">
			OMP(COMM) Nos.139/2021 &amp; 171/2021
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 2 of 33
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			thereafter, NTPC issued three Notifications of Awards dated
			<lb />
			26.08.2014 (hereinafter &apos;NoA&apos;) in favour of TPL.
			<lb />
			5.
			<lb />
			The effective date of commencement of the contract was
			<lb />
			26.08.2014 and Unit No.1 was to be executed within a period of thirty
			<lb />
			months and Unit no.2 was to be executed within thirty-four months
			<lb />
			from the effective date of commencement of the contract.
			<lb />
			6.
			<lb />
			Thereafter, on 12.09.2014, three &apos;Contract Agreements&apos;
			<lb />
			(hereinafter collectively referred as the &apos;Agreements&apos;) were signed
			<lb />
			between the parties for a total consideration of EURO 5,10,000/-and
			<lb />
			₹321,95,59,742/-. The details of the three Agreements are tabulated
			<lb />
			below:
			<lb />
			Contract Agreement [CS-9548-
			<lb />
			155(R)-2-FC-COA-6200] for
			<lb />
			contract price of EUR
			<lb />
			5,10,000/-
			<lb />
			(hereinafter referred to as
			<lb />
			&apos;Foreign Supply Contract&apos;)
			<lb />
			Design,
			<lb />
			engineering,
			<lb />
			manufacture, procure, shop
			<lb />
			fabrication, testing, inspection
			<lb />
			at
			<lb />
			manufacturers
			<lb />
			works,
			<lb />
			packing, supply, forwarding
			<lb />
			and dispatch of offshore plant
			<lb />
			arid equipment on CIF (Indian
			<lb />
			Port-of-Entry) basis for the
			<lb />
			Coal Handling Plant Package
			<lb />
			for Lara Super Power Thermal
			<lb />
			Project, Stage 1 (2 x 800 MW).
			<lb />
			Contract Agreement [CS-9548-
			<lb />
			155(R)-2-FC-COA-6201] for
			<lb />
			Design,
			<lb />
			engineering,
			<lb />
			manufacture, procure, testing,
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note palce="footnote">
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
			Digitally Signed
			<lb />
			By:DUSHYANT
			<lb />
			RAWAL
			<lb />
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
		</note>
		<note place="footnote">
			OMP(COMM) Nos.139/2021 &amp; 171/2021
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 3 of 33
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			contract
			<lb />
			price
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			₹195,38,42,140/-(hereinafter
			<lb />
			referred to as &apos;Domestic
			<lb />
			Supply Contract&apos;)
			<lb />
			inspection at manufacturers
			<lb />
			works,
			<lb />
			packing,
			<lb />
			supply,
			<lb />
			forwarding and dispatch of
			<lb />
			plant and equipment on Ex-
			<lb />
			Works (India) supply basis for
			<lb />
			the Coal Handling Plant
			<lb />
			Package for Lara Super Power
			<lb />
			Thermal Project, Stage 1 (2 x
			<lb />
			800 MW)
			<lb />
			Contract Agreement [CS-9548-
			<lb />
			155(R)-2-FC-COA-6202] for a
			<lb />
			contract
			<lb />
			price
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			₹126,57,17,602/-(hereinafter
			<lb />
			referred to as &apos;Services
			<lb />
			Contract&apos;)
			<lb />
			In-land Transportation, Inland
			<lb />
			Insurance, Erection, Testing,
			<lb />
			Commissioning and conducting
			<lb />
			guarantee tests of the Coal
			<lb />
			Handling Plant Package for
			<lb />
			Lara Super Power Thermal
			<lb />
			Project, Stage 1 (2 x 800 MW)
			<lb />
			7.
			<lb />
			The works under the aforesaid three Agreements were awarded
			<lb />
			on a lump sum basis. The Agreements for supply -the Domestic Supply
			<lb />
			Contract and Foreign Supply Contract -were exclusive of taxes and
			<lb />
			duties and, the Agreement for Services was inclusive of taxes.
			<lb />
			8.
			<lb />
			On 18.09.2014, TPL submitted copies of L1 and L2 schedules to
			<lb />
			NTPC. The said schedules set out the manner in which TPL proposed
			<lb />
			to execute the Project works.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note palce="footnote">
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
			Digitally Signed
			<lb />
			By:DUSHYANT
			<lb />
			RAWAL
			<lb />
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
		</note>
		<note place="footnote">
			OMP(COMM) Nos.139/2021 &amp; 171/2021
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 4 of 33
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			9.
			<lb />
			In accordance with the terms of the Agreements, TPL submitted
			<lb />
			three Performance Securities amounting to ₹19,53,84,214/-,
			<lb />
			₹12,65,71,761/-and EURO 51,000, under the cover of its letter dated
			<lb />
			19.09.2014. These Securities were valid upto 26.03.2019.
			<lb />
			10. On 19.01.2017, the Ministry of Labour and Employment,
			<lb />
			Government of India issued a notification [Notification No S.O. 188
			<lb />
			(E)] under the Minimum Wages Act, 1948 increasing the minimum
			<lb />
			basic rate of wages for various categories of labour.
			<lb />
			11. In 2017, the Government of India announced the implementation
			<lb />
			of the Integrated Goods and Service Tax and Central Goods and Service
			<lb />
			Tax Act with effect from 01.07.2017.
			<lb />
			12. Admittedly, there were delays in execution of the Project. TPL
			<lb />
			requested NTPC to grant extension of time in terms of Clause 40 of the
			<lb />
			General Conditions of Contract (GCC), as applicable to the
			<lb />
			Agreements.
			<lb />
			13. NTPC granted such provisional extensions from time to time and
			<lb />
			requested TPL to extend the bank guarantees, insurance, labour license
			<lb />
			and other statutory requirements. NTPC also stated in its
			<lb />
			communications that the grant of extension would be without any extra
			<lb />
			financial burden on it and it reserved its right to levy liquidated
			<lb />
			damages. However, TPL claimed that the delays were for reasons not
			<lb />
			attributable to it and the commercial/financial implications arising out
			<lb />
			of the extensions would be on account of NTPC.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note palce="footnote">
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
			Digitally Signed
			<lb />
			By:DUSHYANT
			<lb />
			RAWAL
			<lb />
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
		</note>
		<note place="footnote">
			OMP(COMM) Nos.139/2021 &amp; 171/2021
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 5 of 33
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			14. The controversy essentially relates to (i) TPL&apos;s claim for
			<lb />
			payment of additional amounts on account of prolongation/delay costs;
			<lb />
			(ii) TPL&apos;s claim for reimbursement of Goods and Services Tax (GST);
			<lb />
			and (iii) TPL&apos;s claim for increase in costs resulting from increase in the
			<lb />
			basic wage rate in terms of the Notification No S.O. 188 (E) dated
			<lb />
			19.01.2017; and (iv) NTPC&apos;s claim for liquidated damages. TPL claims
			<lb />
			that that the Agreements entailed reciprocal obligations and NTPC was
			<lb />
			obliged to provide the requisite work fronts and land; access to site;
			<lb />
			provision of power for construction; timely payment of running account
			<lb />
			bills; to enable TPL to perform its obligations and complete the Project
			<lb />
			within the stipulated time. TPL alleged that NTPC had failed to perform
			<lb />
			its obligation in a timely manner. Accordingly, it claimed prolongation
			<lb />
			costs and additional costs incurred due to stoppage of works.
			<lb />
			15. NTPC claimed that TPL was unable to complete the Project
			<lb />
			works within the stipulated time period and thus, sought several
			<lb />
			extensions during the course of the Project. NTPC stated that it had
			<lb />
			granted such extensions from time to time but was not liable to pay any
			<lb />
			compensation for prolongation of contract; on the contrary, it was
			<lb />
			entitled to damages. TPL was also informed that any change in cost of
			<lb />
			labour would be paid through Price Adjustment provisions as provided
			<lb />
			in Appendix 2 of the Agreements. And, a separate claim on account of
			<lb />
			additional cost or expenditure incurred by TPL due to the hike in
			<lb />
			minimum wages was inadmissible. TPL was further informed that the
			<lb />
			Contract Price is inclusive of all taxes and, duties and was covered
			<lb />
			under the benefit being given for Mega Power Project. NTPC further
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note palce="footnote">
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
			Digitally Signed
			<lb />
			By:DUSHYANT
			<lb />
			RAWAL
			<lb />
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
		</note>
		<note place="footnote">
			OMP(COMM) Nos.139/2021 &amp; 171/2021
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 6 of 33
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			claimed that since the delay was on part of TPL, it would have to bear
			<lb />
			the GST which was payable after 01.07.2017
			<lb />
			16. On 26.08.2017, a revised L2 work schedule was submitted by
			<lb />
			TPL and subsequently, a meeting was held between the parties for L2
			<lb />
			schedule revision. The Minutes of the Meeting record that TPL had
			<lb />
			asked for extension of time for completion of the Project works on the
			<lb />
			basis of the delay in providing the requisite fronts and strikes at the
			<lb />
			Project site. On 21.11.2017, NPTC granted extension of time for
			<lb />
			completing the works for Unit 1 and Unit 2 till 30.01.2018 and
			<lb />
			30.05.2018 respectively. TPL was also requested to submit revised PV
			<lb />
			bills, extended bank guarantees, insurance, labour license and comply
			<lb />
			with other statutory requirements. Further, NTPC had also advised TPL
			<lb />
			to finish the balance works and achieve completion of the Project works
			<lb />
			within the abovementioned timeline, failing which NTPC would have
			<lb />
			the right to levy liquidated damages
			<lb />
			17. On 25.01.2018, TPL notified NTPC about the successful
			<lb />
			completion and commissioning of the facilities for Unit 1 and requested
			<lb />
			for the issuance of a Completion Certificate. TPL also requested NTPC
			<lb />
			to take over the facilities in accordance with the provisions of the GCC.
			<lb />
			TPL claimed that though the plant was commissioned, it could not reach
			<lb />
			full capacity due to non-availability of coal, which was required to be
			<lb />
			supplied by NTPC. Thereafter, by a letter dated 16.03.2018, TPL
			<lb />
			requested NTPC to issue the Completion Certificate and to take over
			<lb />
			the facilities from TPL with an assurance that TPL was ready for
			<lb />
			carrying out the Performance Guarantee Test.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note palce="footnote">
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
			Digitally Signed
			<lb />
			By:DUSHYANT
			<lb />
			RAWAL
			<lb />
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
		</note>
		<note place="footnote">
			OMP(COMM) Nos.139/2021 &amp; 171/2021
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 7 of 33
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			18. TPL, by a letter dated 06.07.2018, raised various claims relating
			<lb />
			to additional expenses on account of (i) stoppage of work by local
			<lb />
			groups; (ii) deployment of additional security at site; (iii) deployment
			<lb />
			of DG sets due to frequent non availability of construction power at site;
			<lb />
			and (iv) compensation on account of extended stay, quantified to
			<lb />
			approximately ₹70,37,36,551/-for expenses incurred till March 2018
			<lb />
			and projected costs till December 2018. TPL also claimed GST
			<lb />
			payments to the tune of ₹69.67 lakhs and CST payments amounting to
			<lb />
			₹45.77 lakhs and also requested NTPC to release the abovesaid
			<lb />
			amounts. TPL also called upon NTPC to refer the matter to an
			<lb />
			adjudicator in terms of Clause 6.1 of the GCC, if it was not agreeable
			<lb />
			to release the outstanding payments, and requested NTPC to confirm
			<lb />
			the name of the adjudicator.
			<lb />
			19. Thereafter, on 19.07.2018, NTPC issued the Completion
			<lb />
			Certificate for Unit 1 reflecting the date of completion as 23.03.2018.
			<lb />
			TPL claims that the said completion date was erroneous and the
			<lb />
			completion date should have been reflected as 25.01.2018. By a letter
			<lb />
			dated 31.07.2018, TPL requested NTPC to issue a revised Completion
			<lb />
			Certificate with the effective date of completion as 25.01.2018. NTPC
			<lb />
			responded to the aforesaid communication on 01.08.2018 and informed
			<lb />
			TPL that it had issued the Completion Certificate with respect to Unit 1
			<lb />
			in terms of Clause 24.7 of the GCC. Since the coal reclaiming circuit
			<lb />
			was made operational on 21.03.2018, TPL&apos;s request for a revised
			<lb />
			certificate was not tenable.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note palce="footnote">
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
			Digitally Signed
			<lb />
			By:DUSHYANT
			<lb />
			RAWAL
			<lb />
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
		</note>
		<note place="footnote">
			OMP(COMM) Nos.139/2021 &amp; 171/2021
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 8 of 33
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			20. By a letter dated 10.08.2018, TPL reiterated its request for
			<lb />
			appointment of an adjudicator to resolve the disputes between the
			<lb />
			parties. Further, it stated that if an adjudicator is not appointed by
			<lb />
			20.08.2018, TPL would be constrained to invoke arbitration in terms of
			<lb />
			Clause 6.2 of GCC.
			<lb />
			Arbitral Proceedings
			<lb />
			21. In view of the above disputes, TPL issued a notice dated
			<lb />
			07.09.2018 invoking the arbitration agreement, under Clause 6.2.1 of
			<lb />
			the GCC and, sought reference of the disputes to arbitration. TPL
			<lb />
			appointed Justice (Retd.) Badar Durrez Ahmed as its nominee
			<lb />
			Arbitrator. On 18.10.2018, NTPC nominated Justice (Retd.) Mukul
			<lb />
			Mudgal as its nominee arbitrator. Thereafter, Justice (Retd.) Dr.
			<lb />
			Mukundakam Sharma was appointed as the Presiding Arbitrator.
			<lb />
			22. Before the Arbitral Tribunal, TPL filed its Statement of Claims
			<lb />
			claiming an amount of approximately ₹38,51,44,254/-along with
			<lb />
			pendente lite and future interest at the rate of 14% per annum till
			<lb />
			realisation. TPL also claimed costs and expenses. Before the Arbitral
			<lb />
			Tribunal, TPL submitted that in terms of Clause 10 and Clause 2.4 of
			<lb />
			the GCC, NTPC was obligated to make due payments; approve the
			<lb />
			design; ensure supply of electricity; and availability of the different
			<lb />
			fronts during execution of the works. But NTPC had failed to perform
			<lb />
			its obligations. TPL further claimed that there had been a disruption in
			<lb />
			the supply of electricity and TPL had to stop the works due to shortage
			<lb />
			of supply of electricity. In addition to this, TPL also contended that
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note palce="footnote">
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
			Digitally Signed
			<lb />
			By:DUSHYANT
			<lb />
			RAWAL
			<lb />
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
		</note>
		<note place="footnote">
			OMP(COMM) Nos.139/2021 &amp; 171/2021
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 9 of 33
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			there were hindrances in executing the Project works due to the
			<lb />
			agitations by the villagers, resulting in delay in completion of the
			<lb />
			Project. TPL had claimed that even after NTPC had granted several
			<lb />
			extensions of time, there were lapses on the part of NTPC including in
			<lb />
			making the requisite fronts available to it. Therefore, it was entitled to
			<lb />
			prolongation costs in terms of Sections 54 and 55 of the Indian Contract
			<lb />
			Act, 1872. TPL further submitted that since the extension of time and
			<lb />
			prolongation of the Contract was attributable to NTPC, it could not levy
			<lb />
			any liquidated damages. TPL also claimed expenses incurred on
			<lb />
			account of statutory increase in labour wages and the balance GST
			<lb />
			amount payable to it.
			<lb />
			23. A tabular statement stating the claims made by TPL in its
			<lb />
			Statement of Claims are summarised below:
			<lb />
			Claim no 1 -Claim relating to
			<lb />
			unconditional Extension of Time till
			<lb />
			30.12.2018 and Prolongation cost due
			<lb />
			to extended stay
			<lb />
			₹35,34,01,340
			<lb />
			Claim no 2-Additional Expenses
			<lb />
			incurred during stoppage of works
			<lb />
			₹59,07,067
			<lb />
			Claim no 3-Cost for Additional
			<lb />
			Security
			<lb />
			₹48,38,771
			<lb />
			Claim no 4-Costs of DG sets due to
			<lb />
			irregular construction power
			<lb />
			₹11,33,579
			<lb />
			Claim no 5-Additional expenses
			<lb />
			incurred due increase in labour wages
			<lb />
			₹1,15,31,579
			<lb />
			Claim no 6-Claim for payment of
			<lb />
			balance Goods and Services Tax
			<lb />
			(GST)
			<lb />
			₹83,31,918
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note palce="footnote">
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
			Digitally Signed
			<lb />
			By:DUSHYANT
			<lb />
			RAWAL
			<lb />
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
		</note>
		<note place="footnote">
			OMP(COMM) Nos.139/2021 &amp; 171/2021
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 10 of 33
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			Claim no 7-Interest
			<lb />
			Pendente lite and future
			<lb />
			interest at the rate of
			<lb />
			14% per annum till
			<lb />
			realisation
			<lb />
			Claim no 8-Costs
			<lb />
			Costs of Arbitration
			<lb />
			24. NTPC filed its Statement of Defence disputing TPL&apos;s claims.
			<lb />
			However, it did not raise any counter claims. Before the Arbitral
			<lb />
			Tribunal, NTPC contended that its obligations were limited to those
			<lb />
			stipulated in the contractual provisions and there was no lapse or fault
			<lb />
			on its part in due performance of its obligations under the Agreements.
			<lb />
			NTPC also referred to Clause 20.01.00 of the Technical Specifications
			<lb />
			and contended that in terms of the said clause, TPL could not raise any
			<lb />
			claims against NTPC for delays caused due to the act or omission of
			<lb />
			other contractors and it would be entitled to extension of time as per
			<lb />
			Clause 40 of the GCC, which was duly granted to it. NTPC further
			<lb />
			contended before the Arbitral Tribunal that although it had granted such
			<lb />
			extensions from time to time, it had specifically mentioned that the
			<lb />
			same was without prejudice to impose liquidated damages. NTPC also
			<lb />
			claimed that the disturbances created by the villagers in execution of the
			<lb />
			Project works and the disruption of supply of electricity were covered
			<lb />
			under the Force Majeure clause and TPL would be entitled to extension
			<lb />
			of time without involving any financial implications. NTPC further
			<lb />
			contended that TPL was not entitled for additional expenses claimed on
			<lb />
			account of increase in labour wages and balance GST payment as the
			<lb />
			same were covered by the contractual provisions. Before the Arbitral
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note palce="footnote">
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
			Digitally Signed
			<lb />
			By:DUSHYANT
			<lb />
			RAWAL
			<lb />
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
		</note>
		<note place="footnote">
			OMP(COMM) Nos.139/2021 &amp; 171/2021
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 11 of 33
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			Tribunal, NTPC also contended that TPL was not entitled to the
			<lb />
			declaration that NTPC was not entitled to levy any liquidated damages
			<lb />
			for the delay caused by it.
			<lb />
			25. In view of the rival contentions, the Arbitral Tribunal struck the
			<lb />
			following issues:
			<lb />
			&quot;1. Whether the Claimant completed the work of Unit #
			<lb />
			1 within the extended time granted by the respondent till
			<lb />
			31.01.2018?
			<lb />
			2. Whether the Claimant is entitled in the alternative to
			<lb />
			extension of time till 23.03.2018 with respect to Unit no
			<lb />
			1?
			<lb />
			3. Whether the Claimant is entitled to prolongation cost
			<lb />
			due to the extended stay?
			<lb />
			4. Whether the Claimant is entitled to reimbursement of
			<lb />
			additional expenses incurred for stoppage of works
			<lb />
			5. Whether the Claimant is entitled to be awarded the
			<lb />
			cost for additional security?
			<lb />
			6. Whether the-Respondent was obligated to provide
			<lb />
			construction power under the Contract
			<lb />
			7. Whether the Claimant is entitled to be awarded the
			<lb />
			cost for additional DG sets incurred due to the irregular
			<lb />
			supply of construction power by the Respondent?
			<lb />
			8. Whether the Claimant is to be reimbursed the
			<lb />
			additional expense incurred due to increase-in labour
			<lb />
			wages?
			<lb />
			9. Whether the Claimant is entitled to be reimbursed the
			<lb />
			payment of balance Goods and Services Tax (GST)?
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note palce="footnote">
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
			Digitally Signed
			<lb />
			By:DUSHYANT
			<lb />
			RAWAL
			<lb />
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
		</note>
		<note place="footnote">
			OMP(COMM) Nos.139/2021 &amp; 171/2021
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 12 of 33
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			10. Whether the Claimant is entitled to interest at the rate
			<lb />
			of 14% per annum on the aforementioned amounts?&quot;
			<lb />
			Findings of the Arbitral Tribunal
			<lb />
			26. The Arbitral Tribunal found that neither NTPC nor TPL could be
			<lb />
			held responsible for any shortcomings in the performance of the
			<lb />
			contractual obligations and the same had been revised time and again
			<lb />
			with the mutual consent of both the parties. The Arbitral Tribunal
			<lb />
			declined to award the prolongation costs or additional expenses
			<lb />
			incurred during the stoppage of work as claimed by TPL and held that
			<lb />
			Sections 54 and 55 of the Indian Contract Act, 1872 had no application
			<lb />
			to the facts of the present case. The Tribunal also held that the
			<lb />
			disturbances caused by the villagers and the occasional non supply of
			<lb />
			electricity was covered under the scope of force majeure. TPL was
			<lb />
			entitled to extension of time on account of the same but no additional
			<lb />
			compensation. The Arbitral Tribunal also held that NTPC was not
			<lb />
			entitled to levy liquidated damages as claimed by NTPC. Accordingly,
			<lb />
			the Tribunal held that TPL was granted extension of time for completion
			<lb />
			of Unit 1 till 25.03.2018 and for Unit 2 till 31.12.2018. TPL&apos;s claim for
			<lb />
			prolongation costs amounting to ₹35,34,01,340/-and additional
			<lb />
			expenses incurred for stoppage of works amounting to ₹59,07,067/-,
			<lb />
			were rejected.
			<lb />
			27. The Arbitral Tribunal found that there was no disturbance in the
			<lb />
			law and order situation within the premises of the Project site and the
			<lb />
			entire plant was protected by the boundary wall and by deployment of
			<lb />
			CISF personnel. The Arbitral Tribunal accepted that since the labourers
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note palce="footnote">
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
			Digitally Signed
			<lb />
			By:DUSHYANT
			<lb />
			RAWAL
			<lb />
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
		</note>
		<note place="footnote">
			OMP(COMM) Nos.139/2021 &amp; 171/2021
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 13 of 33
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			were provided accommodation inside the premises, TPL could not have
			<lb />
			faced any hindrance or difficulty in executing the Project works. The
			<lb />
			Arbitral Tribunal referred to Clauses 22.3 and 22.7 of the GCC and
			<lb />
			concluded that TPL was responsible to provide safety, security, gate
			<lb />
			control at the Project site and thus, it was not entitled to receive any
			<lb />
			payment towards the cost of additional security. Accordingly, the
			<lb />
			Arbitral Tribunal rejected Claim no. 3 of TPL and decided Issue no. 5
			<lb />
			as framed, in favour of NTPC.
			<lb />
			28. The Arbitral Tribunal concluded that there was no responsibility
			<lb />
			on the part of NTPC to allow and pay for the DG sets for uninterrupted
			<lb />
			supply of power at the Project site. Accordingly, the Arbitral Tribunal
			<lb />
			rejected Claim no. 4 of TPL and decided Issue nos. 6 and 7 as framed,
			<lb />
			in favour of NTPC
			<lb />
			29. The Arbitral Tribunal considered the claim for additional
			<lb />
			expenses incurred, due to increase in labour wages and accepted TPL&apos;s
			<lb />
			contention that the substantial increase of 40% cost on account of
			<lb />
			revision of minimum basic rate of wages in terms of the Notification
			<lb />
			dated 19.02.2017 fell within the sweep of Clause 17 of the GCC and
			<lb />
			therefore, NTPC was responsible to reimburse the said expense.
			<lb />
			Accordingly, the Arbitral Tribunal accepted Claim no. 5 of TPL and
			<lb />
			decided Issue no. 8, in favour of TPL.
			<lb />
			30. The Arbitral Tribunal referred to Clause 7.2 of the SCC and
			<lb />
			Clause 36 of the GCC and found that any change in law regarding the
			<lb />
			liability to pay tax during the currency of the Contract would be
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note palce="footnote">
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
			Digitally Signed
			<lb />
			By:DUSHYANT
			<lb />
			RAWAL
			<lb />
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
		</note>
		<note place="footnote">
			OMP(COMM) Nos.139/2021 &amp; 171/2021
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 14 of 33
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			applicable and the Contract Price would be accordingly adjusted
			<lb />
			considering the increase in the tax liability. The Tribunal found that the
			<lb />
			Project could not be completed due to multiple reasons and was
			<lb />
			extended from time to time by the parties. There was a change in law
			<lb />
			during the extended period as a new set of taxes were imposed, and
			<lb />
			NTPC would be liable to reimburse the same. NTPC had reimbursed a
			<lb />
			sum of ₹14,80,219/-towards liability to pay for GST. The Arbitral
			<lb />
			Tribunal concluded that NTPC could not make any adjustment in the
			<lb />
			Contract Price against the said payment of GST. Accordingly, the
			<lb />
			Arbitral Tribunal accepted Claim no. 6 of TPL and awarded a sum of
			<lb />
			₹68,51,699/-[₹83,31,918/-(as claimed) less ₹14,80,219/-(sum already
			<lb />
			paid)] to TPL. Issue no. 9, was decided in favour of TPL. TPL&apos;s claim
			<lb />
			for interest at the rate of 14% per annum (Claim no. 7) was accepted by
			<lb />
			the Tribunal and, accordingly, Issue no. 10 was decided in TPL&apos;s
			<lb />
			favour.
			<lb />
			31. Aggrieved by the impugned award, the parties have filed these
			<lb />
			petitions.
			<lb />
			Submissions
			<lb />
			32. Mr Parekh, learned counsel appearing for TPL assailed the
			<lb />
			impugned award principally on the ground that the Arbitral Tribunal&apos;s
			<lb />
			decision to decline the prolongation/delay costs to TPL is ex facie
			<lb />
			erroneous. He submitted that the reference to Clause 20.01 of the
			<lb />
			Technical Specifications was patently erroneous as the same was not
			<lb />
			applicable.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note palce="footnote">
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
			Digitally Signed
			<lb />
			By:DUSHYANT
			<lb />
			RAWAL
			<lb />
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
		</note>
		<note place="footnote">
			OMP(COMM) Nos.139/2021 &amp; 171/2021
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 15 of 33
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			33. He referred to Sections 54 and 55 of the Indian Contract Act,
			<lb />
			1872 with respect to TPL&apos;s claim for prolongation costs and also relied
			<lb />
			on the decisions of the Supreme Court in M/s Hind Construction
			<lb />
			Contractors by its Sole Proprietor Bhikam-Chand Mulchand Jain
			<lb />
			(Dead) by LR&apos;s v. State of Maharashtra: (1979) 2 SCC 70; Arosan
			<lb />
			Enterprises Ltd. v. Union of India and Another: (1999) 9 SCC 449
			<lb />
			and McDermott International Inc. v. Burn Standard Co. Ltd. and
			<lb />
			Others: (2006) 11 SCC 181, in support of his contention that in
			<lb />
			contracts relating to construction, time is not the essence of the contract
			<lb />
			and more so, when the contract contains specific provisions for
			<lb />
			extension of time. He submitted that if there were any delays for reasons
			<lb />
			not attributable to TPL, it was entitled to extension of time. And insofar
			<lb />
			as the delays caused by NTPC, it was entitled to prolongation/delay
			<lb />
			costs.
			<lb />
			34. He submitted that since NTPC did not provide TPL with the
			<lb />
			requisite work fronts resulting in delay in execution of the works, it was
			<lb />
			liable to compensate TPL for the same. He referred to the decisions of
			<lb />
			the Supreme Court in Assam SEB v. Buildworth (P) Ltd: 2017 (8) SCC
			<lb />
			146 and, of this Court in Rawla Construction Co v. UOI: ILR 1982
			<lb />
			Delhi 44; Food Corporation of India v. A.M Ahmed &amp; Co.: (2006) 13
			<lb />
			SCC 779 and K. N. Sathya-palan v. State of Kerala: (2007) 13 SCC
			<lb />
			43, in support of his contention.
			<lb />
			35. Next, he submitted that the Arbitral Tribunal had found that the
			<lb />
			delays were caused by NTPC and therefore, several extensions of time
			<lb />
			were granted by it. The Arbitral Tribunal had rejected NTPC&apos;s claim to
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note palce="footnote">
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
			Digitally Signed
			<lb />
			By:DUSHYANT
			<lb />
			RAWAL
			<lb />
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
		</note>
		<note place="footnote">
			OMP(COMM) Nos.139/2021 &amp; 171/2021
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 16 of 33
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			levy liquidated damages on the aforesaid basis. However, the Arbitral
			<lb />
			Tribunal had relied on Clause 20.01.00 of the Technical Specifications
			<lb />
			and Clause 37 of the GCC (Force Majeure clause) to decline the award
			<lb />
			of prolongation costs to TPL. He submitted that the Arbitral Tribunal
			<lb />
			had failed to appreciate the nature of the delays caused by NTPC and,
			<lb />
			the Arbitral Tribunal had erred in assuming that the delays were covered
			<lb />
			under the aforesaid clauses. He submitted that due to the nature of the
			<lb />
			contract, the works were divided amongst different contractors and the
			<lb />
			primary obligation of NTPC was to provide the requisite fronts, without
			<lb />
			which, the execution of works was not possible. He contended that
			<lb />
			Clause 20.01.00 of the Technical Specifications was not applicable to
			<lb />
			the facts of the case. The said clause stipulates that &quot;the Contractor shall
			<lb />
			co-operate with all other Contractors or tradesmen of the Employer&quot;
			<lb />
			and did not relate to the obligation of NTPC. Thus, the Arbitral Tribunal
			<lb />
			had wrongly relied on the said clause. Further, he contended that the
			<lb />
			aforesaid clause should be read as contra proferentem.
			<lb />
			36. He submitted in the alternative that if the aforesaid clause was
			<lb />
			interpreted in the manner as contended by NTPC, it would be void under
			<lb />
			Section 23 of the Indian Contract Act, 1872. He relied on the decision
			<lb />
			of the Supreme Court in General Manager Northern Railways v.
			<lb />
			Sarvesh Chopra: (2002) 4 SCC 45. He submitted that the Tribunal had
			<lb />
			erred in holding that the said clause could not be declared
			<lb />
			unconscionable as the parties were bound by the contractual
			<lb />
			obligations.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note palce="footnote">
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
			Digitally Signed
			<lb />
			By:DUSHYANT
			<lb />
			RAWAL
			<lb />
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
		</note>
		<note place="footnote">
			OMP(COMM) Nos.139/2021 &amp; 171/2021
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 17 of 33
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			37. Mr. Sharma, learned ASG appearing for NTPC, countered the
			<lb />
			aforesaid submissions. He submitted that in terms of Clause 10 of the
			<lb />
			GCC, on 26.09.2014, NTPC was liable to provide the legal and physical
			<lb />
			possession of land for office, store, crusher house and access to the site
			<lb />
			to TPL for execution of the Project works and, the said contractual
			<lb />
			obligations and responsibility were admittedly fulfilled by NTPC as the
			<lb />
			land was free of encumbrances. He further submitted that as per the
			<lb />
			contractual provisions, NTPC was liable to provide fronts to TPL
			<lb />
			progressively and the same was duly provided.
			<lb />
			38. Next, he submitted that there was also no delay on the part of
			<lb />
			NTPC in fulfilling the reciprocal obligations and the same is evident
			<lb />
			from the fact that NTPC had granted various extensions of time to TPL,
			<lb />
			however, the said extensions of time had included a rider that such
			<lb />
			extensions were without any financial implications on NTPC and would
			<lb />
			also be subject to levy of liquidated damages by NPTC. Thereafter, on
			<lb />
			the basis of a mutual agreement regarding the availability of fronts
			<lb />
			between the parties, a revised L2 Schedule was made and was binding
			<lb />
			on both the parties. Further, TPL had not raised any claims regarding
			<lb />
			prolongations costs or other costs at the material time of submitting the
			<lb />
			revised L2 schedule. He submitted that TPL was only entitled to the
			<lb />
			relief of extension of time in terms of Clause 40 of the GCC for
			<lb />
			completion of the work and the same was duly granted.
			<lb />
			39. He submitted that the findings of the Arbitral Tribunal are based
			<lb />
			on cogent material and evidence. The Arbitral Tribunal had interpreted
			<lb />
			the contractual provisions in a reasonable manner and thus, the
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note palce="footnote">
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
			Digitally Signed
			<lb />
			By:DUSHYANT
			<lb />
			RAWAL
			<lb />
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
		</note>
		<note place="footnote">
			OMP(COMM) Nos.139/2021 &amp; 171/2021
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 18 of 33
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			impugned award cannot be interfered with. He referred to the decisions
			<lb />
			of the Supreme Court in MMTC Ltd v. Vedanta Ltd: (2019) 4 SCC 163,
			<lb />
			Ssangyong Engineering and Construction Company Ltd. v. National
			<lb />
			Highways Authority of India: (2019) 15 SCC 131 and, of this Court in
			<lb />
			Elta Systems Limited v. Government of India: OMP (COMM) 307 of
			<lb />
			2018, decided on 16.06.2021.
			<lb />
			40. He submitted that the finding of the Arbitral Tribunal that NTPC
			<lb />
			could not levy liquidated damages is perverse as levy of liquidated
			<lb />
			damages is a contractual right available with NTPC. He further
			<lb />
			submitted that the Tribunal had held that majority of the delay was
			<lb />
			attributable to TPL and had therefore, erred in holding that NTPC was
			<lb />
			barred from imposing any liquidated damages.
			<lb />
			41. Further, he submitted that the decision of the Arbitral Tribunal to
			<lb />
			grant increase in minimum wages of labour is perverse and deserves to
			<lb />
			be set aside. He submitted that the cost implications arising out of the
			<lb />
			Notification dated 19.01.2017 issued by the Government of India, is
			<lb />
			duly covered within the scope of Appendix 2 of the Agreements and,
			<lb />
			the impugned award was contrary to the terms of the Agreements.
			<lb />
			42. Next, he submitted that the decision of the Arbitral Tribunal to
			<lb />
			grant the award of GST in favour of TPL is also liable to be set aside.
			<lb />
			He contended that TPL was not entitled for any reimbursement on
			<lb />
			account of change in law beyond the stipulated supply period. And,
			<lb />
			since the delay in execution of the Project works is attributable to TPL,
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note palce="footnote">
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
			Digitally Signed
			<lb />
			By:DUSHYANT
			<lb />
			RAWAL
			<lb />
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
		</note>
		<note place="footnote">
			OMP(COMM) Nos.139/2021 &amp; 171/2021
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 19 of 33
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			neither its claim for GST amount nor the claim for increase in wages
			<lb />
			could have been awarded to TPL.
			<lb />
			Reasons and Conclusion
			<lb />
			43. Both the parties have assailed the impugned award. TPL had
			<lb />
			assailed the same on the limited ground that the Arbitral Tribunal has
			<lb />
			disallowed its claim for additional costs/compensation on account of
			<lb />
			prolongation of work. TPL states that the work in respect of Unit 1 and
			<lb />
			Unit 2 were to be completed within a period of thirty and thirty-four
			<lb />
			months respectively. However, the works under the Agreement were
			<lb />
			inordinately delayed.
			<lb />
			44. Mr Parekh, learned counsel for TPL submitted that no contractor
			<lb />
			could possibly suffer the cost overruns on account of such delays and
			<lb />
			therefore, the Arbitral Tribunal had grossly erred in rejecting TPL&apos;s
			<lb />
			claim in this regard. He contended that the Arbitral Tribunal&apos;s finding
			<lb />
			as recorded in paragraph 46 of the impugned award, to the effect that
			<lb />
			TPL was responsible for the delay, is perverse and contrary to the
			<lb />
			record. Mr Parekh referred to the Minutes of the Meeting dated
			<lb />
			26.08.2017 and on the strength of the said document, contended that
			<lb />
			NTPC had specifically agreed that the delays were attributable to it. He
			<lb />
			further submitted that the revised schedule of work (L2 Schedule) also
			<lb />
			indicated that the delays were attributable to NTPC. He contended that
			<lb />
			the Arbitral Tribunal had grossly erred in relying on Appendix 1,
			<lb />
			Appendix 2 and Appendix 3, which were merely tables prepared by
			<lb />
			NTPC for the purposes of arbitration and did not have any evidentiary
			<lb />
			value. He submitted that the instances of delays in respect of the Track
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note palce="footnote">
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
			Digitally Signed
			<lb />
			By:DUSHYANT
			<lb />
			RAWAL
			<lb />
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
		</note>
		<note place="footnote">
			OMP(COMM) Nos.139/2021 &amp; 171/2021
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 20 of 33
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			Hopper as mentioned by the Arbitral Tribunal by way of an illustration
			<lb />
			in paragraph 46, were replete with errors on the face of the record. The
			<lb />
			fronts of the Track Hopper were handed over progressively from
			<lb />
			22.01.2015 to 14.03.2015 and even thereafter, a patch of 50 meters was
			<lb />
			not available. He submitted that this was clearly evident from the noting
			<lb />
			in Appendix 1, which were referred to by the Arbitral Tribunal. He
			<lb />
			states that the Arbitral Tribunal had incorrectly noted that the work was
			<lb />
			partially completed on 29.06.2017 and 14.08.2018. However, Appendix
			<lb />
			1 as furnished by NTPC clearly mentions that the work was completed
			<lb />
			on 14.08.2017 (and not on 14.08.2018). He submitted that this was a
			<lb />
			patent error on the face of the impugned award that vitiated the finding
			<lb />
			of the Arbitral Tribunal to the effect that TPL was responsible for the
			<lb />
			delay.
			<lb />
			45. NTPC also contends that the impugned award to the extent that
			<lb />
			it declares that no liquidated damages can be levied on account of delay
			<lb />
			in execution of the works, is patently erroneous. NTPC claimed that
			<lb />
			since the Arbitral Tribunal had found that the claimant (TPL) was
			<lb />
			responsible for the delays and the delay on account of NTPC was
			<lb />
			&apos;minimal&apos;; the decision that NTPC cannot levy any liquidated damages,
			<lb />
			is perverse and patently erroneous.
			<lb />
			46. As is apparent, both the parties have founded the challenge to the
			<lb />
			impugned award on the basis of the findings recorded by the Arbitral
			<lb />
			Tribunal in paragraph 45 and 46 of the impugned award. However, the
			<lb />
			findings recorded in paragraph 45 and 46 cannot be read in isolation and
			<lb />
			must be read in the proper context.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note palce="footnote">
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
			Digitally Signed
			<lb />
			By:DUSHYANT
			<lb />
			RAWAL
			<lb />
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
		</note>
		<note place="footnote">
			OMP(COMM) Nos.139/2021 &amp; 171/2021
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 21 of 33
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			47. There is no real dispute that the delay in execution of the works
			<lb />
			were caused for various reasons including (i) delays in handing over the
			<lb />
			work fronts; (ii) on account of stoppage of work due to heavy rains; (iii)
			<lb />
			strike and agitation by villagers etc. The Arbitral Tribunal had noted
			<lb />
			that by a letter dated 26.08.2017, TPL had sought revision of L2
			<lb />
			schedule only on two grounds -delay in handing over of fronts by other
			<lb />
			contractors and strike by local villagers. NTPC acceded to TPL&apos;s
			<lb />
			request and extended the time for completion of the contract without
			<lb />
			raising any financial claims.
			<lb />
			48. Insofar as the delay on account of handing over of the work fronts
			<lb />
			is concerned, the Arbitral Tribunal found that no claim on that ground
			<lb />
			was permissible. This was so because the parties had agreed in terms of
			<lb />
			Clause 20.01.00 of the Technical Specifications that if the work was
			<lb />
			delayed because of any acts or omission of another contractor, TPL
			<lb />
			would have no claim against NTPC other than for extension of time for
			<lb />
			completion of the work. The Arbitral Tribunal noted that TPL had
			<lb />
			sought modification of the said clause during the pre-bid discussions.
			<lb />
			However, the parties had thereafter agreed that &quot;provision of bidding
			<lb />
			documents would prevail&quot;.
			<lb />
			49. Next, the Arbitral Tribunal found that some of the reasons that
			<lb />
			had resulted in delay could be classified as Force Majeure events. In
			<lb />
			respect of such events, the parties had agreed -in terms of Clause
			<lb />
			37.5(b) of the GCC -that such events shall not &quot;give rise to any claim
			<lb />
			for damages or additional cost or expense action thereby&quot;.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note palce="footnote">
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
			Digitally Signed
			<lb />
			By:DUSHYANT
			<lb />
			RAWAL
			<lb />
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
		</note>
		<note place="footnote">
			OMP(COMM) Nos.139/2021 &amp; 171/2021
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 22 of 33
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			50. In addition to the above, the Arbitral Tribunal also found that
			<lb />
			NTPC had handed over the possession of the site and access to TPL.
			<lb />
			The decision of the Arbitral Tribunal that TPL is not entitled to any
			<lb />
			compensation for prolongation of the work at site is mainly founded on
			<lb />
			the aforesaid findings. The impugned award is not founded on any
			<lb />
			specific finding regarding handing over of front for Track Hopper.
			<lb />
			51. The reference to partial completion of the work on 14.08.2018
			<lb />
			(as noted in paragraph 46 of the impugned award) appears to be a
			<lb />
			typographical error and the same should be read as 14.08.2017.
			<lb />
			According to the revised L2 Schedule, the said work was required to be
			<lb />
			completed on 04.02.2017. There may be some merit in Mr Parekh&apos;s
			<lb />
			contention that TPL was not responsible for the delay in respect of
			<lb />
			completion of the work for the Track Hopper as mentioned by the
			<lb />
			Arbitral Tribunal in paragraph 46 of the impugned award. However,
			<lb />
			the impugned award is not pivoted on that finding.
			<lb />
			52. NTPC&apos;s contention that it was entitled to levy liquidated damages
			<lb />
			was also rejected on the grounds as stated hereinbefore. Its reliance on
			<lb />
			paragraph 46 of the impugned award is not apposite, when one reads
			<lb />
			various findings returned by the Arbitral Tribunal and the impugned
			<lb />
			award as a whole.
			<lb />
			53. It is also relevant to note that the findings recorded by the Arbitral
			<lb />
			Tribunal in paragraphs 45 and 46 of the impugned award are based on
			<lb />
			certain material as available on record, while Mr Parekh is correct that
			<lb />
			the Minutes of the Meeting dated 26.08.2017 may not support the said
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note palce="footnote">
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
			Digitally Signed
			<lb />
			By:DUSHYANT
			<lb />
			RAWAL
			<lb />
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
		</note>
		<note place="footnote">
			OMP(COMM) Nos.139/2021 &amp; 171/2021
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 23 of 33
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			view. However, that is not the only material, which has been considered
			<lb />
			by the Arbitral Tribunal.
			<lb />
			54. This Court is not required to re-appreciate or re-evaluate the
			<lb />
			evidence and supplant its opinion over that of the Arbitral Tribunal. The
			<lb />
			arbitral award can be interfered with on merits only on the grounds as
			<lb />
			specified under Section 34(2)(b)(ii) and Section 34(2A) of the A&amp;C
			<lb />
			Act.
			<lb />
			55. In Associate Builders v. Delhi Development Authority: (2015) 3
			<lb />
			SCC 49, the Supreme Court had observed as under:
			<lb />
			&quot;It must clearly be understood that when a
			<lb />
			court is applying the &quot;public policy&quot; test to an
			<lb />
			arbitration award, it does not act as a court of appeal
			<lb />
			and consequently errors of fact cannot be corrected.
			<lb />
			A possible view by the arbitrator on facts has
			<lb />
			necessarily to pass muster as the arbitrator is the
			<lb />
			ultimate master of the quantity and quality of
			<lb />
			evidence to be relied upon when he delivers his
			<lb />
			arbitral award. Thus an award based on little
			<lb />
			evidence or on evidence which does not measure up
			<lb />
			in quality to a trained legal mind would not be held
			<lb />
			to be invalid on this score. Once it is found that the
			<lb />
			arbitrators approach is not arbitrary or capricious,
			<lb />
			then he is the last word on facts.&quot;
			<lb />
			56. The said view was reiterated by the Supreme Court in MMTC
			<lb />
			Limited v. M/s Vedanta Limited: (2019) 4 SCC 163. In the said
			<lb />
			decision, the Court explained as under:
			<lb />
			&quot;11. As far as Section 34 is concerned, the
			<lb />
			position is well-settled by now that the Court does
			<lb />
			not sit in appeal over the arbitral award and may
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note palce="footnote">
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
			Digitally Signed
			<lb />
			By:DUSHYANT
			<lb />
			RAWAL
			<lb />
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
		</note>
		<note place="footnote">
			OMP(COMM) Nos.139/2021 &amp; 171/2021
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 24 of 33
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			interfere on merits on the limited ground provided
			<lb />
			under Section 34(2)(b)(ii) i.e. if the award is against
			<lb />
			the public policy of India. As per the legal position
			<lb />
			clarified through decisions of this Court prior to the
			<lb />
			amendments to the 1996 Act in 2015, a violation of
			<lb />
			Indian public policy, in turn, includes a violation of
			<lb />
			the fundamental policy of Indian law, a violation of
			<lb />
			the interest of India, conflict with justice or morality,
			<lb />
			and the existence of patent illegality in the arbitral
			<lb />
			award. Additionally, the concept of the
			<lb />
			&quot;fundamental policy of Indian law&quot; would cover
			<lb />
			compliance with statutes and judicial precedents,
			<lb />
			adopting a judicial approach, compliance with the
			<lb />
			principles
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			natural
			<lb />
			justice,
			<lb />
			and Wednesbury [Associated Provincial Picture
			<lb />
			Houses v. Wednesbury Corpn., (1948) 1 KB 223
			<lb />
			(CA)] reasonableness. Furthermore, &quot;patent
			<lb />
			illegality&quot; itself has been held to mean contravention
			<lb />
			of the substantive law of India, contravention of the
			<lb />
			1996 Act, and contravention of the terms of the
			<lb />
			contract.
			<lb />
			12. It is only if one of these conditions is met
			<lb />
			that the Court may interfere with an arbitral award in
			<lb />
			terms of Section 34(2)(b)(ii), but such interference
			<lb />
			does not entail a review of the merits of the dispute,
			<lb />
			and is limited to situations where the findings of the
			<lb />
			arbitrator are arbitrary, capricious or perverse, or
			<lb />
			when the conscience of the Court is shocked, or
			<lb />
			when the illegality is not trivial but goes to the root
			<lb />
			of the matter. An arbitral award may not be
			<lb />
			interfered with if the view taken by the arbitrator is
			<lb />
			a possible view based on facts. (See Associate
			<lb />
			Builders v. DDA [Associate
			<lb />
			Builders v. DDA,
			<lb />
			(2015) 3 SCC 49 : (2015) 2 SCC (Civ) 204] . Also
			<lb />
			see ONGC
			<lb />
			Ltd. v. Saw
			<lb />
			Pipes
			<lb />
			Ltd. [ONGC
			<lb />
			Ltd. v. Saw Pipes Ltd., (2003) 5 SCC 705]
			<lb />
			; Hindustan
			<lb />
			Zinc
			<lb />
			Ltd. v. Friends
			<lb />
			Coal
			<lb />
			Carbonisation [Hindustan Zinc Ltd. v. Friends Coal
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note palce="footnote">
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
			Digitally Signed
			<lb />
			By:DUSHYANT
			<lb />
			RAWAL
			<lb />
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
		</note>
		<note place="footnote">
			OMP(COMM) Nos.139/2021 &amp; 171/2021
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 25 of 33
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			Carbonisation, (2006) 4 SCC 445] ; and McDermott
			<lb />
			International
			<lb />
			Inc. v. Burn
			<lb />
			Standard
			<lb />
			Co.
			<lb />
			Ltd. [McDermott
			<lb />
			International
			<lb />
			Inc. v. Burn
			<lb />
			Standard Co. Ltd., (2006) 11 SCC 181] )
			<lb />
			13. It is relevant to note that after the 2015
			<lb />
			Amendment to Section 34, the above position stands
			<lb />
			somewhat modified. Pursuant to the insertion of
			<lb />
			Explanation 1 to Section 34(2), the scope of
			<lb />
			contravention of Indian public policy has been
			<lb />
			modified to the extent that it now means fraud or
			<lb />
			corruption in the making of the award, violation of
			<lb />
			Section 75 or Section 81 of the Act, contravention of
			<lb />
			the fundamental policy of Indian law, and conflict
			<lb />
			with the most basic notions of justice or morality.
			<lb />
			Additionally, sub-section (2-A) has been inserted in
			<lb />
			Section 34, which provides that in case of domestic
			<lb />
			arbitrations, violation of Indian public policy also
			<lb />
			includes patent illegality appearing on the face of the
			<lb />
			award. The proviso to the same states that an award
			<lb />
			shall not be set aside merely on the ground of an
			<lb />
			erroneous application of the law or by reappreciation
			<lb />
			of evidence.&quot;
			<lb />
			57. In a recent decision in Delhi Airport Metro Express Pvt. Ltd. v.
			<lb />
			Delhi Metro Rail Corporation Ltd.: 2021 SCC OnLine SC 695, the
			<lb />
			Supreme Court found flaw with the approach of the Courts to re-
			<lb />
			examine and re-evaluate the evidence for the purposes of ascertaining
			<lb />
			whether the impugned award was vitiated by patent illegality. It further
			<lb />
			explained the scope of the ground of patent illegality under Section
			<lb />
			34(2A) of the A&amp;C Act as under:
			<lb />
			&quot;24. This Court has in several other judgments
			<lb />
			interpreted Section 34 of the 1996 Act to stress on
			<lb />
			the restraint to be shown by courts while examining
			<lb />
			the validity of the arbitral awards. The limited
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note palce="footnote">
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
			Digitally Signed
			<lb />
			By:DUSHYANT
			<lb />
			RAWAL
			<lb />
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
		</note>
		<note place="footnote">
			OMP(COMM) Nos.139/2021 &amp; 171/2021
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 26 of 33
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			grounds available to courts for annulment of arbitral
			<lb />
			awards are well known to legally trained minds.
			<lb />
			However, the difficulty arises in applying the well-
			<lb />
			established principles for interference to the facts of
			<lb />
			each case that come up before the courts. There is a
			<lb />
			disturbing tendency of courts setting aside arbitral
			<lb />
			awards, after dissecting and reassessing factual
			<lb />
			aspects of the cases to come to a conclusion that the
			<lb />
			award needs intervention and thereafter, dubbing the
			<lb />
			award to be vitiated by either perversity or patent
			<lb />
			illegality, apart from the other grounds available for
			<lb />
			annulment of the award. This approach would lead
			<lb />
			to corrosion of the object of the 1996 Act and the
			<lb />
			endeavours made to preserve this object, which is
			<lb />
			minimal judicial interference with arbitral awards.
			<lb />
			That apart, several judicial pronouncements of this
			<lb />
			Court would become a dead letter if arbitral awards
			<lb />
			are set aside by categorising them as perverse or
			<lb />
			patently illegal without appreciating the contours of
			<lb />
			the said expressions.
			<lb />
			25. Patent illegality should be illegality which
			<lb />
			goes to the root of the matter. In other words, every
			<lb />
			error of law committed by the Arbitral Tribunal
			<lb />
			would not fall within the expression &apos;patent
			<lb />
			illegality&apos;. Likewise, erroneous application of law
			<lb />
			cannot be categorised as patent illegality. In
			<lb />
			addition, contravention of law not linked to public
			<lb />
			policy or public interest is beyond the scope of the
			<lb />
			expression &apos;patent illegality&apos;. What is prohibited is
			<lb />
			for courts to re-appreciate evidence to conclude that
			<lb />
			the award suffers from patent illegality appearing on
			<lb />
			the face of the award, as courts do not sit in appeal
			<lb />
			against the arbitral award. The permissible grounds
			<lb />
			for interference with a domestic award under Section
			<lb />
			34(2-A) on the ground of patent illegality is when
			<lb />
			the arbitrator takes a view which is not even a
			<lb />
			possible one, or interprets a clause in the contract in
			<lb />
			such a manner which no fair-minded or reasonable
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note palce="footnote">
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
			Digitally Signed
			<lb />
			By:DUSHYANT
			<lb />
			RAWAL
			<lb />
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
		</note>
		<note place="footnote">
			OMP(COMM) Nos.139/2021 &amp; 171/2021
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 27 of 33
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			person would, or if the arbitrator commits an error of
			<lb />
			jurisdiction by wandering outside the contract and
			<lb />
			dealing with matters not allotted to them. An arbitral
			<lb />
			award stating no reasons for its findings would make
			<lb />
			itself susceptible to challenge on this account. The
			<lb />
			conclusions of the arbitrator which are based on no
			<lb />
			evidence or have been arrived at by ignoring vital
			<lb />
			evidence are perverse and can be set aside on the
			<lb />
			ground of patent illegality. Also, consideration of
			<lb />
			documents which are not supplied to the other party
			<lb />
			is a facet of perversity falling within the expression
			<lb />
			&apos;patent illegality&apos;.
			<lb />
			26. Section 34 (2) (b) refers to the other
			<lb />
			grounds on which a court can set aside an arbitral
			<lb />
			award. If a dispute which is not capable of settlement
			<lb />
			by arbitration is the subject-matter of the award or if
			<lb />
			the award is in conflict with public policy of India,
			<lb />
			the award is liable to be set aside. Explanation (1),
			<lb />
			amended by the 2015 Amendment Act, clarified the
			<lb />
			expression &apos;public policy of India&apos; and its
			<lb />
			connotations for the purposes of reviewing arbitral
			<lb />
			awards. It has been made clear that an award would
			<lb />
			be in conflict with public policy of India only when
			<lb />
			it is induced or affected by fraud or corruption or is
			<lb />
			in violation of Section 75 or Section 81 of the 1996
			<lb />
			Act, if it is in contravention with the fundamental
			<lb />
			policy of Indian law or if it is in conflict with the
			<lb />
			most basic notions of morality or justice. In
			<lb />
			Ssangyong (supra), this Court held that the meaning
			<lb />
			of the expression &apos;fundamental policy of Indian law&apos;
			<lb />
			would be in accordance with the understanding of
			<lb />
			this Court in Renusagar Power Co. Ltd. v. General
			<lb />
			Electric Co. In Renusagar (supra), this Court
			<lb />
			observed that violation of the Foreign Exchange
			<lb />
			Regulation Act, 1973, a statute enacted for the
			<lb />
			&apos;national economic interest&apos;, and disregarding the
			<lb />
			superior courts in India would be antithetical to the
			<lb />
			fundamental policy of Indian law. Contravention of
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note palce="footnote">
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
			Digitally Signed
			<lb />
			By:DUSHYANT
			<lb />
			RAWAL
			<lb />
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
		</note>
		<note place="footnote">
			OMP(COMM) Nos.139/2021 &amp; 171/2021
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 28 of 33
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			a statute not linked to public policy or public interest
			<lb />
			cannot be a ground to set at naught an arbitral award
			<lb />
			as being discordant with the fundamental policy of
			<lb />
			Indian law and neither can it be brought within the
			<lb />
			confines of &apos;patent illegality&apos; as discussed above. In
			<lb />
			other words, contravention of a statute only if it is
			<lb />
			linked to public policy or public interest is cause for
			<lb />
			setting aside the award as being at odds with the
			<lb />
			fundamental policy of Indian law. If an arbitral
			<lb />
			award shocks the conscience of the court, it can be
			<lb />
			set aside as being in conflict with the most basic
			<lb />
			notions of justice. The ground of morality in this
			<lb />
			context has been interpreted by this Court to
			<lb />
			encompass awards involving elements of sexual
			<lb />
			morality, such as prostitution, or awards seeking to
			<lb />
			validate agreements which are not illegal but would
			<lb />
			not be enforced given the prevailing mores of the
			<lb />
			day.
			<lb />
			27. In light of the principles elucidated herein
			<lb />
			for interference with an arbitral award by a court in
			<lb />
			exercise of its jurisdiction under Section 34 of the
			<lb />
			1996 Act, we proceed to consider the questions that
			<lb />
			arise in these Appeals as to whether the Division
			<lb />
			Bench of the High Court was right in setting aside
			<lb />
			the award of the Arbitral Tribunal dated
			<lb />
			11.05.2017.&quot;
			<lb />
			58. In view of the above, the Court is unable to accept that the
			<lb />
			decision of the Arbitral Tribunal to reject TPL&apos;s claim for additional
			<lb />
			cost/compensation on account of prolongation of work and to reject
			<lb />
			NTPC&apos;s claim for any liquidated damages falls foul of the Public Policy
			<lb />
			of India or can be stated to be vitiated on account of patent illegality.
			<lb />
			59. This Court finds no merit in the contention that Clause 20.01.00
			<lb />
			of the Technical Specifications is unconscionable or illegal. The
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note palce="footnote">
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
			Digitally Signed
			<lb />
			By:DUSHYANT
			<lb />
			RAWAL
			<lb />
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
		</note>
		<note place="footnote">
			OMP(COMM) Nos.139/2021 &amp; 171/2021
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 29 of 33
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			Arbitral Tribunal had examined the decision in General Manager,
			<lb />
			Northern Railways v. Sarvesh Chopra (supra) and found that the same
			<lb />
			does not apply in the facts of this case. The Arbitral Tribunal also found
			<lb />
			that TPL was aware of the import of the said clause as it had sought its
			<lb />
			modification but had subsequently accepted the contractual terms. This
			<lb />
			Court finds no fault with the view of the Arbitral Tribunal.
			<lb />
			60. It was also contended on behalf of NTPC that there was no issue
			<lb />
			framed by the Arbitral Tribunal regarding levy of liquidated damages.
			<lb />
			The said contention is, plainly, unmerited as the principal case before
			<lb />
			the Arbitral Tribunal related to the dispute whether TPL was entitled to
			<lb />
			any prolongation costs. The said claim was rejected on the ground that,
			<lb />
			in the facts and circumstances of the case, neither party would be
			<lb />
			justified to claim any compensation/damages on account of
			<lb />
			prolongation of the work.
			<lb />
			61. NTPC had also assailed the decision of the Arbitral Tribunal to
			<lb />
			award additional expenses incurred due to increase in labour costs. The
			<lb />
			Arbitral Tribunal had found that TPL was entitled to such increase in
			<lb />
			terms of Clause 17 of the SCC, as such increase in cost was relatable to
			<lb />
			the Notification dated 19.01.2017 issued under the Minimum Wages
			<lb />
			Act, 1948. In terms of the said Notification, the basic rate of wages for
			<lb />
			various categories of labour were increased substantially to the extent
			<lb />
			of 40%. According to NTPC, no amount was payable for such increase
			<lb />
			as it was factored in the formula specified in Appendix 2 of the
			<lb />
			Agreement. However, the Arbitral Tribunal found that the price
			<lb />
			variation formula as set out in Appendix 2 factored in an increase in the
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note palce="footnote">
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
			Digitally Signed
			<lb />
			By:DUSHYANT
			<lb />
			RAWAL
			<lb />
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
		</note>
		<note place="footnote">
			OMP(COMM) Nos.139/2021 &amp; 171/2021
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 30 of 33
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			labour cost on the basis of &quot;All India Consumer Price Index for
			<lb />
			Industrial Workers (All India Monthly Average) as published by Labour
			<lb />
			Bureau, Shimla, Government of India&quot;.
			<lb />
			62.
			<lb />
			The &quot;Brief on Consumer Price Index for Industrial Workers
			<lb />
			(New Series)&quot; published by the Labour Bureau of the Government of
			<lb />
			India expressly stated as follows:
			<lb />
			&quot;The CPI-IW purport to measure the temporal
			<lb />
			change in the retail prices of fixed basket of goods
			<lb />
			and services being consumed by an average working
			<lb />
			class family…&quot;
			<lb />
			63. Thus, the said Index was based on the prices of basket of goods
			<lb />
			and services consumed by working class families. It is apparent that this
			<lb />
			was directly relatable to the Variable Dearness Allowance (VDA) as
			<lb />
			periodically declared by the concerned Labour Commissioner.
			<lb />
			64. Section 4 of the Minimum Wages Act, 1948 indicates two
			<lb />
			components of wages. The first being the basic rate of wages and
			<lb />
			special allowance; and the second being the cost of living allowance.
			<lb />
			The Arbitral Tribunal found that whilst the cost of living allowance was
			<lb />
			factored in the formula prescribed in Appendix 2; revision in the
			<lb />
			minimum basic wage rate was not.
			<lb />
			65. Undeniably, the Notification dated 19.01.2017 did constitute a
			<lb />
			change in law resulting in an increase in the cost of labour. The same
			<lb />
			was required to be compensated to the extent that it was not covered
			<lb />
			under Appendix 2. The Arbitral Tribunal found that the formula set out
			<lb />
			in Appendix 2 to the Agreements was relatable to the cost of living.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note palce="footnote">
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
			Digitally Signed
			<lb />
			By:DUSHYANT
			<lb />
			RAWAL
			<lb />
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
		</note>
		<note place="footnote">
			OMP(COMM) Nos.139/2021 &amp; 171/2021
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 31 of 33
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			Therefore, the increase in costs due to increase in the basic minimum
			<lb />
			wage rate was required to be compensated.
			<lb />
			66. The Arbitral Tribunal also referred to the decision in NHAI v.
			<lb />
			ITD Cementation India Ltd.: (2015) 14 SCC 21 and allowed TPL&apos;s
			<lb />
			claim for increase in cost resulting from the Notification.
			<lb />
			67. It is also relevant to note that in Larsen and Toubro Limited v.
			<lb />
			NTPC Limited: OMP COMM 524/2020, decided on 26.11.2021, this
			<lb />
			Court has rejected the challenge to an arbitral award whereby the
			<lb />
			arbitral tribunal that had rendered that award had accepted the aforesaid
			<lb />
			view and had held in favour of the claimant.
			<lb />
			68. The impugned award cannot be faulted on the aforesaid ground
			<lb />
			and NTPC&apos;s challenge to the same is rejected.
			<lb />
			69. In addition to the above, NTPC has also challenged the impugned
			<lb />
			award to the extent that it allows TPL&apos;s claim for GST. TPL had
			<lb />
			claimed an amount of ₹83,31,918/-on account of levy of GST under
			<lb />
			the Integrated Goods and Services Tax Act, 2017 and Central Goods
			<lb />
			and Services Tax Act, 2017.
			<lb />
			70. The levy of Goods and Services Tax came into effect from
			<lb />
			01.07.2017. The Arbitral Tribunal found that the enactment of the
			<lb />
			statute for levy of GST constituted a new law and therefore, the Contract
			<lb />
			Price was liable to be adjusted in terms of Clause 7.2 of the SCC. NTPC
			<lb />
			had disputed the same on the ground that it was not liable to pay the
			<lb />
			GST on account of delay in the execution of the project. The Arbitral
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note palce="footnote">
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
			Digitally Signed
			<lb />
			By:DUSHYANT
			<lb />
			RAWAL
			<lb />
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
		</note>
		<note place="footnote">
			OMP(COMM) Nos.139/2021 &amp; 171/2021
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 32 of 33
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			Tribunal did not find any merit in the said contention. The Arbitral
			<lb />
			Tribunal held that in view of the findings regarding the delay in
			<lb />
			execution of the Project works, no further conditions could be put by
			<lb />
			NTPC. NTPC was bound to give effect to Clause 7.2 of the SCC. The
			<lb />
			Arbitral Tribunal found that after the Statement of Claims was filed, an
			<lb />
			amount of ₹14,80,219/-had been paid and, TPL was thus, entitled to
			<lb />
			the balance amount of ₹68,51,699/-.
			<lb />
			71. This Court finds no error in the aforesaid view. In any view of
			<lb />
			the matter, it is a plausible view. In the circumstances, no interference
			<lb />
			with the impugned award is warranted.
			<lb />
			72. The petitions are unmerited and are, accordingly, dismissed. The
			<lb />
			pending applications are also disposed of.
			<lb />
			VIBHU BAKHRU, J
			<lb />
			DECEMBER 08, 2021
			<lb />
			RK/v
		</body>
		<note palce="footnote">
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
			Digitally Signed
			<lb />
			By:DUSHYANT
			<lb />
			RAWAL
			<lb />
			Signature Not Verified
			<lb />
		</note>
		<note place="footnote">
			OMP(COMM) Nos.139/2021 &amp; 171/2021
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 33 of 33
			<lb />
		</page>
	</text>
</tei>
