<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			IN THE HIGH COURT OF DELHI AT NEW DELHI
			<lb />
			+ O.M.P. (COMM) 570/2016
			<lb />
			STORE ONE RETAIL INDIA LIMITED ..... Petitioner
			<lb />
			Through: Mr Rajiv Nayar, Senior Advocate
			<lb />
			with Mr Sudhir Sharma, Mr Sanjeev
			<lb />
			Kumar Sharma, Mr Abhishek
			<lb />
			Swaroop, Mr Abhishek and Mr Ritesh
			<lb />
			Kumar, Advocates.
			<lb />
			versus
			<lb />
			ANNAPURNA INFRASTRUTURE PVT LTD
			<lb />
			&amp;ORS. ..... Respondents
			<lb />
			Through: Mr Manish Sharma, Ms Chandni
			<lb />
			Mehra, Mr Abhishek Agarwal,
			<lb />
			Advocate for R-3.
			<lb />
			CORAM:
			<lb />
			HONBLE MR. JUSTICE VIBHU BAKHRU
			<lb />
			O R D E R
			<lb />
			% 19.12.2016
			<lb />
			VIBHU BAKHRU, J
			<lb />
		</front>
		<body>
			IA No.15671/2016
			<lb />
			1. Allowed, subject to all just exceptions.
			<lb />
			CAV. No.1065/2016
			<lb />
			2. The learned counsel for the respondent no.3/caveator has entered
			<lb />
			appearance. The caveat stands discharged.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			O.M.P. (COMM) 570/2016
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 1 of 14
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			O.M.P. (COMM) 570/2016 and IA No. 15670/2016
			<lb />
			3.
			<lb />
			Store One Retail India Limited (hereafter &apos;Store One&apos;) has filed the
			<lb />
			present petition under Section 34 of the Arbitration and Conciliation Act,
			<lb />
			1996 (hereafter &apos;the Act&apos;) impugning an arbitral award dated 09.09.2016
			<lb />
			(hereafter &apos;the impugned award&apos;) made and published by the Sole Arbitrator,
			<lb />
			Justice Dr Mukundakam Sharma (Retired), a former Judge of the Supreme
			<lb />
			Court of India.
			<lb />
			4.
			<lb />
			The disputes between the parties relate to the payment of lease rent
			<lb />
			and fees for facility management, in respect of the premises (hereafter &apos;the
			<lb />
			said premises&apos;), which were taken on lease by Store One in a commercial
			<lb />
			complex known as &quot;Shop in Park (North)&quot;. The lease for the said premises
			<lb />
			was terminated by Store One prior to the expiry of the lock-in period and
			<lb />
			that had resulted in claims, inter alia, for rent/damages being made against
			<lb />
			Store One.
			<lb />
			5.
			<lb />
			The Arbitrator considered the disputes and awarded rent for the period
			<lb />
			01.04.2008 to 22.03.2010 alongwith interest at the rate of 12% per annum
			<lb />
			up to the date of the award in favour of M/s Annapurna Infrastructure Pvt.
			<lb />
			Ltd. (hereafter &apos;Annapurna&apos;) and M/s Paliwal Overseas Pvt. Ltd (hereafter
			<lb />
			&apos;Paliwal&apos;). Further, the Arbitrator also awarded damages equivalent to the
			<lb />
			rent for a period of six months from 22.03.2010 in favour of Annapurna and
			<lb />
			Paliwal along with future interest at the rate of 12% per annum. In addition,
			<lb />
			the Arbitrator also made an award in favour of M/s Pragya Products Pvt.
			<lb />
			Ltd. (hereafter &apos;Pragya&apos;) for facility management services and electricity
			<lb />
			charges alongwith interest at the rate of 12% per annum.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			O.M.P. (COMM) 570/2016
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 2 of 14
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			6.
			<lb />
			Store One asserts that the impugned award is opposed to the Public
			<lb />
			Policy of India and, therefore, is liable to be set aside under Section
			<lb />
			34(2)(b)(ii) of the Act; it, inter alia, claims that the Arbitrator has erred in
			<lb />
			holding that the termination of lease of the said premises was invalid and
			<lb />
			consequently awarding rentals in favour of parties even for the period it was
			<lb />
			not in occupation of the said premises.
			<lb />
			7.
			<lb />
			Briefly stated, the necessary facts to consider the aforesaid
			<lb />
			controversy are as under:-
			<lb />
			7.1 Pragya and Store One (then known as Piramyd Retail and
			<lb />
			Merchandising Pvt. Ltd.) entered into a Memorandum of Understanding
			<lb />
			(MoU) dated 23.03.2004 whereby Pragya agreed to participate in a public
			<lb />
			auction of a commercial plot admeasuring 8710 square meters situated at
			<lb />
			Plot No.2, Block B, Community Centre, Shalimar Bagh, Delhi to be
			<lb />
			conducted by the Delhi Development Authority (DDA). Store One agreed
			<lb />
			that if Pragya was declared as a successful bidder, it would lease a covered
			<lb />
			area admeasuring approximately 70,000 square feet at a rent calculated at
			<lb />
			the rate of Rs.55 per sq. ft. per month.
			<lb />
			7.2 The said auction was conducted by the DDA on 26.03.2004; Pragya
			<lb />
			was declared as the successful bidder and a perpetual lease deed dated
			<lb />
			08.10.2004 was executed in its favour. Thereafter, Pragya commenced
			<lb />
			construction of a commercial complex on the said plot of land. Pragya also
			<lb />
			approached Annapurna and Paliwal to sell the said plot on the representation
			<lb />
			that it had already entered into an arrangement (MOU dated 23.03.2004) for
			<lb />
			leasing out 70,000 square feet of covered area to Store One. Accordingly, an
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			O.M.P. (COMM) 570/2016
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 3 of 14
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			Agreement to Sell dated 09.12.2004 was executed between Pragya on one
			<lb />
			part, and Annapurna and Paliwal on the other part whereby Pragya agreed to
			<lb />
			sell and Annapurna and Paliwal agreed to purchase the plot in question.
			<lb />
			Thereafter, a lease deed (hereafter &apos;the Lease Deed&apos;) was also executed
			<lb />
			between Pragya and Store One on 23.11.2005 whereby Store One agreed to
			<lb />
			lease approximately 52,000 square feet of space in the Shopping Mall
			<lb />
			Arcade, Shop in Park (North) -which at the relevant time was under
			<lb />
			construction -for an initial period of 10 years with an option for extension of
			<lb />
			two further terms of 10 years and five years respectively.
			<lb />
			7.3 Store One also agreed to pay a sum of `1,43,00,000/-(One Crore
			<lb />
			Forty Three Lacs) to Pragya as interest free refundable security deposit.
			<lb />
			After the mall was constructed, Store One was put in possession of the said
			<lb />
			premises, admeasuring 67,613 square feet for its outlet. In terms of the
			<lb />
			Lease Deed between Store One and Pragya, Store One commenced payment
			<lb />
			of monthly rent of `41,78,348.18/-with effect from 20.09.2007 to Pragya.
			<lb />
			7.4 Thereafter, on 08.08.2008, Pragya executed sale deeds -sixteen in
			<lb />
			number -in favour of Annapurna and Paliwal. By virtue of the sale deeds,
			<lb />
			Annapurna and Paliwal became joint owners of the property in question
			<lb />
			including the said premises. Although, Annapurna and Paliwal became
			<lb />
			owners of the property in question, Pragya continued to be liable for
			<lb />
			providing facilities/services.
			<lb />
			7.5 Store One claims that there were deficiencies in the services rendered
			<lb />
			and, therefore, Store One stopped the payment of Common Area
			<lb />
			Maintenance (CAM) charges from July, 2008. Thereafter, Store One issued
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			O.M.P. (COMM) 570/2016
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 4 of 14
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			a notice dated 05.08.2008 under Clause 7.2 of the Lease Deed to Pragya
			<lb />
			indicating certain deficiencies and called upon Pragya to rectify the same as
			<lb />
			per Clause 7.2 of the Lease Deed.
			<lb />
			7.6 On 01.09.2008 and 04.09.2008, Annapurna and Paliwal sent notices
			<lb />
			to Store One claiming rent for the said premises with effect from
			<lb />
			01.04.2008. Thereafter, on 08.09.2008, Store One sent a notice to Pragya
			<lb />
			alleging that Pragya had failed to cure the deficiencies as mentioned in the
			<lb />
			earlier notice dated 05.08.2008 sent under Clause 7.2 of the Lease Deed, and
			<lb />
			terminating the lease for the said premises.
			<lb />
			7.7 Thereafter, Store One also filed a petition (OMP No. 528/2008) under
			<lb />
			Section 9 of the Act before this Court. Annapurna and Paliwal filed
			<lb />
			applications (IA No.12982/2008 in OMP 528/2008) seeking impleadment in
			<lb />
			the Store One&apos;s petition under Section 9 of the Act. Subsequently, the said
			<lb />
			applications were withdrawn and Annapurna and Paliwal filed a suit (being
			<lb />
			CS (OS) 493/2009) in this Court for seeking recovery of the outstanding rent
			<lb />
			with effect from 01.04.2008.
			<lb />
			7.8 Store One claims that in compliance with the direction passed by this
			<lb />
			Court, it handed over the keys of the said premises to Annapurna and
			<lb />
			Paliwal on 22.03.2010. Thereafter, Pragya also filed a suit (CS(OS)
			<lb />
			270/2010) against Store One, Annapurna and Paliwal, inter alia, seeking
			<lb />
			recovery of a sum of 2,62,36,672/-on account of unpaid CAM charges and
			<lb />
			electricity charges up to 20.03.2012.
			<lb />
			7.9 In view of the aforesaid disputes, Store One filed a petition under
			<lb />
			Section 11 of the Act (Arb.P.86/2012) for appointment of an Arbitrator. In
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			O.M.P. (COMM) 570/2016
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 5 of 14
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			those proceedings, this Court -with the consent of the parties -appointed
			<lb />
			Justice Dr Mukundakam Sharma (Retired) as a sole arbitrator to adjudicate
			<lb />
			the disputes between the parties. Whereas Annapurna and Paliwal filed a
			<lb />
			statement of claims, inter alia, claiming rent for the period from April, 2008
			<lb />
			to September, 2012, Pragya filed a statement of claims, inter alia, claiming
			<lb />
			CAM charges from 08.08.2008 to 19.03.2012 from Store One, Annapurna
			<lb />
			and Paliwal and electricity charges up to 08.08.2008 from Store One. On
			<lb />
			the other hand, Store One, inter alia, claimed refund of the security deposit
			<lb />
			of 1,43,00,000/-.
			<lb />
			8.
			<lb />
			The Arbitrator held that the notice dated 05.08.2008 served by Store
			<lb />
			One calling upon Pragya to cure the deficiencies was vague and untenable.
			<lb />
			Further the notice of termination was not sent to Annapurna and Paliwal.
			<lb />
			Accordingly, the Arbitrator held that the termination of lease was not valid.
			<lb />
			The Arbitrator held that Annapurna and Paliwal were entitled to damages
			<lb />
			equivalent to rent for the unexpired period of the lock-in period but were
			<lb />
			also obligated to mitigate the damages by letting out the said premises;
			<lb />
			therefore, the Arbitrator limited the damages to rent equivalent to six
			<lb />
			months.
			<lb />
			9.
			<lb />
			The operative part of the impugned award is set out below:-
			<lb />
			&quot;10. CONCLUSIONS:
			<lb />
			10.1 In the light of the discussion, analysis and conclusion
			<lb />
			abovestated, all the issues as framed stand answered.
			<lb />
			10.2 Annapurna is entitled to the following amount
			<lb />
			from Store One:
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			O.M.P. (COMM) 570/2016
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 6 of 14
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			a.
			<lb />
			Rs. 2,67,52,283/-on account of rent from
			<lb />
			01.04.2008 upto 22.03.2010 along with interest @
			<lb />
			12% per annum w.e.f. 23.03.2010 upto the date of
			<lb />
			Award. Be it stated that the aforesaid sum is
			<lb />
			arrived at after deducting the security deposited
			<lb />
			by Store One and ordered to be paid back in terms
			<lb />
			of order contained herein.
			<lb />
			b. Rs. 1,11,56,145/-on account of damages
			<lb />
			equivalent to rent for a period of 6 months from
			<lb />
			22.03.2010.
			<lb />
			c.
			<lb />
			Future interest @ 12% per annum on the amounts,
			<lb />
			as calculated above, from the date of the Award
			<lb />
			till the date of realization.
			<lb />
			10.3 Paliwal is entitled to the following amount from
			<lb />
			Store One:
			<lb />
			a.
			<lb />
			Rs. 2,67,52,283/-on account of rent from
			<lb />
			01.04.2008 upto 22.03.2010 along with interest@
			<lb />
			12% per annum w.e.f. 23.03.2010 upto the date of
			<lb />
			the Award. Be it stated that the aforesaid sum is
			<lb />
			arrived at after deducting the security deposited
			<lb />
			by Store One and ordered to be paid back in terms
			<lb />
			of order contained herein.
			<lb />
			b. Rs. 1,11,56,145/-on account of damages
			<lb />
			equivalent to rent for a period of 6 months from
			<lb />
			22.03.2010.
			<lb />
			c.
			<lb />
			Future interest @ 12% per annum on the amounts,
			<lb />
			as calculated above, from the date of the Award
			<lb />
			till the date of realization.
			<lb />
			10.4 Pragya is entitled to the following amount from
			<lb />
			Store One:
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			O.M.P. (COMM) 570/2016
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 7 of 14
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			a.
			<lb />
			Rs. 27,63,199/-against Store One for Facility
			<lb />
			Management Services and Electricity Charges
			<lb />
			upto 07.08.2008 along with interest @ 12% per
			<lb />
			annum w.e.f. 08.08.2008 upto the date of Award.
			<lb />
			b. Rs.28,08,000/-against Store One for Facility
			<lb />
			Management Services from 08.08.2008 upto
			<lb />
			08.11.2008 along with interest @ 12% per annum
			<lb />
			w.e.f. 09.11.2008 upto the date of Award shall
			<lb />
			also be paid.
			<lb />
			c.
			<lb />
			Future interest @12% per annum on the amounts,
			<lb />
			as calculated above, from the date of the Award
			<lb />
			till the date of realization&quot;.
			<lb />
			Submissions
			<lb />
			10. Mr Rajiv Nayar, learned senior counsel appearing for Store One
			<lb />
			advanced contentions to assail the impugned award on, broadly, three fronts.
			<lb />
			First, he contended that the finding of the Arbitrator that notice issued by
			<lb />
			Store One terminating the Lease Deed was untenable on the ground that it
			<lb />
			was vague, was palpably erroneous and contrary to record. He contended
			<lb />
			that the notice dated 05.08.2008 was not vague inasmuch as Store One had
			<lb />
			specified the deficiencies. He submitted that the finding of the Arbitrator in
			<lb />
			this regard was wholly perverse and unsustainable.
			<lb />
			11. Secondly, he submitted that the Arbitrator had also held the
			<lb />
			termination of the lease to be invalid on the ground that the notice of
			<lb />
			termination had not been served on Annapurna and Paliwal, although they
			<lb />
			were owners of the property. He submitted that Paliwal and Annapurna
			<lb />
			were always aware of the notice of termination sent by Store One to Pragya
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			O.M.P. (COMM) 570/2016
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 8 of 14
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			and there was ample material on record to substantiate the same. He
			<lb />
			contended that this was also clear from the fact that Annapurna and Paliwal
			<lb />
			had sought impleadment in the petition filed by Store One under Section 9
			<lb />
			of the Act (OMP 528/2008).
			<lb />
			12. Lastly, he contended that the Arbitrator had grossly erred in awarding
			<lb />
			rent for a period of six months after Store One had admittedly handed over
			<lb />
			the possession of the said premises. He submitted that Arbitrator had
			<lb />
			assumed that six months was a reasonable time for Annapurna and Paliwal
			<lb />
			to find alternate tenant(s). However, there was no material or evidence on
			<lb />
			record on the basis of which the Arbitrator could have formed this view. He
			<lb />
			submitted that since the Arbitrator had accepted Store One&apos;s contention that
			<lb />
			after issuance of the notice of termination, Annapurna and Paliwal were
			<lb />
			under an obligation to mitigate the loss by leasing out the premises to
			<lb />
			another tenant, the Arbitrator could not have assumed an arbitrary period for
			<lb />
			Annapurna and Paliwal to do so. Since Paliwal and Annapurna had not
			<lb />
			taken steps to mitigate their damages, they would not be entitled to claim the
			<lb />
			same from Store One. He also submitted that there was no reason to
			<lb />
			arbitrarily fix 22.03.2010 as the date from which the period of six months
			<lb />
			would begin.
			<lb />
			13. I have heard the learned counsel for the parties at length.
			<lb />
			14. In order to appreciate the contention that the notice dated 05.08.2008
			<lb />
			issued by Store One was not vague, as held by the Arbitrator, it is necessary
			<lb />
			to refer to Clause 7.2 of the Lease Deed as well as to the notice issued by
			<lb />
			Store One.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			O.M.P. (COMM) 570/2016
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 9 of 14
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			15. Clause 7.2 of the Lease Deed reads as under:-
			<lb />
			&quot;7.2 During the Lock-in-period and the Term of the LEASE
			<lb />
			DEED, the LESSEE shall have the option to terminate this
			<lb />
			LEASE DEED with a prior written notice of thirty (30) days
			<lb />
			on the occurrence of any of the following events:
			<lb />
			7.2.1 The LESSEE is unable to run the operations of the
			<lb />
			STORE from the LEASED PREMISES due to LESSOR&apos;s
			<lb />
			default, act or omission to act.
			<lb />
			7.2.2 Any material breach of representations, warranties and
			<lb />
			other obligations and covenants of the LESSOR, which are not
			<lb />
			rectified or remedied within a period of thirty (30) days of the
			<lb />
			receipt of the notice by the LESSEE to the LESSOR; or
			<lb />
			7.2.3 The LESSOR being declared bankrupt or insolvent.
			<lb />
			The LESSOR shall be entitled to terminate the LEASE DEED
			<lb />
			in the event the LESSEE is declared bankrupt or insolvent.
			<lb />
			In any event of termination, the LESSOR shall be liable to
			<lb />
			refund the entire amount of Security Deposit to the LESSEE
			<lb />
			without any delay or demur simultaneous to handing over of
			<lb />
			possession of the LEASED PREMISES.&quot;
			<lb />
			16. The notice issued by Store One alleges that there had been frequent
			<lb />
			breakdown in the supply and efficacy of the facilities and amenities so
			<lb />
			provided to the Demised Premises and Common Areas. However, no
			<lb />
			specific instance had been mentioned. Mr Nayar has referred to paragraph 5
			<lb />
			of the said notice to contend that the specific deficiencies had been
			<lb />
			mentioned. Paragraph 5 of the said notice is set out below:-
			<lb />
			&quot;5. As you may be aware that we have already planned for the
			<lb />
			coming season and will soon be commencing the stock
			<lb />
			takeover very shortly. We have already made our business
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			O.M.P. (COMM) 570/2016
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 10 of 14
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			plans for our customers. However, with the problems now
			<lb />
			surfacing, it seems that a permanent solution to the same from
			<lb />
			your end are required. The problems for the Demised Premises
			<lb />
			Includes but are not limited to
			<lb />
			(a) Security misdemeanour,
			<lb />
			(b) AC and its standard temperature are not maintained at
			<lb />
			desired levies and require maintenance.
			<lb />
			(c) Dedicated Chillers not performing and requires
			<lb />
			maintenance.
			<lb />
			(d) Frequent breakdown of lifts and escalators.&quot;
			<lb />
			17. It is apparent from the above that the complaint made by Store One
			<lb />
			was general in nature and did not specify any particular covenant of the
			<lb />
			Lease Deed that had been breached. The deficiencies pointed out also lacked
			<lb />
			the necessary specifics. In view of the above, the Arbitrator&apos;s conclusion
			<lb />
			that the notice was vague and untenable cannot by any stretch be held to be
			<lb />
			perverse or patently illegal. The Arbitrator further held that the notice of
			<lb />
			termination dated 08.09.2008 was also untenable since the same had not
			<lb />
			been addressed to Annapurna and Paliwal. The Arbitrator had noticed that,
			<lb />
			admittedly, prior to the issuance of notice of termination dated 08.09.2008,
			<lb />
			Store One had received legal notices dated 01.09.2008 and 04.09.2008 on
			<lb />
			behalf of Annapurna and Paliwal respectively wherein Store One was
			<lb />
			informed that Annapurna and Paliwal had acquired the said premises from
			<lb />
			Pragya. Thus, the notice of termination was required to be addressed to
			<lb />
			Annapurna and Paliwal which was admittedly, not done. The conclusion of
			<lb />
			the Arbitrator that the termination of lease was thus invalid, is also not
			<lb />
			amenable to judicial review under Section 34 of the Act since the same is
			<lb />
			neither patently illegal nor perverse.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			O.M.P. (COMM) 570/2016
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 11 of 14
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			18. The contention that Annapurna and Paliwal were always aware of the
			<lb />
			termination of the lease and therefore the termination of the Lease Deed
			<lb />
			ought to be held valid is also not sustainable. Indisputably, Annapurna and
			<lb />
			Paliwal had, to the knowledge of Store One, stepped into the lease of Pragya
			<lb />
			and were the lessors at the material time when the notice of termination was
			<lb />
			issued by Store One. In view of this, issuance of a termination notice to
			<lb />
			persons other than the lessors cannot be accepted as a valid termination. This
			<lb />
			Court cannot accept the view expressed by the Arbitrator in this regard, to
			<lb />
			be patently illegal or perverse.
			<lb />
			19. At this stage, it is also necessary to state that the scope of judicial
			<lb />
			review under Section 34 of the Act is limited and the Court does not sit in
			<lb />
			appeal over the decision of the Arbitrator. Thus, unless Store One is able to
			<lb />
			establish that any of the grounds as specified under Section 34 of the Act are
			<lb />
			met, the impugned award cannot be set aside.
			<lb />
			20. Store One has sought to place its case within the scope of Section 34
			<lb />
			(2) (b) (ii) of the Act, that is, the impugned award is opposed to the Public
			<lb />
			Policy of India.
			<lb />
			21.
			<lb />
			It is relevant to observe that Explanation 1 to Section 34 (2) (b) (ii)
			<lb />
			of the Act further clarifies that an award would be in conflict with the Public
			<lb />
			Policy of India, only if, (i) the making of the award was induced or affected
			<lb />
			by fraud or corruption or was in violation of Section 75 or Section 81; or
			<lb />
			(ii) it is in contravention with the fundamental policy of Indian law; or (iii) it
			<lb />
			is in conflict with the most basic notions of morality or justice. In the present
			<lb />
			case, there is no allegation that the impugned award was affected by fraud or
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			O.M.P. (COMM) 570/2016
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 12 of 14
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			corruption or is in conflict with the most basic notions of morality or justice.
			<lb />
			And, this Court is not persuaded to accept that the impugned award is in
			<lb />
			contravention with the fundamental policy of Indian Law. Clearly, the
			<lb />
			expression &quot;Fundamental Policy of Indian Law&quot; does not mean violation of
			<lb />
			any particular statute but the policy of law on which the edifice of Indian
			<lb />
			law is based. Thus unless the award is in contravention with any of the
			<lb />
			fundamental principles of Indian law, the impugned award cannot be held to
			<lb />
			be in conflict with the Public Policy of India.
			<lb />
			22. It is also relevant to mention that by introduction of Explanation 2 to
			<lb />
			Section 34 (2) (b) (ii) of the Act, it has been further explained that the test as
			<lb />
			to whether there is a contravention of fundamental policy of Indian law
			<lb />
			would not entail a review on the merits of the dispute. In the present case,
			<lb />
			the submission that the conclusion of the Arbitrator, that the termination of
			<lb />
			lease by Store One was invalid, cannot by any stretch be held to be
			<lb />
			contravening a fundamental policy of Indian law.
			<lb />
			23. The contention that the Arbitrator had grossly erred in arbitrarily
			<lb />
			fixing the period of six months for award of damages is also wholly bereft of
			<lb />
			any merit. Having held that the termination of the lease was invalid, Store
			<lb />
			One would be liable to pay rent or damages equivalent to the rent for the
			<lb />
			entire lock-in period of 54 months as agreed under the Lease Deed.
			<lb />
			However, the Arbitrator did not make an award for the said period as he was
			<lb />
			of the view that Annapurna and Paliwal could have mitigated the damages
			<lb />
			by locating new tenant(s) and assessed six months to be reasonable for the
			<lb />
			said purpose. The contention that no damages could have been awarded
			<lb />
			since Annapurna and Paliwal had not taken steps to mitigate the same, is
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			O.M.P. (COMM) 570/2016
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 13 of 14
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			unmerited. The Arbitrator has merely restricted the award of damages by
			<lb />
			assessing the reasonable period required by Annapurna and Paliwal to find
			<lb />
			new tenant(s). This Court is not persuaded to accept that the said view is in
			<lb />
			any manner unreasonable, perverse or opposed to the Public Policy of India.
			<lb />
			24. The petition is, accordingly, dismissed. Pending application stands
			<lb />
			disposed of. No order as to costs.
			<lb />
			VIBHU BAKHRU, J
			<lb />
			DECEMBER 19, 2016
			<lb />
			RK
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			O.M.P. (COMM) 570/2016
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 14 of 14
			<lb />
		</page>
	</text>
</tei>
