<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb />
			* IN THE HIGH COURT OF DELHI AT NEW DELHI
			<lb />
			%
			<lb />
			Judgment reserved on: 28 th July, 2017
			<lb />
			Judgment delivered on: 31 st July, 2017
			<lb />
			+
			<lb />
			O.M.P. (I) (COMM.) 221/2017
			<lb />
			JETPUR SOMNATH TOLLWAYS LIMITED
			<lb />
			..... Petitioner
			<lb />
			Versus
			<lb />
			NATIONAL HIGHWAYS AUTHORITY OF INDIA ..... Respondent
			<lb />
			AND
			<lb />
			+
			<lb />
			O.M.P. (I) (COMM.) 227/2017
			<lb />
			PUNJAB NATIONAL BANK
			<lb />
			..... Petitioner
			<lb />
			Versus
			<lb />
			NATIONAL HIGHWAYS AUTHORITY
			<lb />
			OF INDIA &amp; ANR.
			<lb />
			..... Respondents
			<lb />
			Advocates who appeared in OMP(I) (COMM.) 221/2017
			<lb />
			For the Petitioner
			<lb />
			:
			<lb />
			Mr Kapil Sibal, Senior Advocate and Mr. Sandeep Sethi,
			<lb />
			Senior Advocate with Mr.Ajay Sondhi and Mr. Abhinav
			<lb />
			Dhingra, Advocates.
			<lb />
			For the Respondent
			<lb />
			:
			<lb />
			Mr Prag P.Tripathi, Senior Advocate with Ms Gunjan Sinha
			<lb />
			Jain, Mr Mukesh Kumar, Mr Rishabh Kapur and Ms Bhavana
			<lb />
			Duhoon, Advocates for NHAI/R-1.
			<lb />
			Advocates who appeared in OMP(I) (COMM.) 227/2017
			<lb />
			For the Petitioner
			<lb />
			:
			<lb />
			Mr. Rajiv Nayyar, Senior Advocate with Mr Mayank Grover,
			<lb />
			Ms Isha J. Kumar, Advocates.
			<lb />
			For the Respondent
			<lb />
			:
			<lb />
			Mr Prag P.Tripathi, Senior Advocate with Ms Gunjan Sinha
			<lb />
			Jain, Mr Mukesh Kumar, Mr Rishabh Kapur and Ms Bhavana
			<lb />
			Duhoon, Advocates for NHAI/R-1.
			<lb />
			Mr Kapil Sibal, Senior Advocate and Mr. Sandeep Sethi,
			<lb />
			Senior Advocate Mr. Ajay Sondhi and Mr. Abhinav Dhingra,
			<lb />
			Advocates for R-2.
			<lb />
		</front>
		<note place="footnote">
			OMP 221/2017 &amp; 227/2017
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 1 of 36
		</page>
		<front>
			OMP 221/2017 &amp; 227/2017
			<lb />
			Page 2 of 36
			<lb />
			CORAM:-
			<lb />
			HON&apos;BLE MR. JUSTICE SANJEEV SACHDEVA
			<lb />
			JUDGMENT
			<lb />
			31.07.2017
			<lb />
			SANJEEV SACHDEVA, J. (ORAL)
			<lb />
		</front>
		<body>
			O.M.P. (I) (COMM.) 221/2017 &amp; O.M.P. (I) (COMM.) 227/2017
			<lb />
			1.
			<lb />
			These are petitions filed under section 9 of the Arbitration and
			<lb />
			Conciliation Act, 1996 (hereinafter referred to as the Act).
			<lb />
			2.
			<lb />
			The petitioner, in OMP (I) (COMM.) 221/2017, JETPUR
			<lb />
			Somnath Tollways Limited (hereinafter referred to as &apos;JETPUR&apos; for
			<lb />
			short) seeks a direction against respondent No.1 -National Highways
			<lb />
			Authority of India (hereinafter referred to as NHAI for short) to
			<lb />
			deposit a sum of Rs. 359.19 crores being the balance part of the
			<lb />
			minimum Termination Payment into the Escrow Account.
			<lb />
			3.
			<lb />
			The petitioner in OMP (I) (COMM.) 227/2017, Punjab National
			<lb />
			Bank (hereinafter referred to as &apos;PNB&apos; for short) seeks a direction to
			<lb />
			NHAI to pay Rs. 374.51 crores into the Escrow Account for
			<lb />
			appropriation by the Lenders.
			<lb />
			4.
			<lb />
			NHAI had invited proposals for construction, operation and
			<lb />
			maintenance of Four Laning of JETPUR-Somnath Section of NH-8D
			<lb />
			for 127 kilometres in the State of Gujarat.
			<lb />
			5.
			<lb />
			Consortium comprising of IDFC Projects Limited and
			<lb />
			Expressways Berhad with IDFC Projects Limited as its lead member
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			OMP 221/2017 &amp; 227/2017
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 2 of 36
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			submitted its bid. The bid was accepted. On 13.09.2010, a letter of
			<lb />
			award was issued to the Consortium. The Consortium subsequently
			<lb />
			incorporated JETPUR for the purposes of undertaking the project.
			<lb />
			6.
			<lb />
			On 07.02.2011, a Concession Agreement was executed between
			<lb />
			JETPUR and NHAI.
			<lb />
			7.
			<lb />
			On 16.08.2011, PNB acting as the Lender&apos;s Representative and
			<lb />
			also being the Escrow Bank executed a Tripartite Escrow Agreement
			<lb />
			with JETPUR and NHAI. PNB, JETPUR and NHAI also executed a
			<lb />
			Substitution Agreement on 16.08.2011 providing for securing of the
			<lb />
			interest of Lenders through assignment, transfer, substitution of the
			<lb />
			concession to a nominated Company to be selected by PNB.
			<lb />
			8.
			<lb />
			On 19.08.2011, PNB along with the Consortium of
			<lb />
			Bank/Financial Institutions extended a term loan facility of Rs. 712
			<lb />
			crores to the JETPUR. The total project cost was stated to be Rs. 981
			<lb />
			crores. The amount in excess of the term loan was to be financed by
			<lb />
			JETPUR by raising equity from its shareholders.
			<lb />
			9.
			<lb />
			JETPUR thereafter commenced execution of the project.
			<lb />
			Disputes subsequently arose between NHAI and JETPUR with regard
			<lb />
			to the execution of the work of a particular stretch of land concerning
			<lb />
			inter alia the time period, the reasons for delay, the default and the
			<lb />
			cost overrun for execution of the work.
			<lb />
			10. On 13.05.2016, JETPUR issued a Cure Period Notice for
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			OMP 221/2017 &amp; 227/2017
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 3 of 36
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			Authority Default and requested NHAI to cure the defaults mentioned
			<lb />
			in their notice.
			<lb />
			11. On 10.08.2016, NHAI sent a notice of Intention to issue
			<lb />
			Termination Notice.
			<lb />
			12. On 05.09.2016, joint meeting between JETPUR, NHAI and
			<lb />
			Senior Lenders was held. As per JETPUR and PNB, in the said
			<lb />
			meeting, NHAI had represented that the Termination Payment to be
			<lb />
			made to the Escrow Account would be upwards of Rs.550 crores.
			<lb />
			13. JETPUR claims that on 26.09.2016 it confirmed that the debt
			<lb />
			outstanding to the Senior Lenders was Rs. 640.86 crores.
			<lb />
			14. On 18.10.2016, PNB convened a meeting of the Consortium of
			<lb />
			Lenders with JETPUR wherein all the Lenders agreed not to exercise
			<lb />
			their substitution rights on account of the commitment by NHAI to
			<lb />
			pay upwards of Rs. 550 crores as Termination Payment being 90% of
			<lb />
			the Debt Due.
			<lb />
			15. The Minutes of Meeting dated 05.09.2016 circulated by NHAI
			<lb />
			did not mention the figure of Rs. 550 crores as the minimum payment
			<lb />
			that NHAI had agreed to pay into the Escrow Account. Both JETPUR
			<lb />
			and PNB issued communications to NHAI contending that a
			<lb />
			representation had been made by NHAI that they shall be depositing
			<lb />
			upwards of Rs. 550 crores into the Escrow Account.
			<lb />
			16. On 10.11.2016, NHAI issued the Termination Notice under
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			OMP 221/2017 &amp; 227/2017
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 4 of 36
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			Clause 37.1.2 of the Concession Agreement and took possession and
			<lb />
			control of the project forthwith.
			<lb />
			17. Subsequent to the termination, on 11.11.2016, PNB called upon
			<lb />
			NHAI to confirm the Termination Amount before taking over the
			<lb />
			project.
			<lb />
			18. On 17.11.2016, JETPUR issued Notice of Termination with
			<lb />
			Authority Event of Default under Clause 37.2 of the Concession
			<lb />
			Agreement treating the Termination Notice of NHAI dated
			<lb />
			10.11.2016 as a repudiatory breach of the Concession Agreement.
			<lb />
			19. By another letter dated 17.11.2016, JETPUR demanded the
			<lb />
			Termination Payment under Clause 37.3.2 of the Concession
			<lb />
			Agreement in the sum of Rs. 945.83 crores along with claims for
			<lb />
			compensation, losses, damages in the sum of Rs. 475.33 crores.
			<lb />
			20. PNB, by its letters dated 21.01.2017, 04.03.2017 and
			<lb />
			22.03.2017, informed NHAI that on account of non-release of the
			<lb />
			Termination Payment by NHAI; JETPUR was not able to meet debt
			<lb />
			service obligation and the account of JETPUR was likely to become a
			<lb />
			Non Performing Asset (NPA). PNB further informed that as the
			<lb />
			project had been handed over to NHAI; JETPUR was no longer
			<lb />
			receiving any toll revenue and was accordingly not in a position to
			<lb />
			service the interest amount and the account of JETPUR was classified
			<lb />
			in SMA-2 category to become a NPA.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			OMP 221/2017 &amp; 227/2017
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 5 of 36
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			21. On 27.03.2017, NHAI released an amount of Rs. 217.59 crores
			<lb />
			(net of TDS) in the Escrow Account of JETPUR.
			<lb />
			22. NHAI, despite several requests from PNB and JETPUR refused
			<lb />
			to deposit any further amount in the Escrow Account leading to the
			<lb />
			filing of the present petition.
			<lb />
			23. The contention of the learned senior counsel for the JETPUR is
			<lb />
			that the entire project had to be funded by JETPUR from its own
			<lb />
			sources by raising loans as well as equity. NHAI was not to make any
			<lb />
			contribution. The recoveries were to be made from Toll Collection
			<lb />
			over the specified period.
			<lb />
			24. It is contended that as per the Concession Agreement, on
			<lb />
			petitioner completing at least 75% of the project, the Termination
			<lb />
			Clause with regard to Termination Payments was to get triggered.
			<lb />
			25. It is submitted that the Termination Clause in the Concession
			<lb />
			Agreement stipulated that in case of termination on account of
			<lb />
			Authority Default (NHAI&apos;s default), NHAI was to pay the Debt Due
			<lb />
			plus 150% of the Adjusted Equity. In case termination was on account
			<lb />
			of JETPUR&apos;s Default, NHAI had to make payment of 90% of the
			<lb />
			Debt due less insurance cover.
			<lb />
			26. It is contended that on termination, the minimum termination
			<lb />
			payment to be made by NHAI is 90% of the Debt Due (if termination
			<lb />
			is for default of JETPUR) and the maximum payment would be 100%
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			OMP 221/2017 &amp; 227/2017
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 6 of 36
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			of the Debt Due plus 150% of the Adjusted Equity (if termination is
			<lb />
			on account of NHAI&apos;s default). It is contended that even if assuming
			<lb />
			that the termination by NHAI is for default of JETPUR, NHAI would
			<lb />
			be required to pay into the Escrow Account 90% of the Debt Due,
			<lb />
			which would amount to over Rs. 576 crores.
			<lb />
			27. Learned senior counsel for JETPUR submits that this is so
			<lb />
			stipulated because there is no financial burden on NHAI for execution
			<lb />
			of the work and the entire project has to be executed by JETPUR from
			<lb />
			its own sources and on termination, the entire project is to be taken
			<lb />
			over by NHAI including the right to Toll Collection.
			<lb />
			28. It is contended that if NHAI were permitted to take over the
			<lb />
			project without any payment, then NHAI would stand to benefit for
			<lb />
			the entire work already executed by JETPUR for its own sources,
			<lb />
			which would include funds sourced by borrowing from Banks and
			<lb />
			Financial Institutions. It is submitted that on termination NHAI has
			<lb />
			got the entire project, which is nearly complete, virtually free of cost
			<lb />
			and the entire cost has been borne by JETPUR from its own sources
			<lb />
			and from loans.
			<lb />
			29. It is contended that since the Debt Due is about Rs. 640 crores,
			<lb />
			NHAI is liable to pay Rs.576.77 crores (being 90% of Debt Due of
			<lb />
			Rs.640.86 crores : reference PNB letter dated 16.11.2016). As NHAI
			<lb />
			has paid a sum of Rs.217.6 crores, NHAI is liable to pay the balance
			<lb />
			sum of Rs.359.19 crores towards minimum Termination Payment
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			OMP 221/2017 &amp; 227/2017
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 7 of 36
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			under the Concession Agreement.
			<lb />
			30. It is contended that NHAI has incorrectly sought to adjust
			<lb />
			recoveries from JETPUR from the Termination Payment. It is
			<lb />
			contended that NHAI is precluded from adjusting any amount as the
			<lb />
			claims are yet to be adjudicated.
			<lb />
			31. Reliance is placed on the judgment of the Supreme Court in
			<lb />
			INDIAN OIL CORPORATION LIMITED VERSUS SPS ENGG. LIMITED,
			<lb />
			(2011) 3 SCC 507 to contend that disputed claims cannot be adjusted
			<lb />
			from crystallised liability.
			<lb />
			32. It is contended that whether the breach, leading to termination,
			<lb />
			is of NHAI or of JETPUR, is an issue which would be decided in
			<lb />
			terms of the Arbitration Clause and till it is decided, no recovery or
			<lb />
			deduction can be made by NHAI. NHAI being one of the parties
			<lb />
			alleging breach on the part of JETPUR, cannot itself proceed further
			<lb />
			to decide that the breach is of JETPUR and accordingly make
			<lb />
			recoveries.
			<lb />
			33. Reliance is placed on the decision of the Supreme Court in
			<lb />
			J.G.ENGINEERS (P) LTD VERSUS UNION OF INDIA, (2011) 5 SCC 758
			<lb />
			to contend that adjudication of breach can only be by a court or a
			<lb />
			tribunal and not by the alleged aggrieved party. It is further
			<lb />
			contended that liquidated damages cannot be permitted to be deducted
			<lb />
			by NHAI at this stage and NHAI, without any demur, has to make the
			<lb />
			termination payment.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			OMP 221/2017 &amp; 227/2017
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 8 of 36
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			34. Learned senior counsel for JETPUR submits that pending
			<lb />
			adjudication of disputes, JETPUR is willing to be put to terms and is
			<lb />
			willing to secure the entire amount being paid by NHAI into the
			<lb />
			Escrow Account by way of an unconditional Bank Guarantee.
			<lb />
			35. Reliance is further placed on the judgment in FORBES
			<lb />
			FACILITY SERVICES PRIVATE LIMITED VERSUS G.B.PANT HOSPITAL ,
			<lb />
			in OMP No.129/2015 decided on 18.02.2015, MAFATLAL INDUSTRIES
			<lb />
			LIMITED &amp; ANOTHER VERSUS MAHANAGAR TELEPHONE NIGAM
			<lb />
			LIMITED : 2002 (64) DRJ 94, VALUE SOURCE MERCANTILE LIMITED
			<lb />
			VERSUS SPAN MECHNOTRONIX LIMITED (2014) 143 DRJ 505,
			<lb />
			SIMPLEX INFRASTRUCTURES LTD. V. NATIONAL HIGHWAYS AUTHORITY
			<lb />
			OF INDIA, ILR (2011) Delhi 274, AJAY SINGH VERSUS KAL AIRWAYS
			<lb />
			PRIVATE LIMITED FAO(OS)(COMM) 62/2016 decided by the
			<lb />
			Division bench of this court dated 03.07.2017 to contend that under
			<lb />
			section 9 of the Act it is just and convenient to direct NHAI to deposit
			<lb />
			the balance termination payment in the Escrow Account.
			<lb />
			36. Learned senior counsel appearing for PNB submits that apart
			<lb />
			from the Concession Agreement, NHAI also executed Tripartite
			<lb />
			Escrow Agreement and Substitution Agreement on 16.08.20911.
			<lb />
			37. It is submitted that NHAI is also bound by the terms of the
			<lb />
			Escrow Agreement. In terms of the Escrow Agreement, NHAI has to
			<lb />
			deposit into the Escrow Account the Termination Payment as and
			<lb />
			when it becomes due and payable. It is contended that NHAI has no
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			OMP 221/2017 &amp; 227/2017
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 9 of 36
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			discretion in the matter and the moment termination payment becomes
			<lb />
			due and payable, the same has to be deposited in the Escrow Account.
			<lb />
			38. It is contended that the NHAI has no discretion in the matter
			<lb />
			and cannot first adjust its claim and then make deposit. NHAI has to
			<lb />
			first deposit the amount, then raise disputes, and seeks settlement of
			<lb />
			its claims against JETPUR in accordance with the Concession
			<lb />
			Agreement.
			<lb />
			39. It is further contended that the Substitution Agreement
			<lb />
			empowers PNB to substitute a concessionaire in case of a default. It
			<lb />
			is submitted that PNB and the Senior Lenders decided not exercise the
			<lb />
			power of substitution because in the meeting held on 05.09.2016,
			<lb />
			NHAI had assured that it shall deposit upwards of Rs. 550 crores in
			<lb />
			the Escrow Account.
			<lb />
			40. It is contended that the Escrow Agreement specifically
			<lb />
			stipulates that upon termination of the Concession Agreement, all
			<lb />
			amounts standing to the credit of the Escrow Account are to be
			<lb />
			appropriated and adjusted in terms of Clause 4.2 of the Escrow
			<lb />
			Agreement.
			<lb />
			41. It is submitted that withdrawal of 90% of the Debt Due is at a
			<lb />
			priority only after payment of all taxes in respect of the project and is
			<lb />
			at a higher priority to all other claims including the claim of NHAI for
			<lb />
			payments and damages due and payable to it by the Concessionaire
			<lb />
			pursuant to the Concession Agreement.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			OMP 221/2017 &amp; 227/2017
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 10 of 36
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			42. It is submitted that since payment of 90% of the Debt Due is at
			<lb />
			a higher priority than the claims of NHAI against JETPUR even
			<lb />
			towards damages and payments due under the Concession Agreement,
			<lb />
			NHAI cannot withhold any payment or make any recoveries from the
			<lb />
			stipulated Termination Payment.
			<lb />
			43. It is contended that money lent for the project has been
			<lb />
			earmarked for disbursal for infrastructure project and cannot be
			<lb />
			withheld on account of any dispute between the JETPUR and NHAI.
			<lb />
			It is contended that being public money, on recovery of the same, it is
			<lb />
			to be utilized for other infrastructure projects and Bank cannot be
			<lb />
			dragged into the inter se disputes between the JETPUR and NHAI.
			<lb />
			44. It is contended that a claim for damages for breach of contract
			<lb />
			is not a claim for a sum presently due and payable and NHAI cannot
			<lb />
			recover the same from the termination payment. Reliance is placed on
			<lb />
			the judgment in GANGOTRI ENTERPRISES LTD. V. UNION OF INDIA,
			<lb />
			(2016) 11 SCC 720.
			<lb />
			45. It is submitted that court has inherent powers to pass orders as
			<lb />
			may appear to the court to be just and convenient to prevent the ends
			<lb />
			of justice from being defeated. Reliance is placed on the judgment in
			<lb />
			S. HARINDER SINGH VERSU S.NIRMAL SINGH &amp; ORS. 2009(113) DRJ
			<lb />
			784(DB)
			<lb />
			46. Per contra, at the outset, learned senior counsel appearing for
			<lb />
			NHAI disputes that any assurance was given by NHAI, in the Meeting
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			OMP 221/2017 &amp; 227/2017
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 11 of 36
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			held on 05.09.2016, that it would deposit upwards of Rs. 550/-crores.
			<lb />
			47. It is further contended that the petitioners are seeking to enforce
			<lb />
			the terms of the Contract by way of a petition under Section 9 of the
			<lb />
			Act. It is contended that what petitioners are seeking are orders
			<lb />
			analogous to Order XII Rule 6 of the Code of Civil Procedure (CPC),
			<lb />
			i.e. passing of a judgment on admission.
			<lb />
			48. It is contended that in a petition under Section 9 of the Act,
			<lb />
			Court cannot pass an order directing payment of even admitted
			<lb />
			amount.
			<lb />
			49. Reliance is placed on the decision in SHIN SATELLITE PUBLIC
			<lb />
			CO. LTD. V. JAIN STUDIOS LIMITED, (2008) 153 DLT 604; NILU
			<lb />
			HANDICRAFTS VERSUS DOLPHIN MART LIMITED, 2009 SCC Online
			<lb />
			Del 2659; ORISSA MANGANESE AND MINERALS PVT. LTD.VERSUS
			<lb />
			SYNERGY ISPAT PRIVATE LIMITED, (2014) 16 SCC 654 and RADHIKA
			<lb />
			AUTOMOBILES PRIVATE LIMITED VERSUS MARUTI UDYOG LIMITED &amp;
			<lb />
			ANOTHER, 113(2004) DLT 837.
			<lb />
			50. It is contended that Section 9 of the Act is for the purposes of
			<lb />
			securing the subject matter of the dispute and petitioners are not
			<lb />
			seeking security but in fact are seeking execution of the Contract and
			<lb />
			an interim award, which is not permissible under Section 9 of the Act.
			<lb />
			51. It is further contended that the Total Project Cost was stipulated
			<lb />
			as Rs. 828 crores and the cost of un-finished construction work is
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			OMP 221/2017 &amp; 227/2017
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 12 of 36
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			Rs.106.6 crores. Accordingly, the adjusted Total Project Cost, comes
			<lb />
			to Rs. 721.4 crores. It is contended that JETPUR had to have equity
			<lb />
			contribution of 27.42% and a debt of 72.58%. It is submitted that
			<lb />
			72.58% of Rs. 721.4 crores implies that the total Debt exposures
			<lb />
			could not be more than Rs. 523.59 crores. It is submitted that
			<lb />
			outstanding Debt Due thus becomes Rs. 522.88 crores, 90% of which
			<lb />
			comes to Rs. 470.59 crores. It is submitted that the NHAI has to
			<lb />
			make recoveries from JETPUR of Rs. 242.42 crores. The net
			<lb />
			termination payment after adjustment and recoveries comes to
			<lb />
			Rs.228.17 crores, out of which Rs. 222.03 crores have been paid by
			<lb />
			NHAI leaving a balance of Rs. 6.14 crores, which NHAI is willing to
			<lb />
			pay.
			<lb />
			52. It is contended that the Debt equity ratio was 72.58 : 27.42%.
			<lb />
			Under the Concession Agreement, the Bank, was to finance only the
			<lb />
			debt element and not the equity contribution element and in case
			<lb />
			JETPUR had got financing for the equity then NHAI is not liable to
			<lb />
			make payment for the same. It is further submitted that since there is
			<lb />
			a dispute, it is for the Arbitrators to adjudicate the same.
			<lb />
			53. It is submitted that though this debt equity ratio is not part of
			<lb />
			the Concession Agreement, the Financing Agreements have been
			<lb />
			specifically made part of the Concession Agreements and the
			<lb />
			Financing Agreements specifically refers to Total Project Cost as
			<lb />
			Rs.981 crores and the Project Equity Capital out of the same as
			<lb />
			Rs.269 crores and Facility as Rs. 712 crores, which shows that the
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			OMP 221/2017 &amp; 227/2017
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 13 of 36
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			debt to equity ratio is 72.58: 27.42.
			<lb />
			54. It is further contended that respondents cannot rely on the
			<lb />
			admissions contained in Annexure R -6 to the counter-affidavit in
			<lb />
			isolation. It is contended that Annexure R -6, wherein the NHAI has
			<lb />
			stated that outstanding Debt Due is Rs. 522.88 crores and has made
			<lb />
			recoveries of Rs. 242.42 crores cannot be read in isolation and has to
			<lb />
			be read as a whole. It is submitted that the said calculation when read
			<lb />
			as a whole shows that NHAI has to make recoveries. Reference is
			<lb />
			made to the judgment in HAJI C.H.MOHAMMAD KOYA VERSUS
			<lb />
			T.K.S.M.A.MUTHUKOYA, (1979) 2 SCC 8.
			<lb />
			55. To resolve the controversy, we would need to examine some of
			<lb />
			the relevant clauses of the Concession Agreement executed between
			<lb />
			NHAI and JETPUR and the tripartite Escrow Agreement and the
			<lb />
			Substitution Agreement executed between NHAI, JETPUR and PNB.
			<lb />
			56. The relevant clauses of the Concession agreement with regard
			<lb />
			to termination payment read as under:
			<lb />
			37.3 Termination Payment
			<lb />
			37.3.1 Upon Termination on account of a Concessionaire
			<lb />
			Default during the Operation Period, the Authority shall
			<lb />
			pay to the Concessionaire, by way of Termination
			<lb />
			Payment, an amount equal to 90% (ninety per cent) of
			<lb />
			the Debt Due less Insurance Cover; provided that if any
			<lb />
			insurance claims forming part of the Insurance Cover
			<lb />
			are not admitted and paid, then 80% (eighty per cent) of
			<lb />
			such unpaid claims shall be included in the computation
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			OMP 221/2017 &amp; 227/2017
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 14 of 36
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			of Debt Due. For the avoidance of doubt, the
			<lb />
			Concessionaire hereby
			<lb />
			acknowledges that no
			<lb />
			Termination Payment shall be due or payable on account
			<lb />
			of a Concessionaire Default occurring prior to COD.
			<lb />
			37.3.2 Upon Termination on account of an Authority
			<lb />
			Default, the Authority shall pay to the Concessionaire, by
			<lb />
			way of Termination Payment, an amount equal to:
			<lb />
			(a) Debt Due; and
			<lb />
			(b) 150% (one hundred and fifty per cent) of the
			<lb />
			Adjusted Equity.
			<lb />
			37.3.3 Termination Payment shall become due and
			<lb />
			payable to the Concessionaire within 15 (fifteen) days of
			<lb />
			a demand being made by the Concessionaire to the
			<lb />
			Authority with the necessary particulars, and in the event
			<lb />
			of any delay, the Authority shall pay interest at a rate
			<lb />
			equal to 3% (three per cent) above the Bank Rate on the
			<lb />
			amount of Termination Payment remaining unpaid;
			<lb />
			provided that such delay shall not exceed 90 (ninety)
			<lb />
			days. For the avoidance of doubt, it is expressly agreed
			<lb />
			that Termination Payment shall constitute full discharge
			<lb />
			by the Authority of its payment obligations in respect
			<lb />
			thereof hereunder.
			<lb />
			37.3.4 The Concessionaire expressly agrees that
			<lb />
			Termination Payment under this Article 37 shall
			<lb />
			constitute a full and final settlement of all claims of the
			<lb />
			Concessionaire on account of Termination of this
			<lb />
			Agreement for any reason whatsoever and that the
			<lb />
			Concessionaire or any shareholder thereof shall not have
			<lb />
			any further right or claim under any law, treaty,
			<lb />
			convention, contract or otherwise.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			OMP 221/2017 &amp; 227/2017
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 15 of 36
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			37.4 Other rights and obligations of the Authority
			<lb />
			Upon Termination for any reason whatsoever, the
			<lb />
			Authority shall:
			<lb />
			(a) be deemed to have taken possession and control of
			<lb />
			the Project Highway forthwith;
			<lb />
			(b) take possession and control of all materials,
			<lb />
			stores, implements, construction plants and equipment on
			<lb />
			or about the Site;
			<lb />
			(c) be entitled to restrain the Concessionaire and any
			<lb />
			person claiming through or under the Concessionaire
			<lb />
			from entering upon the Site or any part of the Project;
			<lb />
			(d) require the Concessionaire to comply with the
			<lb />
			Divestment Requirements set forth in Clause 38.1; and
			<lb />
			(e) succeed upon election by the Authority, without
			<lb />
			the• necessity of any further action by the
			<lb />
			Concessionaire, to the interests of the Concessionaire
			<lb />
			under such of the Project Agreements as the Authority
			<lb />
			may in its discretion deem appropriate, and shall upon
			<lb />
			such election be liable to the Contractors only for
			<lb />
			compensation accruing and becoming due and payable to
			<lb />
			them under the terms of their respective Project
			<lb />
			Agreements from and after the date the Authority elects
			<lb />
			to succeed to the interests of the Concessionaire. For the
			<lb />
			avoidance of doubt, the Concessionaire acknowledges
			<lb />
			and agrees that all sums claimed by such Contractors as
			<lb />
			being due and owing for works and services performed
			<lb />
			or accruing on account of any act, omission or event
			<lb />
			prior to such date shall constitute debt between the
			<lb />
			Concessionaire and such Contractors, and the Authority
			<lb />
			shall not in any manner be liable for such sums. It is
			<lb />
			further agreed that in the event the Authority elects to
			<lb />
			cure any outstanding defaults under such Project
			<lb />
			Agreements, the amount expended by the Authority for
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			OMP 221/2017 &amp; 227/2017
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 16 of 36
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			this purpose shall be deducted from the Termination
			<lb />
			Payment.
			<lb />
			(underlining supplied)
			<lb />
			57. Clause 37.3 of the Concession Agreement makes it clear that
			<lb />
			upon Termination on account of JETPUR&apos;S Default during the
			<lb />
			Operation Period, NHAI has to pay to JETPUR, by way of
			<lb />
			Termination Payment, an amount equal to 90% (ninety per cent) of
			<lb />
			the Debt Due less Insurance Cover and upon Termination on account
			<lb />
			of NHAI&apos;s default, NHAI has to pay to JETPUR, by way of
			<lb />
			Termination Payment, an amount equal to the Debt Due plus 150% of
			<lb />
			the Adjusted Equity.
			<lb />
			58. &quot;Termination Payment&quot; has been defined by the Concession
			<lb />
			Agreement to mean &quot;the amount payable by the Authority to the
			<lb />
			Concessionaire upon Termination and may consist of payments on
			<lb />
			account of and restricted to the Debt Due and Adjusted Equity, as the
			<lb />
			case may be, which form part of the Total Project Cost in accordance
			<lb />
			with the provisions of this Agreement; provided that the amount
			<lb />
			payable in respect of any Debt Due expressed in foreign currency
			<lb />
			shall be computed at the Reference Exchange Rate for conversion into
			<lb />
			the relevant foreign currency as on the date of Termination Payment.
			<lb />
			For the avoidance of doubt, it is agreed that within a period of 60
			<lb />
			(sixty) days from COD, the Concessionaire shall notify to the
			<lb />
			Authority, the Total Project Cost as on COD and its disaggregation
			<lb />
			between Debt Due and Equity, and only the amounts so conveyed
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			OMP 221/2017 &amp; 227/2017
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 17 of 36
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			shall form the basis of computing Termination Payment, and it is
			<lb />
			further agreed that in the event such disaggregation is not notified to
			<lb />
			the Authority, Equity shall be deemed to be the amount arrived at by
			<lb />
			subtracting Debt Due from Total Project Cost.&quot;
			<lb />
			59. &quot;Debt Due&quot; has been defined to mean the aggregate of inter
			<lb />
			alia the sum expressed in Indian Rupees outstanding, on the Transfer
			<lb />
			Date, of the principal amount of the debt provided by the Senior
			<lb />
			Lenders under the Financing Agreements for financing the Total
			<lb />
			Project Cost but excluding any part of the principal that had fallen due
			<lb />
			for repayment two years prior to the Transfer Date;
			<lb />
			60. The &quot;Total Project Cost&quot; has been defined to mean the lowest
			<lb />
			of:
			<lb />
			(a) the capital cost of the Project, less Equity Support as set
			<lb />
			forth in the Financial Package;
			<lb />
			(b) the actual capital cost of the Project upon completion of
			<lb />
			Four-Laning of the Project Highway less Equity Support;
			<lb />
			and
			<lb />
			(c) a sum of Rs. 828.00 crore (Rupees Eight Hundred and
			<lb />
			Twenty Eight crore ), less Equity Support;
			<lb />
			provided that in the event of Termination, the Total Project
			<lb />
			Cost shall be deemed to be modified to the extent of variation in
			<lb />
			WPI or Reference Exchange Rate occurring in respect of
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			OMP 221/2017 &amp; 227/2017
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 18 of 36
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			Adjusted Equity and Debt Due, as the case may be, in
			<lb />
			accordance with the provisions of this Agreement; provided
			<lb />
			further that in the event WPI increases, on an average, by more
			<lb />
			than 6% (six per cent) per annum for the period between the
			<lb />
			date hereof and COD, the Parties shall meet, as soon as
			<lb />
			reasonably practicable, and agree upon revision of the amount
			<lb />
			hereinbefore specified such that the effect of increase in WPI, in
			<lb />
			excess of such 6% (six per cent), is reflected in the Total
			<lb />
			Project Cost.
			<lb />
			61. The contention of JETPUR is that the Total Project cost was
			<lb />
			subsequently increased, however for the purposes of the controversy
			<lb />
			at hand we need not examine the same and assume the total project
			<lb />
			cost to be the lowest of the three i.e. Rs. 828 Crores.
			<lb />
			62. The Debt extended to JETPUR by PNB is over Rs. 712 Crores
			<lb />
			and the balance outstanding as of the date of termination by NHAI is
			<lb />
			Rs. 640.86 Crores.
			<lb />
			63. Both NHAI and JETPUR have exercised their option to
			<lb />
			termination. Each alleging default of the other. If termination is on
			<lb />
			account of it is default of JETPUR then NHAI is liable to pay 90% of
			<lb />
			the Debt Due and if the termination is on account of default of NHAI,
			<lb />
			NHAI is to pay 100% of the Debt Due plus 150% of the Adjusted
			<lb />
			Equity.
			<lb />
			64. This, to my mind, has been stipulated because, under clause
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			OMP 221/2017 &amp; 227/2017
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 19 of 36
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			37.4 of the Concession Agreement, upon Termination for any reason
			<lb />
			whatsoever, NHAI is deemed to have taken possession and control of
			<lb />
			the Project Highway forthwith and NHAI upon its election succeeds
			<lb />
			to the interests of JETPUR under such of the Project Agreements as
			<lb />
			NHAI may in its discretion deem appropriate.
			<lb />
			65. The sequitur of the above stipulation is that NHAI which has no
			<lb />
			financial liability for the execution of the project would come into
			<lb />
			possession of the Project Highway, which would be at least 75%
			<lb />
			complete, and also succeed to all rights of JETPUR, including Toll
			<lb />
			Collection.
			<lb />
			66. The stipulation in the Concession Agreement is that the
			<lb />
			Concessionaire would be entitled to obtain finance facility. The
			<lb />
			Concession agreement gives a comfort to the lenders, that their debt is
			<lb />
			secured in as much as on termination for any reason whatsoever, they
			<lb />
			are assured that at least 90% of their debt outstanding would be
			<lb />
			deposited in the Escrow Account by NHAI.
			<lb />
			67. Clauses 3.2 and 4.2 of the tripartite Escrow Agreement
			<lb />
			stipulate as under:
			<lb />
			3.2 Deposits by the Authority
			<lb />
			The Authority agrees and undertakes that, as and when
			<lb />
			due and payable, it shall deposit into and/or credit the
			<lb />
			Escrow Account with:
			<lb />
			(a) Grant and any other monies disbursed by the.
			<lb />
			Authority to the Concessionaire;
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			OMP 221/2017 &amp; 227/2017
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 20 of 36
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			(b) Revenue Shortfall Loan;
			<lb />
			(c) all Fee collected by the Authority in exercise of its
			<lb />
			rights under the Concession Agreement; and
			<lb />
			(d) Termination Payments:
			<lb />
			Provided that, notwithstanding the provisions of Clause 4.1.1,
			<lb />
			the Authority shall be entitled to appropriate from the aforesaid
			<lb />
			amounts, any Concession Fee due and payable to it by the
			<lb />
			Concessionaire and the balance remaining shall be deposited
			<lb />
			into the Escrow Account.
			<lb />
			4.2 Withdrawals upon Termination
			<lb />
			Upon Termination of the Concession Agreement, all
			<lb />
			amounts standing to the credit of the Escrow Account
			<lb />
			shall, notwithstanding anything in this Agreement, be
			<lb />
			appropriated and dealt with in the following order:
			<lb />
			(a) all taxes due and payable by the Concessionaire
			<lb />
			for and in respect of the Project Highway;
			<lb />
			(b) 90% (ninety per cent) of Debt Due excluding
			<lb />
			Subordinated Debt;
			<lb />
			(c)
			<lb />
			outstanding Concession Fee;
			<lb />
			(d) all payments and Damages certified by the
			<lb />
			Authority as due and payable to it by the
			<lb />
			Concessionaire pursuant to the Concession
			<lb />
			Agreement, including {Premium,} repayment of
			<lb />
			Revenue Shortfall Loan and any claims in
			<lb />
			connection with or arising out of Termination;
			<lb />
			(e) retention and payments arising out of, or in
			<lb />
			relation to, liability for defects and deficiencies set
			<lb />
			forth in Article 39 of the concession Agreement;
			<lb />
			(f)
			<lb />
			outstanding Debt Service including the balance of
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			OMP 221/2017 &amp; 227/2017
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 21 of 36
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			Debt Due;
			<lb />
			(g) outstanding Subordinated Debt;
			<lb />
			(h) incurred or accrued O&amp;M Expenses;
			<lb />
			(i)
			<lb />
			any other payments required to be made under the
			<lb />
			Concession Agreement; and
			<lb />
			(j)
			<lb />
			balance, if any, in accordance with the instructions
			<lb />
			of the Concessionaire:
			<lb />
			Provided that the disbursements specified in Sub-clause
			<lb />
			(j) of this Clause 4.2 shall undertaken only after the
			<lb />
			Vesting Certificate has been issued by the Authority.
			<lb />
			68. In terms of clause 3.2 of the Escrow Agreement, NHAI has to
			<lb />
			deposit in the Escrow Account the Termination Payment as soon as
			<lb />
			the same becomes due and payable. In terms of Clause 4.2, after
			<lb />
			payment of taxes due and payable by JETPUR, the Lenders have the
			<lb />
			right to appropriate 90% of the Debt Due excluding Subordinate Debt.
			<lb />
			69.
			<lb />
			Clause 36.4 of the tripartite Substitution Agreement provides
			<lb />
			for Substitution of Concessionaire and stipulates that At any time
			<lb />
			during the period of Suspension, the Lenders&apos; Representative, on
			<lb />
			behalf of Senior Lenders, shall be entitled to substitute the
			<lb />
			Concessionaire under and in accordance with the Substitution
			<lb />
			Agreement, and upon receipt of notice there under from the Lenders&apos;
			<lb />
			Representative, the Authority shall withhold Termination for a period
			<lb />
			not exceeding 180 (one hundred and eighty) days from the date of
			<lb />
			Suspension, and any extension thereof under Clause 36.1, for
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			OMP 221/2017 &amp; 227/2017
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 22 of 36
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			enabling the Lenders&apos; Representative to exercise its rights of
			<lb />
			substitution on behalf of Senior Lenders.
			<lb />
			70. PNB in terms of clause 36.4 was entitled to substitute the
			<lb />
			Concessionaire and if this right would have been exercised, NHAI
			<lb />
			would have had to withhold Termination for a period of 180 days.
			<lb />
			PNB did not exercise this right. As per PNB, this right was not
			<lb />
			exercised because of an assurance by NHAI that it would make the
			<lb />
			Termination Payment in excess of Rs. 550 Crores. However, this is
			<lb />
			disputed by NHAI. In my view, the alleged assurance would make no
			<lb />
			difference to the rights and liabilities of the parties for the purposes of
			<lb />
			these petitions.
			<lb />
			71.
			<lb />
			It is an admitted position that the contract has been terminated.
			<lb />
			It is terminated by both NHAI and JETPUR alleging breach of the
			<lb />
			other. There is a dispute as to who is at fault leading to the termination
			<lb />
			but that would not affect the liability of NHAI to deposit, the Debt
			<lb />
			Due in the escrow account, it would only affect the quantum of the
			<lb />
			liability of NHAI to deposit the Debt Due in the escrow account. It
			<lb />
			would range between 90% to 100% of the Debt Due.
			<lb />
			72. Admittedly, the outstanding Debt Due on termination was
			<lb />
			640.86 crores (i.e. 621.45 crores towards principal and balance
			<lb />
			towards interest). 90% of the Debt Due is 576.774 Crores.
			<lb />
			73. NHAI does not dispute its liability under the agreements to
			<lb />
			deposit an amount towards the Debt Due in the Escrow account. The
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			OMP 221/2017 &amp; 227/2017
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 23 of 36
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			dispute is with regard to the quantum. It has admittedly deposited Rs.
			<lb />
			222.03 in the Escrow Account. As per the calculation of NHAI,
			<lb />
			balance payable is 6.14 Crores, which they have offered to deposit in
			<lb />
			the Escrow Account.
			<lb />
			74. NHAI has explained the calculation of the outstanding amount
			<lb />
			as under:
			<lb />
			S.No. Particulars
			<lb />
			Amount in
			<lb />
			INR / Crores
			<lb />
			1.
			<lb />
			NHAI Total Project Cost (TPC)
			<lb />
			828.00
			<lb />
			2.
			<lb />
			Less
			<lb />
			Cost
			<lb />
			of
			<lb />
			unfinished
			<lb />
			construction (details enclosed as
			<lb />
			Appendix-I)
			<lb />
			106.60
			<lb />
			3.
			<lb />
			Adjusted TPC
			<lb />
			721.40
			<lb />
			4.
			<lb />
			Debt (72.58% of adjusted TPC)
			<lb />
			523.59
			<lb />
			5.
			<lb />
			Debt repaid
			<lb />
			0.71
			<lb />
			6.
			<lb />
			Outstanding Debt Due
			<lb />
			522.88
			<lb />
			7.
			<lb />
			Accrued Interest of Rs. 19.4 Cr
			<lb />
			(Wilful default, hence no payment)
			<lb />
			Nil
			<lb />
			8.
			<lb />
			90% of debt due
			<lb />
			470.59
			<lb />
			9.
			<lb />
			Less Recoveries (details enclosed
			<lb />
			as Appendix-II
			<lb />
			242.42
			<lb />
			10.
			<lb />
			Net Termination Payment
			<lb />
			228.17
			<lb />
			11.
			<lb />
			Paid by NHAI to Concessionaire
			<lb />
			222.03
			<lb />
			12.
			<lb />
			Balance to be paid
			<lb />
			6.14
			<lb />
			75. There are three broad heads under which NHAI has made
			<lb />
			deductions. First of all , it has made an adjustment in the Total Project
			<lb />
			Cost (TPC) and excluded the alleged cost of unfinished construction
			<lb />
			(serial # 2 above). Secondly, it has made an adjustment in the Debt by
			<lb />
			taking the Debt as 72.58% of the adjusted TPC. This adjustment has
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			OMP 221/2017 &amp; 227/2017
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 24 of 36
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			been made on account of its contention that the debt and equity ratio
			<lb />
			to be maintained by JETPUR was to be 72.58 : 27.42 (serial # 4
			<lb />
			above). Thirdly, adjustment has been made on account of alleged
			<lb />
			recoveries to be made by NHAI from JETPUR (serial # 9 above).
			<lb />
			76. In my view, NHAI has faulted in all the three deductions.
			<lb />
			77. The first adjustment made is to the Total Project Cost on
			<lb />
			account of unfinished Construction. There is no stipulation in any of
			<lb />
			the clauses of the Concession agreement or the Escrow Agreement
			<lb />
			that any such adjustment could be made prior to determining the
			<lb />
			Termination Payment. The Termination Payment is correlated to the
			<lb />
			actual Debt Due. There is no stipulation that any adjustment of the
			<lb />
			said nature can be made from the Debt Due. This adjustment is clearly
			<lb />
			not warranted from the Termination Payment.
			<lb />
			78. The second adjustment made on account of taking the Debt as
			<lb />
			72.58% of the adjusted TPC is also unwarranted. NHAI has taken the
			<lb />
			debt and equity ratio to be maintained by JETPUR to be 72.58 : 27.42.
			<lb />
			There is no such stipulation in the Concession Agreement. The
			<lb />
			Concession Agreement does not require that JETPUR has to maintain
			<lb />
			any such debt equity ratio. NHAI has sought to rely upon the
			<lb />
			Common Loan Agreement dated 19.08.2011 between JETPUR and
			<lb />
			the Lenders and PNB.
			<lb />
			79. Reliance is placed on Recital B to the agreement which reads as
			<lb />
			under:
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			OMP 221/2017 &amp; 227/2017
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 25 of 36
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			&quot;The total cost of construction and development of the
			<lb />
			Project High Way (defined hereinafter) is estimated to be
			<lb />
			Rs. 981,00,00,000 (Rupees Nine Hundred and Eighty
			<lb />
			One Crores Only), which is proposed to be funded, as
			<lb />
			follows:
			<lb />
			Particulars
			<lb />
			Amount in Rupees
			<lb />
			Crores
			<lb />
			Project Equity Capital
			<lb />
			269
			<lb />
			Facility
			<lb />
			712
			<lb />
			Total Project Cost
			<lb />
			981
			<lb />
			80. Based on the above clause it is contended that the Debt to
			<lb />
			equity ratio to be maintained is 72.58 : 27.42. Accordingly, from the
			<lb />
			adjusted TPC another adjustment is made based on the above ratio. It
			<lb />
			is contended that the Concession Agreement in its definition of
			<lb />
			Project Agreements make the Financing Agreements as part of the
			<lb />
			Project Agreements.
			<lb />
			81. There is admittedly, no such stipulation in the Termination
			<lb />
			Payment clause that any such adjustment is to be made prior to
			<lb />
			payment of the Debt Due. As per the definition of Termination
			<lb />
			Payment and Debt Due, only the actual Debt Due has to be taken into
			<lb />
			account.
			<lb />
			82. It is not the contention of NHAI that the lenders have financed
			<lb />
			or provided finance more than what was stipulated under the
			<lb />
			agreement. As per JETPUR, the sanctioned Loan was Rs. 712 Crores
			<lb />
			but JETPUR has availed only Rs. 622 Crores. Admittedly, the project
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			OMP 221/2017 &amp; 227/2017
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 26 of 36
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			is more than 75% complete. As per JETPUR, the project is nearly
			<lb />
			complete.
			<lb />
			83. Third adjustment has been made on account of alleged
			<lb />
			recoveries to be made by NHAI from JETPUR. This is also contrary
			<lb />
			to the stipulations contained in the Concession Agreement with regard
			<lb />
			to Termination Payment.
			<lb />
			84. The clause relating to Termination Payment does not
			<lb />
			contemplate any deduction being made there from. According to
			<lb />
			Clauses 3.2 and 4.2 of the Escrow Agreement and Clauses 31.2 and
			<lb />
			31.4 of the Concession Agreement, NHAI is obliged to deposit the
			<lb />
			Termination Payment comprising of 90% of Debt Due into the
			<lb />
			Escrow Account. The lenders are entitled to appropriate the amount in
			<lb />
			priority to any claim of damages or recoveries that NHAI may have
			<lb />
			from JETPUR. The appropriation of Debt Due is only lower in
			<lb />
			priority to payment of taxes by JETPUR.
			<lb />
			85. This stipulation, as noticed above, appears to be to protect the
			<lb />
			interest of the lenders, who are not concerned with the inter se
			<lb />
			disputes between NHAI and JETPUR. Clearly, NHAI has faulted in
			<lb />
			making the deductions from the Termination Payment.
			<lb />
			86. It is clarified that the merits of the claim for deduction by
			<lb />
			NHAI and the defence of JETPUR to the same is not being examined
			<lb />
			in this petition. It would be for the arbitral tribunal to consider the
			<lb />
			same in accordance with law.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			OMP 221/2017 &amp; 227/2017
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 27 of 36
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			87. The Supreme Court of India in GANGOTRI ENTERPRISES LTD.
			<lb />
			(supra), reaffirmed the earlier decision in UNION OF INDIA VERSUS
			<lb />
			RAMAN IRON FOUNDRY (1974) 2 SCC 231, wherein the Supreme
			<lb />
			Court approved the proposition laid down by the Bombay High Court
			<lb />
			in IRON AND HARDWARE (INDIA) CO. VERSUS SHAMLAL AND BROS
			<lb />
			AIR1954 BOM 423, that &quot;damages are the compensation which a
			<lb />
			court of law gives to a party for the injury which he has sustained.
			<lb />
			But, and this is most important to note, he does not get damages or
			<lb />
			compensation by reason of any existing obligation on the part of the
			<lb />
			person who has committed the breach. He gets compensation as a
			<lb />
			result of the fiat of the court. Therefore, no pecuniary liability arises
			<lb />
			till the court has determined that the party complaining of the breach
			<lb />
			is entitled to damages. Therefore, when damages are assessed, it
			<lb />
			would not be true to say that what the court is doing is ascertaining a
			<lb />
			pecuniary liability, which already existed. The court in the first place
			<lb />
			must decide that the defendant is liable and then it proceeds to assess
			<lb />
			what that liability is. But till that determination there is no liability at
			<lb />
			all upon the defendant.&quot; (underlining supplied)
			<lb />
			88. The Supreme Court of India in INDIAN OIL CORPN. LTD. (supra)
			<lb />
			held
			<lb />
			&quot;26. We may at this stage refer to one aspect of the claim
			<lb />
			for extra cost. The award amount due to the respondent
			<lb />
			under the award dated 27-10-2008 is an ascertained sum
			<lb />
			due, recoverable by executing the award as a decree. On
			<lb />
			the other hand the claim of the appellant for
			<lb />
			reimbursement of the extra cost for getting the work
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			OMP 221/2017 &amp; 227/2017
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 28 of 36
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			completed, is a claim for damages which is yet to be
			<lb />
			adjudicated by an adjudicating forum. The appellant
			<lb />
			cannot therefore adjust the amount due by it under the
			<lb />
			award, against a mere claim for damages made by it
			<lb />
			against the respondent. The appellant will have to pay
			<lb />
			the award amount due to the respondent and if necessary
			<lb />
			modify its claim for extra cost against the respondent.&quot;
			<lb />
			89. Similarly, in the present case, there is no dispute that NHAI has
			<lb />
			to make the Termination Payment. NHAI has sought to make
			<lb />
			recoveries of Rs. 242.42 Crores. The recoveries are yet to be
			<lb />
			adjudicated and determined. It is yet to be determined as to who is at
			<lb />
			fault. Pending determination and adjudication, NHAI cannot be
			<lb />
			permitted to make recoveries on its own.
			<lb />
			90. The Supreme Court in J.G. ENGINEERS PRIVATE LIMITED
			<lb />
			(Supra) held that the question whether the other party committed
			<lb />
			breach cannot be decided by the party alleging breach. A contract
			<lb />
			cannot provide that one party will be the arbiter to decide whether he
			<lb />
			committed breach or the other party committed breach. That question
			<lb />
			can only be decided by only an adjudicatory forum, that is, a court or
			<lb />
			an Arbitral Tribunal. Adjudication upon the issue relating to a breach
			<lb />
			of condition of contract and adjudication of assessing damages
			<lb />
			arising out of the breach are two different and distinct concepts and
			<lb />
			the right to assess damages arising out of a breach would not include
			<lb />
			a right to adjudicate upon as to whether there was any breach at all.
			<lb />
			One of the parties to an agreement cannot reserve to himself the
			<lb />
			power to adjudicate whether the other party has committed breach.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			OMP 221/2017 &amp; 227/2017
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 29 of 36
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			91. The contention of Learned Counsel for NHAI is that admission
			<lb />
			cannot be read in isolation and should be read as a whole. This
			<lb />
			submission is made on the premise that the payment of Rs. 222.03
			<lb />
			Crores by NHAI into the escrow amount is being treated as an
			<lb />
			admission.
			<lb />
			92. Reliance placed by Learned Senior Counsel for the NHAI on
			<lb />
			SHIN SATELLITE PUBLIC CO. LTD (supra) to contend that powers
			<lb />
			under section 9 of the Act should not be exercised to enable the
			<lb />
			petitioner to recover the sums on account of damages in advance of
			<lb />
			the hearing even if part of the liability is undisputed and monetary
			<lb />
			award for some amount may be made, is misplaced in the facts of the
			<lb />
			present case.
			<lb />
			93. The claim of PNB and JETPUR is not for recovery of any sum
			<lb />
			on account of damages. The claim is for payments in terms of the
			<lb />
			Concession Agreement which stipulates the payment of a minimum
			<lb />
			amount on the happening of the event of Termination irrespective of
			<lb />
			the party at fault. On the other hand the claim of NHAI is on account
			<lb />
			of damages, which cannot be adjusted from the Termination Payment.
			<lb />
			94. The Judgment in the case of HAJI C.H. MOHAMMAD KOYA
			<lb />
			(Supra) to contend that admission cannot be split up and part of it
			<lb />
			used; admission must be used either as a whole or not at all, is not
			<lb />
			applicable to the facts of the present case. Reliance placed on
			<lb />
			RADHIKA AUTOMOBILES PVT. LTD (supra) is also misplaced as in the
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			OMP 221/2017 &amp; 227/2017
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 30 of 36
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			said case, the claim was for recovery of money disputed.
			<lb />
			95. In the present case, the admission is not sought to be split up.
			<lb />
			When read as a whole, it is clear that there is no dispute that the Debt
			<lb />
			Due is over Rs. 640 crores. No dispute has been ever raised that the
			<lb />
			amount of loan is in excess of the sanctioned limit. There is no dispute
			<lb />
			that NHAI has to make the termination payment. NHAI is seeking to
			<lb />
			make adjustment, which as noticed above cannot be made from the
			<lb />
			Termination Payment.
			<lb />
			96. The Termination Payment has to be made to the Lenders and
			<lb />
			inter se dispute between NHAI and JETPUR cannot affect the right of
			<lb />
			the Lenders to appropriate 90% of the Termination Payment. There is
			<lb />
			admittedly no dispute with the lenders.
			<lb />
			97. Further, the judgment in the case of ORISSA MANGANESE AND
			<lb />
			MINERALS LIMITED (supra) relied upon by Learned Senior Counsel
			<lb />
			for the Respondent is also not applicable to the facts of the present
			<lb />
			case. In the said case, damages were found to be an adequate
			<lb />
			compensation for the loss, if any, to be sustained by the respondent.
			<lb />
			98. In the present case, damages would not be an adequate
			<lb />
			compensation as on the one hand JETPUR is liable to be declared as
			<lb />
			NPA, which would have irreversible consequences and PNB and the
			<lb />
			lenders would also suffer irreparable loss and injury. On the other
			<lb />
			hand the interest of NHAI, which has taken over the Project Highway
			<lb />
			and the right of Toll Collection can be adequately protected by putting
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			OMP 221/2017 &amp; 227/2017
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 31 of 36
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			JETPUR to terms.
			<lb />
			99. In the present case, there was no financial outflow of NHAI for
			<lb />
			the Project Highway. The cost of the Project is upwards of Rs. 828
			<lb />
			Crores. The entire Highway had to be constructed by JETPUR from
			<lb />
			its own sources. JETPUR has admittedly constructed more than 75%
			<lb />
			of the Highway. As per JETPUR, apart from loans, JETPUR has also
			<lb />
			made substantial equity contribution. The recovery of cost and
			<lb />
			investment by JETPUR was to be from Toll Collection. The Lenders
			<lb />
			have advanced loans of over Rs. 622 Crores. As per PNB the Debt
			<lb />
			Due, including interest, as on date of termination was over Rs. 640
			<lb />
			Crores. On termination, the Project Highway including the right of
			<lb />
			Toll Collection has been taken over by NHAI, without any financial
			<lb />
			outflow except the liability of Termination Payment.
			<lb />
			100. At this stage, the maximum financial outflow from NHAI
			<lb />
			would be 90% of the Debt Due i.e. 90% of Rs. 640.86 Crores (i.e.
			<lb />
			Rs.576.774 crores). With this outflow, NHAI gets the entire
			<lb />
			constructed Project Highway and the right to collect Toll. NHAI has
			<lb />
			already made the payment of Rs. 222.03 Crores. The Balance due is
			<lb />
			Rs. 354.744 Crores, out of which NHAI has offered to make the
			<lb />
			additional payment of Rs. 6.14 Crores.
			<lb />
			101. In case, this payment is not made by NHAI, the account of
			<lb />
			JETPUR would be declared as NPA and irreparable loss and injury
			<lb />
			would be suffered. Not only would JETPUR suffer irreparable, the
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			OMP 221/2017 &amp; 227/2017
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 32 of 36
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			Lenders including PNB would suffer grave injury. The concern is
			<lb />
			more of the public funds that have been provided by PNB and the
			<lb />
			lenders which would be embroiled in the inter se disputes between
			<lb />
			JETPUR and NHAI. Equity demands that the lenders and PNB should
			<lb />
			get their amount and the inter se disputes can be sorted out between
			<lb />
			the NHAI and JETPUR through the process of Arbitration.
			<lb />
			102. Under section 9 of the Act, Court has the power to pass orders
			<lb />
			as appear to the court to be just and convenient to prevent ends of
			<lb />
			Justice from being defeated. 1
			<lb />
			103. The Division bench of this court in KAL AIRWAYS PRIVATE
			<lb />
			LIMITED (supra) held as under:
			<lb />
			&quot;26. Though apparently, there seem to be two divergent
			<lb />
			strands of thought, in judicial thinking, this court is of the
			<lb />
			opinion that the matter is one of the weight to be given to
			<lb />
			the materials on record, a fact dependent exercise, rather
			<lb />
			than of principle. That Section 9 grants wide powers to
			<lb />
			the courts in fashioning an appropriate interim order, is
			<lb />
			apparent from its text. Nevertheless, what the authorities
			<lb />
			stress is that the exercise of such power should be
			<lb />
			principled, premised on some known guidelines -
			<lb />
			therefore, the analogy of Orders 38 and 39. Equally, the
			<lb />
			court should not find itself unduly bound by the text of
			<lb />
			those provisions rather it is to follow the underlying
			<lb />
			principles. In this regard, the observations of Lord
			<lb />
			Hoffman in Films Rover International Ltd. v. Cannon
			<lb />
			Film Sales Ltd.(1986) 3 All ER 772 are fitting:
			<lb />
			&quot;But I think it is important in this area to
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			1 S. HARINDER SINGH (supra)
			<lb />
		</note>
		<note place="footnote">
			OMP 221/2017 &amp; 227/2017
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 33 of 36
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			distinguish between fundamental principles and
			<lb />
			what are sometimes described as &apos;guidelines&apos;, i.e
			<lb />
			useful generalisations about the way to deal with
			<lb />
			the normal run of cases falling within a particular
			<lb />
			category. The principal dilemma about the grant of
			<lb />
			interlocutory injunctions, whether prohibitory or
			<lb />
			mandatory, is that there is by definition a risk that
			<lb />
			the court may make the &apos;wrong&apos; decision, in the
			<lb />
			sense of granting an injunction to a party who fails
			<lb />
			to establish his right at the trial (or would fail if
			<lb />
			there was a trial) or alternatively, in failing to
			<lb />
			grant an injunction to a party who succeeds (or
			<lb />
			would succeed) at trial. A fundamental principle is
			<lb />
			therefore that the court should take whichever
			<lb />
			course appears to carry the lower risk of injustice
			<lb />
			if it should turn out to have been &apos;wrong&apos; in the
			<lb />
			sense I have described. The guidelines for the
			<lb />
			grant of both kinds of interlocutory injunctions are
			<lb />
			derived from this principle.&quot;
			<lb />
			27. It was observed later, in the same judgment that:
			<lb />
			&quot;The question of substance is whether the granting
			<lb />
			of the injunction would carry that higher risk of
			<lb />
			injustice which is normally associated with the
			<lb />
			grant of a mandatory injunction. The second point
			<lb />
			is that in cases in which there can be no dispute
			<lb />
			about the use of the term &apos;mandatory&apos; to describe
			<lb />
			the injunction, the same question of substance will
			<lb />
			determine whether the case is &apos;normal&apos; and
			<lb />
			therefore within the guideline or &apos;exceptional&apos; and
			<lb />
			therefore requiring special treatment. If it appears
			<lb />
			to the court that, exceptionally, the case is one in
			<lb />
			which withholding a mandatory interlocutory
			<lb />
			injunction would in fact carry a greater risk of
			<lb />
			injustice than granting it even though the court
			<lb />
			does not feel a &apos;high degree of assurance&apos; about
			<lb />
			the plaintiff&apos;s chances of establishing his right,
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			OMP 221/2017 &amp; 227/2017
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 34 of 36
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			there cannot be any rational basis for withholding
			<lb />
			the injunction.&quot;
			<lb />
			(underlining supplied)
			<lb />
			104. In exercise of powers under section 9 of the Act, several
			<lb />
			benches, Single and Division, of this court, in the facts of the case,
			<lb />
			have passed mandatory interlocutory directions, directing respondents
			<lb />
			to make payments subject to terms. (See FORBES FACILITY SERVICES
			<lb />
			PRIVATE LIMITED (supra); MAFATLAL INDUSTRIES LIMITED &amp;
			<lb />
			ANOTHER (supra); VALUE SOURCE MERCANTILE LIMITED (supra),
			<lb />
			SIMPLEX INFRASTRUCTURES LTD.(Supra).
			<lb />
			105. In my view the petitioners have shown strong prima facie case
			<lb />
			for grant of interim mandatory measures. Balance of convenience is in
			<lb />
			favour of PNB and JETPUR and against NHAI. As noticed
			<lb />
			hereinabove, in case interim measures are not granted, irreparable loss
			<lb />
			and injury is likely to be caused to the petitioners.
			<lb />
			106. In view of the above,
			<lb />
			(i)
			<lb />
			JETPUR is directed to furnish an unconditional and
			<lb />
			irrevocable Bank Guarantee, in favour of NHAI,
			<lb />
			undertaking to pay to NHAI an amount not exceeding Rs.
			<lb />
			348.604 Crores [i.e. 90% of 640.86 = 576.774 (minus)
			<lb />
			222.03 {already paid} (minus) 6.14 {agreed to be payable
			<lb />
			by NHAI} = 348.604]; and
			<lb />
			(ii) on deposit of the Bank Guarantee, NHAI shall forthwith
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			OMP 221/2017 &amp; 227/2017
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 35 of 36
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			deposit in the Escrow Account the sum of Rs. 354.744
			<lb />
			Crores (i.e. 348.604 + 6.14); and
			<lb />
			(iii) the encashment of the Bank Guarantee shall be subject to the
			<lb />
			final award of the Arbitral Tribunal; and
			<lb />
			(iv) JETPUR shall keep the bank guarantee alive for unto a
			<lb />
			period of four months after the making of the final award by
			<lb />
			the Arbitration Tribunal; and
			<lb />
			(v) Parties shall comply with the provisions of Section 9(2) of
			<lb />
			the Act.
			<lb />
			107. It is clarified that this court has neither considered nor
			<lb />
			expressed any opinion on the merits of the claim of NHAI and the
			<lb />
			defence of JETPUR with regard to the alleged recoveries and the issue
			<lb />
			of the unfinished project.
			<lb />
			108. The Petitions are allowed in the above terms. There shall be no
			<lb />
			orders as to costs.
			<lb />
			109. Copy of the Order be supplied Dasti to parties under signatures
			<lb />
			of Court Master.
			<lb />
			SANJEEV SACHDEVA, J
			<lb />
			JULY 31, 2017
			<lb />
			Sn/HJ
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			OMP 221/2017 &amp; 227/2017
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 36 of 36
			<lb />
		</page>
	</text>
</tei>
