<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			HIGH COURT OF DELHI AT NEW DELHI
			<lb />
			Date of Decision: 30.09.2011
			<lb />
			+ 1. BAIL APPLN. 1512/2009
			<lb />
			SACHIN BANSAL @ ANSHU ..... Petitioner
			<lb />
			Through: Mr. Avadh Bihari Kaushik,
			<lb />
			Advocate.
			<lb />
			Versus
			<lb />
			STATE ..... Respondent
			<lb />
			Through: Mr.Sanjiv K. Jha and
			<lb />
			Mr.Siddharth Srivastava,
			<lb />
			Advocates for complainant.
			<lb />
			Mr.Naveen Sharma, APP.
			<lb />
			+ 2. BAIL APPLN. 1012/2011
			<lb />
			NARENDER MANN ..... Petitioner
			<lb />
			Through: Mr. K.K. Sud, Sr. Advocate
			<lb />
			with Mr. H.Singh,
			<lb />
			Advocate.
			<lb />
			versus
			<lb />
			STATE ..... Respondent
			<lb />
			Through: Mr.Sanjiv K. Jha and
			<lb />
			Mr.Siddharth Srivastava,
			<lb />
			Advocates for complainant.
			<lb />
			Mr.Naveen Sharma, APP
			<lb />
		</front>
		<note place="footnote">
			Bail Appl. Nos.1512/09 &amp; 1012/11
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 1 of 26
			<lb />
		</page>
		<front>
			CORAM :
			<lb />
			HON&apos;BLE MR. JUSTICE V.K. SHALI
			<lb />
			1.
			<lb />
			Whether Reporters of local papers may be allowed to
			<lb />
			see the judgment?
			<lb />
			YES
			<lb />
			2.
			<lb />
			To be referred to the Reporter or not?
			<lb />
			YES
			<lb />
			3.
			<lb />
			Whether the judgment should be reported in the
			<lb />
			Digest?
			<lb />
			YES
			<lb />
			V.K. SHALI, J.
			<lb />
		</front>
		<body>
			1. These are the two regular bail applications bearing
			<lb />
			Nos.1512/2009 &amp; 1012/2011, filed by Sachin Bansal and
			<lb />
			another by Narender Mann respectively.
			<lb />
			2.
			<lb />
			Briefly stated, the prosecution case against the
			<lb />
			petitioners/accused persons is that on 21.03.2006 at about
			<lb />
			4:30 pm a call bell was given at the residence of the
			<lb />
			deceased, S.N.Gupta.
			<lb />
			Smt.Kamla Devi, the wife of the
			<lb />
			deceased S.N. Gupta attended the call. At the main door, she
			<lb />
			found a person with beard, aged about 25-30 years, wearing
			<lb />
			spectacles &amp; black cap, having a bag and posing himself to
			<lb />
			be a Courier boy. He informed her that he had brought a
			<lb />
			letter for S.N.Gupta, the deceased. As the Courier Boy is
			<lb />
			stated to have alleged that the delivery of the letter would be
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			Bail Appl. Nos.1512/09 &amp; 1012/11
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 2 of 26
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			made to Sh.S.N.Gupta only, Smt.Kamla Devi, complainant
			<lb />
			went inside the house and informed her husband about the
			<lb />
			courier. S.N. Gupta went to the door to collect the letter,
			<lb />
			however, in the meantime, the complainant who was in the
			<lb />
			kitchen heard 2-3 gunshots. It transpired that S.N.Gupta had
			<lb />
			been shot by that Courier Boy and he was lying on the floor
			<lb />
			in a pool of blood. He was rushed to Jaipur Golden Hospital
			<lb />
			with the help of the neighbours, where he was declared as
			<lb />
			brought dead.
			<lb />
			3.
			<lb />
			An FIR No.200/2006 was registered under Section 302
			<lb />
			IPC read with section 25/27 of the Arms Act by PS
			<lb />
			Mangolpuri, Delhi and investigation conducted. The
			<lb />
			investigation led to the arrest of the petitioner, Sachin Bansal
			<lb />
			on 29.03.2006 on whose disclosure statement the other
			<lb />
			accused/petitioner, Narender Mann, was also arrested. It
			<lb />
			transpired, after investigation, that Sachin Bansal was a
			<lb />
			business partner of the deceased S.N.Gupta and there were
			<lb />
			apparently some business differences between them. In
			<lb />
			addition to this, the deceased S.N.Gupta had to recover 70-
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			Bail Appl. Nos.1512/09 &amp; 1012/11
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 3 of 26
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			80 Lakhs of rupees, from Sachin Bansal and his father Shiv
			<lb />
			Charan Bansal, which was given to them in connection with
			<lb />
			some committees, which were being run by them. Narender
			<lb />
			Mann, the other co-accused, had to recover approximately
			<lb />
			30-40 lakhs of rupees from the nephew of the deceased. It is
			<lb />
			the case of the prosecution that a conspiracy was weaved
			<lb />
			between Sachin Bansal and Narender Mann with the help of
			<lb />
			few other persons. Narender Mann was arrested on the
			<lb />
			disclosure statement of Sachin Bansal. One Rajbir Malik
			<lb />
			arranged the pistol similar to the licensed pistol of Narender
			<lb />
			Mann. The disclosure statement of Narender Mann led to the
			<lb />
			recovery of the car used in the crime and the pistol used as
			<lb />
			the weapon of offence along with two live cartridges from the
			<lb />
			accused Shailender Singh. One Joginder Singh Sodhi is
			<lb />
			alleged to have disguised as a Courier Boy and a friend of
			<lb />
			Sachin Bansal, Rajbir Singh, an Advocate had also allegedly
			<lb />
			helped Sachin Bansal in devising a conspiracy from choosing
			<lb />
			the weapon till the time of collecting the booty for the
			<lb />
			murder. So far as Narender Mann is concerned his role unlike
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			Bail Appl. Nos.1512/09 &amp; 1012/11
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 4 of 26
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			Sachin Bansal, who was alleged to be the kingpin of the
			<lb />
			entire conspiracy, was limited to the extent that his
			<lb />
			disclosure has resulted in recovery of certain incriminating
			<lb />
			articles from the dickey of his car, which were alleged to be
			<lb />
			actually used by the person, named, Joginder Singh Sodhi,
			<lb />
			who disguised himself as a Courier Boy. In addition to this,
			<lb />
			the prosecution case against Narender Mann is that his
			<lb />
			licensed pistol was recovered from Sachin Bansal and the
			<lb />
			bullets, which were used from the weapon of offence were of
			<lb />
			the same or the same type, which were issued to Narender
			<lb />
			Mann for his licenced weapon.
			<lb />
			4.
			<lb />
			The trial Court had discharged Sachin Bansal as well as
			<lb />
			Narender Mann for the offence of murder but the High Court
			<lb />
			vide its order dated 29.05.2009, directed framing of charges
			<lb />
			against both of them under section 120B as well as under
			<lb />
			Section 302 IPC.
			<lb />
			The High Court had by the same order
			<lb />
			discharged some other accused persons.
			<lb />
			Special Leave
			<lb />
			Petitions have been preferred by Sachin Bansal, complainant
			<lb />
			as well as the State against the order of the High Court dated
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			Bail Appl. Nos.1512/09 &amp; 1012/11
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 5 of 26
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			29.5.2009 though for different reasons.
			<lb />
			So far as Sachin
			<lb />
			Bansal is concerned, he has challenged the framing of charge
			<lb />
			under Section 302. In this matter, special leave has been
			<lb />
			granted, although there is no stay. So far as the other two
			<lb />
			SLP&apos;s are concerned, they are also pending though it is not
			<lb />
			disclosed whether they are admitted or not. The Supreme
			<lb />
			Court has not stayed the trial Court proceedings but the trial
			<lb />
			Court record has been summoned and thus the trial is
			<lb />
			practically stand still as no effort is being made by any of the
			<lb />
			party to get the record released or to get the hearing of
			<lb />
			SLP&apos;s expedited.
			<lb />
			Bail Application No.1512/2009 (filed by Accused-
			<lb />
			Sachin Bansal)
			<lb />
			5.
			<lb />
			So far as the accused, Sachin Bansal, is concerned his
			<lb />
			application for grant of bail was filed in the year 2009, which
			<lb />
			is pending till date. There is no dispute about the fact that
			<lb />
			this Court, vide order, dated 29.05.2009, had set aside the
			<lb />
			order of discharge of Sachin Bansal and directed framing of
			<lb />
			charge against him under Section 302 IPC read with Section
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			Bail Appl. Nos.1512/09 &amp; 1012/11
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 6 of 26
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			120B IPC. Against the said order of 29.05.2009, Sachin
			<lb />
			Bansal had filed an SLP, which was granted by the Apex
			<lb />
			Court on 26.11.2010 but pending adjudication and there was
			<lb />
			no stay against the trial. The Apex Court rejected an
			<lb />
			application for grant of bail as late as on 13.05.2011. Copy of
			<lb />
			this order has also been filed by the learned counsel for the
			<lb />
			respondent.
			<lb />
			6.
			<lb />
			The learned counsel for the petitioner in the present
			<lb />
			case has prayed for grant of regular bail and, if not regular,
			<lb />
			than, at least, interim bail on the ground that the petitioner
			<lb />
			has been in custody since 26.03.2006 (except for a brief
			<lb />
			period, when he was discharged), as the trial is not
			<lb />
			proceeding. It has been contended that non conduct of the
			<lb />
			trial is violating his right to speedy trial guaranteed under
			<lb />
			Article 21 of the Constitution of India. It is also contended by
			<lb />
			him that so far as the present petitioner is concerned he has
			<lb />
			not misused his liberty and the delay in conclusion of the trial
			<lb />
			is a vital factor for consideration of the benefit of grant of
			<lb />
			bail to him. Reliance, in this regard, has been placed by the
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			Bail Appl. Nos.1512/09 &amp; 1012/11
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 7 of 26
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			learned counsel for the petitioner on judgment of the Apex
			<lb />
			Court in State of Kerala Vs. Raneef, (2011) 1 SCC 784,
			<lb />
			wherein the Court has observed as under:
			<lb />
			&quot;In deciding bail applications an important
			<lb />
			factor which should certainly be taken into
			<lb />
			consideration by the court is the delay in
			<lb />
			concluding the trial. Often this takes several
			<lb />
			years, and if the accused is denied bail but is
			<lb />
			ultimately acquitted, who will restore so many
			<lb />
			years of his life spent in custody? Is Article 21
			<lb />
			of the Constitution, which is the most basic of
			<lb />
			all the fundamental rights in our Constitution,
			<lb />
			not violated in such a case? Of course this is
			<lb />
			not the only factor, but it is certainly one of
			<lb />
			the important factors in deciding whether to
			<lb />
			grant bail. In the present case the respondent
			<lb />
			has already spent 66 days in custody (as
			<lb />
			stated in Para 2 of his counter-affidavit), and
			<lb />
			we see no reason why he should be denied
			<lb />
			bail. A doctor incarcerated for a long period
			<lb />
			may end up like Dr.Manette in Charles
			<lb />
			Dicken&apos;s novel A Tale of Two Cities, who
			<lb />
			forgot his profession and even his name in the
			<lb />
			Bastille.&quot;
			<lb />
			7.
			<lb />
			The learned counsel for the petitioner has also placed
			<lb />
			reliance on H.B.Chaturvedi Vs. CBI, 2010 (3) JCC 2109, to
			<lb />
			contend that the bail is not to be withheld as a punishment,
			<lb />
			even assuming that the accused is prima facie guilty of a
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			Bail Appl. Nos.1512/09 &amp; 1012/11
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 8 of 26
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			grave offence bail cannot be refused as it would amount to
			<lb />
			punishing the accused before he is convicted.
			<lb />
			7A. It was also contended that he is a law abiding citizen
			<lb />
			and there is no direct evidence against him with regard to
			<lb />
			the allegation of killing of S.N.Gupta. It is also stated that he
			<lb />
			is a family man and he has a small daughter of five years
			<lb />
			who has also not seen him for the last so many months. The
			<lb />
			learned counsel has also relied upon case titled Pritam Singh
			<lb />
			@ Pappu Vs. State 2002 92) JCC 930 and Anil Mahajan Vs.
			<lb />
			Commissioner Customs and Another 2000 (84) DLT 854.
			<lb />
			8.
			<lb />
			As against this, both the learned APP as well as learned
			<lb />
			counsel for the Complainant, has vehemently opposed the
			<lb />
			application for grant of bail to the accused, Sachin Bansal.
			<lb />
			The learned APP has contended that so far as the question of
			<lb />
			grant of bail to the petitioner, in the instant case, is
			<lb />
			concerned the most important thing to be seen is the
			<lb />
			seriousness or the gravity of the offence, which can be seen
			<lb />
			from the quantum of sentence, which it carries, apart from
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			Bail Appl. Nos.1512/09 &amp; 1012/11
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 9 of 26
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			the prima facie nature of allegations against him. It is also
			<lb />
			contended that so far as the question of bail is concerned
			<lb />
			delay in conclusion of trial cannot be the sole basis of
			<lb />
			extending the benefit of grant of bail to an accused more so
			<lb />
			in a case where he himself is responsible for the same. It has
			<lb />
			been contended that the petitioner himself has gone to the
			<lb />
			Apex Court assailing the order dated 29.05.2009, passed by
			<lb />
			the High Court and it was for the petitioner himself to have
			<lb />
			ensured that the record of the High Court, which has been
			<lb />
			summoned by the Apex Court be got released from the said
			<lb />
			Court so that the trial could continue expeditiously as there
			<lb />
			was no stay against the trial. But the petitioner has made no
			<lb />
			sincere efforts in this regard.
			<lb />
			9.
			<lb />
			The learned APP has also raised the plea that earlier
			<lb />
			also the petitioner had filed a bail application, which was
			<lb />
			rejected and even the Apex Court turned down the
			<lb />
			application for grant of bail to the petitioner as late as on
			<lb />
			13.05.2011. Under these circumstances, as there is no
			<lb />
			change in the circumstances of the present petitioner,
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			Bail Appl. Nos.1512/09 &amp; 1012/11
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 10 of 26
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			therefore, he does not deserve to be enlarged on bail. The
			<lb />
			learned counsel for the complainant, who was present, has
			<lb />
			also vehemently supported the points urged by the learned
			<lb />
			APP for the State.
			<lb />
			10. I have carefully considered the submissions made by
			<lb />
			the respective sides and gone through the records.
			<lb />
			11. So far as the question of grant of bail in a non-bailable
			<lb />
			offence, more so, in an offence, where the petitioner is
			<lb />
			accused of having alleged to have committed the most
			<lb />
			heinous crime of murder is concerned the factors, which have
			<lb />
			to be taken into consideration, while exercising such a
			<lb />
			discretion are almost well settled by now in catena of
			<lb />
			authorities. These parameters are: the gravity of the offence;
			<lb />
			the nature of allegations; the past conduct of the accused;
			<lb />
			his roots in the society and the chance of his fleeing from the
			<lb />
			processes of law or tampering with the evidence. The
			<lb />
			analysis, based on the aforesaid parameters, the very first
			<lb />
			parameter regarding the nature of allegations against the
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			Bail Appl. Nos.1512/09 &amp; 1012/11
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 11 of 26
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			petitioner are very serious. The prosecution case is that the
			<lb />
			petitioner, Sachin Bansal was the kingpin of the entire
			<lb />
			conspiracy in ensuring the liquidation of the victim,
			<lb />
			S.N.Gupta, in a most meticulous and pre-planned manner in
			<lb />
			order to settle his professional difference and to ensure that
			<lb />
			neither he nor his father S.C.Bansal have to return the huge
			<lb />
			amount of Rs.70-80 lakhs, which was purported to have
			<lb />
			been invested by the deceased in the various committees
			<lb />
			being run by the father of the present petitioner. The offence
			<lb />
			of murder is the most heinous crime and carries the sentence
			<lb />
			of death and life imprisonment, therefore, naturally the
			<lb />
			gravity of the offence is very serious and so far as the role of
			<lb />
			the petitioner, in this regard, and the evidence which has
			<lb />
			been gathered is concerned, on a prima facie view of the
			<lb />
			matter not only to show the involvement of the petitioner but
			<lb />
			a great deal of planning and deliberation by the petitioner. It
			<lb />
			also shows the meticulous method in which the crime has
			<lb />
			been committed. The petitioner has gone to the extent of
			<lb />
			even utilizing the alleged services of an Advocate in order to
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			Bail Appl. Nos.1512/09 &amp; 1012/11
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 12 of 26
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			pre-empt that offence is not detected. This is reflected from
			<lb />
			the fact of recovery of Narender Mann&apos;s licenced weapon
			<lb />
			from him and the alleged user of the bullets either issued to
			<lb />
			Narender Mann though for a different but somewhat similar
			<lb />
			weapon. Therefore, these facts in itself are such a serious
			<lb />
			thing which makes the Court reluctant to extend the benefit
			<lb />
			of grant of bail in his favour and I need not dwell on other
			<lb />
			parameters or their existence, so far as Sachin Bansal is
			<lb />
			concerned. So far as, the delay in conclusion of trial is
			<lb />
			concerned, no doubt it is a vital ground for consideration but
			<lb />
			delay cannot be taken advantage of by the accused in a case
			<lb />
			where he himself is responsible for the same. Further the
			<lb />
			judgment in Raneef case (Supra) is distinguishable from the
			<lb />
			facts of the present case, in view of the above observations.
			<lb />
			Apart from this, that was case under Foreign Exchange which
			<lb />
			cannot be said to be as serious as the present case.
			<lb />
			Chaturvedi&apos;s case (Supra) is also distinguishable as bail is
			<lb />
			not being denied because of punishment but because of the
			<lb />
			gravity of the offence with which he is charged. Since, this is
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			Bail Appl. Nos.1512/09 &amp; 1012/11
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 13 of 26
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			a case of conspiracy there will hardly be a direct evidence as
			<lb />
			claimed by the learned counsel.
			<lb />
			12. In the instant case, the petitioner was discharged by
			<lb />
			the trial Court and on revision being filed by the State in the
			<lb />
			High Court, vide order dated 29.05.2009, charges were
			<lb />
			directed to be framed against him. The petitioner himself has
			<lb />
			challenged the said order in the Apex Court in which leave
			<lb />
			has been granted to him but the Apex Court has not stayed
			<lb />
			the proceedings of the trial Court and the record of the trial
			<lb />
			Court has been summoned by the Apex Court for the
			<lb />
			purpose of hearing of the appeal, it was open to the present
			<lb />
			petitioner to have filed an application to get the record of the
			<lb />
			trial Court released so that the trial could have continued
			<lb />
			because the Apex Court has not consciously stayed the trial.
			<lb />
			13. On the contrary, the petitioner has chosen to file an
			<lb />
			application for grant of bail before the Apex Court, which was
			<lb />
			dismissed as late as on 13.05.2011. If the delay would have
			<lb />
			been a ground, the Apex Court itself would have granted the
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			Bail Appl. Nos.1512/09 &amp; 1012/11
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 14 of 26
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			bail to the petitioner or observed something in this regard
			<lb />
			but it dismissed the application and since then there has
			<lb />
			been absolutely no change in the circumstances. As a matter
			<lb />
			of fact, when the application of the present petitioner has
			<lb />
			been dismissed by the Apex Court despite special leave
			<lb />
			having been granted, I feel it will be totally inappropriate for
			<lb />
			this Court to pre-empt the entire matter and release the
			<lb />
			present petitioner on bail, which was filed in the year 2009
			<lb />
			because the order of rejection of the bail by the Apex Court
			<lb />
			cannot be nullified by a Court, which is certainly inferior to
			<lb />
			the Apex Court, by extending the benefit of bail to the
			<lb />
			petitioner. So far as the other two judgments are concerned,
			<lb />
			they are also not helpful to the petitioner. Bail is a matter of
			<lb />
			judicial discretion to be exercised keeping in view the facts of
			<lb />
			each individual case and merely because it is granted in one
			<lb />
			particular fact of situation, it does not mean that the
			<lb />
			petitioner is also entitled on bail.
			<lb />
			14. For the reasons mentioned above, I feel that the
			<lb />
			petitioner is not entitled to the grant of regular bail. So far as
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			Bail Appl. Nos.1512/09 &amp; 1012/11
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 15 of 26
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			the prayer made during the course of oral submissions, by
			<lb />
			the learned counsel for the petitioner for grant of an interim
			<lb />
			bail with a view to enable the petitioner to undergo
			<lb />
			treatment for mental disease or for any other reason, is
			<lb />
			concerned, the same cannot be made a ground for grant of
			<lb />
			interim bail as the petitioner is being taken care in the
			<lb />
			hospital and proper treatment is being given to him.
			<lb />
			15. Accordingly, the bail application of the petitioner-
			<lb />
			Sachin Bansal is dismissed.
			<lb />
			Bail A.No.1012/2011 (filed by the Petitioner/
			<lb />
			Narender Mann)
			<lb />
			16. So far as the bail of the petitioner/accused, Narender
			<lb />
			Mann, is concerned, it was contended by Mr.K.K. Sud,
			<lb />
			learned senior counsel for the petitioner that the nature of
			<lb />
			evidence, which have been gathered against the petitioner is
			<lb />
			not of the type, which will be able to show that he was a part
			<lb />
			of the conspiracy. It was contended by him that the
			<lb />
			petitioner has been falsely implicated in as much as he has
			<lb />
			been arrested on the basis of the disclosure statement
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			Bail Appl. Nos.1512/09 &amp; 1012/11
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 16 of 26
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			purported to have been made by the accused, Sachin Bansal
			<lb />
			and that the disclosure statement is totally inadmissible. So
			<lb />
			far as the recovery of various incriminating articles like the
			<lb />
			gloves, goggles, the photographs of the deceased, which
			<lb />
			were purported to have been used by the actual assailant,
			<lb />
			who carried out the killing, are stated to have been planted
			<lb />
			on the present petitioner. As regards the user of the bullets
			<lb />
			purported to have been issued to the present petitioner for
			<lb />
			his licensed weapon is concerned it was contended that the
			<lb />
			prosecution case is that the bullets, which were actually used
			<lb />
			from the unlicensed weapon for killing S.N.Gupta was issued
			<lb />
			to the petitioner has not even been prima facie established.
			<lb />
			This is only a conjecture and surmise, which can be
			<lb />
			dislodged, only by way of cross-examination of the
			<lb />
			witnesses, who are produced. In any case, it was contended
			<lb />
			that the petitioner is being made to suffer for a delayed
			<lb />
			disposal of his trial, which is his fundamental right
			<lb />
			guaranteed under Article 21 of the Constitution for no rhyme
			<lb />
			and reason. It was contended that admittedly the petitioner
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			Bail Appl. Nos.1512/09 &amp; 1012/11
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 17 of 26
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			has not gone to the Apex Court challenging the framing of
			<lb />
			charge against the petitioner though he was discharged by
			<lb />
			the trial Court and ordered to be charged by the High Court.
			<lb />
			17. It is contended that he has roots in the society, his
			<lb />
			business has suffered considerably and there is no chance of
			<lb />
			his fleeing from the processes of law much less his tampering
			<lb />
			with the evidence. In this regard, it was contended by
			<lb />
			Mr.Sud, learned senior counsel that the petitioner after his
			<lb />
			arrest was released on bail, he was falsely implicated by the
			<lb />
			complainant in respect of an offence under Section 506 IPC
			<lb />
			on account of the alleged threats having been given to the
			<lb />
			complainant side to not to testify against him, which has
			<lb />
			ultimately resulted in his discharge which clearly belies the
			<lb />
			apprehension of the complainant that the petitioner will be a
			<lb />
			threat to the holding of a fair trial, if he is released on bail. It
			<lb />
			was contended by the learned senior counsel that if not on
			<lb />
			regular bail, the petitioner may be enlarged at least on
			<lb />
			interim bail for a period of six months so as to enable him to
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			Bail Appl. Nos.1512/09 &amp; 1012/11
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 18 of 26
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			resume his contact with the family and also to take steps to
			<lb />
			get the trial expedited by approaching the Apex Court.
			<lb />
			18. The learned APP has vehemently opposed the grant of
			<lb />
			bail to the petitioner, Narender Mann also. The grounds,
			<lb />
			which have been urged for opposing the bail application of
			<lb />
			the accused, Sachin Bansal, have been reiterated and stated
			<lb />
			to be equally applicable to the case of the present petitioner.
			<lb />
			Similarly, the learned counsel for the complainant has also
			<lb />
			supported the submissions made by the learned APP
			<lb />
			opposing the grant of bail to the present petitioner on the
			<lb />
			ground that delay cannot be the basis or rather consideration
			<lb />
			for grant of bail to an accused who is alleged to have
			<lb />
			committed a heinous crime. For this purpose, the learned
			<lb />
			counsel for the complainant has placed reliance on case titled
			<lb />
			Kalyan Chandra Sarkar Vs. Rajesh Ranjan, AIR 2004 SC
			<lb />
			1866. It has been contended by the learned counsel for the
			<lb />
			complainant that earlier also when the petitioner was
			<lb />
			released on bail he had threatened the witnesses of the
			<lb />
			complainant side for which an FIR was registered and,
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			Bail Appl. Nos.1512/09 &amp; 1012/11
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 19 of 26
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			therefore, there is a reasonable apprehension that in case he
			<lb />
			is released on bail he will threaten the witnesses afresh.
			<lb />
			19. I have carefully considered the submissions made by
			<lb />
			the learned counsel for the parties and gone through the
			<lb />
			record. No doubt, the nature of allegations against the
			<lb />
			petitioner are very serious in nature and he is alleged to be a
			<lb />
			part of a group which conspired to kill an innocent person,
			<lb />
			S.N. Gupta but the fact of the matter remains that the
			<lb />
			petitioner though an accused of a serious crime has a right to
			<lb />
			have a speedy and expeditious disposal of his trial. The
			<lb />
			petitioner has been admittedly in custody for almost 5½
			<lb />
			years as claimed by the learned senior counsel except for a
			<lb />
			brief period when he was discharged. There is no doubt that
			<lb />
			the allegations against the petitioner are also very serious on
			<lb />
			account of being a part of a conspiracy which he carried out
			<lb />
			together with Sachin Bansal and other accused to liquidate
			<lb />
			the deceased. This was allegedly also actuated by personal
			<lb />
			gain by way of recovery of money which he would have got
			<lb />
			from Sachin Bansal, which was otherwise payable to the
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			Bail Appl. Nos.1512/09 &amp; 1012/11
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 20 of 26
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			deceased. His role is further prima facie established because
			<lb />
			of recovery of various incriminating articles from the dickey
			<lb />
			of his car, dickey and coupled with the fact of recovery of his
			<lb />
			licensed weapon and cartridges from Sachin Bansal.
			<lb />
			20. There being no immediate sign of the SLP coming up
			<lb />
			for hearing in routine course or on account of no semblance
			<lb />
			of efforts being made by any of the three parties, who have
			<lb />
			preferred SLP&apos;s to expedite the hearing of their SLP&apos;s against
			<lb />
			the order dated 29.05.2009, the right of the petitioner to get
			<lb />
			an early hearing are getting defeated as the entire trial is
			<lb />
			held up despite there being no stay as the trial Court record
			<lb />
			is stated to have been summoned by the Apex Court. None
			<lb />
			of the parties despite the suggestions having been given by
			<lb />
			the Court to approach the Apex Court for the release of the
			<lb />
			record seems to have taken any step for getting the record
			<lb />
			released.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			Bail Appl. Nos.1512/09 &amp; 1012/11
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 21 of 26
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			21. I feel that the case of the present petitioner is slightly
			<lb />
			distinguishable from the case of Sachin Bansal, in this regard
			<lb />
			as he cannot be blamed for the delay.
			<lb />
			22. So far as the judgment of Kailash Chandra&apos;s case
			<lb />
			(supra) is concerned, I have gone through the same. No
			<lb />
			doubt, in the said judgment, the period of incarceration,
			<lb />
			which was 3½ years, has not been held to be a ground so
			<lb />
			different to warrant the grant of bail but the facts of that
			<lb />
			case were slightly different as compared to the facts of the
			<lb />
			present case. In the case, which has been cited by the
			<lb />
			learned counsel for the petitioner, the respondent Rajesh
			<lb />
			Ranjan @ Pappu Yadav, was granted bail by the High Court,
			<lb />
			and, thereafter witnesses examined had turned hostile, while
			<lb />
			as in the instant case, the trial itself is not able to proceed
			<lb />
			for want of record and consequently there is no question of
			<lb />
			any witness turning hostile and the right under Article 21 of
			<lb />
			the Constitution of the petitioner to have a speedy trial is
			<lb />
			defeated. Therefore, I feel so far as the case of the petitioner
			<lb />
			is concerned, it deserves to be dealt on a different footing
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			Bail Appl. Nos.1512/09 &amp; 1012/11
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 22 of 26
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			and at least the prayer of the petitioner for grant of interim
			<lb />
			bail for a limited period till the time the trial recommences be
			<lb />
			granted to him. For this purpose, the other aspects with
			<lb />
			regard to his enlargement on bail being a threat to fail trial
			<lb />
			or his past conduct of misusing his liberty or apprehension of
			<lb />
			his fleeing away from the processes of law need to be
			<lb />
			examined.
			<lb />
			23. If done so, no doubt, the past conduct of the petitioner
			<lb />
			is alleged to be not clean in as much as he had threatened
			<lb />
			the complainant side for which FIR was registered. But it has
			<lb />
			been stated by the learned senior counsel for the petitioner
			<lb />
			that he was discharged in that case by the trial Court. No
			<lb />
			doubt, the petitioner has been able to earn discharge, I feel
			<lb />
			that this can be taken care of by not only warning the
			<lb />
			present petitioner but also by putting the condition that he
			<lb />
			shall not approach directly or indirectly any witnesses or the
			<lb />
			complainant or threaten them in any manner whatsoever and
			<lb />
			even a slightest deviation from the same will be visited with
			<lb />
			the cancellation order.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			Bail Appl. Nos.1512/09 &amp; 1012/11
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 23 of 26
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			24. The petitioner is admittedly a married person having
			<lb />
			roots in the society as alleged in the petition, therefore, I feel
			<lb />
			that the petitioner must be permitted to breathe at least
			<lb />
			fresh air for a limited period till the trial recommences. I am
			<lb />
			clear in my mind that this period of interim relief to the
			<lb />
			petitioner has to be for a very limited span so as to enable
			<lb />
			the petitioner to take steps to approach the Apex Court for
			<lb />
			expeditious return of the trial Court record or alternatively
			<lb />
			expeditious disposal of the SLP by bringing to its notice that
			<lb />
			his rights are also getting defeated by non-disposal of the
			<lb />
			SLP which none of the three parties, namely, Sachin Bansal,
			<lb />
			complainant or for that matter the State are ready to
			<lb />
			expedite by approaching the Apex Court.
			<lb />
			25. For the above-mentioned reasons, I feel that the
			<lb />
			petitioner deserves to be granted interim bail for a period of
			<lb />
			three months from the date of his release, subject to his
			<lb />
			furnishing a personal bond in the sum of Rs.50,000/-with
			<lb />
			two sureties of the like amount to the satisfaction of the
			<lb />
			learned trial Court. It is made clear in the opening itself that
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			Bail Appl. Nos.1512/09 &amp; 1012/11
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 24 of 26
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			this period of three months is subject to the condition that in
			<lb />
			case the trial commences prior to the expiry of three months
			<lb />
			then the petitioner will have to necessarily surrender and the
			<lb />
			examination of the witnesses will take place only after the
			<lb />
			petitioner has surrendered so as to ensure that there is free
			<lb />
			and fair recording of the testimony of the witnesses. It is also
			<lb />
			made clear in the beginning itself that in no circumstances
			<lb />
			whatsoever, the petitioner shall file an application seeking
			<lb />
			enlargement of this period of interim bail and if filed the
			<lb />
			same shall not be entertained in any manner whatsoever
			<lb />
			before he surrenders before the Jail Superintendent after
			<lb />
			availing of his benefit of interim bail. It is also made clear
			<lb />
			that this grant of interim bail is subject to the condition that
			<lb />
			he shall not threaten the witnesses or leave the country or
			<lb />
			the National Capital Region of Delhi without the permission of
			<lb />
			the Court and he shall keep the Jail Superintendent as well
			<lb />
			as the Investigating Officer informed about his mobile
			<lb />
			number.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			Bail Appl. Nos.1512/09 &amp; 1012/11
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 25 of 26
			<lb />
		</page>
		<body>
			26. With these directions, the application of the petitioner-
			<lb />
			Narender Mann is partly allowed.
			<lb />
			27. Expression of any opinion herein before may not be
			<lb />
			treated as an expression on merits of the case.
			<lb />
			V.K. SHALI, J.
			<lb />
			September 30, 2011
			<lb />
			SS
		</body>
		<note place="footnote">
			Bail Appl. Nos.1512/09 &amp; 1012/11
			<lb />
		</note>
		<page>
			Page 26 of 26
			<lb />
		</page>
	</text>
</tei>
