<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			HIGH COURT OF JUDICATURE FOR RAJASTHAN AT
			<lb />
			JODHPUR
			<lb />
			S.B. Civil Writ Petition No. 16674/2021
			<lb />
			Ashok Kumar Mehta S/o Nagraj Ji Mehta, Aged About 54 Years,
			<lb />
			R/o 28/30, C.P. Tank Road, 1 st Floor, 3 rd Kumbharwada, Mumbai,
			<lb />
			Maharashtra.
			<lb />
			----Petitioner
			<lb />
			Versus
			<lb />
			Bank Of Baroda, Through Authorized Officer, Branch Office SSI
			<lb />
			Sukher, Industrial Area, Udaipur, District Udaipur, Rajasthan.
			<lb />
			----Respondent
			<lb />
			For Petitioner(s)
			<lb />
			: Mr. Abhishek Pareek
			<lb />
			For Respondent(s)
			<lb />
			: Mr. Dhanesh Saraswat
			<lb />
			JUSTICE DINESH MEHTA
			<lb />
			Order
			<lb />
			17/02/2022
			<lb />
		</front>
		<body>
			1.
			<lb />
			By way of the present writ petition, the petitioner has prayed
			<lb />
			thus:-
			<lb />
			&quot;A. By an appropriate writ, order or direction, the
			<lb />
			respondents may kindly be directed to return the
			<lb />
			original title deeds in respect of the properties
			<lb />
			belonging to the petitioner which were given as
			<lb />
			security by way of deposit of title deeds in respect of
			<lb />
			the transaction covered by sanctioning letter dated
			<lb />
			18.04.2015.
			<lb />
			B. By an appropriate writ, order or direction, the
			<lb />
			respondent may further be directed to return the
			<lb />
			original title deeds of the properties stated below:-
			<lb />
			a. Commercial office No.514, 515 &amp; 516
			<lb />
			admeasuring approx. 570 Sq. ft. situated at 3 rd
			<lb />
			floor, SM Lodha Complex, Plot No.109-C. Shastri
			<lb />
			Circle Post Office, Near Court Chauraha, Udaipur,
			<lb />
			Rajasthan;
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			(2 of 8)
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			[CW-16674/2021]
			<lb />
		</note>
		<body>
			b. Commercial office No.513 admeasuring 165
			<lb />
			Sq. ft. situated at 3 rd floor, SM Lodha Complex,
			<lb />
			Plot No.109-C. Shastri Circle Post Office, Near
			<lb />
			Court Chauraha, Udaipur, Rajasthan;
			<lb />
			c. Commercial office No.512 admeasuring 305
			<lb />
			Sq. ft. situated at 3 rd floor, SM Lodha Complex,
			<lb />
			Plot No.109-C. Shastri Circle Post Office, Near
			<lb />
			Court Chauraha, Udaipur, Rajasthan.
			<lb />
			C. By an appropriate writ, order or direction the
			<lb />
			response of the respondent bank Dt. 28.10.2021
			<lb />
			whereby they have denied releasing the mortgaged
			<lb />
			property, may kindly be castigated and appropriate
			<lb />
			directions be issued to act in fair and lawful manner.&quot;
			<lb />
			2.
			<lb />
			Undisputed facts, which emanate from the record are that
			<lb />
			the borrower M/s. Marudhar Metals and Minerals availed a credit
			<lb />
			facility from the respondent -Bank of Baroda, in which the
			<lb />
			present petitioner (Ashok Kumar Mehta) stood guarantor and
			<lb />
			created security interest of his four properties.
			<lb />
			3.
			<lb />
			The borrower, however failed to honor its commitment, due
			<lb />
			to which the respondent-Bank initiated proceedings under the
			<lb />
			Securitisation and Reconstruction of Financial Assets and
			<lb />
			Enforcement of Security Interest (SARFAESI) Act, 2002
			<lb />
			(hereinafter referred to as &quot;the Act of 2002&quot;) and a notice under
			<lb />
			section 13(2) of the Act was issued, whereafter the possession of
			<lb />
			the secured assets were taken and after issuance of notice of
			<lb />
			possession under section 13(4) of the Act of 2002, a notification
			<lb />
			for e-auction notice was issued. Accordingly, e-auction was held
			<lb />
			on 07.06.2019.
			<lb />
			4.
			<lb />
			In the e-auction aforesaid, all the four properties of the
			<lb />
			guarantor were offered for sale. Scanned copy of the e-auction
			<lb />
			notice is placed hereinfra:-
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			(3 of 8)
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			[CW-16674/2021]
			<lb />
		</note>
		<front>
			5.
			<lb />
			During e-auction property being farm house situated at Plot
			<lb />
			No.1, Khasra No.533, 534, 535 MI, 536, Revenue Village Tulsi Das
			<lb />
			Ki Saray, Udaipur (Raj.) admeasuring 39300 sq. ft (hereinafter
			<lb />
			referred to as &quot;the property No.1&quot;) stood sold in favour of the
			<lb />
		</front>
		<page>
			(4 of 8)
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			[CW-16674/2021]
			<lb />
		</note>
		<body>
			successful bidder and sale letter/communication for the same was
			<lb />
			issued.
			<lb />
			6.
			<lb />
			In the meantime, the petitioner, guarantor for the loan
			<lb />
			managed to deposit the entire outstanding amount with the
			<lb />
			respondent-Bank. Out of which, a part payment was made prior
			<lb />
			to the auction and remaining amount was paid after the auction
			<lb />
			proceedings were held, however, before the sale letter got
			<lb />
			registered.
			<lb />
			7.
			<lb />
			The petitioner has challenged the confirmation of sale of the
			<lb />
			1 st property made in favour of the successful bidder before the
			<lb />
			Debt Recovery Appellate Tribunal (hereinafter referred to as &quot;the
			<lb />
			Appellate Tribunal&quot;) and the matter is still pending consideration.
			<lb />
			8.
			<lb />
			The lis pending before the Appellate Tribunal is mainly for
			<lb />
			consideration on the issue -&quot;as to whether the authorized officer
			<lb />
			was justified in confirming the sale in favour of successful bidder&quot;.
			<lb />
			9.
			<lb />
			The petitioner made a representation before the respondent-
			<lb />
			Bank to release the original documents of his other three
			<lb />
			properties, which are not subject matter of any dispute, as the
			<lb />
			entire loan amount has been paid by the petitioner and there is no
			<lb />
			dispute so far as the remaining three properties (property No.2, 3
			<lb />
			and 4) are concerned.
			<lb />
			10. The respondent-Bank turned down petitioner&apos;s request,
			<lb />
			inter-alia, observing that the matter is pending before the
			<lb />
			Appellate Tribunal and according to the terms and condition of the
			<lb />
			loan, petitioner&apos;s remaining properties cannot be released.
			<lb />
			11. Mr. Abhishek Pareek, learned counsel for the petitioner
			<lb />
			argued that indisputably, the entire outstanding amount of the
			<lb />
			respondent-Bank in relation to the credit facility availed by the
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			(5 of 8)
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			[CW-16674/2021]
			<lb />
		</note>
		<body>
			borrower has been paid and rather the petitioner has deposited an
			<lb />
			excess amount of more than Rs. 10 lacs.
			<lb />
			12. Learned counsel further argued that even if the petitioner&apos;s
			<lb />
			appeal, pending before the Debt Recovery Appellate Tribunal, is
			<lb />
			rejected or allowed, the sale would be either finalised in favour of
			<lb />
			the auction purchaser or set aside. In either of the eventualities
			<lb />
			respondent-Bank would not be requiring any further amount.
			<lb />
			Hence, the respondent-Bank&apos;s action of not releasing documents
			<lb />
			qua property No.2, 3 &amp; 4 is arbitrary.
			<lb />
			13. Mr. Dhanesh Saraswat, learned counsel appearing for the
			<lb />
			respondent-Bank, on the other hand, submitted that as per the
			<lb />
			loan agreement, unless the entire loan is cleared and &apos;No
			<lb />
			Objection Certificate (NOC)&apos; is issued in this regard, neither the
			<lb />
			security interest created against the assets of the borrower or the
			<lb />
			guarantor can be eschewed, nor can the documents be released.
			<lb />
			14. Learned counsel for the respondent-Bank argued that the
			<lb />
			petitioner should pursue his appeal before the Appellate Authority
			<lb />
			and get the matter finally adjudicated. Whereafter, the Bank
			<lb />
			would naturally release the original documents in accordance with
			<lb />
			law.
			<lb />
			15. It was also argued that in the representation/letter sent by
			<lb />
			the petitioner, no extraordinary circumstances were pointed out
			<lb />
			by the petitioner, under which the Bank should accede to his
			<lb />
			request of releasing the documents.
			<lb />
			16. An objection was also raised by learned counsel for the
			<lb />
			respondent-Bank that the petitioner -a guarantor has approached
			<lb />
			this Court, without impleading the borrower as party. Hence, the
			<lb />
			writ petition is not competent.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			(6 of 8)
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			[CW-16674/2021]
			<lb />
		</note>
		<body>
			17. Mr. Saraswat nevertheless submitted that as per the
			<lb />
			instructions available to him, no excess amount has been
			<lb />
			deposited by the petitioner.
			<lb />
			18. Heard learned counsel for the parties and perused the
			<lb />
			material available on record.
			<lb />
			19. It is undisputed fact that the entire loan amount or the
			<lb />
			amount advanced to the borrower M/s. Marudhar Metals and
			<lb />
			Minerals stands paid by the borrower/guarantor.
			<lb />
			20. The dispute, which is pending consideration before the
			<lb />
			Appellate Tribunal is that, as to whether auction sale of property
			<lb />
			No.1 made in favour of the successful bidder was valid or not.
			<lb />
			21. In the opinion of this Court, in any eventuality, if the
			<lb />
			petitioner&apos;s appeal succeeds or fails, the respondent-Bank is
			<lb />
			having the original documents of title qua property No.1 and,
			<lb />
			therefore, the contingency arising out of petitioner&apos;s appeal being
			<lb />
			dismissed would be taken care of by the excess amount paid by
			<lb />
			the petitioner.
			<lb />
			22. Concededly, there is no quarrel in relation to remaining three
			<lb />
			properties. The respondent-Bank&apos;s stand that unless the entire
			<lb />
			dispute is resolved and NOC is issued in this regard, by the
			<lb />
			respondent-Bank, it cannot handover the documents to the
			<lb />
			petitioner, cannot be countenanced.
			<lb />
			23. This Court does not find any substance in the respondent-
			<lb />
			Bank&apos;s stance that the petitioner has not stated any specific
			<lb />
			circumstance for which, the documents in question should be
			<lb />
			released.
			<lb />
			24. According to this Court, stand of the respondent-Bank per-se
			<lb />
			is contradictory.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			(7 of 8)
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			[CW-16674/2021]
			<lb />
		</note>
		<body>
			25. If the stand of the respondent-Bank is, that it cannot release
			<lb />
			the documents unless NOC is granted then, it is inconsequential
			<lb />
			whether reasons have been assigned or not by the petitioner. In
			<lb />
			case their such stand does not find favour, then, they cannot sit
			<lb />
			over the documents simply because the petitioner has failed to
			<lb />
			give good reasons, why he requires the documents.
			<lb />
			26. In the opinion of this Court, the petitioner is not required to
			<lb />
			satisfy the respondent-Bank, as to why he is in requirement of the
			<lb />
			document of other three properties.
			<lb />
			27. The mere fact that the entire loan amount has been paid is
			<lb />
			reason enough for a borrower/guarantor to ask for the documents.
			<lb />
			28. In order to meet with the contingency, in case petitioner&apos;s
			<lb />
			appeal before the Debt Recovery Appellate Tribunal fails (though
			<lb />
			according to the petitioner excess amount is lying with the
			<lb />
			respondent Bank) the petitioner may be called upon to file an
			<lb />
			undertaking to pay the remaining amount (if any).
			<lb />
			29. The writ petition is allowed.
			<lb />
			30. The petitioner shall be required to file an undertaking before
			<lb />
			the respondent-Bank that in case any further liability arises on
			<lb />
			account of the dispute being pending before the Appellate
			<lb />
			Tribunal, he shall pay the same to the respondent-Bank in
			<lb />
			accordance with law, however, subject to his right of raising just
			<lb />
			objection and challenging the same.
			<lb />
			31. The respondent-Bank is directed to handover the original
			<lb />
			documents to the petitioner of property No.2, 3 and 4 (excluding
			<lb />
			the property No.1) within a period of one week of furnishing duly
			<lb />
			notarised undertaking alongwith affidavit of petitioner.
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			(8 of 8)
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			[CW-16674/2021]
			<lb />
		</note>
		<body>
			32. In case, the petitioner fails to honor his undertaking, the
			<lb />
			respondent-Bank shall be free to take up appropriate proceedings,
			<lb />
			including filing of contempt petition.
			<lb />
			33. The writ petition as well as stay application stands disposed
			<lb />
			of.
			<lb />
			(DINESH MEHTA),J
			<lb />
			15-Ramesh/-
		</body>
	</text>
</tei>
