<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<page>
			( 1 of 3 )
			<lb />
		</page>
		<front>
			HIGH COURT OF JUDICATURE FOR RAJASTHAN AT
			<lb />
			JODHPUR
			<lb />
			S.B. Criminal Appeal No. 450/2021
			<lb />
			1. Khetdan S/o Sh. Ganesh Dan, Aged About 30 Years, R/o
			<lb />
			Anandgarh, Tehsil Khajuwala, Dist. Bikaner.
			<lb />
			2. Pappu Dan S/o Sh. Kalu Dan, Aged About 33 Years, R/o
			<lb />
			W.No. 7, Village Gokulgarh Tehsil Khajuwala Dist. Bikaner.
			<lb />
			(At Present Lodged In Central Jail, Bikaner).
			<lb />
			----Appellants
			<lb />
			Versus
			<lb />
			1. State Of Rajasthan
			<lb />
			2. Ramrakhi W/o Tota Ram, resident of W.No. 7, Suratgarh
			<lb />
			Dist. Sri Ganganagar.
			<lb />
			----Respondents
			<lb />
			For Appellant(s) : Mr.R.S.Chouhan, Adv. through VC
			<lb />
			For Respondent(s) : Mr.S.S.Rajpurohit, PP
			<lb />
			HON'BLE MR. JUSTICE MANOJ KUMAR GARG
			<lb />
			Order
			<lb />
			12/05/2021
			<lb />
		</front>
		<body>
			Heard learned counsel for the appellants and learned public
			<lb />
			prosecutor. Perused the material available on record.
			<lb />
			The instant appeal has been filed under Section 14A (2)
			<lb />
			Scheduled Castes and the Scheduled Tribes (Prevention of
			<lb />
			Atrocities) Act on behalf of the appellants, who are in custody in
			<lb />
			connection with FIR No.69/2021, Police Station Suratgarh City,
			<lb />
			Distt. Sri Ganganagar for the offence under Section 365, 458,
			<lb />
			323, 147, 149 IPC and Section 3(2)(V)(Va) of SC/ST (Prevention
			<lb />
			of Atrocities) Act, against the order dated 08.04.2021 passed by
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			(2 of 3)
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			[CRLAS-450/2021]
			<lb />
		</note>
		<body>
			the learned Special Judge SC/ST (Prevention of Atrocities) Cases,
			<lb />
			Sri Ganganagar (Link Officer Addl. Sessions Judge No.2, Sri
			<lb />
			Ganganagar) in Criminal Misc. Case No.124/2021 whereby, the
			<lb />
			bail application preferred on behalf of the appellants under Section
			<lb />
			439 Cr.P.C. was rejected.
			<lb />
			Learned counsel for the appellants submits that the
			<lb />
			appellants have not committed the offences as alleged against
			<lb />
			them and they are innocent. The learned court below has grossly
			<lb />
			erred in law and facts as well as in declining to release the
			<lb />
			appellants on bail. Furthermore, similarly situated co-accused
			<lb />
			have already been granted bail by this Court.
			<lb />
			Learned Public Prosecutor has opposed the prayer for bail.
			<lb />
			Having regard to the entirety of facts and circumstances of
			<lb />
			the case and upon a consideration of the arguments advanced at
			<lb />
			the bar, this Court is of the opinion that the order rejecting the
			<lb />
			application for bail filed on behalf of the appellants, cannot be
			<lb />
			sustained and deserves to be set aside.
			<lb />
			Consequently, the instant appeal is allowed. The impugned
			<lb />
			order dated 08.04.2021 passed by the Special Judge SC/ST
			<lb />
			(Prevention of Atrocities) Cases, Sri Ganganagar (Link Officer
			<lb />
			Addl. Sessions Judge No.2, Sri Ganganagar) is set aside. It is
			<lb />
			ordered that the accused-appellants 1) Khetdan S/o Sh. Ganesh
			<lb />
			Dan and (2) Pappu Dan S/o Sh. Kalu Dan shall be released on bail
			<lb />
			in FIR No. 69/2021, P.S. Suratgarh City, Distt. Sri Ganganagar
			<lb />
			provided he furnishes a personal bond of Rs.1,00,000/-and two
			<lb />
			surety bonds of Rs.50,000/-each to the satisfaction of the learned
			<lb />
		</body>
		<page>
			(3 of 3)
			<lb />
		</page>
		<note place="headnote">
			[CRLAS-450/2021]
			<lb />
		</note>
		<body>
			trial Court with the stipulation to appear before that Court on all
			<lb />
			dates of hearing and as and when called upon to do so.
			<lb />
			(MANOJ KUMAR GARG),J
			<lb />
			98-NK/-
		</body>
	</text>
</tei>
