<tei>
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc xml:id="_1168270.pdf"/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">


		<figure type="table">

            <figDesc>-<lb/>Coram<lb/> The Hon&apos;ble Mr. Justice Tarlok Singh Chauhan, Judge<lb/> The Hon&apos;ble Ms. Justice Jyotsna Rewal Dua, Judge<lb/> Whether approved for reporting? 1 No<lb/> Mr. Ashwani Kumar Chopra, Mr. K.D. Sood, Mr. Bipin C.<lb/> Negi, Mr. Ramakant Sharma, Mr. Ankush Dass and Mr. Ajay<lb/> Sharma, Senior Advocates with Mr. Sukrit Sood, Ms. Shweta<lb/> Joolka, Ms. Devyani Sharma, Mr. Nitin Thakur, Mr. Amit<lb/> Jamwal, Mr. Rajiv Rai, Mr. Satish Kumar Awasthi, Mr. Vivek<lb/> Negi, Mr. Brahmjot Singh Nahar and Mr. Ajay Thakur,<lb/> Advocates, for the respective petitioners in all the petitions.<lb/> Mr. Ashok Sharma, Advocate General with Mr. Ajay Vaidya,<lb/> Senior Additional Advocate General, Mr. Shiv Pal Manhans,<lb/> Mr. Nand Lal Thakur &amp; Mr. Vinod Thakur, Additional<lb/> Advocates General and Ms. Seema Sharma, Mr. Bhupinder<lb/> Thakur &amp; Mr. Yudhvir Singh Thakur, Deputy Advocates<lb/> General, for the respondents-State.<lb/> </figDesc>
<lb/> 
            <table>Mr. Anup Rattan, Advocate, for the respective respondents in<lb/> CWP Nos.1961 and 4203 of 2020.<lb/> (Through Video Conference)</table>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <note>).<lb/> On 08.05.2020, respondent-State approved<lb/> extension of Excise Policy 2019-20 upto 31.05.2020 and<lb/> operation of Excise Police 2020-21 from 01.06.2020 to<lb/> 31.05.2021. Further, no excise levy was to be deposited<lb/> after 22.03.2020 for the period the liquor vends remained<lb/> closed due to the lockdown. Retail Excise Licensees were<lb/> also allowed to lift the remaining MGQ of the year 2019-20<lb/> if due against the already deposited license fee before<lb/> 31.03.2020 and in case the complete license fee had not<lb/> been deposited by 31.03.2020, then such excise licensees<lb/> were permitted to lift the pending quota against deposition<lb/> of pending license fee for 2019-20 in the months of April<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>H<lb/> i g h<lb/> C<lb/> o u r t o f H<lb/> . P .<lb/> and May, 2020, on the opening of vends. There was to be<lb/> no MGQ of country liquor and IMFS for the months of<lb/> April/May, 2020. The license fees were to be deposited by<lb/> the retailers on actual lifting for these two months. The<lb/> excise licensees were not entitled for additional quota for<lb/> the year 2019-20 during extended period of Excise Policy<lb/> 2019-20, i.e. for the months of April-May, 2020.<lb/> 2(viii).<lb/> On 13.05.2020, another representation was sent<lb/> by the petitioner to the respondents for reduction of MGQ<lb/> by 25 to 30% for the excise year 2020-21, commencing from<lb/> 01.06.2020 and ending on 31.05.2021 and for calculation<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>of annual license fee thereupon. Alternatively, request was<lb/> made for scrapping MGQ altogether and for making the<lb/> license fee proportional to actual lifting of liquor by retail<lb/> licensees.<lb/> 2(ix).<lb/> On 19.05.2020, liquor vends were allowed to<lb/> function from 9:00 am to 5:00 pm. Petitioner submitted<lb/> another representation on 25.05.2020 to the respondents,<lb/> indicating therein that in case her request made in the<lb/> earlier representations was not accepted, then it would be<lb/> impossible for her to continue w.e.f. 01.06.2020 and that<lb/> she would be forced to close the vend. The respondent-<lb/></note>
<lb/>
            <table>H<lb/> i g h<lb/> C<lb/> o u r t o f H<lb/> . P .</table>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <figDesc>).<lb/> </figDesc>
<lb/> 
            <table>On 01.06.2020, liquor vends were allowed to<lb/> function from 10:00 am to 8:00 pm. Acknowledging the<lb/> receipt of various representations from a large number of<lb/> retail excise licensees expressing inability to clear excise<lb/> dues owing to reduced sale of liquor on account of<lb/> COVID-19 pandemic, the respondent-Department, on<lb/> 01.06.2020, issued directions to the field officers to keep<lb/> daily record of actual lifting and consumption of liquor<lb/> during first fortnight of June, 2020 and to submit the<lb/> report of the same to the Department for onward<lb/> submission to government for further decision. Data was to<lb/> be shown separately for tourist and non-tourist areas.<lb/> Petitioner alongwith various other similarly situated<lb/> licensees submitted representation on 01.06.2020 for<lb/> deciding the issues raised in the previous representations<lb/> H<lb/> i g h<lb/> C<lb/> o u r t o f H<lb/> . P .<lb/> after the compilation and examination of the data collected<lb/> in terms of directions issued by the respondents on<lb/> 01.06.2020.<lb/> 2(xii).<lb/> On 16.06.2020, the respondents-State approved<lb/> charging a fixed license fee and minimum annual quota on<lb/> pro-rata basis for Bar Licensees for the year 2020-21.<lb/> Accordingly, vide separate notifications of even date,<lb/> amendments were made in Rule 18-AA(i) as well as in<lb/> Schedule A of Himachal Pradesh Liquor License Rules,<lb/> 1986. Whereas in respect of retail excise licensees, on<lb/> 15.06.2020, time to submit FDR/Bank Guarantee of 8% of<lb/> MVV of Unit was extended from earlier fixed date of<lb/> 15.06.2020 to 30.06.2020, failing which licenses were to be<lb/> cancelled.<lb/> 3.<lb/> Filing of Writ Petitions:-<lb/>3(i).<lb/> Petitioner once again represented to the<lb/> respondents on 26.06.2020 for acceding to the request<lb/> made in her previous representations and also asserted<lb/> therein that otherwise it would not be possible for her to<lb/> continue w.e.f. 01.07.2020 and she shall be forced to close<lb/> the liquor vend. In such eventuality, the Department was<lb/> requested to make arrangements to allot the liquor vend as<lb/> H<lb/> i g h<lb/> C<lb/> o u r t o f H<lb/> . P .<lb/> deemed fit and to refund her the amount of renewal fee as<lb/> well as advance license fee. The liquor vends were<lb/> eventually shut by her on 01.07.2020. It is at this stage<lb/> that the petitioner preferred the instant writ petition on<lb/> 30.06.2020, praying for following substantive reliefs:-<lb/>&quot;a) Issue a writ of Certiorari by calling the records and quashing<lb/> the provisions relating to Minimum Guarantee Quota (MGQ) as<lb/> also Minimum Vend Value (MVV), based on MGQ for the Year<lb/> 2020-21, contained in the Policy document termed as<lb/> &quot;Announcements for the allotment of retail excise vends by<lb/> renewal/draw of lots/tender-cum-auction for the Year 2020-<lb/>21&quot;, Annexure P/2;<lb/> b)<lb/> Issue a writ of Mandamus directing the Respondents to revisit<lb/> the Excise Policy, 2020-21 keeping in view the change in<lb/> circumstances due to the intervening event of global COVID-19<lb/> Pandemic and make suitable modifications/changes therein<lb/> so as to make it conducive, practicable and possible for its<lb/> implementation, as the said Policy was framed and formulated<lb/> considering existence and continuance of the normal<lb/> circumstances then prevailing in the State and the Country;<lb/> c)<lb/> Issue a writ of Mandamus directing the Respondents<lb/> especially Respondents No.1 and 2 to take the decision upon<lb/> the Representations, Annexures P-6, P-8, P1-&amp; P-15 to its<lb/> logical end and refix the MGQ and MVV and suitably<lb/> supplement the terms and conditions of the license issue to the<lb/> Petitioner for the Year 2020-21 including the license fee<lb/> considering all the prevalent facts and circumstances created<lb/> due to the COVID-19 Pandemic and appropriately<lb/> adjust/refund the excess amount so paid against it;<lb/> d)</table>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <table>They had<lb/> applied unmindful of the extent of COVID-19 spread in<lb/> future and its adverse affect on their business. All liquor<lb/> vends remained closed on 22.03.2020 to observe Janta<lb/> curfew. Lockdown was imposed in the respondent-State on<lb/> 23.03.2020 followed by curfew. Liquor vends continued to<lb/> remain closed. Lockdown was extended. Taking note of<lb/> prevailing situation, on 30.03.2020, State Government<lb/> ordered extension of Excise Policy 2019-20 upto<lb/> 31.05.2020 and permitted operation of Excise Policy<lb/> 2020-21 w.e.f. 01.06.2020 to 31.05.2021. Gradually, liquor<lb/> vends were allowed to function with restrictive operative<lb/> hours. Lockdown was gradually eased, but social<lb/> restrictions remained in force. Threat of virus never actually<lb/> went away. Kullu, being a tourist place, remained worst<lb/> affected due to cessation of all tourism related activities and<lb/> H<lb/> i g h<lb/> C<lb/> o u r t o f H<lb/> . P .<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>businesses</note>

            <figDesc>. Petitioners though operated the vends under<lb/> the interim orders of the Court, but could not lift the MGQ<lb/> for the relevant period fixed in the Excise Announcements<lb/> for the year 2020-21. Actual sales have remained very low.<lb/> </figDesc>
<lb/> 
            <table>Therefore, MGQ fixed for the year 2020-21 for District Kullu<lb/> should be reduced by 30% or alternatively the excise fees<lb/> should be made proportional to actual lifting of the quantity<lb/> of the liquor. Petitioners have also laid emphasis upon their<lb/> various representations preferred in this regard to the<lb/> respondents prior to 01.06.2020 and even thereafter.<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>During hearing of the case, learned Senior Counsel<lb/> appearing on behalf of the petitioners submitted that<lb/> though their liquor vends have still not been able to lift the<lb/> MGQ fixed in the Excise Announcements 2020-21,<lb/> however, due to some leeway in resumption of tourism<lb/> activities in District Kullu, the petitioners would be willing<lb/> to abide by excise fee payments/MGQ/MVV of Excise Policy<lb/> 2020-21 w.e.f. 01.10.2020 onwards. However, the excise<lb/> levies for the period 01.06.2020 to 30.09.2020 be realized<lb/> from them only on pro-rata basis and not on the basis of<lb/> MGQ/MVV fixed in the Excise Policy 2020-21. With the<lb/> help of tabulated figures, it has been proclaimed that<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>H<lb/> i g h<lb/> C<lb/> o u r t o f H<lb/> . P .<lb/> reduction in MGQ by 5 and 10% for L-2 and L-14 licenses,<lb/> respectively, for first quarter of excise year 2020-21 does<lb/> not recompense business strains of the petitioners.<lb/> 4(ii).<lb/> Learned Advocate General vehemently opposed<lb/> the petitions. On facts, it was put forth that COVID-19 had<lb/> already spread its tentacles by the time the petitioners<lb/> applied for renewal of their excise licenses. A simile was<lb/> given that the petitioners though would never share their<lb/> advantage with State in case of boost in their sale, which<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>may occasion for any reason, say for example likely spurt of<lb/> tourism in the area on account of recent opening of Atal<lb/> Tunnel in Rohtang, Lahaul &amp; Spiti, but will crib over their<lb/> alleged losses or inability to lift the fixed MGQ due to<lb/> COVID-19 spread and wish State to come to their rescue.<lb/> He further submitted that the State Government has<lb/> already taken into consideration the losses during first<lb/> quarter of excise year 2020-21 and various decisions have<lb/> appropriately been taken for the benefit of liquor licensees<lb/> of the State. No special treatment can be given to liquor<lb/> licensees of District Kullu.<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>Relying upon (1994) 4 SCC 104, titled<lb/> Assistant Excise Commissioner and others Versus Issac<lb/> H<lb/> i g h<lb/> C<lb/> o u r t o f H<lb/> . P .<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <figDesc>Peter and others, learned Advocate General submitted<lb/> that the petitioners have entered into excise contract with<lb/> the State. The terms and conditions of the same are binding<lb/> upon the government and the licensees. Neither of them<lb/> can depart from the same. He pressed following para 14 of<lb/> the judgment in furtherance of his submissions:-<lb/>&quot;14. The contract between the parties is governed by statutory<lb/> provisions, i.e., provisions of the Act, the rules, the conditions<lb/> of licence and the counterpart agreement. They constitute the<lb/> terms and conditions of the contract. They are binding both<lb/> upon the Government and the licensee. Neither of them can<lb/> depart from them. It is not open to any officer of the<lb/> Government to either modify, amend or alter the said terms<lb/> and conditions, not even to the Minister for Excise…………..</figDesc>

            <note>&quot;<lb/> Learned Advocate General further relied upon<lb/> following extract of the above judgment to highlight the<lb/> point that executory contracts always carry in them an<lb/> element of risk. Even then the licensees cannot wriggle out<lb/> of their contractual obligations. When licensees cannot be<lb/> compelled to share their advantage with the State in a<lb/> converse situation, then they cannot ask the State to share<lb/> their alleged losses due to COVID-19 pandemic:-<lb/><note>&quot;16. ……………………………….. Even otherwise, having regard to<lb/> the context and the object underlying, there is no warrant for<lb/> holding that the words &quot;may permit&quot; in Rule 8(1) should be<lb/> read as &quot;shall permit&quot;. </note>
 
            <figDesc>The fallacy in the contention advanced<lb/> by the licensees can be demonstrated by taking a converse<lb/> case. Suppose in a given year, the production of arrack is<lb/> abundant. The Government has huge stocks of arrack, and<lb/> they are piling up. Can the Government force and compel the<lb/> licensees to lift additional quantities to clear its own stocks?<lb/> Would not the licensees say in such a case that they cannot be<lb/> </figDesc>
<lb/> 
            <table>H<lb/> i g h<lb/> C<lb/> o u r t o f H<lb/> . P .<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>forced </note>
 
            <figDesc>to lift quantities which they are not able to sell? If they<lb/> cannot be so forced, on what parity of reasoning is it claimed<lb/> that even if there are no supplies with the Government, it must<lb/> somehow supply the additional quantities demanded and if it<lb/> cannot so supply, it is not entitled to demand the monies as<lb/> per the contract? All this demonstrates amply that there is no<lb/> right in the licensees to compel the Government to supply what<lb/> all they demand nor has the State the right to compel the<lb/> licensees to purchase all that it proposes to sell to them. We<lb/> see no unreasonableness in this statement. We are of the<lb/> opinion that in the absence of a statutory right in the licensees<lb/> to get additional supplies demanded by him, there is no basis<lb/> in law for the claim of remission or rebate. As stated by this<lb/> Court in Panna Lal v. State of Rajasthan, (1975) 2 SCC 633,<lb/> the onerous nature of the terms is no ground for the licensees<lb/> to resile from the express obligations undertaken by them. The<lb/> Court observed: (SCC p. 638, para 21)<lb/> &quot;</figDesc>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <figDesc>No decision has been brought to our notice<lb/> supporting the said proposition. Secondly, in view of the<lb/> scarcity that had developed during the last two months of the<lb/> previous excise year (i.e., during February and March, 1981),<lb/> the plea of legitimate expectation sounds quite weak. That the<lb/> bidders were apprehensive and highly sceptical of alleged<lb/> official assurances is proved by the repeated adjournment of<lb/> auction and the fact pleaded by the licensees themselves that<lb/> during the said excise year (1981-82) half the shops in the<lb/> State remained unsold. It is inconceivable that the licensees<lb/> yet expected legitimately that additional supplies equal to the<lb/> previous year&apos;s additional supplies would be supplied during<lb/> this year. The plea is unacceptable.&quot;<lb/> </figDesc>
<lb/> 
            <table>Regarding<lb/> Doctrine<lb/> of<lb/> fairness<lb/> and<lb/> reasonableness, relying upon the following para of the<lb/> judgment in Issac Peter&apos;s case, supra, learned Advocate<lb/> General contended that the doctrine of fairness is developed<lb/> in the administrative law field to ensure the rule of law and<lb/> to prevent failure of justice where the action is<lb/> administrative in nature. It cannot be invoked to amend,<lb/> alter or vary the express terms of contract executed<lb/> between the parties. Para 26 of the judgment reads as<lb/> under:-<lb/>H<lb/> i g h<lb/> C<lb/> o u r t o f H<lb/> . P .<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>&quot;</note>

            <figDesc>26. Learned counsel for respondents then submitted that doctrine<lb/> of fairness and reasonableness must be read into contracts to<lb/> which State is a party. It is submitted that the State cannot act<lb/> unreasonably or unfairly even while acting under a contract<lb/> involving State power. Now, let us see, what is the purpose for<lb/> which this argument is addressed and what is the<lb/> implication?</figDesc>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <note>::: on -11/07/2022 23:28:38 :::CIS<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>H<lb/> i g h<lb/> C<lb/> o u r t o f H<lb/> . P .</table>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <table>Sr. No.<lb/> MGQ Quarter-wise<lb/> Percentage to be lifted<lb/> 1.<lb/> 1 st Quarter<lb/> 25<lb/> 2.<lb/> 2 nd Quarter<lb/> 20<lb/> 3.<lb/> 3 rd Quarter<lb/> 30<lb/> 4.<lb/> 4 th Quarter<lb/> 25<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <figDesc>The licensee shall be liable to pay penalty on the unlifted quota<lb/> failing short of 80% MGQ payable on quarterly basis by the last<lb/> day of the concerned quarter. If during a quarter, lifting fall<lb/> short of 80 percent of the MGQ in respect of the vends/units<lb/> allotted to him, he shall be liable to pay penalty @ Rs.370 per<lb/> proof liter on IMFS and Rs.320 per proof liter on Country Liquor<lb/> on such unlifted quota falling short of 80%. The concerned<lb/> district incharge shall review the lifting of MGQ, calculate and<lb/> intimate the penalty amount to the licensee latest by 5 th day of<lb/> end of the quarter and for the 4 th quarter by 10 th of March.&quot;<lb/> </figDesc>
<lb/> 
            <table>Liquor vends are located in tourist as well as in<lb/> non-tourist areas of the respondent-State. Writ Petition<lb/> Nos.1967, 1961 and 1969 of 2020 were instituted on<lb/> 30.06/01.07.2020. The liquor vends in these three writ<lb/> petitions are located in District Kullu. It was not till<lb/> October, 2020 that the State allowed resumption of some<lb/> activities in District Kullu. District Kullu is a tourist<lb/> place. Major part of its economy depends upon tourism<lb/> related activities. Closure of hotels, ban on social<lb/> gatherings, sports events, other functions and cultural<lb/> events, restrictions on tourism, hit hard the sale of liquor<lb/> H<lb/> i g h<lb/> C<lb/> o u r t o f H<lb/> . P .<lb/> 34<lb/> vends in tourist place like Kullu. It has not been disputed<lb/> that highest average per capita annual MGQ of IMFL at<lb/> 4.39 Pls (almost double of State&apos;s average @ 2.34 Pls) has<lb/> been fixed for District Kullu, where 80% sale of the liquor<lb/> vends comes from tourists. Following district-wise per<lb/> capita MGQ fixed for the year 2020-21 has been placed on<lb/> record by the petitioners:-<lb/>Name of District Populations<lb/> as<lb/> 2011<lb/> MGQ of IMFL for<lb/> the year 2020-21<lb/> Per Capita MGQ<lb/> Chamba<lb/> 518844<lb/> 854423<lb/> 1.65<lb/> Kangra<lb/> &amp;<lb/> Nurpur RD<lb/> 1507223<lb/> 3375808<lb/> 2.24<lb/> Lahaul &amp; Spiti<lb/> 31528<lb/> 114045<lb/> 3.62<lb/> Kullu<lb/> 437474<lb/> 1919148<lb/> 4.39<lb/> Mandi<lb/> 999518<lb/> 1518939<lb/> 1.52<lb/> Hamirpur<lb/> 454293<lb/> 976579<lb/> 2.15<lb/> Una<lb/> 521057<lb/> 1243553<lb/> 2.39<lb/> Bilaspur<lb/> 382056<lb/> 873765<lb/> 2.29<lb/> Solan &amp; BBM<lb/> RD<lb/> 576670<lb/> 2202181<lb/> 3.82<lb/> Sirmaur<lb/> 530164<lb/> 578599<lb/> 1.09<lb/> Shimla<lb/> 813384<lb/> 2176075<lb/> 2.68<lb/> Kinnaur<lb/> 84298<lb/> 217411<lb/> 2.58<lb/> Total<lb/> 6856509<lb/> 16050526<lb/> 2.34<lb/> Perhaps perceiving abysmal liquor sale figures,<lb/> the respondent-State on 16.06.2020, amended Himachal<lb/> Pradesh Liquor License Rules, 1986 and notified that<lb/> license fee and MGQ for bar licensees for the entire excise<lb/> year 2020-21 shall be charged on pro-rata basis. Welfare<lb/> State not only changed the terms of executed contract for<lb/> Bar Licenses for the benefit of licensees, but made the<lb/> altered terms valid for the entire excise year, whereas for<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>::: Downloaded on -11/07/2022 23:28:38 :::CIS<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>H<lb/> i g h<lb/> C<lb/> o u r t o f H<lb/> . P .<lb/> 35<lb/> retail excise licensees, there was no respite for the excise<lb/> year 2020-21. The time period of excise year 2020-21<lb/> remains the same despite its extension by two months. The<lb/> retail licensees of the year 2019-20 were allowed to operate<lb/> the vends during April and May, 2020, but the fact remains<lb/> that for the most part of these two months, the liquor vends<lb/> either remained closed or carried out very dismal business.<lb/> It is not even the case of the respondent-State that<lb/> immediately on commencement of excise year 2020-21,<lb/> normalcy had returned or the retail liquor sale figures had<lb/> jumped. Even the impugned order dated 31.08.2020<lb/> acknowledges this fact. Following figures in respect of lifting<lb/> of liquor reflect the tale of liquor vends&apos; business in the<lb/> State of Himachal Pradesh and we focus on District Kullu<lb/> as an example:-<lb/>H<lb/> i g h<lb/> C<lb/> o u r t o f H<lb/> . P .<lb/> 36<lb/> 2020, the lifting of Country Liquor and IMFS in District<lb/> Kullu was short by 66% and 71%, respectively, whereas for<lb/> the month of July, 2020, it was short by 74% and 82%,<lb/> respectively, when compared to data of same period of<lb/> excise year 2019-20.<lb/> Since the liquor sale had been low, therefore,<lb/> the Government of Himachal Pradesh in the order dated<lb/> 31.08.2020 decided to reduce MGQ of country liquor and<lb/> IMFL for first three months of excise year 2020-21, i.e.<lb/> June, July and August, 2020, by 5% and 10%, respectively,<lb/> for all L-2 and L-14 licenses. The reduction in MGQ gives<lb/> credence to the grievances of the petitioners regarding loss<lb/> of their business or else these decisions would not have<lb/> been taken. Reduction of MGQ by 5% and 10% also adds to<lb/> the argument that in the given unprecedented scenario<lb/> emerging from COVID-19, the terms &amp; conditions of the<lb/> excise contract executed between the parties were not<lb/> treated as concluded by the State.<lb/> 5(iv).<lb/> The above leads to next aspect as to whether<lb/> reduction by 5% and 10% in the MGQ for all L-2 and L-14<lb/> licenses during June, July and August, 2020 as allowed in<lb/> order dated 31.08.2020 meets the ends of justice or not.<lb/> H<lb/> i g h<lb/> C<lb/> o u r t o f H<lb/> . P .<lb/> Learned Advocate General would contend that<lb/> considering overall position, excise licensees have already<lb/> been provided various reliefs including the following major<lb/> respites, therefore, no other concession needs to be granted<lb/> to them:-<lb/>(a).<lb/> Petitioners/Retail Excise Licensees for 2019-20<lb/> were allowed to run the vends during April and May, 2020<lb/> by extending Excise Policy 2019-20 to 31.05.2020. License<lb/> fee during these months was levied only on pro-rata basis.<lb/> But the fact remains that for most of the period<lb/> during these two months, either no business was<lb/> transacted by liquor vends or it remained on very low side.<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <figDesc>Also no additional quota during extended Excise Policy<lb/> 2019-20 was allowed to be lifted by the licensee.<lb/> </figDesc>
<lb/> 
            <table>(b).<lb/> Excise Policy 2020-21 has already been<lb/> extended till 31.05.2021. Therefore, loss of revenue<lb/> especially in tourist destinations like Shimla, Kullu and<lb/> Dharamshala will be compensated during next tourist<lb/> season, which starts in April/May.<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <figDesc>What future holds cannot be guessed at this<lb/> stage. Fact alive today is that pandemic still predominates<lb/> everything without any known cure or solution. In any case,<lb/> </figDesc>
<lb/> 
            <note>::: Downloaded on -11/07/2022 23:28:38 :::CIS</note>
		</figure>



    </text>
</tei>

