<tei>
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc xml:id="_1214362.pdf"/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">


		<figure type="table">

            <table>J.WP.1394.2018.odt<lb/> Though the petitioner had retired from service the departmental<lb/> enquiry is continued by virtue of clause 34.2 of the CDA Rules. It is<lb/> further the contention of the respondent that leave encashment and<lb/> T.A. bills are withheld on the ground that if charge-sheet for major<lb/> penalty has been served and if on the conclusion of the disciplinary<lb/> proceeding, service is terminated then encashment of leave can be<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>forfeited in terms of the Coal India Limited Executives Leave Rules<lb/> and T.A. Rules, however, if service is not terminated on conclusion<lb/> of the disciplinary proceedings these may be released. The<lb/> respondent has further taken a stand that the petitioner is not<lb/> covered under Section ii(h) or ii(j) of the Mines Act, 1952. The<lb/> encashment of half pay leave has to be given as per the Executive<lb/> Leave Rules. The Executive of the Coal India Limited has to<lb/> perform their duties not only in mines but in other places as well<lb/> and many other places do not fall under the definition of the Mines<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>as provided under the Mines Act, 1952, hence Coal India Limited<lb/> has framed it&apos;s own rules related to earned leave. The earned leave<lb/> credited under the rules of Coal India is not linked with attendance.<lb/> It is the contention of the respondent that once the petitioner had<lb/> subjected himself to the terms of the appointment letter which<lb/> J.WP.1394.2018.odt<lb/> 6<lb/> specifically apply to him the leave Rules of the CPSE and his<lb/> petition proceeds on the basis that the Coal India Executive Leave<lb/> Rules, 2010 are a complete code in itself, then it is not open to him<lb/> to urge that rules of the Mines Act, 1952 are applicable to him and,<lb/> therefore, petition deserves to be dismissed.<lb/> 5.<lb/> Heard Shri Bhandarkar, learned Counsel for the<lb/> petitioner. He submitted that the petitioner is entitled for the leave<lb/> encashment. He is already retired from the service. The leave<lb/> encashment is towards the work or services rendered by him during<lb/> his tenure. In support of his contention, he relied upon the<lb/> decision of this Court in the case of Pramod Kumar Battad Vs.<lb/> Western Coalfields Ltd. and anr. (W.P. No.3866 of 2017) decided on<lb/> 19/03/2018, wherein it is held that the petitioner is entitled to<lb/> leave encashment benefits as the petitioner has retired on attaining<lb/> the age of superannuation but the same are wrongfully denied to<lb/> the petitioner. He is also relied upon the decision of this Court in<lb/> the case of Sharda Nandlal Das s/o Late Mahabir Lal Das Vs. Coal<lb/> India Ltd. and anr. (W.P. No.2163 of 2012) decided on 10/08/2012,<lb/> wherein it is held that the petitioner is entitled for the encashment<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>J.WP.1394.2018.odt<lb/> 7<lb/> of Earned Leave and Half Pay Leave. He further relied upon the<lb/> decision of the Hon&apos;ble Apex Court in the case of Jaswant Singh<lb/> Gill Vs. Bharat Coking Coal Limited and others (2007) 1 SCC 663.<lb/> 6.<lb/> On the basis of the decisions referred by him, he<lb/> submitted that as the petitioner was working in the mines the<lb/> provisions of Section 52(10) of the Mines Act, 1952, the petitioner<lb/> is entitled to leave encashment dues.<lb/> 7.<lb/> He submitted that in view of the judgment of this Court<lb/> in the case of Pramod s/o Gulabchand Baid Vs. Coal India Limited<lb/> and another (W.P. No.3430/2010) decided on 26/11/2010, the<lb/> petitioner is entitled for the claims.<lb/> 8.<lb/> He also invited our attention towards the rules of the<lb/> Coal India Executives Leave Rules, 2010 and submitted that clause<lb/> 7.3 states about Earned Leave on full pay as per clause 7.3.4(a) the<lb/> credit for the half year in which an executive is due to retire or<lb/> resigns from the service, shall be afforded only at the rate of two<lb/> <note>J</note>

            <figDesc>.WP.1394.2018.odt<lb/> 8<lb/> and half days per completed calendar month in that half year up to<lb/> date of retirement/resignation. In view of clause 7.3.5 Earned<lb/> leave can be accumulated upto 300 days. He submitted that the<lb/> petitioner is entitled for the leave encashment in accordance with<lb/> the Rule 12.1 of the Coal India Services Rules. Hence, the action of<lb/> the respondent is arbitrary and illegal.<lb/> </figDesc>
<lb/> 
            <note>9.<lb/> On the other hand, Shri Ghare, learned Counsel for the<lb/> respondent submitted that the petitioner has not come before the<lb/> Court with clean hand. He has suppressed the fact that he was<lb/> charge sheeted under Rule 29 of the Coal India Executives CDA<lb/> Rules, 1978 on an allegation that he had misused his official<lb/> position as a General Manager and as a tender committee member<lb/> in tendering process of supply, installation and commission of<lb/> secondary crusher. He gave undue favor while working as a<lb/> member of Tender Committee. As the reply given by him was<lb/> unsatisfactory, the departmental enquiry was ordered against him<lb/> and the same has not been completed. If he is exonerated from the<lb/> said enquiry he is entitled for the said encashment. He invited the<lb/> attention towards CDA Rules 34.2 which specifically states that<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>J.WP.1394.2018.odt<lb/> 9<lb/> disciplinary proceeding, if instituted while an employee was in<lb/> service whether before his retirement or during his re-employment<lb/> shall, after the final retirement of the employee, be deemed to be<lb/> proceeding and shall be continued and concluded by the authority<lb/> by which it was commenced in the same manner as if the employee<lb/> had continued in service. He submitted that the provisions of the<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>Mines Act, 1972 are not at all applicable to the petitioner as he was<lb/> working as an Executive. As the petitioner was charge sheeted his<lb/> leave encashment is withheld. The petitioner is very well aware<lb/> about the said fact which is specifically mentioned in the<lb/> memorandum which was issued to him. The memorandum bearing<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>No. CIL/VIG/2015 dated 08/09/2015 specifically states that it laid<lb/> down vide CIL/VIG/05057/Part-I/2600 dated 22/02/2006 that in<lb/> case of final settlement of dues on superannuation or voluntary<lb/> retirement/resignation, Vigilance Status shall be withheld only if a<lb/> major penalty proceeding memorandum has been served on the<lb/> employee and till the issue of final order in the case. Despite such<lb/> clear stipulation, it has come to notice that the gratuity/leave salary<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>etc. is being withheld merely because any investigation by Vigilance<lb/> or CBI is going on or any report is under consideration of CVO/DA/<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>J.WP.1394.2018.odt<lb/> 10<lb/> MOC/CVC etc. at the time of superannuation.<lb/> The said<lb/> memorandum specifically states that the leave encashment and T.A.<lb/> bill can be withheld if charge-sheet for major penalty has been<lb/> served till its finalisation. He submitted that in accordance with the<lb/> specific policy of the Company and as charge-sheet is served upon<lb/> the petitioner the leave encashment is withheld. Hence the action<lb/> of the respondent is legal and proper one and the petition deserves<lb/> to be dismissed.<lb/> 10.<lb/> After hearing of both the sides and on perusal of the<lb/> record it is an admitted position that the petitioner was appointed<lb/> as a Junior Executive Trainee (E and M) under the Central Mine<lb/> Planning and Design Institute (CMPDI), Ranchi. On 06/07/2003,<lb/> the petitioner was transferred in respondent-Company. On<lb/> 30/11/2016, the petitioner retired from the respondent/Company<lb/> on attaining the age of 60 years from the post of General Manager.<lb/> Thus it is clear from the record that the petitioner entered in the<lb/> service of the respondent as an Executive and he retired from the<lb/> service as an Executive on 30/11/2016. When he was in service, on<lb/> 25/11/2016 the charge-sheet was served upon him vide reference<lb/> J.WP.1394.2018.odt<lb/> 11<lb/> No.WCL/CMD/VIG/2016-17/2246. As per the charge-sheet, he<lb/> was charged with an allegation that while functioning as a General<lb/> Manger (E and M) at WCL headquarters, being a public servant, he<lb/> has committed grave misconduct by abusing his official position.<lb/> As General Manager and a tender committee member in tendering<lb/> process of supply, installation and commissioning of secondary<lb/> crushers for different areas of WCL he granted undue favor to<lb/> M/s. Larsen and Toubro Ltd. by qualifying the firm in Part-I of bid<lb/> in deviation to the provisions of NIT (Tender Document) experience<lb/> criteria. He was further charged on an allegation that being a<lb/> member of tender committee he granted undue favor to M/s. Black<lb/> Diamond Equipment Pvt. Ltd. by qualifying the firm in Part-II of bid<lb/> in deviation to the provisions of NIT (Tender Document). He was<lb/> further charged on an allegation that he illegally disqualified<lb/> M/s. Karam Chand Thappar &amp; Sons in Tender No.15, although the<lb/> firm submitted its bid as per the laid down norms of NIT. It is<lb/> further alleged in the charge-sheet that being a Member of Tender<lb/> Committee, he had not considered the preparation of justified cost<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>with price index of material handling equipment and order price of<lb/> M/s Adani Power placed on M/s Larsen and Tourbo Company Ltd.<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>J.WP.1394.2018.odt<lb/> 12<lb/> for same model quoted to the Company and accepted by the tender<lb/> Committee. Thus as per the charge he had committed grave<lb/> misconduct by abusing his official position and caused a huge loss<lb/> to the tune of Rs.1,16,56,989/-(Rs. One crore sixteen lacs fifty six<lb/> thousand nine hundred and eighty nine). Said charge-sheet was<lb/> served upon him when he was in service on 25/11/2016 and<lb/> thereafter he retired from service on 30/11/2016. The respondent<lb/> on 08/09/2015 vide reference No. CIL/VIG/2015/1243 issued a<lb/> memorandum to all the Executives regarding the subject final<lb/> settlement of dues on superannuation. The memorandum states<lb/> that it is laid down in OM No.CIL/VIG/05057/Part-I/2600 dated<lb/> 22/02/2006 that in case of final settlement of dues on<lb/> superannuation or voluntary retirement/resignation, Vigilance<lb/> Status shall be withheld only if a major penalty proceeding<lb/> memorandum has been served on the employee and till the issue of<lb/> final order in the case. Despite such clear stipulation, it has come<lb/> to notice that gratuity/leave salary etc. was being withheld merely<lb/> because any investigation by Vigilance or CBI is going on or any<lb/> report is under consideration of CVO/DA/MOC/CVC etc. at the<lb/> time of superannuation. This memorandum further clarifies that<lb/> J.WP.1394.2018.odt<lb/> 13<lb/> under the existing provisions, if no charge-sheet is issued till his<lb/> retirement, no charge-sheet can be issued after retirement and his<lb/> service cannot be terminated even on deemed basis. In such a<lb/> situation, there is no scope for forfeiting gratuity or leave salary or<lb/> Travelling Allowance.<lb/> 11.<lb/> It further states in paragraph No.3 that however, if<lb/> charge-sheet for major penalty has been served before<lb/> superannuation, the decision for gratuity may be taken in terms of<lb/> clarification issued vide office order No.CIL/C-5A(PC)/CDA/58<lb/> dated 08/09/2011. It further clarifies that leave encashment and<lb/> T.A. bills can be withheld if charge-sheet for major penalty has been<lb/> served till its finalisation. If on conclusion of the Disciplinary<lb/> Proceeding, service is terminated through deemed dismissal/<lb/> deemed removal/deemed compulsory retirement, encashment of<lb/> leave can be forfeited in terms of note. However, if service is not<lb/> terminated on conclusion of disciplinary proceeding the same may<lb/> be released. Thus it appears from the memorandum dated<lb/> 08/09/2015 that specific policy is accepted by the respondent in<lb/> respect of final settlement of dues on superannuation. This policy<lb/> J.WP.1394.2018.odt<lb/> 14<lb/> clarifies that if there is a charge-sheet for major penalty then leave<lb/> encashment and T.A. bills can be withheld.<lb/> 12.<lb/> The petitioner has relied upon the Coal India Executives<lb/> Leave Rules, 2010. Rule No.12.3 speaks about the extent of<lb/> encashment of earned leave.<lb/> Rule No.12.4 states about<lb/> encashment of earned leave on termination of service/retirement.<lb/> Rule 12.4.1 says that leave at credit shall not be granted for<lb/> encashment if an executive resigns from the service. However an<lb/> executive who has resigned from the service can avail the benefit<lb/> for the encashable portion of earned leave prior to the date of his<lb/> actual quitting/release from service. Rule 12.4.2 speaks about the<lb/> termination which states that an executive governed under the Coal<lb/> India Service Rules, whose services are terminated, otherwise than<lb/> on disciplinary grounds, or who retires on superannuation, may be<lb/> allowed to encash the earned leave at his credit, subject to a<lb/> maximum of 300 days. This rule specifically states that a person<lb/> who is terminated otherwise than on disciplinary ground may be<lb/> allowed to encash the earned leave at his credit and Rule No.12.4.3<lb/> speaks about the contingency in case of death. Admittedly in the<lb/> J.WP.1394.2018.odt<lb/> 15<lb/> present case, the petitioner served with the charge-sheet it means<lb/> disciplinary action has been taken and the enquiry is pending.<lb/> 13.<lb/> It is submitted by the petitioner that in view of Section<lb/> 52 of the Mines Act, 1952, he is entitled for the said leave<lb/> encashment. Admittedly the Mines Act, 1952 was passed with a<lb/> view to amend and consolidating the law relating to the regulation<lb/> of labour and safety in mines. The statement and objects as per the<lb/> Mines (Amendment) Act No.42 of 1983 speaks about regulating the<lb/> working condition in mines by providing for measures to be taken<lb/> for safety of the workers employed therein and certain amenities<lb/> for them. Section 52 of the Mines Act, 1952 states about annual<lb/> leave wages. Wages are a sum of money paid under the contract by<lb/> an employers to a worker for services rendered. Wages are<lb/> payments for labour services rendered in hourly rates while a salary<lb/> is a similar payment expressed in weekly, monthly or annual rates.<lb/> Section 52(10) specifically states about the wages to a persons<lb/> employed in mines. The petitioner was working with the Company<lb/> as a Junior Executive Trainee. At no point of time he worked as a<lb/> worker. As he was working as an Executive he had to perform his<lb/> J.WP.1394.2018.odt<lb/> 16<lb/> duty not in the mines and, therefore, the provisions of Mines Act,<lb/> 1952 are not applicable to him.<lb/> 14.<lb/> The aspects whether the provisions of the Mines Act,<lb/> 1952 are applicable to the Executives is dealt by this Court in W.P.<lb/> No.4104/2017 (Shri Gurjit Singh s/o Late Gopal Singh Vs. Coal<lb/> India Ltd. and anr.) and W.P. No.4318/2017 (Mrs. Anjana Mehta<lb/> wd/o Deceased Dr. Surendraprasad Mehta Vs. Coal India Ltd. and<lb/> ors.) wherein it is held by this Court that in view of the provisions<lb/> contained in Section 2(h) and Section 17 of the Act read with<lb/> Section 52(10) thereof as well as the provisions contained in the<lb/> Coal Mines Regulations 1957 (hereinafter referred to as &apos;the<lb/> Regulations&apos; for short) the legal position was clear that the Act<lb/> provides the benefits for those who are actually employed in mines<lb/> and similar such benefits cannot be extended to Officers/Executives<lb/> of the WCL. </table>
 
            <figDesc>It is observed by this Court that in view of the<lb/> marginal note given under Section 52 says &quot;Annual Leave with<lb/> Wages&quot;, it was primarily relatable to entitlement to and release of<lb/> wages to any person employed in a mine. The word &apos;wages&apos; has not<lb/> been defined in the Act, but is defined in the Industrial Disputes<lb/> J.WP.1394.2018.odt<lb/> 17<lb/> Act, 1947. Wages are ordinarily paid to workmen/labourers.<lb/> Officers/executives are not paid wages in the sense the term is used<lb/> with reference to workmen/labourers. It is further clarified by this<lb/> Court in the said writ petitions that the term Manager in Section<lb/> 2(h) read with Section 17 read with Regulation 31 of the<lb/> Regulations would mean only those Managers, who have the<lb/> requisite qualifications to work in mine and are comprehended<lb/> within the meaning of the words &quot;a person is said to be employed<lb/> in a mine&quot;. It is observed by this Court that the said petitioners had<lb/> no right in law to claim leave encashment benefits, which otherwise<lb/> were due to them but for the orders of removal on disciplinary<lb/> ground and dismissal consequent to conviction recorded by the<lb/> Special Court, in view of clear provision in Rule 7.2 of the Service<lb/> Rules.</figDesc>
		</figure>



    </text>
</tei>

