<tei>
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc xml:id="_13442700.pdf"/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">


		<figure type="table">

            <table>2. Dindayal Mandavi, S/o Shri Bharat Singh Mandavi, aged 40<lb/> Years, At Present:Sub Divisional Officer Keshkal,<lb/> Kondagaon District-Kondagon, Chhattisgarh.<lb/> 3. Arjun Shrivastava, aged 57 Years, S/o Shri Y.L. Shrivastava<lb/> Tahsildar (In-Charge) -Lohandiguda Bastar, District Bastar<lb/> Chhattisgarh.<lb/> 4. Dharam Narayan Sahu, aged 64 Years, S/o Shri Lakhan<lb/> Sahu Retd Patwari, R/o Bhagat Singh Ward-6 Patharaguda,<lb/> Jagdalpur District Jagdapur Chhattisgarh.<lb/> ----Appellants<lb/> Versus<lb/> 4. Station House Officer, Police Station Jagdalpur, District<lb/> Jagdalpur Chhattisgarh.<lb/> ----Respondents<lb/> WA No. 119 of 2022<lb/> 1. Suresh B. Matali, S/o Shri B.S. Matali, Aged About 52 Years<lb/> Addl. General Manager (Civil), R/o House No. 10, Aashoka<lb/> Lifestyle, Dharampura-3, Police Station City Kotwali,<lb/> Jagdalpur, District Bastar Chhattisgarh. Permanent R/o<lb/> H.No.-MIG-39, Jalanagar, Vijayapura, 586101, Karnatka,<lb/> 2. A.V.R. Murty, S/o Shri A. Krishna Murty, Aged About 54<lb/> Years, Joint General Manager (Civil), R/o House No. 69,<lb/> Ashoka Lifestyle, Dharampura-3, Police Station City Kotwali,<lb/> Jagdalpur, District Bastar Chhattisgarh. Permanent R/o<lb/> H/No. 12-2-16/2, Chinna Veedhi, Samalkot, 533440, East<lb/> Godawari District, Andhra Pradesh.<lb/> ----Appellants<lb/> Versus<lb/> 1. State of Chhattisgarh, Through The Secretary to the<lb/> Government of Chhattisgarh Department of Revenue and<lb/> Disaster Management Mahanadi Bhawan, Atal Nagar,<lb/> Raipur District Raipur Chhattisgarh.<lb/> 2. Union of India Through The Secretary to the Department of<lb/> Railway, Raisina Road, Rail Bhawan, 1, New Delhi, District<lb/> New Delhi, Delhi.<lb/> 3. The Collector Jagadalpur, District Bastar, Chhattisgarh.<lb/> 4. Station House Officer, Police Station Jagdalpur, District-<lb/>Bastar, Chhattisgarh.<lb/> ----Respondents<lb/> (Cause-title taken from Case Information System)<lb/> _________________________________________________<lb/> For Appellants<lb/> : Heard Mr. Prashant Bhushan, learned<lb/> senior<lb/> counsel<lb/> (through<lb/> video-<lb/>conferencing) assisted by Mr. Amit<lb/> Verma, learned counsel, appearing for the<lb/> appellant in WA No. 81/2022 and WA No.<lb/> 64/2022, Mr. Anurag Dayal Shrivastava,<lb/> learned counsel, appearing for the<lb/> appellant, in WA No. 77/2022, 83/2022<lb/> and 129/2022, Mr. Siddharth Shukla,<lb/> learned counsel, appearing for the<lb/> appellant in WA No. 115/2022, Mr. Arvind<lb/> Shrivastava, learned counsel, appearing<lb/> for the appellant, in WA No. 119/2022, Mr.<lb/> Varun<lb/> Sharma,<lb/> learned<lb/> counsel,<lb/> appearing for the appellants, in WA No.<lb/> 144/2022.<lb/> For Respondents<lb/> : Mr. Vikas Singh, learned senior counsel<lb/> (through video-conferencing), assisted by<lb/> Mr. Vaibhav Shukla, Mr. Ujjwal Choubey<lb/> and Mr. Chandradeep Prasad, learned<lb/> counsel, appearing for the respondent-<lb/>Bastar Railway Private Limited, Ms. Astha<lb/> Shukla, learned Government Advocate<lb/> and Mr. Vikram Sharma, learned Deputy<lb/> Government Advocate for the State and<lb/> Mr. Ramakant Mishra, learned Assistant<lb/> Solicitor General for the Union of India.<lb/> Date of hearing<lb/> : 13-05-2022<lb/> Date of Judgment<lb/> : 28-06-2022<lb/> Hon&apos;</table>

            <head>ble Shri Arup Kumar Goswami, Chief Justice<lb/> Hon&apos;ble Shri Rajendra Chandra Singh Samant, Judge<lb/> C.A.V. Judgment<lb/> Per R.C.S. Samant, J.<lb/> </head>
<lb/> 
            <table>1.<lb/> Writ Appeal No.64/2022 has been preferred challenging the<lb/> order dated 10.01.2022 passed in Writ Petition(Civil) No.<lb/> 3355/2019 by which the petition was allowed and the award<lb/> dated 12.02.2018 passed by the Competent Authority and<lb/> the Arbitration Award passed by the Commissioner,<lb/> Jagdalpur dated 11.7.2019 were set aside.<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>Writ Appeal No.81/2022 has been preferred against<lb/> the order dated 10.1.2022 in Writ Petition(Cr.)<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <figDesc>No.1031/2019. Writ Appeal No.81/2022 is preferred against<lb/> the same order by which the order dated 10.1.2022 in WPC<lb/> </figDesc>
<lb/> 
            <table>No.3355/2019 has been challenged.<lb/> In Writ Appeal No.119/2022 the order of Single Bench<lb/> in Writ Petition(Cr.)No.828/2019 passed on 10.1.2022,<lb/> dismissing the petition is under challenge.<lb/> In Writ Appeal No.144/2022 the order of Single Bench<lb/> dated 10.1.2022 dismissing the Writ Petition(Cr.)<lb/> No.1096/2019 has been challenged.<lb/> Writ Appeal No.129/2022 has been preferred against<lb/> the same order dated 10.1.2022 by which the Writ<lb/> Petition(Cr.) No.674/2019 preferred by the appellants, was<lb/> dismissed.<lb/> Writ Appeal No.83/2022 has been preferred by the<lb/> appellants against the order dated 10.1.2022 of Single<lb/> Bench dismissing the Writ Petition(Cr.) No.751/2019.<lb/> Writ Appeal No.115/2022 has been preferred against<lb/> the order dated 10.1.2022 of Single Bench by which the Writ<lb/> Petition(Cr.) No.1037/2019 has been dismissed.<lb/> Writ Appeal No.77/2022 has been preferred against<lb/> the judgment dated 10.1.2022 by which the Writ<lb/> Petition(Civil) No.3355/2019, was allowed.<lb/> 2.<lb/> A project for construction of single railway line of length of<lb/> 140km named as Rowghat, Jagdalpur broad-gauge single<lb/> railway line was declared as Special Railway Project by<lb/> Gazette Notification dated 4.4.2016. For execution of this<lb/> railway project, 1863 hectares of land was proposed to be<lb/> acquired, out of which 140.233 hectares were private lands.<lb/> A notification dated 21.8.2017 was issued under Section 20A<lb/> of the Railways Act, 1989 (for short &apos;the Act, 1989&apos;), by the<lb/> competent authority declaring the intention to acquire the<lb/> lands for the execution of the Special Railway Project. After<lb/> granting time for objections, the notification for acquisition of<lb/> lands was issued under Section 20E of the Act, 1989, on<lb/> 21.12.2017. The appellants in Writ Appeal No.64/2022,<lb/> 81/2022, 77/2022 and 83/2022 were the land owners, whose<lb/> land was situated in Village-Palli. They were the affected<lb/> persons as their lands were acquired for this Special<lb/> Railway Project. The Additional Collector District-<lb/>Bastar/Competent Authority, proceeded for determination of<lb/> the award in application No.34/2017 and passed the award<lb/> date 12.2.2018 granting compensation of Rs.188.83 crores.<lb/> Khasra No.123/1 of area 7000 sq. meter and khasra<lb/> No.123/2 of area 19900 sq.meter was acquired from<lb/> appellant Bali Nagwanshi. Plot bearing Khasra No.125/1 to<lb/> 125/29, 125/31, 125/33 to 125/37, which were plots situated<lb/> in the colony developed in the name of &quot;Neelima Spandan&quot;<lb/> were also acquired for this project. Compensation for land<lb/> acquired from Bali Nagwanshi was determined as 70.62<lb/> Crores for the total area of the land which was acquired<lb/> being 2.69 hectares. Similarly, the compensation was<lb/> determined in favor of appellant Neelima Belsariya to the<lb/> tune of Rs.25.19 Crores for the total area of the land which<lb/> was acquired being 1.040 hectares.<lb/> 3.<lb/> Appellant Bali Nagwanshi in WA No.81/2022 &amp; 64/2022, not<lb/> being satisfied with the compensation determined, preferred<lb/> arbitration reference before the Commissioner, Bastar<lb/> Division, on which vide order dated 11.7.2019, the<lb/> Arbitration Award was given, by enhancing the<lb/> compensation and granting additional amount of<lb/> Rs.7,79,04,091/-.<lb/> 4.<lb/> The arbitration reference was also made by appellant-<lb/>Neelima Belsariya in WA No.83/2022 &amp; 77/2022 before<lb/> Additional Commissioner, Bastar Division, which was<lb/> decided by order dated 11.7.2019 and she got an<lb/> enhancement of Rs.98,39,610/-.<lb/> 5.<lb/> The Collector District-Bastar took cognizance of a news item<lb/> published in daily newspaper-Navbharat dated 19.7.2019<lb/> about discrepancies and scam in the acquisition matter and<lb/> he constituted a Committee of three members to inquire into<lb/> the matter.<lb/> 6.<lb/> The Committee made an inquiry and submitted a report. The<lb/> Collector District-Bastar, by a memo dated 30.7.2019, by<lb/> relying upon the report of the Committee, came to the<lb/> conclusion that the determination of compensation by the<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>Competent Authority and the Arbitrator was erroneous and<lb/> that the Railway Officials, the then Additional Collector, SDM<lb/> and others were involved in the conspiracy for determination<lb/> of huge compensation in favor of Bali Nagwanshi and<lb/> Neelima Belsariya beyond their entitlement and on this<lb/> basis, he directed lodging of FIR. The FIR was lodged as<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>Crime No.409/2019 against the Dharmnarayan Sahu<lb/> (Patwari), Arjun<lb/> Shrivastava<lb/> (Revenue<lb/> Inspector),<lb/> Deendayal Mandavi (Tahsildar), Siyaram Kurre (SDO,<lb/> Revenue), Heeralal Nayak (Additional Collector cum<lb/> Competent Authority), Kaushal Thakur (in-charge sub-<lb/>Registrar), Officer from IRCON Suresh B. Mitali, Officer from<lb/> IRCON A.R. Murthy, Range Officer G.R. Rao, Bali<lb/> Nagwanshi and Neellima Belsariya. Various writ petitions<lb/> have been disposed off by the Single Bench by the<lb/> impugned order and they are the appellants before this<lb/> Court in their respective writ appeals.<lb/> 7. The petitioners in Writ Petition(Cr.) 674/2019 Siyaram and<lb/> others are the Revenue Officers. The petitioners in Writ<lb/> Petition(Cr.) No.1027/2019, Heeralal Nayak was Competent<lb/> Authority, the petitioner in Writ Petition(Cr.) No.1096/2019<lb/> Kaushal Kumar Thakur was the Clerk/In-Charge of Sub-<lb/>Registrar Office, Neelima Belsariya and one another<lb/> petitioner in Writ Petition(Cr.) No.97/2019. Neelima Belsariya<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>again the petitioner in Writ Petition(Cr.) No.751/2019, Bali<lb/> Nagwanshi the petitioner in Writ Petition(Cr.) No.1031/2019<lb/> and Suresh B. Mitali and another petitioner in Writ<lb/> Petition(Cr.) No.828/2019 had preferred the writ petitions<lb/> praying for quashment of the FIR lodged against them. The<lb/> Bastar Railway Pvt. Ltd. (for short &apos;BRPL&apos;), petitioner in Writ<lb/> Petition(Civil) No.3355/2019 had preferred the petition<lb/> praying for quashment of the compensation award of the<lb/> Competent Authority and also the Arbitration Award given by<lb/> the Arbitrator / Commissioner, Bastar Division. The learned<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>Single Bench has by the detailed order allowed the Writ<lb/> Petition(Civil) No.3355/2019, by setting aside the Award<lb/> passed by the Competent Authority dated 12.2.2018 and by<lb/> the Commissioner dated 11.7.2019. All the other writ<lb/> petitions(criminal) preferred were dismissed.<lb/> 8.<lb/> Mr. Prashant Bhushan, learned counsel for the petitioner Bali<lb/> Nagwanshi submits, that Writ Petition(Civil) No.3355/2019<lb/> was not maintainable, as there was remedy available under<lb/> Section 34 of the Arbitration and Conciliation Act, 1996., (for<lb/> short, &apos;the Act, 1996&apos;). Such an application has also been<lb/> preferred by the respondent Bastar Railway Pvt. Ltd, before<lb/> the Court of District Judge, Bastar. Hence, the petition was<lb/> not maintainable on this ground. It is further submitted, that<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>according to the reliefs that were claimed by the petitioner<lb/> BRPL in Writ Petition(Civil) No.3355/2019, initially, the<lb/> petition was not maintainable. An application for amendment<lb/> was filed by which additional relief, which was prayer for<lb/> setting aside the award dated 11.7.2019 passed by the<lb/> Commissioner was allowed at the final hearing stage and<lb/> then the same relief was granted to the petitioner BRPL. It<lb/> is further submitted that after filing of an application under<lb/> Section 34 of the Act, 1996, such a prayer for setting aside<lb/> the Award of the Arbitrator under Article 226 Constitution<lb/> was not maintainable. Reliance was placed on judgment of<lb/> Supreme Court in SBP &amp; Co. Vs. Patel Engg. Ltd.,<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>reported in (2005) 8 SCC 618 and Haryana Urban<lb/> Development Authority, Karnal Vs. Mehta Construction<lb/> Company, reported in 2022 SCC OnLine SC 396. This<lb/> objection was raised by the petitioner side, but the same<lb/> was not decided. Hence, the order allowing the Writ<lb/> Petition(Civil) No.3355/2019, is erroneous. The learned<lb/> Single Judge has made an erroneous mention in the<lb/> paragraph No. 117 of the impugned order, that no one has<lb/> raised objection about maintainability of the writ petition at<lb/> the initial stage, which is not a correct statement and hence,<lb/> the order of the learned Single Bench in Writ Petition(Civil)<lb/> No.3355/2019, is liable to be set aside.<lb/> 9.<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>It is submitted by Mr. Prashant Bhushan, learned counsel for<lb/> the petitioner, that the land of the petitioner Bali Nagwanshi<lb/> that was acquired was urban land, which was situated<lb/> adjacent to the main road and the compensation was<lb/> determined in accordance with guidelines of 2017-2018, by<lb/> the Inspector General Registrar and Superintendent(Stamp),<lb/> Raipur. There was provision of compensation in accordance<lb/> with per square meter market value of the plot situated<lb/> within the depth of 20 meters from the main road and<lb/> accordingly, compensation was determined by the<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>Competent Authority and was enhanced by the<lb/> Commissioner, Bastar Division / Arbitrator.<lb/> 10. The guidelines of 2017-2018 specifically mentions in Serial<lb/> No.34 &amp; 37, that for the land situated on the way from MGM<lb/> School to Palli Naka, the compensation was to be<lb/> determined at the rate of Rs.13,800/-per sq. meter, for such<lb/> lands which are situated within the 20 meters depth from the<lb/> main road.<lb/> 11. By the Government Notification dated 2.7.2014, the State<lb/> Government determined the Extent of Wards of Nagar<lb/> Nigam, Jagdalpur. According to the Schedule, the Serial<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>No.37 mentions of Lokmanya Tilak Ward, which includes the<lb/> Palli area. In the details of the Ward No.37, there is mention<lb/> of Palli Naka. Clause No.10 of the guidelines itself mentions,<lb/> that the urban residential area which is situated adjacent the<lb/> main road, being used for Commercial/Industrial purpose for<lb/> that, the market price was to be calculated at the enhanced<lb/> rate upto 25% of the compensation for that area. Clause<lb/> No.11 further provides, that the locality/colony/route in the<lb/> urban area, which has been shown in the guidelines, in that<lb/> place, the market price will be calculated according to the<lb/> rate of the locality/colony/route, which has been followed in<lb/> determining the compensation. It is submitted that the<lb/> Collector is bound to follow the provision under Section 26 of<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>the Right to Fair Compensation and Transparency in Land<lb/> Acquisition, Rehabilitation and Resettlement Act, 2013 (for<lb/> short, &apos;the Act, 2013&apos;) and, therefore, there is no error<lb/> committed by the Competent Authority, in determining the<lb/> compensation and, further, the Commissioner also has not<lb/> committed any error in enhancing the compensation in favor<lb/> of the appellant Bali Nagwanshi. The Award of the<lb/> Competent Authority and the Arbitrator both are sustainable.<lb/> The land that had been acquired by the respondent<lb/> authorities was purchased by the petitioner Bali Nagwanshi<lb/> about nine years prior to its acquisition. On these grounds,<lb/> the impugned order is challenged and he contends that the<lb/> FIR is baseless and vexatious.<lb/> 12. Mr. Anurag Dayal Shrivastava, learned counsel in Writ<lb/> Appeal No.77/2022, 129/2022 &amp; 83/2022 submits, that Writ<lb/> Petition(Civil) No.3355/2019 was not maintainable as it was<lb/> based only on the report of the Collector. The Collector has<lb/> no authority to inquire into the matter under the provisions of<lb/> the Act, 1989. The whole procedure of acquisition has taken<lb/> place under the provisions of the Act, 1989. The Additional<lb/> Collector was notified as Competent Authority. The<lb/> notification dated 21.8.2007 issued under Section 20A of the<lb/> Act, 1989, can neither be challenged in any Court nor can it<lb/> be examined by a Criminal Court. It is submitted that the<lb/> petitioners filed a Writ Petition(Civil) No.3355/2019 after long<lb/> delay and hence it was not maintainable. On the basis of the<lb/> prayer clause which was initially present the petition was not<lb/> maintainable. The learned Single Bench has allowed the<lb/> amendment in prayer clause, which was included later on,<lb/> regarding which the objection was raised, that when an<lb/> application under Section 34 of the Act, 1996, was pending,<lb/> prayer for setting aside the award of the arbitrator should not<lb/> have been entertained by this Court in the writ petition.<lb/> Hence, the order of Single Bench in Writ Petition(Civil)<lb/> No.3355/2019 is not sustainable.<lb/> 13. It is further submitted by Mr. Shrivastava, learned counsel<lb/> that the land belonging to the appellant-Neelima Belsaria<lb/> was urban land situated in Ward No.37 and there was a<lb/> diversion order for the same regarding land use. This land<lb/> was present in the colony developed and styled as &quot;Neelima<lb/> Spandan&quot;. The State Government had passed the order<lb/> restraining transfer/ sale of land in the project area for the<lb/> Railway construction. The appellant-Neelima Belsaria had<lb/> challenged this order in Writ Petition(227) No.238/2012<lb/> which was disposed off on 07.08.2014 by the learned Single<lb/> Judge partly allowing the petition. It was held in that order<lb/> that the diversion for the land use was just and proper and in<lb/> accordance with law.<lb/> He endorses the submissions made by the learned<lb/> counsel for Bali Nagwanshi, that the land in question is<lb/> situated in the urban area under the municipal limits of<lb/> Municipal<lb/> Corporation,<lb/> Jagdalpur.<lb/> Therefore,<lb/> the<lb/> determination of compensation as per the guidelines, was<lb/> proper. It is again submitted that in the Collector report,<lb/> suspicion has been raised on the notification itself regarding<lb/> which the Collector has no authority or jurisdiction and,<lb/> therefore, the notification concerned cannot be examined by<lb/> a criminal Court. Hence, the order in Writ Petition(Civil)<lb/> No.3355/2019 is not sustainable and also the FIR lodged<lb/> against the petitioner is liable to be quashed.<lb/> 14. Mr. Arvind Shrivastava, learned counsel in Writ Appeal<lb/> no.119/2022 submits, that the appellants are not the<lb/> employees of Bastar Railway Private Limited. They are<lb/> employees of the IRCON International Limited(Government<lb/> of India undertaking under the Ministry of Railways). These<lb/> appellants have nothing to do with the acquisition process or<lb/> determination of compensation. There had been no<lb/> involvement of these appellants in whatsoever manner. In<lb/> the FIR lodged, the offence under Section 109 of IPC has<lb/> been added to show a conspiracy and that these appellants<lb/> were the part of the conspiracy. It is submitted that the<lb/> proposal for construction of Railway Station in Palli, was not<lb/> given by these appellants. In the report of the Collector<lb/> dated 30.7.2019, it is mentioned in Clause F , that there is<lb/> requirement for inquiry by Competent Railway Authorities,<lb/> regarding the involvement of Railway Officers and necessity<lb/> of criminal action against them. Therefore, it was not a<lb/> recommendation for making any inquiry against the<lb/> appellants, who are not the railway employees. The learned<lb/> Single Bench has very cursorily decided this point raised by<lb/> the appellants/petitioners holding, that the ground raised<lb/> cannot be examined by the Writ Court, which is erroneous,<lb/> therefore, the appellants in this case are entitled for grant of<lb/> relief as prayed in this writ appeal.<lb/> 15. Mr. Varun Sharma, learned counsel for the appellant in Writ<lb/> Appeal No.144/2022 submits, that the appellant in this case<lb/> was Registration Clerk and his only role was to provide the<lb/> calculation sheet as per the guidelines, which was laid down<lb/> under the provisions of Stamp Act. A departmental action<lb/> was initiated against this appellant which was withdrawn<lb/> later on. It is further submitted that under Section 186 of the<lb/> Act, 1989, immunity has been granted to the public servant<lb/> under which this appellant is also protected, hence, the<lb/> lodging of FIR against him was liable to be quashed, it is<lb/> prayed that this writ appeal be allowed and relief be granted.<lb/> 16. Mr. Siddharth Shukla, learned counsel for the appellant in<lb/> Writ Appeal No.115/2022 submits, that the appellant in this<lb/> case was the Competent Authority and he has not played<lb/> any role in the said conspiracy as alleged in the Collector&apos;s<lb/> report. The award was passed on the basis of the<lb/> documents that were supplied, which included the guidelines<lb/> of 2017-2018. The appellant has performed his duty strictly<lb/> in accordance with law. Therefore, there is no criminality<lb/> present on the part of this appellant. The learned Single<lb/> Judge has erred in holding, that the case requires<lb/> investigation. Whereas the FIR lodged was liable to be<lb/> quashed, hence, it is prayed that this writ appeal be allowed<lb/> and the appellant may be granted relief as prayed.<lb/> 17. Ms. Astha Shukla, learned State counsel, representing State<lb/> of Chhattisgarh, Collector, Bastar and the S.H.O. of the<lb/> Police Station, Kotwali, Jagdalpur, submits that the Collector<lb/> had the authority to make an inquiry into the allegation of<lb/> corruption and fraud, in determination of compensation by<lb/> the concerned authority and also against the persons hugely<lb/> benefited, without there being any entitlement of them. As<lb/> soon as the matter came to the notice of Collector from the<lb/> news reports published regarding large scale irregularity and<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>illegality committed in land acquisition proceeding for Bastar<lb/> Railway project, inquiry has been ordered and on the basis<lb/> of the inquiry report the F.I.R. has been lodged. The learned<lb/> Single Judge has very correctly held that Collector is<lb/> competent to make such an inquiry and that the lodging of<lb/> F.I.R. is a correct step taken. It is further submitted that the<lb/> land belonging to the appellant Bali Nagwanshi and Neelima<lb/> Belsariya was clearly situated in the rural areas, which has<lb/> been erroneously considered as urban area for determining<lb/> enhanced compensation in favour of these appellants,<lb/> therefore, there is no error in the impugned order passed by<lb/> the learned Single Judge. Therefore, all the Writ Appeals are<lb/> liable to be dismissed.<lb/> 18. Shri Vikas Singh, learned Senior Counsel for respondent<lb/> BRPL, firstly submits on the ground of maintainability of<lb/> WPC No.3355/2019, that the High Court is empowered<lb/> under Article 226 of the Constitution to entertain the petition<lb/> regarding which he has placed reliance on the judgments of<lb/> Hon&apos;ble the Supreme Court in the cases of Andi </note>
 
            <head>Mukta<lb/> Sadguru Shree Muktajee Vandas Swami Suvarna Jayanti<lb/> Mahotsav Smarak Trust Vs</head>

            <note>. V.R. Rudani, (1989) 2 SCC<lb/> 691, PRP Exports &amp; Ors. Vs. Chief Secretary,<lb/> Government of Tamil Nadu &amp; Ors., (2014) 13 SCC 692,<lb/> State of U.P. Vs. Mahindra &amp; Mahindra Ltd., (2011) 13<lb/> SCC 77. </note>
 
            <figDesc>It is submitted that it is a case of large scale<lb/> corruption and huge discrepancy in the determination of the<lb/> compensation in the acquisition process. Therefore, it is an<lb/> exceptional case which was required to be challenged under<lb/> Article 226 of the Constitution of India. Therefore, invoking of<lb/> Section 34 of the Act, 1996 is not adequate remedy. It is<lb/> further submitted that at the time of filing of WPC<lb/> </figDesc>
<lb/> 
            <note>No.3355/2019 on 12-09-2019, no proceeding was initiated<lb/> under Section 34 of the Act, 1996. However, an application<lb/> under Section 34 of the Act, 1996 had been filed on 18-02-<lb/>2021, which is not yet registered by the court concerned.</note>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <note>Chengalvaraya Naidu Vs. Jagannath, (1994) 1 SCC 1,<lb/> Bhaurao Dagdu Paralkar Vs. State of Maharashtra,<lb/> (2005) 7 SCC 605, State of U.P. and others Vs. Ravindra<lb/> Kumar Sharma and others, (2016) 4 SCC 791 and<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>Rameshwar Vs. State of Haryana, (2018) 6 SCC 215.<lb/> It is also submitted that subsequent events can be<lb/> taken into consideration by a writ Court, regarding which<lb/> reliance has been placed on the judgment of Hon&apos;ble the<lb/> Supreme Court in the case of State of U.P. Vs. Mahindra &amp;<lb/> Mahindra Ltd., (2011) 13 SCC 77.<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>It is submitted that in the peculiar circumstances of the<lb/> case, the writ is maintainable even if there exists any<lb/> alternative remedy, as has been held in the case of<lb/> Whirlpool Corpn. Vs. Registrar of Trade Marks, (1998) 8<lb/> SCC 1.<lb/> It is submitted by learned Senior Counsel that the writ<lb/> appeals are not fit to be entertained, therefore, the same<lb/> may be dismissed and also the interim protection granted by<lb/> learned Single Judge may be quashed.<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>22.<lb/> Shri Prashant Bhushan learned counsel for appellant Bali<lb/> Nagwanshi submits in rebuttal, that the notification dated 02-<lb/>07-2014 is not meant only for elections. The boundaries and<lb/> areas are very clearly defined with respect to ward No.37,<lb/> Lokmanya Tilak ward. It starts from Palli Naka via<lb/> Dharampura No.2 via Shankar Mandir upto Urwasshi<lb/> Pandey&apos;s house in the North and mentions starting from<lb/> Shankar Mandir Narmunda via Rajat Jainti Kangoli via B.M.<lb/> cold storage upto Palli Naka. Village Palli is situated well<lb/> within this area. The land belonging to appellant Bali<lb/> Nagwanshi is adjacent to the road leading from MGM school<lb/> to Palli Naka. It is on this basis the competent authority has<lb/> calculated the compensation and enhancement of 25% was<lb/> given according to the guidelines present. Therefore, on the<lb/> basis of the notification dated 02-07-2014, it can be<lb/> assumed that land belonging to appellant Bali Nagwanshi<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>was urban land and the assessment was to be done in<lb/> accordance with Section 20(G) of the Act, 1989 and Section<lb/> 26 of the Act, 2013, which has been done by the competent<lb/> authority and further enhancement has been granted by the<lb/> Commissioner. Therefore, the award of the compensation of<lb/> the competent authority and the Commissioner are<lb/> maintainable and lodging of the FIR against appellant Bali<lb/> Nagwanshi is baseless, which is liable to be quashed.<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>23.<lb/> Shri Anurag Dayal Shrivastava, learned counsel for appellant<lb/> Neelima Belsaria submits in rebuttal, that the notification<lb/> under Section 29 of the Act, 1961 is not limited for the<lb/> purposes of elections only. The guidelines that has been<lb/> issued by the authorities is to be strictly applied and the<lb/> same has been applied accordingly, in determining the<lb/> compensation. The submission of the counsel for<lb/> respondents regarding conspiracy is totally baseless. In the<lb/> report given by the Collector, the planning regarding<lb/> construction of railway station has been assailed, which<lb/> could not have been assailed by the Collector. The<lb/> notification issued under Section 20(E) of the Act, 1989 has<lb/> resulted in the vesting of acquired lands with the Central<lb/> Government, which has not been challenged by the<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>respondent BRPL. The diversion and transfer of project in<lb/> the matter of construction of railway station at Palli has not<lb/> affected the original acquisition plan and the construction of<lb/> railway station only is not the reason for enhancement of the<lb/> compensation amount. As the lands acquired were in the<lb/> acquisition plan from the very beginning, therefore,<lb/> conspiracy theory as propounded by the respondent BRPL<lb/> finds no support. It is submitted that the lands that were<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>acquired from appellant Neelima Belsaria were diverted<lb/> plots regarding which the appellant has the confirmation<lb/> from the order of the High Court in WP227 No.238/2012.<lb/> Therefore, it was fit to be assessed for compensation at<lb/> market value per square meter. Respondent BRPL has not<lb/> challenged the guidelines of 2017-18.<lb/> It is submitted, that in the report of the Collector even<lb/> the grant of 12% interest has been considered as<lb/> conspiracy, whereas, the appellant has entitlement of such<lb/> interest on the compensation. Reliance has been placed on<lb/> the judgment in the matter of Union of India and another<lb/> Vs. Tarsem Singh and others, AIR 2019 SC 4689. It is<lb/> submitted that Section 20(F) (vi) and (vii) of the Act, 1989,<lb/> provide for remedy against the award passed, which shall be<lb/> by way of arbitration. Respondents BRPL has challenged<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>the award before the Court of District Judge. Relying on the<lb/> judgment of Hon&apos;ble the Supreme Court in matter of<lb/> Pradeep Singh Vs. State of U.P., 2010 (2) SCC 114, it is<lb/> submitted that in case of concealment of fact by a party the<lb/> relief claimed can be denied by the court. It is further<lb/> submitted that the Collector had constituted inquiry<lb/> committee of officers below the rank of the persons accused,<lb/> especially the Competent Authority who held the rank of<lb/> Addl. Collector. Further, the application under Section 34 of<lb/> the Act, 1996 has also been filed with delay, which is clearly<lb/> bared by limitation as held by Hon&apos;ble the Supreme Court in<lb/> the case of P. Radha Bai and others Vs. P. Ashok Kumar<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>and others, AIR (2018) SC 5013. Hence, there is no basis<lb/> or evidence of conspiracy present in the case. The prayer<lb/> made in the appeals filed by Neelima Belsaria are fit to be<lb/> allowed.<lb/> 24. Shri Siddharth Shukla, learned counsel for appellant in WA<lb/> No.115/2022 submits in rebuttal, that appellant Hira Lal<lb/> Nayak passed the initial award dated 12-02-2018 and then<lb/> he was transferred. Therefore, compensation amount was<lb/> neither deposited in his tenure nor was disbursed. The<lb/> calculation of the compensation was made on the basis of<lb/> the guidelines and also on the report submitted by the office<lb/> of the Sub-Registrar. This appellant has no part in<lb/> conspiracy as alleged. The lodging of the FIR against him is<lb/> unsustainable.<lb/> 25. Shri Arvind Shrivastava, learned counsel for appellants in<lb/> WA No.119/2022 submits in rebuttal, that railway station at<lb/> Palli was proposed by BRPL. The appellants in this appeal<lb/> had not played any part in the diversion of the railway<lb/> project. Therefore, the allegation regarding their participation<lb/> in the conspiracy is totally baseless.<lb/> 26. Shri Varun Sharma, learned counsel for appellant in WA<lb/> No.144/2022 submits in rebuttal, that the appellant in this<lb/> case was working as Registration Clerk and he had<lb/> proposed the calculations for making assessment of<lb/> compensation on the basis of the guidelines of 2017-18. The<lb/> spot inspection was conducted by Sub-Registrar, Jagdalpur<lb/> and it was reported by letter dated 03-01-2011 to the<lb/> appellant Neelima Belsaria, that her land is situated in<lb/> municipal area of Jagdalpur. Therefore, there is no<lb/> conspiracy at all and neither any offence has been<lb/> committed in this case. Therefore, the writ appeal filed by<lb/> this appellant is fit to be allowed.<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>27. Mr. R.K. Mishra, learned Asst.S.G. for U.O.I. adopts the<lb/> arguments advanced by the learned counsel for respondent-<lb/>BRPL and learned State counsel and submits that all the<lb/> Writ Appeals are fit to be dismissed.</note>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <table>the case of Bhaurao Dagdu Paralkar Vs. State of<lb/> Maharashtra and others (Supra), it was held that &quot;Fraud&quot;<lb/> as is well known vitiates every solemn act. Fraud and justice<lb/> never dwell together. It has been similarly held in the case of<lb/> State of U.P. and Others Vs. Ravindra Kumar Sharma<lb/> and Others (Supra) and Rameshwar Vs. State of Haryana<lb/> (Supra). Section 34 (2) of the Act, 1996 is relevant in this<lb/> case, which is as follows:-<lb/>&quot;Section 34(2) in THE ARBITRATION AND<lb/> CONCILIATION ACT, 1996:-<lb/>(2) An arbitral award may be set aside by the Court only if<lb/> -<lb/>(a) the party making the application furnishes proof<lb/> that-<lb/>(i) a party was under some incapacity, or<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>(ii) the arbitration agreement is not valid under the law<lb/> to which the parties have subjected it or, failing any<lb/> indication thereon, under the law for the time being in<lb/> force; or<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>(iii) the party making the application was not given<lb/> proper notice of the appointment of an arbitrator or of<lb/> the arbitral proceedings or was otherwise unable to<lb/> present his case; or<lb/> (iv) the arbitral award deals with a dispute not<lb/> contemplated by or not falling within the terms of the<lb/> submission to arbitration, or it contains decisions on<lb/> matters beyond the scope of the submission to<lb/> arbitration:<lb/> Provided that, if the decisions on matters submitted to<lb/> arbitration can be separated from those not so<lb/> submitted, only that part of the arbitral award which<lb/> contains decisions on matters not submitted to<lb/> arbitration may be set aside; or<lb/> (v) the composition of the arbitral tribunal or the arbitral<lb/> procedure was not in accordance with the agreement<lb/> of the parties, unless such agreement was in conflict<lb/> with a provision of this Part from which the parties<lb/> cannot derogate, or, failing such agreement, was not in<lb/> accordance with this Part; or<lb/> (b) the Court finds that-<lb/>(i) the subject-matter of the dispute is not capable of<lb/> settlement by arbitration under the law for the time<lb/> being in force, or<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>(ii) the arbitral award is in conflict with the public policy<lb/> of India.<lb/> 39. On a plain reading of this provision under Section 34(2) of<lb/> the Act, 1996, it is revealed that fraud and conspiracy is not<lb/> one of the grounds present for challenging an arbitral award.<lb/> It was held in the case of Andi </note>
 
            <head>Mukta Sadguru Shree<lb/> Muktajee Vandas Swami Suvarna Jayanti Mahotsav<lb/> Smarak Trust Vs. V.R. Rudani </head>
 
            <table>(Supra) in paragraph No.17<lb/> and 19, which are as follows:-<lb/>&quot;17.There, however, the prerogative writ of mandamus<lb/> is confined only to public authorities to compel<lb/> performance of public duty. The &apos;public authority&apos; for<lb/> them mean every body which is created by statute--<lb/>and whose powers and duties are defined by statue.<lb/> So Government departments, local authori-ties, police<lb/> authorities,<lb/> and<lb/> statutory<lb/> undertakings<lb/> and<lb/> corporations, are all &apos;public authorities&apos;. But there is no<lb/> such limitation for our High Courts to issue the writ &apos;in<lb/> the nature of mandamus&apos;. Article 226 confers wide<lb/> powers on the High Courts to issue writs in the nature<lb/> of prerogative writs. This is a striking departure from<lb/> the English law. Under Article 226, writs can be issued<lb/> to &quot;any person or authority&quot;. It can be issued &quot;for the<lb/> enforcement of any of the fundamental rights and for<lb/> any other purpose&quot;.<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>40. In the case of State of U.P. Vs. M/s Mahindra &amp; Mahindra<lb/> Ltd. (Supra), it is held that the High Court can always take<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>notice of the subsequent events and developments that<lb/> have taken place after filing of the Writ Petition etc., which is<lb/> the case present here, that the application under Section 34<lb/> of Act, 1996 has been filed by the respondent BRPL before<lb/> the District Court, but the fact remains that the same<lb/> application is clearly time-barred, therefore, the said remedy<lb/> is no longer available to the respondent BRPL. On the other<lb/> hand, it has been amply discussed here-in-above that the<lb/> fact and scenario of the present case is totally different as<lb/> the respondent BRPL is claiming that the award dated<lb/> 12.02.2018 by the competent authority and the award dated<lb/> 11.07.2019 by the Commissioner are non-est and void being<lb/> vitiated by fraud and criminal conspiracy. Therefore, in such<lb/> a case, we are of the view that the Writ Petition Civil<lb/> No.3355 of 2019 was maintainable under Article 226 of<lb/> Constitution of India.<lb/> Reliance on the judgment in SBP &amp; Co. Vs. Patel<lb/> Engg. Ltd. (supra) and Haryana Urban Development<lb/> Authority, Karnal vs M/S. Mehta Construction Company<lb/> and another (supra) by the appellant side is distinguishable.<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>Similarly, the reliance of the appellant on the judgment on<lb/> the case of M/s Kelkar and Kelkar Vs. M/s Hotel Pride<lb/> Executive Pvt. Ltd in Civil Appeal No.3479/2022 decided on<lb/> 4.5.2022 by the Supreme Court and the judgment of<lb/> Supreme Court in Bhaven </note>
 
            <head>Construction vs Executive<lb/> Engineer Sardar Sarovar Narmada Nigam Ltd.&amp; another,<lb/> </head>
<lb/> 
            <table>reported in AIR OnLine 2021 SC 6, are also distinguishable<lb/> on the basis of the discussions made hereinabove as the<lb/> alternative remedy, though available against the arbitration<lb/> award, here the challenge of the respondent side to the<lb/> same is based on the touch-stone of commission of offences<lb/> of fraud and conspiracy, therefore, the remedy under Article<lb/> 226 of Constitution of India can be availed in view of the<lb/> pronouncement of Supreme Court in Andi Mukta Sadguru<lb/> (supra). As per the submissions and the facts presented, the<lb/> filing of application under Section 34 of the Act, 1996 was<lb/> done subsequent to the filing of Writ Petition(Civil)<lb/> No.3355/2019. Therefore, it cannot be said that there had<lb/> been any concealment of fact. Reliance of the appellant side<lb/> on the judgment in the case of Pradeep Singh Vs. State of<lb/> U.P. (supra) does not give any guidance in such a case.<lb/> Similarly, the judgment in the case of Union of India and<lb/> another Vs. Tarsem Singh and others (supra) can also be<lb/> distinguished on the basis of the facts and circumstances<lb/> present in this case.<lb/> 41. Another ground raised by the appellant side is that the<lb/> application for amendment to incorporate additional relief for<lb/> setting aside the award dated 11.07.2019 was allowed at the<lb/> final hearing stage and as the application under Section 34<lb/> of the Act, 1996 was already filed, therefore, this amendment<lb/> for additional relief was not fit to be allowed. The objection<lb/> raised by the appellant/petitioner side was not decided by<lb/> the learned Single Judge.</table>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <table>&apos; side has referred to notification dated<lb/> 02.07.2014, which is a notification regarding constitution of<lb/> gram panchayats. In Sr. No.23 there is mention of Gram<lb/> Panchayat-<lb/>Kumrawand,<lb/> which<lb/> includes<lb/> villages<lb/> Kumrawand and Palli. The relevant extract is as follows :-<lb/>**dk;kZ y;] dys DVj] ftyk cLrj ¼NRrhlx&lt;½<lb/> cLrj] fnuka d 21 tq ykbZ 2014<lb/> vf/klw puk<lb/> dz eka d@482@ia pk;r@2014&amp;15&amp; NRRkhlx&lt; &apos;kklu] ia pk;r ,oa<lb/> xz keh.k fodkl foHkkx dh vf/klw puk dz eka d ,Q &amp;1&amp;11&amp; 95&amp;<lb/> 22&amp; ia &amp;02] fnuka d 23 Qjojh 1999 Onkjk iz nRRk &apos;kfDr;ks a dks<lb/> iz ;ks x es a ykrs gq ,]NRrhlx&lt; ia pk;r jkt vf/kfu;e 1993¼dz eka d<lb/> 1 lu~ 1994½ ¼ftls blds i&apos;pkr~ mDr vf/kfu;e dgk x;k gS ½<lb/> dh /kkjk 129 [k ¼ 1 ½ ds iz ko/kkuks a ds v/khu es a va fdr<lb/> vkua n]dys DVj] ftyk cLrj la yXu lkj.kh ¼ ftls ]blds i&apos;pkrS<lb/> lkj.kh S dgk x;k gS ½ ds Lrka Hk ¼ 4 ½ es a n&apos;kkZ ;s x;s xka o ;k xka oks a<lb/> ds leq g ds fy, ftldh tula [;k lkj.kh ds Lra Hk ¼ 5 ½ es a<lb/> n&apos;kkZ ;h xbZ gS ]lkj.kh ds Lra Hk¼ 3 ½ es a mYys f[kr uke ls mDr<lb/> vf/kfu;e ds iz ;s ktuks a ds fy, S xz ke Sds :i es fofufnZ &quot;V djrk<lb/> gW W w rFkk lkoZ tfud tkudkjh ds fy, ,rn~ Onkjk iz dkf&apos;kr fd;k<lb/> tkrk gS A<lb/> bl LFkkfir xz ke es a vf/kfu;e dh /kkjk 8 ¼ d ½ ds<lb/> vuq lkj xz ke ia pk;r dk xBu fd;k tk;s xk]bl iz dkj xfBr xz ke<lb/> ia pk;rks a dks vf/kfu;e dh /kkjk 11 ds va rxZ r of.kZ r vf/kfu;e ds<lb/> iz ;ks tu ds fy, vko&apos;;d vU; leLr &apos;kfDr;ka iz kIr gks a xh-<lb/>Sr. No.23 is as follows :-<lb/>23<lb/> dq Egjkoa<lb/> M<lb/> dq Egjkoa M<lb/> 912<lb/> 2<lb/> iYyh<lb/> 618<lb/> 2<lb/> ;ks x<lb/> 1530<lb/> 56. Although this notification does not mention the lands<lb/> included in the panchayat area but inclusion of village -Palli<lb/> in the panchayat area is sufficient to reflect that the village-<lb/>Palli continues as a village in the gram panchayat<lb/> Kumrawand. It is the submission of the respondents&apos; side<lb/> that the respective lands that were purchased by the<lb/> appellants/petitioners are shown as agricultural lands in the<lb/> respective sale deeds and their areas were mentioned in<lb/> hectares, which had not been denied by the appellants&apos; side.<lb/> 57. In the guidelines issued by the Office of Inspector General of<lb/> Registrar and Superintendent (Stamp), Raipur for the year<lb/> 2017-18, market price is mentioned with respect to Ward<lb/> No.37, which is as follows :-<lb/>iz k:i &amp;,d<lb/> ¼fu;e&amp;7 ns f[k;s ½<lb/> uxjh; la ifRr;ks a ds cktkj ew Y; ekxZ nf&apos;kZ d fl)ka r o&quot;kZ 2017&amp;2018<lb/> uxj ikfyd fuxe&amp;txnyiq j<lb/> ¼nj iz froxZ ehVj :i;s es a ½<lb/> dz 0 okMZ dk<lb/> uke ,oa<lb/> dz eka d<lb/> eks gYyk@dkW yks uh@lks lk;Vh@ekxZ dk uke<lb/> Hkw [k.M dk ew Y;<lb/> la ifRr eq [; ekxZ<lb/> la ifRr eq [; ekxZ<lb/> ij fLFkr gks us dh<lb/> ls va nj gks us ij<lb/> fLFkfr es a 20 ehVj nj ¼ftles a eq [;<lb/> rd nj<lb/> ekxZ ls 20 ehVj<lb/> i&apos;pkr dh nj<lb/> Hkh lfEefyr gS a<lb/> 37 yks d ekU;<lb/> fryd<lb/> okMZ dz eka d<lb/> 1-,e-th-,e-Ldw y tkus dk jkLrk ls iYyh ukdk rd<lb/> 2-iYyh ukdk ls fxVṼh [knku rd<lb/> 3-v&apos;kks dk ykbZ Q LVkbZ y@ukxoa &apos;kh js lhMs Ulh@fuyhek<lb/> 13800<lb/> 6000<lb/> ---<lb/>----<lb/>8500<lb/> 11300<lb/> Lia nu ¼iYyh½<lb/> 4-x.ks &apos;k pkS d ls jk;y xkMZ u rd ¼ukxoa &apos;kh js lhMs a lh½<lb/> 5-x.ks &apos;k pkS d ls fxVṼh [knku tkus okyh jks M rd<lb/> 7300<lb/> 7100<lb/> 5400<lb/> 5300<lb/> 58. There is mention of &quot;Nagwanshi Residency&quot; and &quot;Neelima<lb/> Spandan&quot;, regarding which, the appellants have their claims.<lb/> However, these properties are shown to be present beyond<lb/> 20 meters from the road.<lb/> 59. Further in the same guidelines under Format -III, there is<lb/> mention of village-Palli in Revenue Inspector Circle<lb/> Jagadalpur. The relevant entry at Sr.No.2 is as follows :-<lb/>iz k:i &amp;rhu<lb/> ¼fu;e&amp;7 ns f[k;s ½<lb/> df&quot;k Hkw fe ds fy;s cktkj ew Y; ekxZ nf&apos;kZ d fl)ka r o&quot;kZ 2017&amp;2018<lb/> rglhy&amp;txnyiq j ftyk &amp; cLrj<lb/> ¼nj iz fr gs DVs ;j es a ½<lb/> i-<lb/>g-<lb/>ua -<lb/>xz ke dk uke<lb/> lHkh fdLe<lb/> eq [; ekxZ ij<lb/> fLFkr<lb/> fla fpr<lb/> vfla fpr<lb/> df&quot;k Hkw fe ds Vq dMs +<lb/> 500 oxZ ehVj rd<lb/> lM+ d ls 20 lM+ d ls 20<lb/> ehVj rd<lb/> ehVj ckn<lb/> 1</table>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <table>-<lb/>2<lb/> ?kkVinew j<lb/> 4795500<lb/> 3294000<lb/> 3212<lb/> 2188<lb/> dq Egjkoa M<lb/> 5061000<lb/> 3294000<lb/> 2891<lb/> 2188<lb/> iYyh<lb/> 5061000<lb/> 3294000<lb/> 2891<lb/> 2188<lb/> 60. On a minute perusal of the order dated 12.02.2018, given by<lb/> the Competent Authority, there appears to be no mention<lb/> that land that was acquired from the appellants Bali<lb/> Nagwanshi and Neelima Belsaria were within that the Ward<lb/> schedule annexed here to shall be acquired for<lb/> the aforesaid purpose;<lb/> And, further, in pursuance of subsection<lb/> (2) of section 20E of the said Act, the Central<lb/> Government<lb/> hereby<lb/> declares<lb/> that<lb/> on<lb/> publication of this notification in the official<lb/> Gazette, the land specified in the Schedule<lb/> annexed here to shall vest absolutely in the<lb/> Central<lb/> Government<lb/> free<lb/> from<lb/> all<lb/> encumbrances.<lb/> Relevant entries in Sr. No. 1, 2 and 5 of the notification<lb/> are as under :-<lb/>SCHEDULE<lb/> Name of District: Bastar<lb/> Taluka: Jagdalpur<lb/> Serial<lb/> No.<lb/> Name of<lb/> Village<lb/> Khasra<lb/> /Plot<lb/> Numbe<lb/> r<lb/> Area (in<lb/> Hect.)<lb/> Type<lb/> of<lb/> Land<lb/> Nature of<lb/> land<lb/> Name of Land Owner<lb/> 1.<lb/> Palli<lb/> 123/1<lb/> 1.990<lb/> Pvt.<lb/> Fallow<lb/> Land<lb/> Bali Nag Vanshi Father<lb/> Buter Nagvanshi Caste<lb/> Hulba<lb/> 2.<lb/> Palli<lb/> 123/2<lb/> 0.700<lb/> Pvt.<lb/> Fallow<lb/> Land<lb/> Bali Nag Vanshi Father<lb/> Buter Nagvanshi Caste<lb/> Hulba<lb/> 3.<lb/> -<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>4.<lb/> -<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>5.<lb/> Palli<lb/> 125/1<lb/> to<lb/> 125/29,<lb/> 125/31,<lb/> 125/33<lb/> to<lb/> 125/37<lb/> 1.040<lb/> Pvt.<lb/> Fallow<lb/> Land<lb/> Shirmati Neelima Father<lb/> Pillu Ram, Bell Saria<lb/> Husband<lb/> T.K.<lb/> Ravi<lb/> Caste Hulba</table>
		</figure>



    </text>
</tei>

