<tei>
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc xml:id="_18345.pdf"/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">


		<figure type="table">

            <note>CRL. APP. NOS.1398/2013, 1399/2013 AND 1414/2013</note>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <head>CRL. APP. NOS.1398/2013, 1399/2013 AND 1414/2013<lb/> bus </head>
 
            <figDesc>along. During the crime many injuries had been<lb/> caused to me on my head, face, eyes, knees and on my<lb/> body. As soon as I entered the bus, I had seen a dark<lb/> complexion person, whom his companions were calling as<lb/> &apos;Ram Singh&apos;. At that time, three other boys were sitting in<lb/> the cabin other than the driver and outside the cabin, one<lb/> boy was sitting on the seat for two persons and another<lb/> one boy was sitting on the seat for three persons. At that<lb/> time, I thought those boys who were sitting outside (the<lb/> cabin) were passengers. Those three boys were<lb/> addressing themselves with the names of Raju, Pawan<lb/> and Vinay when they were talking with each other. The<lb/> name of the person, who was driving the bus, was<lb/> Mukesh or Ramesh. The boys who had taken the<lb/> Prosecutrix towards the rear side of the bus, were being<lb/> addressed with the names of Ram </figDesc>
 
            <head>Singh and Thakur by<lb/> the other boys</head>

            <note>. They were committing rape with the<lb/> Prosecutrix by going towards rear side one-by-one. After<lb/> enquiry you have recorded my statement while sitting in<lb/> Airport Hotel. I have heard the statement and the same is<lb/> correct.<lb/> 20. Apart from the aforesaid statements made by the complainant,<lb/> the complainant also gave his statement under Section 164 Cr.P.C. to<lb/> the Metropolitan Magistrate, PW-69 Shri Prashant Sharma. The<lb/> said statement is exhibited as Ex.PW-1/B and bears the certificate of<lb/> the Metropolitan Magistrate regarding its correctness, which is<lb/> Ex.PW-69/B. The application for recording of the said statement is<lb/> Ex.PW-69/A and the record of questions put to the complainant by<lb/> the concerned M.M. to satisfy himself as to the voluntariness of the<lb/> said statement is Ex.PW-69/D. As per the deposition of PW-69 Shri<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>Prashant Sharma, learned M.M., he recorded the statement of the<lb/> complainant verbatim. The English translation of the said statement<lb/> of the complainant (Ex.PW-1/B) recorded on 19.12.2012 at around<lb/> 3:30 PM reads as under:-<lb/></table>
<lb/>
            <note>CRL. APP. NOS.</note>

            <head>1398/2013, 1399/2013 AND 1414/2013<lb/> -Statement of Sh. Awninder Pratap Pandey under<lb/> Section 164 Cr.P.C<lb/> </head>
<lb/> 
            <table>I and my friend (Prosecutrix) had come to Mall Select City Walk<lb/> located at Saket on</table>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <head>DEATH SENTENCE REFERENCE NO.6/2013,<lb/> Page 20 of 340<lb/> CRL. APP. NOS.1398/2013, 1399/2013 AND 1414/2013</head>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <table>what time the incident happened?<lb/> i.<lb/> 20/12/2012<lb/> 2. 13/12/2012 3. 16/12/2012<lb/> Ans. : 16/12/12<lb/> (</table>

            <head>by writing after taking time)<lb/> CRL. APP. NOS.1398/2013, 1399/2013 AND 1414/2013<lb/> </head>
<lb/> 
            <table>Ques.: Have you seen the staff of the bus?<lb/> 1.<lb/> Yes<lb/> 2. No<lb/> Ans. : 1 </table>
 
            <head>yes by gesture (nodding her head)<lb/> </head>
<lb/> 
            <table>Ques.: Have you seen those people at that time?<lb/> 1.<lb/> Yes<lb/> 2. No<lb/> Ans. : 1<lb/> Ques.: By which article they have given beatings? (answer by<lb/> writing)<lb/> Ans. : </table>
 
            <head>By iron rod which was long.<lb/> </head>
<lb/> 
            <table>Ques.: What happened of your belongings means mobile etc.?<lb/> 1.<lb/> Fell down<lb/> 2. Snatched by them 3. Don&apos;t know<lb/> Ans. : 2<lb/> Ques.: Besides rape where and how did you get the injuries?<lb/> (tried to answer by writing)<lb/> Ans. : </table>
 
            <head>Head, face, back, whole body including genital parts<lb/> (by gesture indication)<lb/> Ques</head>

            <note>.: By which names they were addressing to each other?<lb/> (tried answer by writing)<lb/> Ans. : 1. </note>
 
            <head>Ram Singh, Mukesh, Vinay, Akshay, Vipin, Raju.<lb/> </head>
<lb/> 
            <table>Ques.: What did they do after rape?<lb/> 1. Left at home 2. Threw at unknown place<lb/> 3. Got down at some other bus stop.<lb/> Ans:<lb/> 2.‖<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>31. Mr. A.P. Singh and Mr. M.L. Sharma, learned counsel for the</note>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <note>CRL. APP. NOS.1398/2013, 1399/2013 AND 1414/2013<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>word YADAV is written, moving in front of the hotel at 9.34PM<lb/> and 9.53PM.‖<lb/> 37. PW-76 Gautam Roy, Sr. Scientific Officer and also the Head<lb/> of the Department Computer Forensic Division in CFSL, CBI</table>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <note>Ex.PW-76/B, PW-76/C and PW-76/D, and his detailed report as<lb/> Ex.PW-76/E.<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>38. It may be noted that Gautam Roy (PW-76) clarified that there<lb/> was a typographical mistake in his report (Ex.PW-76/E), where only<lb/> one time is written, i.e., 21:34, but in his observation and draft report<lb/> the bus is seen two times, i.e., at 21:34 and 21:54 and the said timings<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>are mentioned in the said photographs Ex.PW76/B, Ex.PW76/C and<lb/> CRL. APP. NOS.1398/2013, 1399/2013 AND 1414/2013<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <figDesc>Ex.PW76/D. The witness proved the said draft report as Ex.PW-76/F.<lb/> It is also relevant to note at this juncture that in the course of cross-<lb/></figDesc>
<lb/>
            <table>examination of Gautam Roy (PW-76), the CCTV footage was once<lb/> again played in Court at the request of the defence counsel while PW-<lb/>76 Gautam Roy was in the box and a specific question was put to him<lb/> with regard to tampering, the answer to which is extremely<lb/> significant. The question and answer are accordingly extracted<lb/> below:-<lb/></table>
<lb/>
            <note>-Question: Is it correct that pictures, being played in the laptop<lb/> today are not clear as the same are not (sic.) tampered with?<lb/> Ans: There is no tampering in the CD or the pen drive. I<lb/> need to add that CCTV footage are always not clear. Vol.:<lb/> However this footage was clear in my system. Vol.: Even<lb/> today the picture is totally clear and we have a video<lb/> forensic software which make the pictures more clear.‖<lb/> 39. PW-79 P.K. Gottam from CFSL, CBI in respect of the<lb/> photographs aforesaid testified that on 17.12.2012 and 18.12.2012, he<lb/> took photographs of the bus bearing No.DL-1P-C-0149 parked at<lb/> Thyagraj Stadium, INA, New Delhi from different angles as per the<lb/> requirements of finger print and biology experts. He further testified<lb/> that he handed over the positives of the said photographs Mark B1 in<lb/> Ex.PW-76/B, photographs Mark C1 and C2 in Ex.PW-76/C, and<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>photograph Mark D1 in Ex.PW-76/D to Shri Gautam Roy (PW-76) as<lb/> per his requisition. He deposed that there was no possibility of<lb/> tampering with the photographs as the software used for developing<lb/> them was tamper proof.<lb/> 40. A look now at the CFSL report, which is marked as Ex.PW-<lb/>76/E. </table>
 
            <head>The opinion given by the CFSL is that there was no<lb/> DEATH SENTENCE REFERENCE NO.6/2013,<lb/> Page 31 of 340<lb/> CRL. APP. NOS.1398/2013, 1399/2013 AND 1414/2013</head>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <head>DEATH SENTENCE REFERENCE NO.6/2013,<lb/> Page 32 of 340<lb/> CRL. APP. NOS.1398/2013, 1399/2013 AND 1414/2013</head>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <head>DEATH SENTENCE REFERENCE NO.6/2013,<lb/> Page 34 of 340<lb/> CRL. APP. NOS.1398/2013, 1399/2013 AND 1414/2013</head>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <head>DEATH SENTENCE REFERENCE NO.6/2013,<lb/> Page 37 of 340<lb/> CRL. APP. NOS.1398/2013, 1399/2013 AND 1414/2013</head>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <figDesc>at 1:30<lb/> PM on the pointing out of accused Ram Singh from in front of Ravi<lb/> Dass Mandir Road, Sector-3, R.K. Puram, New Delhi, vide arrest<lb/> memo Ex.PW-60/B.<lb/> 58. H.C. Mahabir (PW-60) has testified that accused Vinay was<lb/> interrogated in his presence and his disclosure statement recorded,<lb/> which is Ex.PW-60/H in which he stated that he could get recovered<lb/> the clothes and chappals worn by him at the time of the incident and<lb/> the looted articles from his jhuggi. Apparently however, on further<lb/> CRL. </figDesc>
 
            <head>APP. NOS.1398/2013, 1399/2013 AND 1414/2013<lb/> investigation </head>
 
            <figDesc>by the I.O. on the following day, i.e., on 19.12.2012, he<lb/> changed his stand.<lb/> 59. S.I. Mandeep (PW-68) testified in Court about the further<lb/> interrogation of accused Vinay on 19.12.2012 and the recoveries made<lb/> by the I.O. in his presence. The relevant portion of the testimony of<lb/> the witness is as under:-<lb/>-In my presence, interrogation was made from accused Vinay.<lb/> His supplementary disclosure statement Ex. PW-68/A was<lb/> recorded which bears my signature at point A. Accused<lb/> disclosed that he is wearing the same clothes which he was<lb/> wearing at the time of incident i.e. one blue colour jean, one<lb/> black colour sport jacket, one t-shirt of full sleeve and one pair<lb/> of rubber chappal. These items were converted into a pulanda<lb/> and then were sealed with the seal of PS and thereafter it was<lb/> seized vide memo Ex. PW-68/B which bears my signature at<lb/> point A. Thereafter both the accused led the police party to the<lb/> area of Ravi Dass Camp and accused Vinay led the police party<lb/> to his jhuggi J-105, Ravi Dass Camp. Accused Vinay produced<lb/> one pair of leather shoes make Hush Puppy by saying that<lb/> these shoes are of the complainant. This pair of shoes was<lb/> sealed in a parcel with the seal of PS and this parcel was<lb/> seized vide memo Ex. PW-68/C which bears my signature at<lb/> point A. </figDesc>
 
            <head>From the same jhuggi, he took out one polythene<lb/> from a portion of the jhuggi behind the door and from this<lb/> polythene, accused took out one NOKIA mobile phone<lb/> Model 3110. The IMEI of this mobile was checked. This<lb/> IMEI was tallying with the IMEI number of the prosecutrix.<lb/> </head>
<lb/> 
            <figDesc>This mobile phone was seized vide memo Ex. PW-68/D which<lb/> bears my sign at point A. The IMEI no. of the phone was noted<lb/> down in the seizure memo itself. Investigating officer prepared<lb/> the rough site plan of the place of recovery which is Ex. PW-<lb/>68/E bears my signature at point A.‖</figDesc>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <table>&quot;ELECTRONIC EVIDENCE CORROBORATING THE ROUTE,<lb/> LOCATION OF ACCUSED AND VICTIMS<lb/> Witness<lb/> Evidence/Phone<lb/> No.<lb/> Time<lb/> Cell ID Location<lb/> Rajinder Singh<lb/> Bisht (PW-25) and<lb/> Sandeep Singh<lb/> (PW-26)<lb/> Select City Mall,<lb/> Saket<lb/> CCTV Footage,<lb/> Saket<lb/> 6:15 P.M. to<lb/> 8:57 P.M.<lb/> NA Saket Select<lb/> City Mall<lb/> Vishal Gaurav,<lb/> Airtel (PW-19)<lb/> Note: Asha Devi<lb/> (PW-75) proves<lb/> that this phone<lb/> was being used by<lb/> the prosecutrix.<lb/> 9818358144<lb/> [Being used by the<lb/> prosecutrix]<lb/> 9:09 P.M.<lb/> (SMS)<lb/> 52171 Lado Sarai<lb/> Rakesh<lb/> Soni,<lb/> Dolphin (PW-24)<lb/> 9868612958<lb/> [Registered in the<lb/> name of accused<lb/> Ram Singh]<lb/> 9:16 P.M.<lb/> (13 seconds)<lb/> 3091 Hauz Khas<lb/> Deepak, Vodafone<lb/> (PW-23)<lb/> Note:<lb/> Santosh<lb/> (PW-12)<lb/> corroborates this<lb/> call.<lb/> 9711927157<lb/> [Registered in the<lb/> name of accused<lb/> Pawan]<lb/> 9:32 P.M.<lb/> (54 seconds)<lb/> 2991-<lb/>4591<lb/> Naval<lb/> Officer&quot;s<lb/> Mess-<lb/>Mehram<lb/> Nagar<lb/> Col.<lb/> A.K.<lb/> Sachdeva, GSM,<lb/> Reliance (PW-20)<lb/> 7827917720<lb/> [Registered in the<lb/> name of the<lb/> complainant (PW-<lb/>1)]<lb/> 9:34 P.M.<lb/> (2 seconds)<lb/> 11541 Mahipalpur<lb/> Extension<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>CRL. APP. NOS.1398/2013, 1399/2013 AND 1414/2013<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>Pramod Jha (PW-<lb/>67)<lb/> CCTV Footage,<lb/> Hotel Delhi<lb/> Airport<lb/> 9:34 P.M.<lb/> and 9:53/54<lb/> P.M.<lb/> Mahipalpur<lb/> Shishir Malhotra,<lb/> Aircel (PW-22)<lb/> 8285947545<lb/> [Registered in the<lb/> name of Champa<lb/> Devi and was<lb/> admittedly being<lb/> used by accused<lb/> Vinay]<lb/> 9:55 P.M.<lb/> (58 seconds)<lb/> 55043 NH-8, Near<lb/> IGI,<lb/> Mahipalpur<lb/> Rakesh Soni,<lb/> Dolphin (PW-24)<lb/> 9868612958<lb/> [Registered in the<lb/> name of accused<lb/> Ram Singh]<lb/> 10:04 P.M.<lb/> (51 seconds)<lb/> and 10:06<lb/> (25 seconds)<lb/> P.M.<lb/> 47541-<lb/>47633<lb/> Vasant<lb/> Gaon-<lb/>Munirka<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>111. Suffice it to note at this juncture that no flaw or error could be<lb/> pointed out by the defence in the aforesaid chart or even the CDR<lb/> analysis placed on record. Thus, according to the prosecution, it may<lb/> safely be presumed that the route chart (Ex.PW-80/H) prepared at the<lb/> instance of accused Mukesh and the CDR Analysis refered to<lb/> hereinabove as well as the CCTV footage complement and<lb/> supplement each other, and cumulatively </note>
 
            <head>taken the aforesaid<lb/> electronic evidence substantiates the case of the prosecution.<lb/> </head>
<lb/> 
            <table>Medical Evidence<lb/> 112. It is proposed next to deal with the medical evidence relating to<lb/> the prosecutrix who was treated in the first instance by PW-49 Dr.<lb/> Rashmi Ahuja on her arrival at Safdarjung Hospital. The relevant<lb/> portion of the testimony of Dr. Rashmi Ahuja (PW-49) has already<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>been reproduced hereinabove and her opinion vide Ex.PW-49/D,<lb/> <note>DEATH SENTENCE REFERENCE NO.6/</note>

            <head>2013,<lb/> Page 65 of 340<lb/> CRL. APP. NOS.1398/2013, 1399/2013 AND 1414/2013</head>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <table>-These OT notes were prepared by Dr. Gaurav under my<lb/> supervision. As per this record the diagnosis of surgery team<lb/> was blunt trauma abdomen with sexual assault with complete<lb/> perineal tear with hemoperitoneum &amp; small and large bowel<lb/> injuries. The operative findings were as under:<lb/> a.<lb/> Collection of around 500 ml of blood in peritoneal cavity.<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>b.<lb/> stomach pale,<lb/> CRL. APP. NOS.1398/2013, 1399/2013 AND 1414/2013<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>c.<lb/> Duodenum contused.<lb/> d.<lb/> Jejunum contused &amp; bruised at whole of the length and<lb/> lacerated &amp; transected at many places. First transection<lb/> was 5cm away from D J junction. Second was 2 feet from<lb/> the D.J., after that there was transection and laceration at<lb/> many places. Jejunal loop was of doubtful viability. Distal<lb/> ileum was completely detached from the mesentry till ICJ<lb/> (ileocaecal junction). It was completely devascularized.<lb/> e.<lb/> Large bowel was also contused bruised and of doubtful<lb/> viability.<lb/> Descending colon was lacerated vertically<lb/> downward in such a manner that it was completely open.<lb/> f.<lb/> Sigmoid colon &amp; rectum was lacerated at many places<lb/> linearly, mucosa was detached completely at places, a<lb/> portion of it around 10cm was prolapsing through perineal<lb/> wound.<lb/> g.<lb/> Liver and spleen was normal.<lb/> h.<lb/> both sides retro peritoneal (posterior wall of the abdomen)<lb/> haematoma present.<lb/> i.<lb/> Mesentry &amp; omentum was totally contused and bruised.<lb/> j.<lb/> Vaginal tear present, recto vaginal septum was<lb/> completely torn.<lb/> Gut was totally bruised and contused in such a manner that it<lb/> could not be repaired so proximal jejunostomy was made. `<lb/> Laparostomy (abdomen was left open) was made.‖<lb/> 115. According to PW-50 Dr. Raj Kumar Chejara, after performing<lb/> the operation, the patient was shifted to ICU. Since the first surgery<lb/> was damage control surgery, she was taken up for a second surgery<lb/> on 19.12.2012. In the said surgery, doctors from the surgical,<lb/> gynaecological and anaesthetic teams were associated. The findings<lb/> were as follows:-<lb/>-Abdominal findings:<lb/> i.<lb/> Rectum was longitudinally torn on anterior aspect in<lb/> continuation with perineal tear. This tear was continuing upward<lb/> involving sigmoid colon, descending colon which was splayed<lb/> open. The margin were edematous. There were multiple<lb/> longitudinal tear in the mucosa of recto sigmoid area.<lb/> Transverse colon was also torn and gangrenous. Hepatic<lb/> flexure, ascending colon &amp; caecum were gangrenous with<lb/> multiple perforations at many pleaces.<lb/> Terminal ileum<lb/> approximately one and a half feet loosely hanging in the<lb/> abdominal cavity, it was avulsed from its mesentry and was non<lb/> viable. Rest of the small bowel was non existent with only<lb/> patches of mucosa at places and borders of the mesentry was<lb/> contused. The contused mesentry borders initially appeared<lb/> (during 1 st surgery) as contused small bowel.<lb/> ii.<lb/> Jejunostomy stoma was gangrenous for approximately<lb/> 2cm.<lb/> iii.<lb/> Stomach and duodenum was distended but healthy.<lb/> Surgical procedure:<lb/> 1.<lb/> Resection of gangrenous terminal ileum, caecum<lb/> appendix, ascending colon, hepatic flexure and transverse<lb/> colon was done.<lb/> 2.<lb/> Resection of necrotic jejunal stoma with closure of DJ<lb/> flexure in two layers by 3&apos;0&apos; vicryl.<lb/> 3.<lb/> Diverting lateral tube duodenostomy (viz 18f foley&apos;s<lb/> catheter) brought through right flank.<lb/> 4.<lb/> Tube gastrostomy was added as another decompressive<lb/> measure (28 size portex tube was used). Tube gastrostomy<lb/> was brought from previous jejunostomy site.<lb/> 5.<lb/> Abdominal drain placed in pelvis.<lb/> 6.<lb/> Rectus sheath closed by using no. ‗1&apos; -prolene,<lb/> interrupted suture.<lb/> 7.<lb/> Skin closed by using 1 ‗0&apos; nylon.<lb/> 8.<lb/> Perineal wound packed with Betadine soaked gauze<lb/> piece.<lb/> 9.<lb/> Dressing was done.‖<lb/> 116. PW-50 Dr. Raj Kumar Chejara further testified that the clinical<lb/> notes Ex.PW-50/C formed part of the summoned medical record and<lb/> were in the hand writing of Dr. Pintu, Sr. Resident, who was in his<lb/> team and these notes were prepared under his supervision. During<lb/> this surgery the notes prepared by the gynaecology team in his<lb/> presence were Ex.PW-50/D which bear the signature of Dr. Rekha.<lb/> According to PW-50, after the surgery the prosecutrix was shifted<lb/> back to ICU and remained critical and on 23.12.2012 she had to be re-<lb/></table>
<lb/>
            <head>CRL. APP. NOS.1398/2013, 1399/2013 AND 1414/2013<lb/> </head>
<lb/> 
            <table>operated (peritoneal lavage and placement of drain under general<lb/> anaesthesia). He deposed that the clinical notes prepared on<lb/> 23.12.2012 (Ex.PW-50/E) were in his handwriting and were signed<lb/> by him. As per his further deposition, on 26.12.2012 the condition of<lb/> the patient was again examined by a team of doctors and it was<lb/> decided to shift her abroad for further management. The note<lb/> prepared in this regard was proved by him as Ex.PW-50/F which he<lb/> stated bears his signatures and also bears the signatures of the four<lb/> other doctors, namely, Dr. Sunil Kumar, Dr. Aruna Batra, Dr. P.K.<lb/> Verma and one other doctor. On the following day, i.e., on<lb/> 27.12.2012, an application being Ex.PW-49/C was moved by the I.O.<lb/> S.I. Pratibha for an opinion regarding the nature of the injuries and he<lb/> (PW-50) opined that </table>
 
            <head>the abdominal injuries were sufficient to cause<lb/> death in the ordinary course of nature. His </head>
 
            <table>opinion in this regard<lb/> was Ex.PW-50/G. After tendering this opinion, he forwarded this<lb/> application to HOD (Gynae) for opinion about perineal injuries.<lb/> 117. PW-50 Dr. Raj Kumar Chejara further testified that thereafter,<lb/> on 02.01.2013, Inspector Anil Sharma (PW-78) moved an application<lb/> being Ex.PW-49/F for obtaining opinion from the doctors regarding<lb/> the weapons of offence. On examination of the weapons viz., the iron<lb/> rods after the same were unsealed before him and the other doctors,<lb/> including Dr. Sunil Kumar, Dr. Arun Batra, Dr. Rashmi Ahuja,<lb/> Dr.Sachin Bajaj and Dr.Dheeraj Sharma who were treating the<lb/> prosecutrix, the opinion of their team was that the injuries on the<lb/> body of the prosecutrix could be caused by the weapons examined.<lb/> Further, it was opined by them that &quot;</table>

            <head>the perineal injury was severe&quot;<lb/> DEATH SENTENCE REFERENCE NO.6/2013,<lb/> Page 69 of 340<lb/> CRL. APP. NOS.1398/2013, 1399/2013 AND 1414/2013<lb/> and there was a &quot;complete tear involving lower 2/3 rd of posterior<lb/> vaginal wall, recto vaginal septum, anus, anal canal, anterior rectal<lb/> wall extending upwards into adjoining large intestine. This injury<lb/> could have been caused by thrusting of blunt rod like object forcibly<lb/> through vagina and/or anus.&quot; Also, as per their opinion: &quot;During<lb/> the struggle and withdrawal of rod like structure from abdomen,<lb/> intestines, prolapsed/herniated which led to irreparable damage,<lb/> loss and severe injuries to large and small intestine.&quot;<lb/> 118. It is </head>
 
            <table>relevant to point out that the rods (Ex. P-49/1 and Ex. P-<lb/>49/2) were shown to Dr. Rashmi Ahuja (PW-49), Dr. Chejara (PW-<lb/>50) and Dr. Sachin Bajaj (PW-51), who identified the same during<lb/> their examination in Court.</table>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <head>DEATH SENTENCE REFERENCE NO.6/2013,<lb/> Page 73 of 340<lb/> CRL. APP. NOS.1398/2013, 1399/2013 AND 1414/2013<lb/> </head>
<lb/> 
            <table>removed and analysis of the medical evidence would also clearly<lb/> show, beyond any reasonable doubt, that the injuries sustained by the<lb/> prosecutrix were extremely severe and would cause death in the<lb/> ordinary course of nature, and that death ensued on account of her<lb/> injuries and not due to any other cause, as alleged, such as unhygienic<lb/> conditions in the hospital.<lb/> 128. It is also relevant to note at this juncture that the evidence of<lb/> the postmortem doctors has been recorded through video<lb/> conferencing, for which purpose the service of summons has been<lb/> effected through the MLAT process (Mutual Legal Assistance Treaty)<lb/> and the note verbale confirming the same has been placed on record.<lb/> This has been done in terms of the guidelines laid down by the<lb/> Hon&quot;ble Supreme Court </table>
 
            <head>in State of Maharashtra v. Praful Desai,<lb/> (2003) 4 SCC 601 and </head>
 
            <table>the proviso to Section 275(1) Cr.P.C.<lb/> 129. Adverting next to the injuries suffered by the complainant, the<lb/> complainant was treated </table>
 
            <head>by PW-51 Dr. Sachin Bajaj and his MLC is<lb/> </head>
<lb/> 
            <table>Ex.PW-51/A, which shows wounds over the scalp, left upper leg and<lb/> right knee. PW-51 further proves that on 02.01.2013, Inspector Anil<lb/> Sharma (PW-78) moved an application (Ex.PW-51/B) for obtaining<lb/> an opinion regarding the weapon of offence. The doctor (PW-51) in<lb/> his opinion (Ex.PW-51/C), has stated that the injuries on the body of<lb/> the complainant could be caused by the said weapons of offence viz.,<lb/> iron rods.<lb/> 130. As regards the medical examination of the accused, suffice it to<lb/> note that the sexual potency test of accused Ram Singh was done vide<lb/> Ex.PW-2/DA which need not detain us as Ram Singh has since died.<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <head>DEATH SENTENCE REFERENCE NO.6/2013,<lb/> Page 74 of 340<lb/> CRL. APP. NOS.1398/2013, 1399/2013 AND 1414/2013<lb/> The sexual potency test of accused Mukesh and collection of samples<lb/> was done by PW-3 Dr. Chetan Kumar, who has proved on record<lb/> </head>
<lb/> 
            <table>his report Ex.PW-3/A; that of Vinay Sharma was done by PW-6 Dr.<lb/> Kulbhushan Prasad, who has proved his report as Ex.PW-6/A; that<lb/> of Akshay Thakur, was done by </table>
 
            <head>PW-7 Dr. Shashank Pooniya, who<lb/> </head>
<lb/> 
            <table>has proved his report as Ex.PW-7/A; and that of accused Pawan was<lb/> done by PW</table>

            <head>-10 Dr. Mohit Gupta, who </head>
 
            <table>has proved his report as<lb/> Ex.PW-10/A. The aforesaid medical reports clearly prove that all the<lb/> accused were capable of performing sexual intercourse. This apart,<lb/> PW-7 Dr. Shashank Pooniya proves in his report Ex.PW-7/A injuries<lb/> on accused Akshay Thakur, which are suggestive of a struggle; in his<lb/> report Ex.PW-7/B that the injuries present on the body of accused<lb/> Pawan Kumar were about 2-3 days old and in his report Ex.PW-7/C<lb/> that the injuries present on the body of accused Vinay Sharma were<lb/> suggestive of a possible struggle.</table>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <table>v) In answer to Question No.10, he stated that the other accused<lb/> persons put off the lights inside the bus at the flyover of Malai<lb/> Mandir and thereafter he did not know what they had done with<lb/> the prosecutrix or the complainant.<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <head>CRL. APP. NOS.1398/2013, 1399/2013 AND 1414/2013<lb/> </head>
<lb/> 
            <table>(vi) In answer to Question No.11, he stated that at about 12:30 AM<lb/> he found torn clothes and other material inside the bus.<lb/> Accused Akshay and the JCL had washed the bus which he had<lb/> parked in front of Ravi Dass Mandir, Sector 3, Ravi Dass<lb/> Camp, R.K. Puram, New Delhi.<lb/> (vii) In answer to Question No.17, he stated that the prosecutrix and<lb/> the complainant were thrown out by stopping the bus at the<lb/> spot near Mahipalpur flyover, though added that he did not<lb/> know who had thrown them out of the bus as the light inside<lb/> the bus was put off.<lb/> (viii) In answer to Question Nos.42 and 43 and on being asked as to<lb/> whether he was taking water in cans inside the bus for the<lb/> purpose of washing the bus from inside, he replied that he was<lb/> only standing outside the bus.<lb/> (ix) In answer to Question Nos.55 and 56, he admitted that he was<lb/> carrying his mobile phone No.9540967311 on that night and it<lb/> was on this phone that accused Ram Singh had called him to<lb/> Munirka and he had gone there with his nephew.<lb/> (x) In answer to Question No.67, he again admitted that he was<lb/> driving the bus when it was boarded by the prosecutrix and her<lb/> friend from Munirka while his brother Ram Singh and the JCL,<lb/> (name withheld), were calling for passengers by saying<lb/> &quot;Palam/Dwarka Mod&quot;. He further admitted that the windows<lb/> of the bus Ex.P-1 had black film; that Ram Singh used to drive<lb/> the bus daily and on that day since he was drunk heavily he had<lb/> gone to Munirka and was driving the bus and that the other<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <head>CRL. APP. NOS.1398/2013, 1399/2013 AND 1414/2013<lb/> </head>
<lb/> 
            <table>boys along with Ram Singh had already taken the bus from<lb/> R.K. Puram.<lb/> (xi) In answer to Question Nos.68 and 69, he again admitted that he<lb/> was driving the bus at that time.<lb/> (xii) In answer to Question No.149, he admitted that he had pointed<lb/> out the place from where the victims had boarded the bus Ex.P-<lb/>1 and the place where both were thrown out of the moving bus<lb/> though stated that he had shown the said places to Inspector<lb/> Ram Sahai and S.I. Gajender (PW-55) and not to S.I. Pratibha<lb/> Sharma (PW-80).<lb/> (xiii) In answer to Question No.200, he stated that he had taken only<lb/> one round while driving the bus Ex.P-1. He had taken the bus<lb/> from Munirka to Dwarka and took a U-turn underneath a<lb/> flyover at Palam and then drove the bus at NH-8 and then they<lb/> went to Mahipalpur and from Mahipalpur he drove the bus to<lb/> Munirka and then to R.K. Puram. To be noted that he does not<lb/> say that the bus did not take two rounds.<lb/> (xiv) In answer to Question No.211, he admitted that PW-82 Shri<lb/> Ram Adhar had boarded the bus Ex.P-1 on 16.12.2012 prior to<lb/> the boarding of the bus Ex.P-1 by the complainant and the<lb/> victim and in answer to Question No.213, he admitted that he<lb/> was driving the bus at that time. He stated that PW-82 boarded<lb/> the bus from Sabzi Mandi at Sector 4 of R.K. Puram on the<lb/> main road, but stated that he did not know PW-82 was beaten<lb/> by any of the co-accused as he was in the driver&quot;s cabin and<lb/> driving the bus. His co-accused however brought PW-82 to the<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <head>DEATH SENTENCE REFERENCE NO.6/2013,<lb/> Page 78 of 340<lb/> CRL. APP. NOS.1398/2013, 1399/2013 AND 1414/2013<lb/> front </head>
 
            <figDesc>door of the bus Ex.P-1, saying that PW-82 should get<lb/> down since he had no money to pay the bus fare.<lb/> </figDesc>
<lb/> 
            <table>134. Accused Pawan in his statement under Section 313 Cr.P.C. in<lb/> response to Question No.3 and Question No.4 categorically stated<lb/> that he was not in the bus Ex.P-1 at the time of the incident. In<lb/> answer to Question No.58 pertaining to his mobile phone bearing</table>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <table>The very same story was again reiterated by him with embellishments<lb/> in answer to Question No.219. He stated:<lb/> -In the evening when I came out of my jhuggi I saw the quarrel<lb/> between accused Vinay and accused Ram Singh since<lb/> deceased. I returned to my jhuggi since I had taken liquor. </table>
 
            <head>After<lb/> sometime I again came out of my jhuggi and I saw accused<lb/> Vinay with his mother, sister and a neighbour, going to a<lb/> musical party. I accompanied them. In the musical party I took<lb/> more liquor and got intoxicated. I lay down on a bench and my<lb/> mobile phone was lost.‖<lb/> 135. It </head>
 
            <table>may be noted at this juncture that in his supplementary<lb/> statement recorded on 16.08.2013 under Section 313 Cr.P.C., accused<lb/> Pawan took a complete somersault from the stand taken by him in his<lb/> aforesaid statement recorded under Section 313 Cr.P.C. as is evident<lb/> from the answer given by him to Question No.9. In direct<lb/> contradiction to what he had earlier stated, he stated </table>
 
            <head>that he did not<lb/> know if he had accompanied accused Vinay to the DDA District<lb/> Park on that evening. On </head>
 
            <figDesc>the next day, his mother told him that his<lb/> father had lifted him from the said park in the night.<lb/> </figDesc>
<lb/> 
            <table>136. A look now at the statement of accused Vinay Sharma<lb/> recorded under Section 313 Cr.P.C. in which he introduced his<lb/> plea of alibi that he was not present in bus Ex.P-1 as he had gone<lb/> to attend a musical party at a park in Green Park and made a bid<lb/> to explain the struggle marks detected on his person by PW-6 Dr.<lb/> Kulbhushan Prasad during his medical examination. On being<lb/> asked vide Question No.32 about his medical examination<lb/> pursuant to his arrest, the accused introduced a case of fight with<lb/> accused Ram Singh on 16.12.2012, </table>
 
            <head>at about 8:30 P.M. as Ram<lb/> </head>
<lb/> 
            <table>Singh had misbehaved with his sister. He further stated that both<lb/> accused Mukesh and Ram Singh had threatened to implicate him<lb/> in a false case. It may be noted that this is in direct contradiction<lb/> to his answer to Question No.7 wherein he stated that he did not<lb/> know accused Thakur or accused Mukesh. Further, as per him,<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <head>CRL. APP. NOS.1398/2013, 1399/2013 AND 1414/2013<lb/> </head>
<lb/> 
            <table>after the fight he had gone to attend a party. On being<lb/> questioned with regard to his mobile phone vide connection<lb/> No.8285947545 in the name of Champa Devi (his mother),<lb/> resident of J-105, Ravi Dass Camp (Question No.57), he gave the<lb/> following significant answer:-<lb/>-Though the phone no. 8285947545 belongs to my mother but<lb/> its sim was </table>
 
            <head>lost prior to 16-12-2012. My friend had concealed<lb/> my phone and when he returned it, it was not having sim card<lb/> and the memory card.‖<lb/> 137. On </head>
 
            <figDesc>being queried about the call detail records of the aforesaid<lb/> </figDesc>
<lb/> 
            <table>mobile phone (Ex.PW-23/B), which showed that on 16.12.2012 at<lb/> 9:55 PM, he had made a call which was recorded by the tower at NH-<lb/>8 near IGI Airport, Mahipal Pur having Cell ID No.55043, he stated<lb/> that he did not know anything about the call as his SIM had been lost.<lb/> He had not filed any complaint but had telephoned the customer care<lb/> to deactivate the SIM card. It may be noted at this juncture that he<lb/> neither chose to summon any witness from the customer care nor<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <head>summoned the records to show that he had asked for deactivation of<lb/> the SIM card. Subsequently, in answer to Question No. 217, he took<lb/> a complete somersault on his statement that the SIM Card was lost<lb/> prior to 16.12.2012, as under:-<lb/></head>
<lb/>
            <table>-Q.217:<lb/> It is in evidence against you Vinay that at the time<lb/> of your arrest a Nokia black colour mobile phone bearing IMEI<lb/> No. 35413805830824/8 was recovered from your personal<lb/> search, seized vide memo Ex.PW60/D, which you later got<lb/> released on superdari. What do you have to say?<lb/> Ans: It is correct that the said phone belongs to me<lb/> but on 16-12-2012 at about 9:30 PM while I was in the party,<lb/> one Vipin, a friend of accused Ram Singh, had taken my<lb/> phone for making a call and left the party. Later on 17-12-<lb/>2012, he returned my above phone on charging Rs.200/-<lb/></table>
<lb/>
            <head>CRL. APP. NOS.1398/2013, 1399/2013 AND 1414/2013<lb/> from me but without sim card. The </head>
 
            <table>recording of the party,<lb/> prior to 9:30 PM, was in the said mobile phone, which I<lb/> wanted to show to SI Pratibha Sharma and SI Mandeep but<lb/> they did not look into it. It was not recovered in my<lb/> personal search. The police had recovered this mobile<lb/> phone from my house.‖<lb/> 138. Finally, in answer to Question No.221, he gave his version with<lb/> regard to the events which took place on 16.12.2012 as under:-<lb/>-Q.221:<lb/> Do you have anything else to say?<lb/> Ans: On 16-12-2012 I was working in the Sab-fitness<lb/> Gym at Srifort Complex, Khel Gaon Marg, New Delhi. I left<lb/> the said gym at about 2:30 PM. At about 4:30/5 PM my<lb/> friend told me that Ram Singh had teased my sister when<lb/> she was going to purchase milk from the market. I along<lb/> with my brother then went to find out Ram Singh but he did<lb/> not meet us as he was not in the camp. Again at about<lb/> 8/8:30 PM we again went to meet him and we found Ram<lb/> Singh near his bus Ex.P1 near the Gurudwara of our Camp.<lb/> He was drunk at that time and he started abusing us.<lb/> Thereafter, we had a scuffle and we exchanged fist blows<lb/> and blood started oozing out from my face. Even my clothes<lb/> were torn. One of his friends, who was with Ram Singh, had<lb/> also beaten me. Thereafter I returned to my jhuggi as I<lb/> became afraid because one of the brothers of accused Ram<lb/> Singh was also involved in a similar matter of rape and<lb/> there being a criminal record of his brother. I then left for a<lb/> musical party in a park at Green Park, New Delhi. </table>
 
            <head>I met<lb/> Pawan and that my friend Ram Babu had prepared a<lb/> video in that function. My sister and mother had also<lb/> accompanied to the said park. My other friends were also<lb/> enjoying the said party. At about 11/11:30 PM I returned to<lb/> my jhuggi and informed my parents about the scuffle I had<lb/> with accused Ram Singh. I am innocent and I have not<lb/> </head>
<lb/> 
            <table>committed any crime. I have not done anything. I have<lb/> been involved in this case because of the enmity with<lb/> accused Ram Singh and his brother.‖<lb/> 139. Adverting to the statement of accused Akshay Kumar Singh<lb/> @ Thakur, he too introduces his plea of alibi in his statement under<lb/> Section 313 Cr.P.C. by stating in answer to Question No.2 that he<lb/> had left Delhi on 15.12.2012. Again, in answer to Question No.70,<lb/> he states that his name is not &quot;Thakur&quot; but is Akshay Kumar Singh<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <head>DEATH SENTENCE REFERENCE NO.6/2013,<lb/> Page 82 of 340<lb/> CRL. APP. NOS.1398/2013, 1399/2013 AND 1414/2013<lb/> and </head>
 
            <figDesc>he was not in Delhi on 16.12.2012, having left Delhi for his<lb/> village on 15.12.2012 from New Delhi Railway Station, in<lb/> </figDesc>
<lb/> 
            <table>Mahabodhi Express. It is his case that he was arrested from Tandwa<lb/> in Bihar. In answer to Question No.122, he states so. The said<lb/> question and answer being apposite are reproduced hereunder:-<lb/>-Q.122: It is in evidence against you that on 21.12.2012 it<lb/> was informed that you accused Askhay had come to your house<lb/> at village Kamaralangh. A raid was conducted and you were<lb/> found present in your house. Your were apprehended,<lb/> interrogated and arrested vide arrest </table>
 
            <head>memo Ex.PW-53/A. The<lb/> information about your arrest was conveyed to your father vide<lb/> memo Ex.PW-53/B ; your personal search was conducted vide<lb/> memo Ex.PW-53/C and your disclosure Ex.PW53/D was </head>
 
            <table>also<lb/> recorded. What do you have to say?<lb/> Ans: On 21-12-2012 I had come to my house from<lb/> the house of my Bua as the police had apprehended my father<lb/> and he was made to sit in the police station Tandwa. I reached<lb/> P.5 Tandwa at about 8:30 PM of 21-12-2012, where I was<lb/> apprehended by the police. The timings of 9:15 PM of 21-12-<lb/>2012, of my arrest, as shown in the arrest memo, are wrong.‖<lb/> 140. Significantly, in his statement under Section 313 Cr.P.C.,<lb/> accused Akshay @ Thakur does not dispute that he was working as a<lb/> helper in bus Ex.P-1 owned by Shri Dinesh Yadav. On being<lb/> questioned about the same, he concedes:-<lb/>-It is correct that I was working as a helper in the<lb/> bus Ex.P1. I joined Ram Singh, since deceased as helper on 3-<lb/>11-2012 but I left the company of Ram Singh on 15-12-2012 at<lb/> about 10:30 AM and I left for my village at 11:30 am and I went<lb/> to New Delhi Railway Station and I left Delhi in the train at<lb/> about 2:30 PM.‖</table>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <head>DEATH SENTENCE REFERENCE NO.6/2013,<lb/> Page 84 of 340<lb/> CRL. APP. NOS.1398/2013, 1399/2013 AND 1414/2013</head>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <table>Sharma was 01.03.1994, the learned Sessions Court held that the<lb/> question of obtaining medical opinion with regard to the bone age<lb/> of the accused did not arise. For arriving at the </table>
 
            <head>aforesaid<lb/> CRL. APP. NOS.1398/2013, 1399/2013 AND 1414/2013<lb/> conclusions</head>

            <figDesc>, the learned Sessions Court relied upon the judgment<lb/> of the Hon&quot;ble Supreme Court in </figDesc>
 
            <head>Shah Nawaz vs. State of Uttar<lb/> Pradesh and Another, (2011) 13 SCC 751, the </head>
 
            <table>relevant extract<lb/> whereof reads as under:-<lb/>-The documents furnished above clearly show that the date of<lb/> birth of the appellant had been noted as 18-6-1989. Rule 12 of<lb/> the Rules categorically envisages that the medical opinion from<lb/> the Medical Board should be sought only when the<lb/> matriculation certificate or school certificate or any birth<lb/> certificate issued by a corporation or by any panchayat or<lb/> municipality is not available. We are of the view that though the<lb/> Board has correctly accepted the entry relating to the date of<lb/> birth in the marksheet and school certificate, the Additional<lb/> Sessions Judge and the High Court committed a grave error in<lb/> determining the age of the appellant ignoring the date of birth<lb/> mentioned in those documents which is illegal, erroneous and<lb/> contrary to the Rules.‖<lb/> It was further observed that :<lb/> xxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxx<lb/> -We are also satisfied that Rule 12 of the Rules which was<lb/> brought in pursuance of the Act describes four categories of<lb/> evidence which have been provided in which preference has<lb/> been given to school certificate over the medical report.‖<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <head>152. The learned Sessions Court was also guided by the<lb/> observations made by the Supreme Court in Ashwani Kumar<lb/> Saxena vs. State of M.P., (2012) 9 SCC 750, wherein the Hon&quot;ble<lb/> </head>
<lb/> 
            <table>Supreme Court in the context of the procedure to be followed for<lb/> enquiring into the claim of juvenility under Section 7-A of the<lb/> Juvenile Justice Care and Protection Act, 2000 read with Rule 12<lb/> of the 2007 Rules held as under:-<lb/>-29. The procedure laid down for inquiring into the specific<lb/> matters under the Code naturally cannot be applied in inquiring<lb/> into other matters like the claim of juvenility under Section 7A<lb/> read with Rule 12 of the 2007 Rules.‖<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <head>CRL. APP. NOS.1398/2013, 1399/2013 AND 1414/2013<lb/> </head>
<lb/> 
            <table>30. Consequently, the procedure to be followed under the J.J.<lb/> Act in conducting an inquiry is the procedure laid down in that<lb/> statute itself i.e. Rule 12 of the 2007 Rules.<lb/> 31. We also remind all Courts/Juvenile Justice Board and the<lb/> Committees functioning under the Act that a duty is cast on<lb/> them to seek evidence by obtaining the certificate etc.<lb/> mentioned in Rules 12 (3) (a) (i) to (iii). The courts in such<lb/> situations act as a parens patriae because they have a kind of<lb/> guardianship over minors who from their legal disability stand<lb/> in need of protection.<lb/> 32. -Age determination inquiry‖ contemplated under section 7A<lb/> of the Act read with Rule 12 of the 2007 Rules enables the<lb/> court to seek evidence and in that process, the court can<lb/> obtain the matriculation or equivalent certificates, if available.<lb/> Only in the absence of any matriculation or equivalent<lb/> certificates, the court needs to obtain the date of birth<lb/> certificate from the school first attended other than a play<lb/> school. Only in the absence of matriculation or equivalent<lb/> certificate or the date of birth certificate from the school first<lb/> attended, the court needs to obtain the birth certificate given by<lb/> a corporation or a municipal authority or a panchayat (not an<lb/> affidavit but certificates or documents). </table>
 
            <head>The question of<lb/> obtaining medical opinion from a duly constituted Medical<lb/> Board arises only if the above mentioned documents are<lb/> unavailable. In case </head>
 
            <table>exact assessment of the age cannot be<lb/> done, then the court, for reasons to be recorded, may, if<lb/> considered necessary, give the benefit to the child or juvenile<lb/> by considering his or her age on lower side within the margin of<lb/> one year.<lb/> 33. Once </table>
 
            <head>the court, following the above mentioned procedures,<lb/> passes an order; that order shall be the conclusive proof of the<lb/> age as regards such child or juvenile in conflict with law. It has<lb/> been made clear in sub-rule (5) or Rule 12 that no further<lb/> </head>
<lb/> 
            <table>inquiry shall be conducted by the court or the Board after<lb/> examining and obtaining the certificate or any other<lb/> documentary proof after referring to sub-rule (3) of the Rule 12.<lb/> Further, Section 49 of the J.J. Act also draws a presumption of<lb/> the age of the juvenility on its determination.<lb/> 34. …….There may be situations where the entry made in the<lb/> matriculation or equivalent certificates, date of birth certificate<lb/> from the school first attended and even the birth certificate<lb/> given by a corporation or a municipal authority or a panchayat<lb/> may not be correct. </table>
 
            <head>But court, Juvenile Justice Board or a<lb/> committee functioning under the J.J. Act is not expected to<lb/> conduct such a roving enquiry and to go behind those<lb/> DEATH SENTENCE REFERENCE NO.6/2013,<lb/> Page 90 of 340<lb/> CRL. APP. NOS.1398/2013, 1399/2013 AND 1414/2013<lb/> certificates to examine the correctness of those<lb/> documents, kept </head>
 
            <table>during the normal course of business. Only in<lb/> cases where those documents or certificates are found to be<lb/> fabricated or manipulated, the court, the Juvenile Justice Board<lb/> or the committee need to go for medical report for age<lb/> determination.‖</table>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <head>DEATH SENTENCE REFERENCE NO.6/2013,<lb/> Page 94 of 340<lb/> CRL. APP. NOS.1398/2013, 1399/2013 AND 1414/2013</head>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <note>as:<lb/> -(i) omissions, unless by necessary implication be<lb/> deemed to be part of the statement, cannot be used to<lb/> contradict the statement made in the witness-box;‖<lb/> CRL. APP. NOS.1398/2013, 1399/2013 AND 1414/2013</note>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <note>(SCC, page 128 to 129)<lb/> <note>-16. Once we find that the eye witness account of PW 13 is<lb/> corroborated by material particulars and is reliable, we cannot<lb/> discard his evidence only on the ground that there are some<lb/> discrepancies in the evidence of PW 1, PW 2, PW 13 and PW<lb/> 19. As has been held by this Court in State of Rajasthan v.<lb/> Kalki (1981) 2 SCC 752, in the deposition of witnesses there<lb/> are always normal discrepancies due to normal errors of<lb/> observation, loss of memory, mental disposition of the<lb/> witnesses and the like. Unless, therefore, the discrepancies are<lb/> -material discrepancies‖ so as to create a reasonable doubt<lb/> about the credibility of the witnesses, the Court will not discard<lb/> the evidence of the witnesses…...‖<lb/> 170. In Pudhu Raja (supra), the Supreme Court made the<lb/> following pertinent observations:-(SCC, page 202)</note>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <head>CRL. APP. NOS.1398/2013, 1399/2013 AND 1414/2013<lb/> normal </head>
 
            <figDesc>errors of observation, normal errors of memory<lb/> due to lapse of time, due to mental disposition such as<lb/> shock and horror at the time of occurrence, and the<lb/> like. Material discrepancies are those which are not<lb/> normal and not expected of a normal person.<lb/> </figDesc>
<lb/> 
            <table>8.<lb/> Referring to and relying upon the earlier<lb/> judgments of this Court in </table>
 
            <head>State of U.P. v. M.K.<lb/> Anthony, Tahsildar Singh v. State of U.P.,<lb/> Appabhai v. State of Gujarat and Rammi v. State of<lb/> M.P.,this Court in a recent case Leela Ram v. State of<lb/> Haryana held:</head>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <head>[Vide State vs. Saravanan,<lb/> Arumugam vs. State, Mahendra Pratap Singh vs. State of<lb/> CRL. APP. NOS.1398/2013, 1399/2013 AND 1414/2013</head>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <head>CRL. APP. NOS.1398/2013, 1399/2013 AND 1414/2013<lb/> </head>
<lb/> 
            <figDesc>Code of Criminal Procedure which obliges the<lb/> investigating agency to hold, or confers a right upon the<lb/> accused to claim a test identification parade. They do not<lb/> constitute substantive evidence and these parades are<lb/> essentially governed by Section 162 of the Code of<lb/> Criminal Procedure. Failure to hold a test identification<lb/> parade would not make inadmissible the evidence of<lb/> identification in court. The weight to be attached to such<lb/> identification should be a matter for the courts of fact. In<lb/> appropriate cases it may accept the evidence of<lb/> identification even without insisting on corroboration. [See<lb/> Kanta </figDesc>
 
            <head>Prashad v. Delhi Admn., AIR 1958 SC 350,<lb/> Vaikuntam Chandrappa v. State of A.P., AIR 1960 SC<lb/> 1340, Budhsen v. State of U.P., (1970) 2 SCC 128 and<lb/> Rameshwar Singh v. State of J and K., (1971) 2 SCC<lb/> 715).<lb/> </head>
<lb/> 
            <table>49. We may also refer to the decision of this Court in Pramod<lb/> Mandal v. State of Bihar [(2004) 13 SCC 150 : 2005 SCC (Cri)<lb/> 75] where this Court observed: (SCC p. 158, para 20)<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>-20. It is neither possible nor prudent to lay down any<lb/> invariable rule as to the period within which a test<lb/> identification parade must be held, or the number of<lb/> witnesses who must correctly identify the accused, to<lb/> sustain his conviction. These matters must be left to the<lb/> courts of fact to decide in the facts and circumstances of<lb/> each case. If a rule is laid down prescribing a period<lb/> within which the test identification parade must be held, it<lb/> would only benefit the professional criminals in whose<lb/> cases the arrests are delayed as the police have no clear<lb/> clue about their identity, they being persons unknown to<lb/> the victims. They, therefore, have only to avoid their arrest<lb/> for the prescribed period to avoid conviction. Similarly,<lb/> there may be offences which by their very nature may be<lb/> witnessed by a single witness, such as rape. The offender<lb/> may be unknown to the victim and the case </note>
 
            <table>depends<lb/> solely on the identification by the victim, who is otherwise<lb/> found to be truthful and reliable. What justification can be<lb/> pleaded to contend that such cases must necessarily<lb/> result in acquittal because of there being only one<lb/> identifying witness? Prudence therefore demands that<lb/> these matters must be left to the wisdom of the courts of<lb/> fact which must consider all aspects of the matter in the<lb/> light of the evidence on record before pronouncing upon<lb/> the acceptability or rejection of such identification.‖<lb/> 50. The decision of this Court in Malkhansingh case [(2003) 5<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>SCC 746 : 2003 SCC (Cri) 1247] and Aqeel Ahmad v. State of<lb/> CRL. APP. NOS.1398/2013, 1399/2013 AND 1414/2013<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>U.P. [(2008) 16 SCC 372 : (2010) 4 SCC (Cri) 11] adopt a<lb/> similar line of reasoning.‖<lb/> 185. The aforesaid aspect has also been perspicaciously dealt with in<lb/> Manu Sharma v. State (NCT of Delhi), (2010) 6 SCC 1, wherein the<lb/> Hon&quot;ble Mr. Justice Sathashivam (as his Lordship then was) while<lb/> writing the judgment, after noting that the reason given by accused<lb/> Manu Sharma for his refusal to participate in TIP, being that he had<lb/> been shown to the witnesses, was false, opined: (SCC, page 93)<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>-In </note>
 
            <head>the absence of any defence, refusal of TIP on this<lb/> ground is totally unjustified and an adverse inference<lb/> ought to be drawn in this regard.‖<lb/> 186</head>

            <note>. The Court further observed as under:-(SCC, page 99)<lb/> <note>-258. </note>
 
            <head>The learned Solicitor General submitted that, even<lb/> otherwise, an adverse inference ought to be drawn<lb/> against the appellants for their refusal to join the TIP. This<lb/> view has found favour time and again by this Court. It is<lb/> pertinent to note that it is dock identification which is<lb/> substantive piece of evidence. Therefore even where no<lb/> TIP is conducted no prejudice can be caused to the case<lb/> of the prosecution.<lb/> 259. In Mullagiri Vajram v. State of A.P it was held that<lb/> though the accused was seen by the witness in custody,<lb/> any infirmity in TIP will not affect the outcome of the case,<lb/> since the depositions of the witnesses in court were<lb/> reliable and could sustain a conviction. The photo<lb/> identification and TIP are only aides in the investigation<lb/> and does not form substantive evidence. The substantive<lb/> evidence is the evidence in the court on oath.‖<lb/> 187. </head>
 
            <figDesc>In view of the aforesaid, we conclude this aspect of the case by<lb/> noting that insofar as accused Ram Singh, accused Vinay and accused<lb/> Pawan are concerned, the said accused persons refused to participate<lb/> in TIP and this circumstance can by no means have any adverse<lb/> bearing on the case of the prosecution. </figDesc>
 
            <head>Of necessity, an adverse<lb/> CRL. APP. NOS.1398/2013, 1399/2013 AND 1414/2013<lb/> inference is required to be drawn against them for their refusal<lb/> without justifiable cause to participate in the TIP.<lb/> </head>
<lb/> 
            <table>188. On the aspect of recovery of blood stained clothes and the<lb/> weapon of offence being the iron rods, Mr. Singh placed reliance<lb/> upon the judgment of this Court in Raj Kumar @ Raju vs. State,<lb/> (2010) 169 DLT 517 (DB) to contend that the said recoveries were in<lb/> the nature of &quot;weak evidence&quot;. We extract hereinbelow the portion of<lb/> the judgment in the said case pertaining to recoveries:-(DLT, page<lb/> 520)<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>-15. As regards the recovery of counterfoils of bank deposit<lb/> slips from the appellant and the co-accused it would be of<lb/> importance to note that the diary Ex.P-9 was admittedly<lb/> recovered from the pocket of the deceased and there is a<lb/> possibility that the said counterfoils may have been recovered<lb/> from the diary and later on planted. Way back in the year 1943,<lb/> in the decision AIR 1943 Null 5, Shera vs. Emperor the Court<lb/> had cautioned of such kind of ordinary articles being planted.<lb/> 16. As regards the recovery of the hammer Ex.P-3 and the<lb/> leather bag Ex.P-4 from near the scene of the crime, it assumes<lb/> importance that when the dead body was detected in the<lb/> evening of 29.7.2004 not only the investigating officer but even<lb/> the crime team had accessed the place and we find it strange<lb/> that nobody could detect the said hammer or the leather bag<lb/> nearby.<lb/> 17. Now, as the case set up by the prosecution, the appellant<lb/> runs a tea stall and probably acts as a postal agent, thus </note>
 
            <table>his<lb/> being possessed with Rs.4,500/-is not a fact wherefrom eye-<lb/>brows had to be raised; it be noted that with reference to the<lb/> number on the currency notes nobody has been able to link the<lb/> same to the deceased.<lb/> 18. The recoveries of blood-stained clothes at the instance of<lb/> the appellant have to be viewed in light of various decisions of<lb/> the Supreme Court where such kind of recoveries have been<lb/> held to be very weak evidence.<lb/> 19. In the decision reported as AIR 1963 SC 1113 Prabhu vs.<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>State of U.P. recovery of a blood-stained shirt and a dhoti as<lb/> also an axe on which human blood was detected was held to be<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>extremely weak evidence. Similarly, in the decision reported as<lb/> (1977) 4 SCC 600(1) : AIR 1977 SC 1753 Narsinbhai Haribhai<lb/> Prajapati etc. vs. Chhatrasinh &amp; Ors. the recovery of a blood-<lb/>stained shirt and a dhoti as also the weapon of offence a<lb/> dhariya were held to be weak evidence. In the decision reported<lb/> as 1993 Supp.(1) SCC 208 = AIR 1994 SC 110 Surjit Singh &amp;<lb/> Anr. vs. State of Punjab the recovery of a watch stated to be<lb/> that of deceased and a dagger stained with blood of the same<lb/> group as that of the deceased were held to be weak evidence.<lb/> As late as in the decision reported as JT 2008 (1) SC 191 Mani<lb/> vs. State of Tamil Nadu recoveries of blood stained clothes and<lb/> weapon of offence stained with blood were held to be weak<lb/> recoveries.<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>20. We may only add that the part of the disclosure statement of<lb/> the accused that the clothes which he was wearing at the time<lb/> when he committed the crime got stained with blood of the<lb/> deceased and his getting the clothes recovered attracts Section<lb/> 27 of the Evidence Act limited to the extent that the accused got<lb/> recovered blood stained clothes. Independent evidence has to<lb/> be led to prove that the said clothes were being worn by the<lb/> accused at the time when the crime was committed and said<lb/> fact cannot be proved through his disclosure statement.‖</note>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <note>DEATH SENTENCE REFERENCE NO.6/</note>

            <head>2013,<lb/> Page 119 of 340<lb/> CRL. APP. NOS.1398/2013, 1399/2013 AND 1414/2013</head>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <figDesc>Udai Bhan v. State of<lb/> CRL. </figDesc>
 
            <head>APP. NOS.1398/2013, 1399/2013 AND 1414/2013</head>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <note>DEATH SENTENCE REFERENCE NO.6/</note>

            <head>2013,<lb/> Page 128 of 340<lb/> CRL. APP. NOS.1398/2013, 1399/2013 AND 1414/2013</head>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <head>DEATH SENTENCE REFERENCE NO.6/2013,<lb/> Page 129 of 340<lb/> CRL. APP. NOS.1398/2013, 1399/2013 AND 1414/2013</head>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <head>DEATH SENTENCE REFERENCE NO.6/2013,<lb/> Page 130 of 340<lb/> CRL. APP. NOS.1398/2013, 1399/2013 AND 1414/2013<lb/> of </head>
 
            <figDesc>the defence witnesses who profess to have attended the musical<lb/> programme in which the Appellant Vinay Sharma claims he played<lb/> the &quot;tabla&quot;.<lb/> </figDesc>
<lb/> 
            <head>212. In Binay Kumar Singh Vs. State of Bihar (1997) 1 SCC 283,<lb/> the </head>
 
            <figDesc>Supreme Court described the plea of alibi as a rule of evidence<lb/> and lucidly discussed the law with regard to the said plea as under:-<lb/></figDesc>
<lb/>
            <table>(SCC, Page 293)<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>-22. </note>
 
            <figDesc>We must bear in mind that an alibi is not an exception<lb/> (special or general) envisaged in the Indian Penal Code or any<lb/> other law. It is only a rule of evidence recognised in Section 11<lb/> of the Evidence Act that facts which are inconsistent with the<lb/> fact in issue are relevant. Illustration (a) given under the<lb/> provision is worth reproducing in this context:</figDesc>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <table>379] ; State of Maharashtra v.<lb/> Narsingrao Gangaram Pimple [(1984) 1 SCC 446 : 1984 SCC<lb/> (Cri) 109 : AIR 1984 SC 63].‖<lb/> 213. </table>
 
            <figDesc>The Supreme Court in the case of Jitender </figDesc>
 
            <head>Kumar Vs. State of<lb/> Haryana, (</head>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <figDesc>) The voice of the speaker should be clearly audible and<lb/> not lost or distorted by other sounds or disturbances.‖<lb/> </figDesc>
<lb/> 
            <head>{See: Yusufalli Esmail Nagree Vs. State of Maharashtra,<lb/> (1967) 3 SCR 720; N.Sri Rama Reddy Vs. V.V. Giri, (1970) 2<lb/> SCC 340; R.M. Malkani Vs. State of Maharashtra, (1973) 1<lb/> SCC 471; 1973 SCC (Cri) 399; Ziyauddin Burhanuddin<lb/> Bukhari Vs. Brijmohan Ramdass Mehra, (1976) 2 SCC 17; R.<lb/> Vs. Maqsud Ali, (1965) 2 All ER 464; R. Vs. Robson, (1972) 2<lb/> All ER 699, relied on}<lb/> 217. In Ram Singh&quot;s case (supra), the </head>
 
            <figDesc>Supreme Court further<lb/> noted the American Jurisprudence on the subject as under:-<lb/></figDesc>
<lb/>
            <head>DEATH SENTENCE REFERENCE NO.6/2013,<lb/> Page 134 of 340<lb/> CRL. APP. NOS.1398/2013, 1399/2013 AND 1414/2013<lb/> </head>
<lb/> 
            <table>-35. In American Jurisprudence 2d (Vol. 29) the learned Author<lb/> on a conspectus of the authorities referred to in the foot-note in<lb/> regard to the admissibility of tape-recorded statements at p. 494<lb/> observes thus:<lb/> The cases are in general agreement as to what<lb/> constitutes a proper foundation for the admission of a<lb/> sound recording, and indicate a reasonably strict<lb/> adherence to the rules prescribed for testing the<lb/> admissibility of recordings, which have been outlined as<lb/> follows:<lb/> (1) a showing that the recording device was capable of<lb/> taking testimony;<lb/> (2) a showing that the operator of the device was<lb/> competent;<lb/> (3) establishment of the authenticity and correctness of<lb/> the recording;<lb/> (4) a showing that changes, additions, or deletions have<lb/> not been made;<lb/> (5) a showing of the manner of the preservation of the<lb/> recording;<lb/> (6) identification of the speakers; and<lb/> (7) a showing that the testimony elicited was voluntarily<lb/> made without any kind of inducement.<lb/> ... </table>
 
            <head>However, the recording may be rejected if it is so<lb/> inaudible and indistinct that the jury must speculate<lb/> as to what was said.‖<lb/> (emphasis supplied)<lb/> 218. In Tukaram S. Dighole Vs. Manikrao Shivaji Kokate, (2010)<lb/> 4 SCC 329</head>

            <note>, the Supreme Court discussed the admissibility of<lb/> electronic evidence/tape records referring to earlier decisions on the<lb/> subject as follows:-(SCC, Page 338)<lb/> <note>-24. In Yusufalli Esmail Nagree v. State of Maharashtra [AIR</note>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <table>3 SCR 720] this Court<lb/> observed that since the tape-records are prone to tampering,<lb/> the time, place and accuracy of the recording must be proved<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>by a competent witness. It is necessary that such evidence<lb/> must be received with caution. The court must be satisfied,<lb/> CRL. APP. NOS.1398/2013, 1399/2013 AND 1414/2013<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>beyond reasonable doubt that the record has not been<lb/> tampered with.<lb/> 25. In R. v. Maqsud Ali [(1966) 1 QB 688 : (1965) 3 WLR 229 :<lb/> (1965) 2 All ER 464 (CCA)] it was said (QB p. 701 D-E) that it<lb/> would be<lb/> -wrong to deny to the law of evidence advantages to be<lb/> gained by new techniques and new devices, provided the<lb/> accuracy of the recording can be proved and the voices<lb/> recorded [are] properly identified…. Such evidence should<lb/> always be regarded with some caution and assessed in<lb/> the light of all the circumstances of each case.‖<lb/> 26. In Ziyauddin Burhanuddin Bukhari [(1976) 2 SCC 17],<lb/> relying on R. v. Maqsud Ali [(1966) 1 QB 688 : (1965) 3 WLR<lb/> 229 : (1965) 2 All ER 464 (CCA)], a Bench of three Judges of<lb/> this Court held that the tape-records of speeches were<lb/> admissible in evidence on satisfying the following conditions:<lb/> (SCC p. 26, para 19)<lb/> -(a) The voice of the person alleged to be speaking<lb/> must be duly identified by the maker of the record or<lb/> by others who know it.<lb/> (b) Accuracy of what was actually recorded had to<lb/> be proved by the maker of the record and<lb/> satisfactory evidence, direct or circumstantial, had<lb/> to be there so as to rule out possibilities of<lb/> tampering with the record.<lb/> (c) The subject-matter recorded had to be shown to<lb/> be relevant according to rules of relevancy found in<lb/> the Evidence Act.‖<lb/> Similar conditions for admissibility of a tape-recorded statement<lb/> were reiterated inRam Singh v. Col. Ram Singh [1985 Supp<lb/> SCC 611] and recently in R.K. Anand v.Delhi High Court [(2009)<lb/> 8 SCC 106 : (2010) 2 SCC (Cri) 563] .<lb/> 27. </table>
 
            <figDesc>Tested on the touchstone of the tests and safeguards<lb/> enumerated above, we are of the opinion that in the instant<lb/> case the appellant has miserably failed to prove the authenticity<lb/> of the cassette as well as the accuracy of the speeches<lb/> purportedly made by the respondent. Admittedly, the appellant<lb/> did not lead any evidence to prove that the cassette produced<lb/> on record was a true reproduction of the original speeches by<lb/> the respondent or his agent. On a careful consideration of the<lb/> evidence and circumstances of the case, we are convinced that<lb/> the appellant has failed to prove his case that the respondent<lb/> was guilty of indulging in corrupt practices.‖<lb/> 219. We have taken care to note the aforesaid conditions laid<lb/> down by the Supreme Court for the reason that there is no<lb/> evidence on record suggestive of the fact that the conditions for<lb/> the admissibility of the video clip as laid down by the Hon&quot;ble<lb/> Supreme Court in the case of Ram Singh (supra) were proved by<lb/> the defence. This being so, the necessary corollary is that the<lb/> video clip must be held to be inadmissible in evidence. The<lb/> inadmissibility of this exhibit notwithstanding, we took pains to view<lb/> the video clip produced before us and found the same to be inaudible,<lb/> </figDesc>
<lb/> 
            <note>indistinct and visually unclear.<lb/> 220. Unfortunately, therefore, the plea of alibi taken by accused<lb/> Vinay Sharma in his statement under Section 313 Cr.P.C. and sought<lb/> to be corroborated by leading defence evidence cannot bear scrutiny.<lb/> As delineated above, the prosecution has proved the call detail<lb/> records Ex.PW-23/B of the mobile phone of accused Vinay Sharma,<lb/> having SIM No.8285947545, which was admittedly in the name of<lb/> his mother, Smt. </note>
 
            <figDesc>Champa Devi, but in the possession of accused<lb/> Vinay Sharma in the evening of 16.12.2012. Allegedly, this phone<lb/> was snatched by one Vipin at the music party and returned to Vinay<lb/> </figDesc>
<lb/> 
            <table>Sharma in the morning of 17.12.2012. The call detail records<lb/> (Ex.PW-23/B) show otherwise. As per the call detail records, the<lb/> accused had been making calls to one particular number viz.,<lb/> 8601274533 from 15.12.2012 till 20:19:37 A.M. on 17.12.2012. The<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>authenticity of the CDR is proved under Section 65-B of the Indian<lb/> CRL. APP. NOS.1398/2013, 1399/2013 AND 1414/2013<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <figDesc>Evidence Act, 1872. The question which arises is if the accused was<lb/> not having a SIM card in his phone No. 8285947545, then how could<lb/> he call from this SIM on 15.12.2012, then on 16.12.2012 and in the<lb/> morning of 17.12.2012 till about 8:23:42 PM.</figDesc>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <head>CRL. APP. NOS.1398/2013, 1399/2013 AND 1414/2013<lb/> </head>
<lb/> 
            <table>(xii)<lb/> It defies logic that when the dying declaration of the<lb/> prosecutrix had been recorded by the SDM on 21.12.2012,<lb/> where was the necessity to hurriedly record another dying<lb/> declaration on 25.12.2012.<lb/> (xiii)<lb/> The alleged third dying declaration recorded on 25.12.2012<lb/> ought to have been videographed.<lb/> (xiv)<lb/> There is nothing on record to suggest that the learned<lb/> Metropolitan Magistrate (PW-30) had directed the<lb/> Investigating Officer of the case, who had been called for<lb/> identification of the prosecutrix, to vacate the room and<lb/> close the door of the ICU.<lb/> (xv)<lb/> At the time of the recording of her statement Ex.PW-30/D-<lb/>1, which was recorded by PW-30 Shri Pawan Kumar on<lb/> 25.12.2012, the prosecutrix was unfit for statement both<lb/> physically and mentally. The condition of the prosecutrix<lb/> was extremely serious on 25.12.2012 as is evident from<lb/> document Ex.DW-64/DA wherein it is stated:-<lb/>&quot;Considering the further deterioration in the<lb/> patient&quot;s condition on 25 th December, 2012 night<lb/> due to cardiac arrest, which was promptly<lb/> resuscitated, a team of doctors, which included,<lb/> Dr. Sandeep Bansal, HOD, Cardiology and Dr. S.<lb/> Raghavan, HOD Neurology opined that patient be<lb/> shifted abroad for further management.&quot;<lb/> Further, the document Exhibit PW-30/B shows that at<lb/> 12:35 PM on the relevant day, i.e., 25.12.2012, Dr. P.K.<lb/> Verma opined that patient had endotracheal tube in place (that<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>DEATH SENTENCE REFERENCE NO.6/</note>

            <head>2013,<lb/> Page 143 of 340<lb/> CRL. APP. NOS.1398/2013, 1399/2013 AND 1414/2013<lb/> is</head>

            <figDesc>, in larynx and trachea) and was on ventilater and hence<lb/> could not speak. At 12:40 PM on the same day, there is an<lb/> endorsement made on the said document (Ex.PW-30/B) by<lb/> PW-28 Dr. Rajesh Rastogi to the effect that the patient is<lb/> </figDesc>
<lb/> 
            <table>conscious, cooperative, meaningfully communicative,<lb/> oriented, responding through non-verbal gestures, she is fit to<lb/> give statement.<lb/> Learned defence counsel vociferously<lb/> contended that it is inconceivable that the prosecutrix who<lb/> was on life support system at 12:35 P.M., within five minutes,<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>i.e., at 12:40 PM was opined to be conscious, cooperative and<lb/> fit to give statement. Such change in the medical condition<lb/> within a short span of five minutes only was to say the least<lb/> unprecedented in medical history. The question before the<lb/> Court is whether it is possible for a patient put on ventilation<lb/> to be conscious, oriented, meaningfully communicative<lb/> through verbal gestures, and how did PW-28 Dr. Rajesh<lb/> Rastogi put questions to the prosecutrix to know that she is fit<lb/> to answer through verbal gestures correctly? The fitness<lb/> given by PW-28 Dr. Rajesh Rastogi is, therefore, not worthy<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>of credence. Hence, the dying declaration recorded by PW-30<lb/> Sh. Pawan Kumar, learned Metropolitan Magistrate is of no<lb/> value and is inadmissible in evidence (Ex.PW-30/D-1).<lb/> (xvi)<lb/> None of the statements given by the prosecutrix can be<lb/> treated as dying declarations of the prosecutrix as she<lb/> expired on 29.12.2012 and before her death, no statement<lb/> CRL. APP. NOS.1398/2013, 1399/2013 AND 1414/2013<lb/> of the prosecutrix was recorded at Mount Elizabeth<lb/> Hospital, Singapore.<lb/> (xvii)<lb/> None of the statements given by the prosecutrix can be treated<lb/> as dying declarations since the prosecutrix was never<lb/> administered oath and hence her dying declarations are not<lb/> admissible in evidence. Even otherwise, the said statements/<lb/> dying declarations are not in the form prescribed by the Delhi<lb/> High Court Rules as set out in Chapter XIII, which envisage<lb/> recording of the dying declaration by the Judicial Magistrate<lb/> and that too such recording is required to be done at once.<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>(xviii)<lb/> In any event, the third dying declaration made by gestures<lb/> cannot be relied upon as a dying declaration by signs, gestures<lb/> or nods is to be recorded by an expert. In the instant case, the<lb/> dying declaration was recorded by the learned Metropolitan<lb/> Magistrate, who had no certificate of training to record such<lb/> type of declaration by gestures, signs or nods.<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>223. It is proposed to deal with the aforesaid contentions<lb/> pointwise:-<lb/>(i)<lb/> With regard to the contention of the defence that the first dying<lb/> declaration, viz., MLC Ex.PW-49/B does not bear the<lb/> signature of the prosecutrix and contains only her thumb<lb/> impression, it is apposite that PW-49 Dr. Rashmi Ahuja in her<lb/> cross-examination when questioned in this regard, gave a<lb/> cogent explanation for the same and we see no justifiable<lb/> ground to discard the said explanation, which appears to us to<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>DEATH SENTENCE REFERENCE NO.6/</note>

            <head>2013,<lb/> Page 145 of 340<lb/> CRL. APP. NOS.1398/2013, 1399/2013 AND 1414/2013</head>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <head>-On reaching the hospital I inquired from<lb/> ACP Vasant Vihar as to if the patient has<lb/> been fit for statement or not. He told me that<lb/> the patient has been declared fit for<lb/> statement.<lb/> After being satisfied, I recorded the<lb/> statement of prosecutrix. Same </head>
 
            <table>running into<lb/> 4 page in 2 sheets are Ex. PW-27/A which<lb/> bears my signature at points A. The<lb/> prosecutrix appended her signature on all the<lb/> pages in my presence and on the last page<lb/> she also wrote the date and time. I identify her<lb/> signature at points B on statement Ex. PW-<lb/>27/A.‖<lb/> In the course of her cross-examination, she further<lb/> stated as under:-<lb/></table>
<lb/>
            <note>-It is wrong to suggest that the prosecutrix was on<lb/> ventilator or was under extreme pain and she was<lb/> not able to speak at that time. It is wrong to suggest<lb/> that the </note>
 
            <figDesc>prosecutrix was not capable of breathing<lb/> properly. VOL: When she was speaking with me, it<lb/> can not be said that she was not able to breathe.<lb/> </figDesc>
<lb/> 
            <table>While talking she used to remove her oxygen mask<lb/> at times.<lb/> ………………………………………………………..<lb/> It is wrong to suggest that the prosecutrix was<lb/> incapable of giving long answers to my questions or<lb/> that I made additions in her answers at the instance<lb/> of police.<lb/> It is true that I had not stated in the start of my<lb/> proceedings Ex.PW27/A that I had put questions<lb/> regarding voluntariness or pressure upon the<lb/> prosecutrix, if any, but after recording the statement I<lb/> had put a note at the end wherein she had stated that<lb/> she is giving the statement without any pressure and<lb/> in complete senses. It is wrong to suggest that she<lb/> had not stated to me that she is giving her statement<lb/> without any pressure or in complete senses as<lb/> mentioned in ExPW27/A.<lb/> ………………………………………………………..<lb/> It is wrong to suggest that prosecutrix was in<lb/> severe pain, vomiting, coughing, having breathing<lb/> problem or was on ventilator at that time.<lb/> …………………………………………………………<lb/> The prosecutrix before signing had read her<lb/> statement Ex. PW-27/A herself. Even I read over the<lb/> said statement to her and then only she signed after<lb/> the bed was raised from her back portion.‖</table>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <note>-After recording the statement I had put a note at the<lb/> end wherein she had stated that she is giving the<lb/> statement without any pressure and in complete<lb/> senses. It is wrong to suggest that she had not stated<lb/> to me that she is giving her statement without any<lb/> pressure or in complete senses as mentioned in<lb/> ExPW27/A.‖<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>(ix)<lb/> As regards the contention of the defence that Ex.PW-27/A<lb/> was a worthless document as no such dying declaration<lb/> was recorded on 21.12.2012 and the so-called dying<lb/> declaration recorded by PW-27 was in fact recorded on the<lb/> previous day as evidenced from the overwriting of the date<lb/> on the said document, we see no reason to disbelieve the<lb/> statement made by PW-27 (the SDM) that the statement<lb/> was recorded on 21.12.2012 and that the overwriting on<lb/> the date was a human error. We reproduce hereunder the<lb/> relevant part of her cross-examination:-<lb/>-It is correct that in Ex.PW27/B there is an over writing on<lb/> the date under my signature. VOL: It was a human error.<lb/> The statement was recorded on 21-12-2012, so for all<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>purpose this date will be 21-12-2012.‖<lb/> CRL. APP. NOS.1398/2013, 1399/2013 AND 1414/2013</note>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <head>DEATH SENTENCE REFERENCE NO.6/2013,<lb/> Page 155 of 340<lb/> CRL. APP. NOS.1398/2013, 1399/2013 AND 1414/2013</head>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <head>66 IA 66 : AIR 1939 PC 47] Lord Atkin </head>
 
            <figDesc>held<lb/> that circumstances of the transaction which resulted in<lb/> the death of the declarant will be admissible if such<lb/> circumstances have some proximate relation to the<lb/> actual occurrence. The test laid down by Lord Atkin<lb/> has been quoted in the judgment of Fazal Ali, J. in<lb/> </figDesc>
<lb/> 
            <table>Sharad<lb/> Birdhichand<lb/> Sarda v. State<lb/> of<lb/> Maharashtra [(</table>

            <head>1984) 4 SCC 116 : 1984 SCC (Cri)</head>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <figDesc>Constitution Bench in the case of Laxman </figDesc>
 
            <head>v. State of<lb/> Maharashtra (Supra), which has been reiterated in Shudhakar<lb/> v. State of M.P. (2012) 7 SCC 569 and M. Sarvana v. State of<lb/> </head>
<lb/> 
            <table>Karnataka (2012) 7 SCC 636, it is clear that issues of oath and<lb/> cross-examination are dispensed with while recording a dying<lb/> declaration. It is specifically highlighted in Laxman v. State of<lb/> Maharashtra (Supra), that no oath is necessary and there is no<lb/> statutory format for the recording of a dying declaration by a<lb/> Magistrate or a doctor or a police officer. As regards a dying<lb/> declaration recorded by a Magistrate, be it noted that the Code<lb/> of Criminal Procedure does not require any format for such a<lb/> dying declaration and, in fact, there is no requirement of<lb/> compliance either under Section 164 Cr.P.C. or under the<lb/> Punjab Police Rules. Learned defence counsel have questioned<lb/> the complexity of the Punjab Police Rules and adherence<lb/> thereto. It is, however, well-settled that the Punjab Police<lb/> Rules are only a guide for police officers in the State and<lb/> nothing more. Reference in this context may be made with<lb/> advantage to the judgment of Supreme Court in Paramjit<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <head>Singh v. State of Punjab (2007) 13 SCC 530. </head>
 
            <figDesc>The relevant<lb/> extract of the said judgment is as under (SCC, Page 537):-<lb/></figDesc>
<lb/>
            <table>-18. The Punjab Police Rules do not in any manner<lb/> override the provisions of the Code of Criminal Procedure.<lb/> The said Rules are meant for the guidance of the police<lb/> officers in the State and supplement the provisions of the<lb/> Code of Criminal Procedure but do not supplant them. In<lb/> our considered opinion the truth and veracity of contents<lb/> of FIR cannot in all cases be tested with a reference to<lb/> the entries made in the police station daily diary which is<lb/> maintained under the Punjab Police Rules. This avoidable<lb/> controversy need not detain us any further since it is well<lb/> settled that even a defect, if any, found in investigation,<lb/> however serious has no direct bearing on the competence<lb/> or the procedure relating to the cognizance or the trial. A<lb/> defect or procedural irregularity, if any, in investigation<lb/> itself cannot vitiate and nullify the trial based on such<lb/> erroneous investigation.‖<lb/> (xviii) In the context of recording dying declaration by gestures, the<lb/> settled legal position is that a dying declaration by gestures can<lb/> be recorded and the same possesses evidentiary value. It was<lb/> so held in the case of </table>
 
            <head>Meesala Ramakrishan Vs. State of A.P.<lb/> (1994) 4 SCC 182. </head>
 
            <figDesc>In the said case, the Supreme Court<lb/> categorically held a dying declaration recorded by gestures to<lb/> be admissible. In paras 20 and 21, it was held as under: (SCC,<lb/> </figDesc>
<lb/> 
            <table>Page 188)<lb/> -20. On the basis of what has been noted above, we<lb/> hold that dying declaration recorded on the basis of<lb/> nods and gestures is not only admissible but<lb/> possesses evidentiary value, the extent of which shall<lb/> depend upon who recorded the statement, what is his<lb/> educational attainment, what gestures and nods were<lb/> made, what were the questions asked -whether they<lb/> were simple or complicated -and how effective or<lb/> understandable the nods and gestures were.<lb/> 21. In the present case, the questions being simple<lb/> and short, the recorder being a Magistrate, the certifier<lb/> of mental conscious state of the deceased being a<lb/> doctor, nods being effective and meaningful, we are<lb/> satisfied that full reliance could have been placed on<lb/> the statement of the deceased as recorded by PW 11<lb/> to find the appellant guilty under Section 302.‖<lb/> The dying declaration in question in the instant case<lb/> having been recorded by a Magistrate, the aforesaid law laid<lb/> down in Meesala </table>
 
            <head>Ramakrishan Vs. State of A.P. (Supra)<lb/> DEATH SENTENCE REFERENCE NO.6/2013,<lb/> Page 166 of 340<lb/> CRL. APP. NOS.1398/2013, 1399/2013 AND 1414/2013</head>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <head>DEATH SENTENCE REFERENCE NO.6/2013,<lb/> Page 168 of 340<lb/> CRL. APP. NOS.1398/2013, 1399/2013 AND 1414/2013</head>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <head>DEATH SENTENCE REFERENCE NO.6/2013,<lb/> Page 169 of 340<lb/> CRL. APP. NOS.1398/2013, 1399/2013 AND 1414/2013</head>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <head>DEATH SENTENCE REFERENCE NO.6/2013,<lb/> Page 170 of 340<lb/> CRL. APP. NOS.1398/2013, 1399/2013 AND 1414/2013</head>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <table>Srl.No. For Whom<lb/> Number of<lb/> PW<lb/> Name<lb/> Date<lb/> 2013<lb/> 1.<lb/> Mukesh<lb/> PW-50<lb/> Dr.Raj Kumar<lb/> Chejara<lb/> 22.4.13<lb/> 2.<lb/> Mukesh<lb/> PW-52<lb/> Dr.P.K.Verma 22.4.13<lb/> 3.<lb/> Mukesh<lb/> PW-54<lb/> SI<lb/> Sushil<lb/> Sawariya<lb/> 20.4.13<lb/> 4.<lb/> Mukesh<lb/> PW-56<lb/> Shri Sandeep<lb/> Dabral<lb/> 22.4.13<lb/> 5.<lb/> Mukesh<lb/> PW-58<lb/> SI Arvind<lb/> 20.4.13<lb/> 6.<lb/> Mukesh<lb/> PW-61<lb/> SI Jeet Singh 20.4.13<lb/> 7.<lb/> Mukesh<lb/> PW-64<lb/> Dr.B.D.Athani 23.4.13<lb/> 8.<lb/> Mukesh<lb/> PW-80<lb/> WSI Pratibha<lb/> Sharma, IO<lb/> 8.7.13<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>DEATH SENTENCE REFERENCE NO.6/</note>

            <head>2013,<lb/> Page 175 of 340<lb/> CRL. APP. NOS.1398/2013, 1399/2013 AND 1414/2013<lb/> </head>
<lb/> 
            <table>9.<lb/> Mukesh<lb/> PW-83<lb/> Angad Singh 14.8.13<lb/> 10.<lb/> Pawan Kumar Part<lb/> final<lb/> argument<lb/> 237. Referring to the decision of the Constitution Bench of the<lb/> Supreme Court in State of Madhya Pradesh v. Shobharam and<lb/> Others 1966 (Suppl) SCR 239, Mr. Sharma contended that the<lb/> Constitution Bench had clearly delineated the constitutional right<lb/> conferred by Article 22(1) on a person arrested to be defended by a<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>legal practitioner of his choice as well as one who, though not<lb/> arrested, runs the risk of loss of personal liberty as a result of a trial.<lb/> He submitted that the Appellant Mukesh had filed an affidavit before<lb/> the Sessions Court dated 3.4.2013 [filed in W.P.(Crl.) 516/13] to<lb/> contend that the Appellant was under torture compelled to put his<lb/> thumb impression on the vakalatnama in favour of Mr. V.K. Anand,<lb/> Advocate. Reference was also made by the counsel to five<lb/> vakalatnamas in his favour filed at pages 67, 68, 69, 70 and 71 of the<lb/> additional grounds of appeal. It was contended by him that he (M.L.<lb/> </note>
<lb/> 
            <table>Sharma) was the counsel of the choice of the Appellants, but the<lb/> Appellants had been deprived of his services in clear violation of the<lb/> constitutional mandate contained in Article 22(1) of the Constitution.<lb/> It was also sought to be contended that though he (M.L. Sharma) had<lb/> filed a transfer petition in the Supreme Court for transfer of the trial<lb/> from Delhi to another State, but when the transfer petition was listed<lb/> before the Hon&quot;ble Supreme Court on 23 rd January, 2013, Mr. V.K.<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>Anand, Advocate made a statement that he did not want to get the<lb/> <note>DEATH SENTENCE REFERENCE NO.6/</note>

            <head>2013,<lb/> Page 176 of 340<lb/> CRL. APP. NOS.1398/2013, 1399/2013 AND 1414/2013</head>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <head>CRL. APP. NOS.1398/2013, 1399/2013 AND 1414/2013<lb/> </head>
<lb/> 
            <table>-470. In para 6 of the judgment, this Court further said: [Khatri<lb/> (2) case [(1981) 1 SCC 627 : 1981 SCC (Cri) 228], SCC p. 632,<lb/> para 6]<lb/> -6. But even this right to free legal services would be<lb/> illusory for an indigent accused unless the Magistrate or<lb/> the Sessions Judge before whom he is produced informs<lb/> him of such right. … The Magistrate or the Sessions<lb/> Judge before whom the accused appears must be held to<lb/> be under an obligation to inform the accused that if he is<lb/> unable to engage the services of a lawyer on account of<lb/> poverty or indigence, he is entitled to obtain free legal<lb/> services at the cost of the State. … We would, therefore,<lb/> direct the Magistrates and Sessions Judges in the country<lb/> to inform every accused who appears before them and<lb/> who is not represented by a lawyer on account of his<lb/> poverty or indigence that he is entitled to free legal<lb/> services at the cost of the State. Unless he is not willing to<lb/> take advantage of the free legal services provided by the<lb/> State, he must be provided legal representation at the<lb/> cost of the State.‖<lb/> (emphasis added)<lb/> 471. x<lb/> x<lb/> x<lb/> x<lb/> x<lb/> x<lb/> x<lb/> 472. As noted in Khatri (2) [(1981) 1 SCC 627 : 1981 SCC<lb/> (Cri) 228] as far back as in 1981, a person arrested needs a<lb/> lawyer at the stage of his first production before the Magistrate,<lb/> to resist remand to police or jail custody and to apply for bail.<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>He would need a lawyer when the charge-sheet is submitted<lb/> and the Magistrate applies his mind to the charge-sheet with a<lb/> view to determine the future course of proceedings. He would<lb/> need a lawyer at the stage of framing of charges against him<lb/> and he would, of course, need a lawyer to defend him in trial.‖<lb/> 240. It was next contended by Mr. M.L. Sharma on behalf of the</note>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <head>DEATH SENTENCE REFERENCE NO.6/2013,<lb/> Page 190 of 340<lb/> CRL. APP. NOS.1398/2013, 1399/2013 AND 1414/2013<lb/> </head>
<lb/> 
            <table>Hon&apos;ble High Court of Delhi. He has been requested<lb/> to appear at 2 PM.<lb/> Sd/-<lb/>(Yogesh Khanna)<lb/> ASJ(Special Fast Track Court),<lb/> Saket Courts, New Delhi<lb/> 18-04-2013<lb/> Matter called at 2 PM.<lb/> PW 59 Inspector Raj Kumari and PW65 Ct. Kripal<lb/> are present for their cross examination on behalf of<lb/> accused Mukesh but neither Shri M.L Sharma, Ld.<lb/> Counsel for accused Mukesh nor his associate is present.</table>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <head>DEATH SENTENCE REFERENCE NO.6/2013,<lb/> Page 192 of 340<lb/> CRL. APP. NOS.1398/2013, 1399/2013 AND 1414/2013<lb/> appropriate to appoint an Amicus Curiae to assist the<lb/> court in future, in case such situation arises.<lb/> </head>
<lb/> 
            <table>Hence, I deem it fit to appoint Shri Rajeev Jain,<lb/> Advocate, Saket Court Complex, New Delhi, as an<lb/> Amicus Curiae to assist the court in future. He has<lb/> appeared today. The copy of the charge sheet and all<lb/> connected documents, including the evidence so<lb/> recorded till date, be handed over to Ld. Amicus Curiae to<lb/> assist<lb/> the<lb/> court,<lb/> during<lb/> the<lb/> course<lb/> of<lb/> trial……………………………………….</table>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <head>DEATH SENTENCE REFERENCE NO.6/2013,<lb/> Page 202 of 340<lb/> CRL. APP. NOS.1398/2013, 1399/2013 AND 1414/2013</head>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <figDesc>6 Scale 242].</figDesc>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <head>DEATH SENTENCE REFERENCE NO.6/2013,<lb/> Page 214 of 340<lb/> CRL. APP. NOS.1398/2013, 1399/2013 AND 1414/2013</head>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <table>-Lohey ki rod se mujhe mere paet par maara aur poore<lb/> shareer par danto se kata. Is se pehle mere dost ka<lb/> saman -mobile phone, purse, credit card, debit card,<lb/> ghadi aadi cheen liye. But total chhey (6) log the jinhoney<lb/> bari-bari se oral (oral) vaginal (through vagina) aur<lb/> pichhey se (anal) balatkar kiya. In logo ne lohe ki rod ko<lb/> mere sharer ke andar vaginal guptang aur guda (pichhey<lb/> se) (through rectum) dala aur phir bahar bhi nikala. Aur<lb/> mere guptango haath aur lohe ki rod dal kar mere shareer<lb/> ke andruni hisson ko bahar nikala aur chot pahunchayi.<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>Chhey logo ne bari-bari se mere saath kareeb ek ghante<lb/> CRL. APP. NOS.</note>

            <head>1398/2013, 1399/2013 AND 1414/2013<lb/> tak </head>
 
            <figDesc>balatkar kiya. Chalti huyi bus mein he driver badalta<lb/> raha taaki woh bhi balatkar kar sake.‖</figDesc>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <head>DEATH SENTENCE REFERENCE NO.6/2013,<lb/> Page 222 of 340<lb/> CRL. APP. NOS.1398/2013, 1399/2013 AND 1414/2013</head>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <head>DEATH SENTENCE REFERENCE NO.6/2013,<lb/> Page 224 of 340<lb/> CRL. APP. NOS.1398/2013, 1399/2013 AND 1414/2013</head>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <table>364] , Uka Ram v.<lb/> State of Rajasthan [(2001) 5 SCC 254 : 2001 SCC (Cri) 847]<lb/> , Babulal v. State of M.P. [(2003) 12 SCC 490 : 2005 SCC<lb/> (Cri) 620] , Muthu Kutty v. State [(2005) 9 SCC 113 : 2005<lb/> SCC (Cri) 1202] , State of Rajasthan v. Wakteng [(2007) 14<lb/> SCC 550 : (2009) 3 SCC (Cri) 217] and Sharda v. State of<lb/> Rajasthan [(2010) 2 SCC 85 : (2010) 2 SCC (Cri) 980] .)<lb/> 23</table>

            <head>. </head>
 
            <figDesc>The second dying declaration was recorded by Shri<lb/> Damodar Prasad Mahure, Assistant Sub-Inspector of Police<lb/> CRL. </figDesc>
 
            <head>APP. NOS.1398/2013, 1399/2013 AND 1414/2013</head>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <head>CRL. APP. NOS.1398/2013, 1399/2013 AND 1414/2013<lb/> examination </head>
 
            <figDesc>in Court clearly stated that on that day, that is, on<lb/> 18.12.2012 he had gone to Thyagraj Stadium with the<lb/> </figDesc>
<lb/> 
            <table>Investigating Officer at 5.00 P.M. and thereafter to Safdarjung<lb/> Hopsital. He </table>
 
            <head>further clarified that he actually went to Thyagraj<lb/> Stadium twice. Once before going to the hospital and then from<lb/> S.J. Hospital. In cross-examination, he stated that they left<lb/> Thyagraj Stadium at about 8:30 PM and returned to S.J.<lb/> </head>
<lb/> 
            <table>Hospital where they stayed for about 30/45 minutes before returning<lb/> to the poice station at about 10.00 P.M.<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>296. In the context of non-mention of the names of the<lb/> Appellants in the First Information Report, Mr. M.L. Sharma<lb/> contended that this circumstance by itself was fatal to the case of<lb/> the prosecution. He relied upon the following decisions:-<lb/>(i)<lb/> Mitter Sen and Others vs. State of U.P., AIR 1976 SC 1156<lb/> (ii) Devinder vs. State of Haryana, 1997 SCC (Crl.) 570<lb/> (iii) State vs. </note>
 
            <head>Ramesh, 1998 Criminal Law Journal 4233<lb/> (iv) Rehmat vs. State of Haryana, 1997 Criminal Law Journal<lb/> 764 = AIR 1997 SC 1526<lb/> (v) Jagir Singh v. State of Delhi, 1975 SCC (Cri.) 129<lb/> (vi) Husna vs. State of Punjab, (1996) 7 SCC 382<lb/> 297. </head>
 
            <figDesc>Suffice it to note that in the first five cases, the parties were<lb/> known to each other. These cases, therefore, are of no assistance<lb/> to the defence. In the last case, the Supreme Court came to the<lb/> conclusion that the prosecution was not able to satisfactorily<lb/> establish the case against the Appellant Rupa beyond reasonable<lb/> doubt as his presence at the time of occurrence was not<lb/> CRL. </figDesc>
 
            <head>APP. NOS.1398/2013, 1399/2013 AND 1414/2013<lb/> satisfactorily </head>
 
            <figDesc>proved. The Court, however, came to the conclusion<lb/> that the evidence on the record had brought home the charge<lb/> against Appellant Husna beyond every reasonable doubt and his<lb/> conviction and sentence for the various offences as recorded by<lb/> the trial court called for no interference.<lb/> 298. Relying upon the decision of the Supreme Court in Sunil<lb/> </figDesc>
<lb/> 
            <head>Kumar Sambhudayal Gupta vs. State of Maharashtra, (2010) 13<lb/> SCC 657, </head>
 
            <figDesc>Mr. Sharma further contended that where the complainant<lb/> in the FIR or the witness in his statement under Section 161 Cr.P.C.<lb/> has not disclosed certain facts but meets the prosecution case first<lb/> time before the Court, such version lacks credence and is liable to be<lb/> discarded. Reference was made by him in this context to paragraph<lb/> 33 of the said judgment. We are constrained to state that the said<lb/> paragraph cannot be read in isolation with the rest of the judgment for<lb/> in the succeeding paragraphs, i.e., paragraphs 34 to 37, the Court has<lb/> held that marginal variations in the statements cannot be dubbed as<lb/> improvements as the same may be elaborations of the statement made<lb/> by the witness earlier. It further held that the omissions which<lb/> amount to contradictions in material particulars, i.e., go to the root of<lb/> the case/materially affect the trial or core of the prosecution case,<lb/> render the testimony of the witness liable to be discarded. No such<lb/> contradictions or improvements have been poined out to us in the<lb/> instant case and this judgment, therefore, has no application to the<lb/> facts of the present case.<lb/> 299. Mr. Sharma further contended that if two views are possible<lb/> on the evidence adduced in the case, the view which is favourable<lb/> CRL. </figDesc>
 
            <head>APP. NOS.1398/2013, 1399/2013 AND 1414/2013</head>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <head>DEATH SENTENCE REFERENCE NO.6/2013,<lb/> Page 251 of 340<lb/> CRL. APP. NOS.1398/2013, 1399/2013 AND 1414/2013</head>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <head>DEATH SENTENCE REFERENCE NO.6/2013,<lb/> Page 268 of 340<lb/> CRL. APP. NOS.1398/2013, 1399/2013 AND 1414/2013</head>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <head>DEATH SENTENCE REFERENCE NO.6/2013,<lb/> Page 274 of 340<lb/> CRL. APP. NOS.1398/2013, 1399/2013 AND 1414/2013<lb/> case </head>
 
            <figDesc>FIR No.414/2013, P.S. Vasant Vihar, clearly described the<lb/> incident which took place with the same accused persons being the<lb/> key players and in which he was the unfortunate victim. He testified<lb/> that on 16.12.2012, he finished his work at Munirka at 8.30 PM and<lb/> was proceeding towards Sangam Vihar. He boarded the bus from</figDesc>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <head>DEATH SENTENCE REFERENCE NO.6/2013,<lb/> Page 277 of 340<lb/> CRL. APP. NOS.1398/2013, 1399/2013 AND 1414/2013</head>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <head>DEATH SENTENCE REFERENCE NO.6/2013,<lb/> Page 279 of 340<lb/> CRL. APP. NOS.1398/2013, 1399/2013 AND 1414/2013</head>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <table>-I do regard death sentence as contrary to ahinsa. Only he<lb/> takes life who gives it. All punishment is repugnant to<lb/> ahinsa. Under a State governed according to the principles<lb/> of ahinsa, therefore, a murderer would be sent to a<lb/> penitentiary and then given every chance of reforming<lb/> himself. All crime is a kind of disease and should be<lb/> treated as such.‖<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <head>CRL. APP. NOS.1398/2013, 1399/2013 AND 1414/2013<lb/> 352. </head>
 
            <figDesc>The learned Special Public Prosecutor, on the other hand,<lb/> highlighted the fact that the repeated incidents of gang rape in<lb/> Delhi and Mumbai had led to the widespread feeling that women<lb/> in the two metropolitans were unsafe. </figDesc>
 
            <head>By giving the maximum<lb/> sentence the message to the society would be that deviant<lb/> behavior of an extreme kind will not be tolerated. </head>
 
            <figDesc>By not handing<lb/> out the maximum sentence, the message would be loud and clear that<lb/> criminals can get away with incidents like this.<lb/> </figDesc>
<lb/> 
            <table>353. The learned Special Public Prosecutor emphasized that the<lb/> Hon&quot;ble Supreme Court has repeatedly held that where there is<lb/> grotesque, diabolical and barbaric behavior, death sentence must be<lb/> awarded. In this case, the prosecution has proved not just the<lb/> existence of extreme brutality, but grotesque, diabolical and barbaric<lb/> behavior on the part of the accused. The offence of gang rape in the<lb/> instant case has been compounded with murder and Courts have<lb/> repeatedly awarded the death sentence in cases of brutal rape and<lb/> murder. Also, where depravity and extreme brutality shock the<lb/> collective conscience of the society, death sentence has been held to<lb/> be warranted. Young age of the accused is not a determinative factor<lb/> against awarding of the death sentence nor can the socio-economic<lb/> status of the accused be considered a mitigating factor in sentencing<lb/> in a case of gang rape coupled with murder. Learned Special Public</table>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <head>DEATH SENTENCE REFERENCE NO.6/2013,<lb/> Page 291 of 340<lb/> CRL. APP. NOS.1398/2013, 1399/2013 AND 1414/2013</head>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <figDesc>Public Prosecutor contended at the outset<lb/> that Courts have repeatedly awarded stringent punishment in cases of<lb/> gang rape. In a recent judgment in Shimbhu </figDesc>
 
            <head>vs. State of Haryana,<lb/> CRL. APP. NOS.1398/2013, 1399/2013 AND 1414/2013<lb/> 363. </head>
 
            <figDesc>It may be noted that in the aforesaid case, the Supreme<lb/> Court affirmed its earlier decisions rendered in State </figDesc>
 
            <head>of M.P. vs.<lb/> Bala @ Balaram, (2005) 8 SCC 1 and State of Karnataka vs.</head>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <head>DEATH SENTENCE REFERENCE NO.6/2013,<lb/> Page 298 of 340<lb/> CRL. APP. NOS.1398/2013, 1399/2013 AND 1414/2013<lb/> 365. </head>
 
            <figDesc>Reliance was placed by learned Special Public Prosecutor, in<lb/> this context, upon the judgment in the case of B.</figDesc>

            <head>A. Umesh vs.<lb/> Registrar General, High Court of Karnataka, (2011) 3 SCC 85</head>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <head>CRL. APP. NOS.1398/2013, 1399/2013 AND 1414/2013<lb/> 369. </head>
 
            <figDesc>Further discussing the appropriateness of death sentencing, the<lb/> Supreme Court relied upon and quoted the following extract from its<lb/> judgment in Union </figDesc>
 
            <head>of India vs. Devendra Nath Rai, (2006) 2 SCC<lb/> </head>
<lb/> 
            <table>243:-(SCC, pp.247-49)<lb/> -23. Lord Justice Denning, Master of the Rolls of the Court of<lb/> Appeal in England said to the Royal Commission on Capital<lb/> Punishment in 1950:<lb/> ‗Punishment is the way in which society expresses<lb/> its denunciation of wrongdoing; and, in order to<lb/> maintain respect for the law, it is essential that the<lb/> punishment inflicted for grave crimes should<lb/> adequately reflect the revulsion felt by the great<lb/> majority of citizens for them. It is a mistake to<lb/> consider the objects of punishments as being a<lb/> deterrent or reformative or preventive and nothing<lb/> else. … The truth is that </table>
 
            <head>some crimes are so<lb/> outrageous that society insists on adequate<lb/> punishment, because the wrongdoer deserves<lb/> it, irrespective of whether it is a deterrent or<lb/> not.&apos;<lb/> </head>
<lb/> 
            <table>In J.J. Rousseau&apos;s The Social Contract written in 1762, he says<lb/> the following:</table>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <head>DEATH SENTENCE REFERENCE NO.6/2013,<lb/> Page 309 of 340<lb/> CRL. APP. NOS.1398/2013, 1399/2013 AND 1414/2013</head>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <head>CRL. APP. NOS.1398/2013, 1399/2013 AND 1414/2013<lb/> </head>
<lb/> 
            <table>x<lb/> x<lb/> x<lb/> x<lb/> x<lb/> 60. </table>
 
            <figDesc>This Court has consistently held that only in those<lb/> exceptional cases where the crime is so brutal, diabolical and<lb/> revolting so as to shock the collective conscience of the<lb/> community, would it be appropriate to award death sentence.<lb/> Since such circumstances cannot be laid down as a straitjacket<lb/> formula but must be ascertained from case to case, the<lb/> legislature has left it open for the courts to examine the facts of<lb/> the case and appropriately decide upon the sentence<lb/> proportional to the gravity of the offence.‖<lb/> 391. Learned Special Public Prosecutor next contended that the<lb/> existence of death penalty on the statute book and its constitutionality<lb/> having been upheld by the Apex Court, courts are duty bound to<lb/> award it in befitting cases. Reference in this context was made by<lb/> him to the Constitution-Bench in Bachan </figDesc>
 
            <head>Singh v. State of Punjab<lb/> (supra), Ajit Singh Harnamsingh Gujral v. State of Maharashtra<lb/> (supra) and </head>
 
            <figDesc>to the more recent decision of the Supreme Court in<lb/> </figDesc>
<lb/> 
            <head>Mohammed Ajmal Mohammed Amir Kasab @ Abu Mujahid v.<lb/> State of Maharashtra (2012) 9 SCC 1.<lb/> 392</head>

            <note>. In its judgment in Bachan Singh (supra), the Hon&quot;ble Supreme<lb/> Court held as under:<lb/> <note>-132. </note>
 
            <figDesc>To sum up, the question whether or not death penalty<lb/> serves any penological purpose is a difficult, complex and<lb/> intractable issue. It has evoked strong, divergent views. For the<lb/> purpose of testing the constitutionality of the impugned<lb/> provision as to death penalty in Section 302 of the Penal Code<lb/> on the ground of reasonableness in the light of Articles 19 and<lb/> 21 of the Constitution, it is not necessary for us to express any<lb/> categorical opinion, one way or the other, as to which of these<lb/> two antithetical views, held by the Abolitionists and<lb/> Retentionists, is correct. It is sufficient to say that the very fact<lb/> that persons of reason, learning and light are rationally and<lb/> deeply divided in their opinion on this issue, is a ground among<lb/> others, for rejecting the petitioners argument that retention of<lb/> death penalty in the impugned provision, is totally devoid of<lb/> reason and purpose. If</figDesc>

            <head>, notwithstanding the view of the<lb/> Abolitionists to the contrary, a very large segment of<lb/> people, the world over, including sociologists, legislators,<lb/> CRL. APP. NOS.1398/2013, 1399/2013 AND 1414/2013</head>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <head>DEATH SENTENCE REFERENCE NO.6/2013,<lb/> Page 332 of 340<lb/> CRL. APP. NOS.1398/2013, 1399/2013 AND 1414/2013</head>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <head>DEATH SENTENCE REFERENCE NO.6/2013,<lb/> Page 338 of 340<lb/> CRL. APP. NOS.1398/2013, 1399/2013 AND 1414/2013</head>
		</figure>



    </text>
</tei>

