<tei>
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc xml:id="_902972.pdf"/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">


		<figure type="table">

            <table>RUDs have not been supplied to the Detenus at all, despite the specific<lb/> demand made by them vide Representation dated 21.12.2021<lb/> (Annexure P-26) which inter alia include:-<lb/>&quot;i.<lb/> Search authorisation issued by Deputy Director, DRI, DZU,<lb/> vide DIN No. 202110DDZ4000000C568 dated 18.10.2021;<lb/> ii.<lb/> Order for extension of Judicial Remand of Zakir Khan and<lb/> Sanjeev Kumar for further 14 days till 02.12.2021;<lb/> iii.<lb/> Documents/loose papers found at the Petitioner&quot;s residence<lb/> and mentioned in Panchnama dated 18.10.2021;<lb/> iv.<lb/> Documents/loose papers found at Sanjeev Kumar&quot;s residence<lb/> and mentioned in Panchnama dated 18.10.2021;<lb/> v.<lb/> Grounds of arrest mentioned in Arrest Memo dated<lb/> 19.10.2021;<lb/> vi.<lb/> E-mails downloaded at the office of Custom Broker M/s Sai<lb/> Dutta Clearing Agency Pvt. Limited, situated at Mumbai, and<lb/> mentioned in the Panchnama dated 18.10.2021;<lb/> vii.<lb/> Documents pertaining to M/s Vijay Overseas, M/s Meena<lb/> Prints and M/s Z.K. Overseas which have been seized and<lb/> mentioned in panchnama dated 18.10.2021 drawn at the office<lb/> of Custom Broker M/s Sai Dutta Clearing Agency Pvt.<lb/> Limited;<lb/> viii.<lb/> Pages seized and mentioned in Panchnama dated 22.10.2021<lb/> drawn at the office of M/s Jyoti Enterprises Custom Broker<lb/> situated at Kolkata;<lb/> ix.<lb/> Application for extension of Judicial Remand and the<lb/> subsequent order extending Judicial Remand till 04.11.2021;<lb/> x.<lb/> Application for extension of Judicial Remand and the<lb/> subsequent order extending Judicial Remand till 18.11.2021;<lb/> xi.<lb/> Application for extension of Judicial Remand and the<lb/> subsequent order extending Judicial Remand till 02.12.2021;<lb/> xii.<lb/> RUDs to the 3 Show Cause Notices (at serial number 37, 38 &amp;<lb/> 40 of the list of RUDs respectively);<lb/> xiii.<lb/> Final proceedings in the aforementioned SCNs Notices (at<lb/> serial number 37, 38 &amp; 40 of the list of RUDs respectively) or<lb/> the final orders passed thereof in adjudication or appeal;<lb/> xiv.<lb/> Application has been moved by the Petitioner and Sanjeev<lb/> Kumar informing the Court that they do not want to move any<lb/> bail application;<lb/> xv.<lb/> Preliminary investigation report enclosed in letter dated<lb/> 18.10.2021 received from DRI HQ;<lb/> xvi.<lb/> Statement of Sh. Ravichandra Mishra registered by Income<lb/> Tax department referred to in the Detention Order;<lb/> xvii. Signed pages of Sh. Javed Khan&quot;s statement dated<lb/> 22.10.2021;<lb/> xviii. Summons issued to persons who have allegedly not joined<lb/> investigation (mentioned in Ground [xxvi] of the impugned<lb/> detention order)&quot;<lb/> At this stage it is observed that in the RUDs, that were supplied, the<lb/> following documents were found to be completely illegible: -<lb/>Sr. No.<lb/> of list of<lb/> RUDs<lb/> Description<lb/> Page No.<lb/> 3.<lb/> Statement of Zakir before I/Tax Deptt<lb/> 61 to 68, 75 to 89, 93 to<lb/> 100 &amp; 105 to 110<lb/> 3.<lb/> Statement of Priyanka Razdan before<lb/> I/Tax Deptt<lb/> 135, 137 to 139, 141 to<lb/> 150, 155, 156, 166,<lb/> 167, 170 to 172<lb/> 9.<lb/> Statement of Sanjeev Kumar u/s 108<lb/> Customs Act<lb/> 217, 220 &amp; 223<lb/> 15.<lb/> Panchnama dated 18.10.2021 drawn at<lb/> the office of Custom Broker M/s Sai<lb/> Dutta Clearing Agency Pvt. Ltd<lb/> 244 &amp; 245<lb/> 18.<lb/> Letter dated 19.10.2021 from I/Tax<lb/> pertaining to forensic image of PR<lb/> iphone and Zakir Khan iphone.<lb/> 248<lb/> 19.<lb/> Panchnama dated 21.10.2021 in<lb/> respect of goods stuffed in Container<lb/> consigned in the name of M/s R.K.<lb/> Overseas imported at Kolkata.<lb/> 251 &amp; 252<lb/> 24.<lb/> Panchnama dated 22.10.2021 at the<lb/> office premises of Custom Broker M/s<lb/> Jyoti Enterprises<lb/> 270<lb/> 25.<lb/> Statement under 108 of the Customs<lb/> Act dated 22.10.2021 -Ravichandra<lb/> Mishra, Custom Broker.<lb/> 275<lb/> 26.<lb/> Statement under 108 of the Customs<lb/> Act dated 22.10.2021 -Javed Khan<lb/> 280<lb/> 30.<lb/> Panchnama dated 02.11.2021 in<lb/> respect of goods contained in<lb/> Container<lb/> 293 to 295<lb/> 66.<lb/> Excerpt of extraction report wrt to<lb/> mobile phone of Zakir Khan …….<lb/> 574, 575, 590, 593,<lb/> 596, 599, 605 &amp; 608<lb/> 67.<lb/> Excerpt of extraction report retrieved<lb/> forensically wrt. to mobile phone of<lb/> Zakir Khan ……..<lb/> 612, 635, 649, 653,<lb/> 747, 748, 757 to 759,<lb/> 766 to 768, 936 &amp; 937<lb/> It is further averred that, even if for the sake of argument, it is<lb/> assumed that the said documents were placed before the Detaining<lb/> Authority, the non-consideration thereof in its entirety and not making<lb/> them a part of RUDs, has vitiated the detention order. It is urged that,<lb/> either the Sponsoring Authority has withheld the material and vital<lb/> documents from the gaze of scrutiny of the Detaining Authority or in<lb/> any event, these vital materials have been ignored by the Detaining<lb/> Authority, which is a clear non-application of mind. It is trite to state<lb/> that, if a vital piece of evidence which is likely to influence the<lb/> subjective satisfaction of the Detaining Authority is not placed before<lb/> it, then the detention order would be vitiated in law and fact on the<lb/> ground of suffering from the vice of non-application of mind. In<lb/> support of this argument, the learned Senior Counsel placed reliance<lb/> on the following decisions of the Hon&quot;ble Supreme Court: -<lb/>&quot;(i)<lb/> Taramati Chandulal Sejpal v. State of<lb/> Maharashtra; (1981) 2 SCC 17;<lb/> (ii)<lb/> Icchudevi Choraria v. Union of India, (1980) 4<lb/> SCC 531;<lb/> (iii)<lb/> Kamla Kanyalal Khushalani v. State of<lb/> Maharashtra, (1981) 1 SCC 748;<lb/> (iv)<lb/> Shalini Soni v. Union of India, (1980) 4 SCC 544;<lb/> (v)<lb/> Ibrahim Ahamad Batti v. State of Gujarat, (1982)<lb/> 3 SCC 440;<lb/> (vi)<lb/> Ahmed Nasar v. State of Tamil Nadu, (1999) 8<lb/> SCC 473;<lb/> (vii)<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <head>Kamlesh Kumar Ishwardas Patel v. Union of<lb/> India</head>

            <note>, (1995) 4 SCC 51;<lb/> (viii)<lb/> State of Rajasthan v. Talib Khan, (1996) 11 SCC<lb/> 393; and<lb/> (ix)<lb/> Chandra Prakash v. State of U.P., (2002) 4 SCC<lb/> 234.&quot;</note>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <note>&quot;….you i.e., Zakir Khan has shown a general habit and<lb/> propensity to indulge in fraudulent activities by way of<lb/> smuggling goods, abetting the smuggling of goods, and<lb/> engaging in transporting or concealing or keeping smuggled<lb/> goods at the cost of government revenue and national<lb/> security……&quot;</note>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <note>i.<lb/> Rajesh Vashdev Adnani v. State of Maharashtra<lb/> reported as (2005) 8 SCC 390.<lb/> ii.<lb/> Rakesh Sherpal Singh Rana v. State of Maharashtra,<lb/> reported as 2000 SCC OnLine Bom 684.<lb/> iii.<lb/> Narendra Bahadur Lama v. Union of India, reported as<lb/> 2001 SCC OnLine Del 521.<lb/> iv.<lb/> Dimple Prakash Shah vs. UOI-reported as 2010 SCC<lb/> Online Del 1605.<lb/> v.<lb/> Anwar Abdulla v. UOI, reported as 1991 SCC Online Kar<lb/> 470.<lb/> vi.<lb/> Mohinder Singh Gill v. Chief Election Commr., reported<lb/> as (1978) 1 SCC 405.<lb/> vii.<lb/> Gautam Jain v. Union of India, reported as (2017) 3 SCC<lb/> 133.<lb/> viii.<lb/> Mohd. </note>
 
            <head>Nashruddin v. Union of India, reported </head>
 
            <table>as 2021<lb/> SCC OnLine Del 4017.<lb/> ix.<lb/> Manjit Singh Grewal v. UOI, reported as 1990 (Supp)<lb/> SCC 59.<lb/> x.<lb/> Dharmista Bhagat v. State, reported as 1989 Supp (2)<lb/> SCC 155.<lb/> xi.<lb/> Bhupinder Singh v. UOI, reported as (1987) 2 SCC 234.<lb/> xii.<lb/> A. Geetha vs. State of T.N., reported as (2006) 7 SCC<lb/> 603.</table>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <table>i.<lb/> Naresh Kumar Goyal v. Union of India and<lb/> Others, reported as (2005) 8 SCC 276<lb/> ii.<lb/> State of Maharashtra and others v. Bhaurao<lb/> Punjabrao Gawande, reported as (2008) 3 SCC 613<lb/> iii.<lb/> Haradhan Saha versus State of West Bengal and<lb/> Others, reported as (1975) 3 SCC 198<lb/> iv.<lb/> Romesh Chandra Mehta vs State of West Bengal,<lb/> before the Hon&quot;ble Supreme Court in Criminal<lb/> Appeal No. 27 of 1967<lb/> v.<lb/> Kamarunnissa Etc. vs Union of India and Ors,<lb/> reported as 1991 AIR SC 1640<lb/> vi.<lb/> Gautam Jain v. Union of India, reported as (2017) 3<lb/> SCC 133.</table>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <figDesc>2 are reproduced below: -<lb/></figDesc>
<lb/>
            <table>&quot;xxxvi.<lb/> Zakir Khan filed an application dated 28.10.2021<lb/> before the Ld. CMM, Patiala House, New Delhi stating<lb/> that the statements dated 18/19.10.2021 before the DRI<lb/> officers have been obtained under coercion and torture<lb/> and he was forced to write a statement which is totally<lb/> false. He accordingly prayed the Ld. CMM, Patiala<lb/> House, New Delhi that he may be permitted to retract<lb/> his statement dated 18/19.10.2021 and same may be<lb/> treated as false and inadmissible. The DRI filed a<lb/> rebuttal dated 24.11.2021 before the Ld. CMM, Patiala<lb/> House, New Delhi stating inter alia that retraction<lb/> application contained untrue averments and are without<lb/> any substance, afterthought, and farce. In reply, DRI<lb/> stated that the applicant tendered his voluntary<lb/> statement under his signature and the said statement<lb/> has also been confirmed in his handwriting towards the<lb/> end. Further, the retraction has been made 10 days of<lb/> the statement; the long gap between the recording of<lb/> the statement and the retraction application makes it<lb/> clear that the retraction application filed by him is an<lb/> afterthought and based on legal tutoring. It was further<lb/> stated by DRI that the applicant was medically<lb/> examined at Ram Manohar Lohia Hospital Delhi and<lb/> thereafter produced before the Ld. Duty Magistrate. As<lb/> per the reply of the DRI filed before the Ld. CMM<lb/> Patiala House, New Delhi no injury marks (fresh or<lb/> otherwise) or bruises was reported by the duty doctors<lb/> during the medical examination.<lb/> </table>
<lb/> 
            <note>xxxvii.<lb/> You i.e. Sanjeev Kumar Yadav filed an application<lb/> dated 28.10.2021 before the Ld. CMM, Patiala House,<lb/> New Delhi stating that the statements dated<lb/> 18/19.10.2021 before the DRI officers have been<lb/> obtained under </note>
 
            <figDesc>coercion and torture. You accordingly<lb/> prayed the Hon&quot;ble Court that your statement dated<lb/> 18/19.10.2021 may be ignored and you mat be allowed<lb/> to retract the same. The DRI filed a rebuttal dated<lb/> 24.11.2021 before the Hon&quot;ble Court stating inter alia<lb/> that retraction application contained untrue averments<lb/> and are without any substance, afterthought, and farce.<lb/> In reply, DRI stated that the applicant i.e. you tendered<lb/> your voluntary statement under his signature and the<lb/> said statement has also been confirmed in your<lb/> handwriting towards the end. Further, the retraction has<lb/> been made 10 days of the statement; the long gap<lb/> between the recording of the statement and the<lb/> retraction application makes it clear that the retraction<lb/> application filed by you is an afterthought and based on<lb/> legal tutoring. It was further stated by DRI that the<lb/> applicant i.e. you was medically examined at Ram<lb/> Manohar Lohia Hospital Delhi and thereafter produced<lb/> before the Ld. Duty Magistrate. As per the reply of the<lb/> DRI filed before the Ld. CMM Patiala House, New<lb/> Delhi no injury marks (fresh or otherwise) or bruises<lb/> was reported by the duty doctors during the medical<lb/> examination.&quot;</figDesc>
		</figure>


		<figure type="table">

            <table>Union of India [(2000) 7 SCC 148 : 2000<lb/> SCC (Cri) 1304 : (2000) 5 Scale 372].&quot;<lb/> 35. Further, in </table>
 
            <head>Union of India vs. Ranu Bhandari, reported as<lb/> (2008) 17 SCC 348, the </head>
 
            <figDesc>Hon&quot;ble Supreme Court has observed so in<lb/> Paragraphs 33, 34 and 35, which are reproduced hereunder: -</figDesc>
		</figure>



    </text>
</tei>

